<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="other" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Juntendo Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Juntendo Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4715</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">juntendomedj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Juntendo Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2759-7504</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Juntendo Medical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12086455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12086455.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12086455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12086455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40395923</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14789/ejmj.JMJ24-0041-P</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Treatment Strategy for Long COVID Based on Traditional Chinese Medicine</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>NAGASE</surname><given-names initials="M">MAHIKO</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>TAKESHITA</surname><given-names initials="YUU">YUU</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>TOMOOKA</surname><given-names initials="K">KIYOHIDE</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><aff-alternatives id="aff1"><aff xml:lang="ja"><label>1</label>Division of Medical Education, Juntendo University Faculty of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff><aff><label>1</label>Division of Medical Education, Juntendo University Faculty of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff></aff-alternatives><aff-alternatives id="aff2"><aff xml:lang="ja"><label>2</label>Kichijyoji Traditional Chinese Medicine Clinic, Tokyo, Japan</aff><aff><label>2</label>Kichijyoji Traditional Chinese Medicine Clinic, Tokyo, Japan</aff></aff-alternatives><aff-alternatives id="aff3"><aff xml:lang="ja"><label>3</label>Hokushin-kai; Academic Society of Traditional Japanese Acupuncture and Moxibustion, Osaka, Japan</aff><aff><label>3</label>Hokushin-kai; Academic Society of Traditional Japanese Acupuncture and Moxibustion, Osaka, Japan</aff></aff-alternatives><aff-alternatives id="aff4"><aff xml:lang="ja"><label>4</label>Acupuncture Clinic, Seimei-in, Tokyo, Japan</aff><aff><label>4</label>Acupuncture Clinic, Seimei-in, Tokyo, Japan</aff></aff-alternatives><aff-alternatives id="aff5"><aff xml:lang="ja"><label>5</label>Department of Public Health, Juntendo University Faculty of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff><aff><label>5</label>Department of Public Health, Juntendo University Faculty of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff></aff-alternatives></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Mahiko Nagase, Division of Medical Education, Juntendo University Faculty of Medicine, 2-1-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113-8431, Japan, TEL: +81-3-3813-3111 FAX: +81-3-5689-2635 E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mahiko@kca.biglobe.ne.jp">mahiko@kca.biglobe.ne.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>71</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">488792</issue-id><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-05-21 09:25:27.087"><day>21</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Juntendo Medical Society.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original source is properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="2759-7504-71-2-0102.pdf"/><abstract><p>Post-acute COVID-19 conditions, commonly known as ‘long COVID’, occur in individuals with a history of probable or confirmed severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS CoV-2) infection, typically 3 months from the onset of COVID-19 with symptoms, lasting for at least 2 months, that cannot be explained by any alternative diagnoses.</p><p>Although most symptoms improve over time, some patients experience significant limitations in their social lives. Under such circumstances, complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) interventions are growing in popularity as possible treatments for long COVID symptoms. There are a wide variety of CAM interventions, such as traditional Japanese medicine (Kampo medicine) and traditional Chinese medicine (TCM). In this study, we compared three studies using Kampo medicine with those using TCM and concluded that Kampo medicine, which is often practiced in Japan due to its historical background, may have some limitations in managing the diverse symptoms of long COVID because the symptoms of long COVID vary widely. Therefore, we propose that medical examinations based on TCM should also be considered as an alternative treatment strategy for patients with long COVID.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Key words: </title><kwd>long COVID</kwd><kwd>traditional Chinese medicine</kwd><kwd>traditional Chinese herbal medicine</kwd><kwd>Kampo medicine</kwd><kwd>complementary and alternative medicine</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Post-acute COVID-19 conditions, commonly known as ‘long COVID’, occur in individuals with a history of probable or confirmed SARS CoV-2 infection, typically 3 months from the onset of COVID-19 with symptoms, lasting for at least 2 months, that cannot be explained by any alternative diagnoses<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1)</xref></sup>. Symptoms of long COVID may be new-onset following initial recovery from an acute COVID-19 episode or persist from the initial illness, and they may also fluctuate or relapse over time<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref></sup>. Common symptoms include: fatigue, shortness of breath, and cognitive dysfunction, all of which generally affect daily functioning. Even with the World Health Organization (WHO) ending the global emergency status for COVID-19 in May 2023, with over 600 million cases globally, the burden of disease attributable to post-acute COVID-19 remains a major public health issue<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3)</xref></sup>. To date, hundreds of biomedical findings have been documented, with many patients experiencing dozens of symptoms of long COVID involving multiple organ systems. However, long COVID symptoms are still largely unknown, and no standard treatment has been established. Although most symptoms improve over time, some patients experience significant limitations in their social lives. Therefore, it is important to respond from a multifaceted and holistic perspective because of the wide variety of symptoms and processes involved<sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4)</xref>-<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref></sup>. Under such circumstances, complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) interventions are growing in popularity as possible treatments for long COVID symptoms. Recently, it was reported that CAM interventions may be effective, safe, and acceptable for patients with such symptoms<sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6)</xref></sup>. There are wide variety of CAM interventions, one of which is traditional Chinese medicine (TCM). TCM is a complete system of healing that was developed in China about 3,000 years ago. It includes herbal medicine and acupuncture as two of the most important components of CAM and plays a key role in the realization of integrative medicine. In recent decades, the use of TCM has become more popular in China and throughout the world<sup><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref></sup>. Traditional Japanese medicine (Kampo medicine) has been used for 1,500 years, including Kampo-yaku (herbal medicine) and acupuncture in Japan. Kampo medicine is now widely practiced in Japan and has become fully integrated into the modern health-care system. It is based on TCM but has been adapted to complement Japanese medical situations<sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8)</xref></sup>. In this study, we aim to examine the treatment strategy for long COVID in Japan by comparing studies using Kampo medicine with those using TCM.</p></sec><sec><title>Effective cases of long COVID treatment using Kampo medicine</title><p>Harada et al. reported two cases of hair loss due to coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), sequelae of long COVID, successfully treated with ninjin’ yoeito. They administered ninjin’ yoeito for patterns of both qi and blood deficiency with reference to traditional key treatment, and concluded that it contributed to the improvement of symptoms<sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9)</xref></sup>. Ono et al. reported that fatigue after COVID-19 may be improved by saikokeishito, especially for the treatment of patients with slight fever or inflammatory findings<sup><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10)</xref></sup>. In addition, Tokumasu et al. reported that analysis of clinical data from 102 long COVID patients with general fatigue and accompanying symptoms revealed that the patients had various symptoms, and the most frequent ones accompanying general fatigue were: dysosmia, dysgeusia, headache, insomnia, dyspnea, and hair loss. In that study, Kampo medicine accounted for 24.1% of the total prescriptions (n = 609). The most frequently prescribed Kampo medicine was hochuekkito (71.6%); other prescribed Kampo medicines were tokishakuyakusan, ryokeijutsukanto, juzentaihoto, hangekobokuto, kakkonto, ninjin’yoeito, goreisan, rikkunshito, and keishibukuryogan<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11)</xref></sup>. Based on these results, one single type of Kampo-yaku (herbal medicine) tends to be administered for each patient in Japanese trials.</p></sec><sec><title>Effective treatment of long COVID using traditional Chinese medicine</title><p>Fu et al. reported a case of brain fog, one of the more common long COVID symptoms, for which they administered a combination-drug consisting of bu zhong yi qi tang, wen dan tang, wu wei xiao du yin ban lan gen, da qing ye, and chuan xin lian and the patient improved<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12)</xref></sup>. Hsieh et al. reported that personalized traditional Chinese herbal medicine notably reduced fatigue as well as respiratory and emotional distress symptoms after 14- and 28-day treatment in patients with COVID-19 sequelae. In that study, they administered 27 types of traditional Chinese herbal medicine formulas and single herbs<sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13)</xref></sup>. Furthermore, Zhong et al. evaluated the effects of TCM on the health conditions of post-COVID-19 patients, particularly with the traditional Chinese medicine syndrome diagnosis and body constitutions (an inherent trait of the human body in morphological structure, physiological function and psychological status on the basis of innate inheritance and acquired acquisition, which determines the susceptibility of individuals to certain diseases and similarities in pathological processes<sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14)</xref></sup>) as well as related clinical characteristics<sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15)</xref></sup>. In that clinical trial, fever, fatigue, and dry cough were the most common symptoms, present in 59.3, 55.3, and 46% of participants, respectively. Among the 150 post-COVID patients, the majority (71.3%) had one of two post-COVID TCM syndromes (qi deficiency of lung and spleen, and qi and yin deficiency). The participants received various types of combined TCM treatment based on the recommended prescriptions in the TCM clinical practice guidelines for COVID-19 patients, individual TCM syndromes, and clinical symptoms for three to six months. Upon TCM treatment, there was an observable increase in participants achieving a balanced body constitutions (i.e., healthy body conditions). The increase was more prominent in those without compared with TCM syndromes. The main clinical symptoms in participants with TCM syndromes decreased upon TCM treatment. In summary, as compared with Kampo medicine trials in Japan, clinical studies in TCM commonly involve combining multiple prescriptions, such as 2-3 different formulas, within a single treatment period for each patient.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The WHO defined long COVID as the continuation or development of new symptoms 3 months after the initial SARS-CoV-2 infection, with these symptoms lasting for at least 2 months in the absence of any other explanation<sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16)</xref></sup>. Recently, a meta-analysis revealed that more than 50 symptoms have been identified in long COVID patients, approximately 80% of whom suffer from one or more symptoms<sup><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17)</xref></sup>. As possible causes of these symptoms, multiple etiologies such as direct organ damage, constitutive inflammatory responses including autoimmunity, and psychiatric impairment may be involved<sup><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18)</xref></sup>.</p><p>Under such circumstances, CAM interventions including Kampo medicine and TCM are growing in popularity as possible treatments. Kampo medicine is based on TCM but is adapted to Japanese culture. It can be characterized as a simplified version of TCM<sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19)</xref></sup>. The process of diagnosis and treatment differs between TCM and Kampo medicine. Kampo methodology for diagnosis and treatment is referred to as "formulation corresponding to sho (Kampo diagnosis); each pathologic condition is thus related to its prescription. For example, diseases that are expected to respond to kakkonto therapy are diagnosed as kakkonto-sho and it naturally follows that kakkonto is prescribed in such cases<sup><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20)</xref></sup>. The relationship between these steps is regarded as similar to that of a lock and key<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21)</xref></sup>; therefore, only one type of Kampo-yaku (herbal medicine) tends to be administered to each patient. On the other hand, in TCM, after having recognized the particular zheng (TCM diagnosis), the Chinese practitioner then confirms the ‘treatment principle’. According to this principle, it is possible to choose formulae for treatment and adjust the herbs used in the formula, or make a new formulation adapted to the patient’s particular condition. This step is called the ‘selection of treatment’ in TCM. The process from diagnosis to treatment in TCM is called the ‘selection of treatment based on the differential diagnosis’<sup><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref></sup> Thus, the use of a combination of two or three herbal medicines for each patient has been proposed as effective intervention against long COVID from the perspective of TCM, because residual symptoms of COVID-19 are often viewed as a manifestation of the imbalance of various kinds of TCM syndrome diagnosis and body constitutions<sup><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22)</xref></sup>. In fact, a multi-center observational study in Hong Kong showed that individualized TCM treatments could help resolve clinical symptoms (including fatigue, cough, shortness of breath, post-meal fullness, and loose stools), improve lung functions, and lead to healthier TCM body constitutions in COVID-recovered patients<sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14)</xref></sup>. Recently, we reported that long COVID symptoms were not uniform, with malaise (17%) and cough (15%) being slightly more frequent (31 types), and the 46 herbal medicines prescribed also varied<sup><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23)</xref></sup>. The most frequently prescribed Chinese herbal medicines were toukishakuyakusan and bakumondoutou, each accounting for about 6.8% of all prescriptions. In our study, the most common body constitutions associated with fatigue were blood deficiency and water retention, which are indications for toukishakuyakusan. In addition, lung yin deficiency, an indication for bakumondoutou, is frequently noted in the presence of coughing<sup><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20)</xref></sup>. The symptoms of long COVID vary widely; thus, we can conclude that it is important to prescribe a combination of TCM on an understanding of the pathophysiology of the disease to improve symptoms. Furthermore, Chen et al. reported that compared to Western medicine treatment, TCM treatment effectively improved clinical symptoms and shortened the duration of symptoms in 1426 cases with long COVID<sup><xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24)</xref></sup>. With these considerations, although Kampo medicine is often practiced in Japan due to its historical background, it may have some limitations in managing the diverse symptoms of long COVID. Hence, we suggest that incorporating medical examinations grounded in TCM could also serve as a viable intervention for individuals experiencing long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The diagnostic approaches and examination techniques of TCM are distinct from those used in Japanese Kampo medicine. Consequently, integrating these methods could offer potential relief for symptoms associated with long COVID. Additionally, mitigating long COVID symptoms and reducing the treatment duration may contribute positively to public health, particularly in managing workforce well-being.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was received.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>MN wrote the manuscript. YT and KT read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest statement</title><p>MN receive lecture fee from Tsumura &amp; Co.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">World Health Organization: A clinical case definition of post COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus, 6 October 2021. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-Post_COVID-19_condition-Clinical_case_definition-2021.1">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-Post_COVID-19_condition-Clinical_case_definition-2021.1</uri> (Last accessed Dec 24, 2024)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Relan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname>
<given-names>JV</given-names></string-name></person-group>; WHO Clinical Case Definition Working Group on Post-COVID-19 Condition: A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>, <year>2022</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>e102</fpage>-<lpage>e107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>: WHO Declares End of COVID-19 Global Health Emergency. <source>JAMA</source>, <year>2023</year>; <volume>329</volume>: <fpage>1817</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2023.8656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37195734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nalbandian</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>: Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome. <source>Nat Med</source>, <year>2021</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>-<lpage>615</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753937</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-021-01283-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8893149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Assaf</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>: Characterizing long COVID in an international cohort: 7 months of symptoms and their impact. <source>eClinicalMedicine</source>, <year>2021</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <elocation-id>101019</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34308300</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>: Complementary and Alternative Medicine for Long COVID: Scoping Review and Bibliometric Analysis. <source>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</source>, <year>2022</year>; <volume>2022</volume>: <elocation-id>7303393</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35966751</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2022/7303393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9371860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moriya</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>: Traditional Chinese Medicine and Kampo: A Review from the Distant Past for the Future. <source>J Int Med Res</source>, <year>2006</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>239</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16866016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/147323000603400301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kurihara</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>: General Introduction to Kampo Medicine - The Nuts. and Bolts of Kampo -. <source>Juntendo Med J</source>, <year>2018</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Saita</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fukui</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tadokoro</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>: Two Cases of Hair Loss Due to Long COVID Treated with Ninjin’ yoeito. <source>Kampo Med</source>, <year>2022</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>342</fpage>-<lpage>346</lpage>. (in Japanese)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ono R, Takayama S, Saito N, et al: A Case Series of Post-COVID Conditions with Fatigability Treated with Saikokeishito. <source>Journal of the Japan primary Care Association</source>, <year>2024</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>. (in Japanese)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tokumasu K, Ueda K, honda H, et al: Application of Kampo Medicines for Treatment of General Fatigue Due to Long COVID. <source>Medicina</source>, <year>2022</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>730</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35743993</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/medicina58060730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9227280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Fu A, Wang Y: Chinese Herbal Treatment For Long COVID Brain Fog, A Case Report. Convergent Points, <year>2023</year>; <fpage>2</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tzeng</surname>
<given-names>IS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>: Clinical effects of traditional Chinese herbal medicine management in patients with COVID-19 sequelae: A hospital-based retrospective cohort study in Taiwan. <source>Int J Med Sci</source>, <year>2024</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1280</fpage>-<lpage>1291</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38818462</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7150/ijms.96575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11134583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>,<string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>: Influencing factors analysis of dynamic change of TCM constitution based on multiple methods. <source>Digital Chinese Medicine</source>, <year>2024</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>: Eﬀects of Chinese Medicine for Covid-19 rehabilitation: a multicenter observational study. <source>Chin Med</source>, <year>2022</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35996191</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13020-022-00654-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9395813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">World Health Organization: Post COVID-19 condition (Long COVID), 7 December 2022. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition">https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition</uri> (Last accessed Dec 24, 2024)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Leon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wegman-Ostrosky</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perelman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>: More than 50 long-term effects of COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. <source>Sci Rep</source>, <year>2021</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>16144</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34373540</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-95565-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8352980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matsunaga</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuzuki</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morioka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ohmagari</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ishizaka</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>: Long COVID: current status in Japan and knowledge about its molecular background. <source>Glob Health Med</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>30</volume>; <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.35772/ghm.2022.01013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9066464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35586759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Terasawa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>: Evidence-based reconstruction of Kampo medicine: Part I - Is Kampo CAM? <source>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</source>, <year>2004</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15257321</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ecam/neh003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC442105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">The Japan Society for Oriental Medicine: Introduction to KAMPO Japanese Traditional Medicine. Tokyo: Elsevier Japan K.K., <year>2005</year>: <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Horiguchi K, Tsutani K: A cultural perspective: conceptual similarities and differences between traditional Chinese medicine and traditional Japanese medicine. In: Eskinazi D, eds. What will Influence the Future of Alternative Medicine? Singapore: World Scientific, <year>2001</year>: <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>GG</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>: Efficacy of the combination of modern medicine and traditional Chinese medicine in pulmonary fibrosis arising as a sequela in convalescent COVID-19 patients: a randomized multicenter trial. <source>Infect Dis Poverty</source>, <year>2021</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33731163</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40249-021-00813-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7969149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nagase</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>: Prescribing tendency of Kampo-yaku (herbal medicine) based on the traditional medical theory of the pathophysiology of long COVID in 38 patients. <source>Journal of Kampo Medicine</source>. <year>2024</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>731</fpage>-<lpage>736</lpage>. (in Japanese)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24)</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>: Traditional Chinese medicine application and evidence analysis of 1426 cases of long COVID: A retrospective study. <source>Clinical Traditional Medicine and Pharmacology</source>, <year>2024</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <elocation-id>200175</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>