<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chin Med J Pulm Crit Care Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chin Med J Pulm Crit Care Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4622</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cmjpccm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Chinese Medical Journal Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2097-1982</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2772-5588</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12805394</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12805394.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12805394</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12805394</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41551009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pccm.2025.11.003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2772-5588(25)00068-4</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Unveiling the role of the respiratory microbiome in long COVID pathogenesis and therapeutics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="B">Bo</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names initials="K">Kang</given-names></name><email>ningkang@hust.edu.cn</email><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001">Key Laboratory of Molecular Biophysics of the Ministry of Education, Hubei Key Laboratory of Bioinformatics and Molecular-Imaging, Center of AI Biology, Department of Bioinformatics and Systems Biology, College of Life Science and Technology, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, Hubei 430074, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. <email>ningkang@hust.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">505266</issue-id><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-19 15:25:12.797"><day>19</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p content-type="salutation">Edited by: Peifang Wei</p><p id="para0001">Long COVID, characterized by a constellation of persistent symptoms following acute severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection, represents a growing public health challenge with significant impacts on multiple organ systems, particularly the respiratory tract. Symptoms such as chronic cough, fatigue, and neurocognitive dysfunction often continue for months, impairing quality of life and functional capacity. The respiratory microbiome, comprising dynamic communities of bacteria, viruses, and fungi, is essential for maintaining immune homeostasis and epithelial defense. Its alteration during SARS-CoV-2 infection may underpin many of the prolonged inflammatory and structural changes observed in long COVID patients.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p><p id="para0002">Emerging evidence highlights the role of microbiome dysbiosis in driving immune dysregulation, impairing mucosal barrier function, and facilitating secondary infections. Additionally, systemic interactions—especially along the gut–lung and gut–brain axes—amplify inflammatory processes and contribute to diverse clinical manifestations. The depletion of beneficial bacteria and reduced production of immunomodulatory metabolites, such as short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs), further exacerbate pulmonary and extrapulmonary sequelae in long COVID patients.<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p><p id="para0003">This article examines the interplay between respiratory microbiome alterations and long COVID, from molecular mechanisms to clinical implications. By addressing current methodological challenges and outlining future research directions, we aim to foster a deeper understanding of the microbiome’s role in long COVID and facilitate the development of targeted, effective treatments.</p><p id="para0004">In healthy individuals, the respiratory tract harbors diverse microbial communities, including commensal genera such as <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus, Staphylococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium</italic>. These organisms contribute to host defense by competing with pathogens for nutrients and adhesion sites, producing antimicrobial compounds, and finely modulating local and systemic immune responses. A balanced microbiome is essential for respiratory health, offering resilience against infections and inflammatory diseases.<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></p><p id="para0005">SARS-CoV-2 infection causes direct damage to airway epithelial cells, resulting in impaired barrier function and altered local immune activity.<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> The virus binds to angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptors highly expressed on respiratory epithelial cells, leading to cell death and reduced secretion of antimicrobial peptides. This damage facilitates the overgrowth of opportunistic pathogens such as <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>. Additionally, the robust inflammatory response—characterized by elevated levels of interleukin (IL)-6, IL-1β, and tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α)—further disrupts the ecological balance of microbial communities, promoting dysbiosis that can persist long after the acute infection phase.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p><p id="para0006">Clinical studies indicate that COVID-19 significantly reduces microbial diversity in the respiratory tract. There is a marked decrease in commensal bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella</italic>, whereas opportunistic pathogens like <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic> and Enterobacteriaceae become more abundant. These changes are often correlated with disease severity and can persist for months after the acute infection, potentially contributing to the chronic respiratory symptoms observed in long COVID.<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></p><p id="para0007">The persistence of dysbiosis may lead to chronic inflammatory states, impaired tissue repair, and fibrotic changes in the lungs.<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> The loss of beneficial bacteria reduces the production of immunomodulatory metabolites, such as short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs), which are crucial for maintaining immune homeostasis. This may result in ongoing bronchial hyperreactivity and elevated risk of secondary infections, forming a vicious cycle of inflammation and microbial imbalance.<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref></p><p id="para0008">Respiratory microbiome dysbiosis drives persistent immune activation in long COVID by disrupting the balance between pro-inflammatory and regulatory pathways. A marked shift toward Th17 responses amplifies the production of IL-17 and IL-23, promoting neutrophil recruitment and sustained mucosal inflammation. Concurrently, reduced regulatory T-cell (Treg) function diminishes anti-inflammatory signals, allowing unchecked cytokine release. Elevated levels of IL-6, TNF-α, and IL-1β correlate strongly with fatigue, myalgia, and respiratory discomfort, suggesting systemic immune involvement (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><fig id="fig0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Microbial-mediated mechanisms of long COVID. Microbiome dysbiosis in long COVID causes Th17/Treg imbalance, immune overactivation, and epithelial barrier damage, increasing pathogen colonization. Biofilm formation and antibiotic resistance sustain infection–inflammation cycles. Reduced metabolites like SCFAs promote chronic inflammation via epigenetic changes, leading to T-cell exhaustion and lung fibrosis. Gut–brain axis disruption also contributes to neuroinflammation and neurological symptoms. LPS: Lipopolysaccharide; SCFA: Short-chain fatty acid; Th17: T helper 17 cell; Treg: Regulatory T cell.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Fig 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0001" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="para0009">Long-term immune alterations may also involve trained immunity and epigenetic modifications in innate immune cells, potentially driven by persistent microbial dysbiosis and inflammation. For instance, persistent antigenic exposure or molecular mimicry between viral and microbial antigens could not only exacerbate autoinflammatory conditions, but also entrain innate immune cells toward a hyperresponsive state. Furthermore, microbiome-derived metabolites such as SCFAs are often reduced, weakening their inhibitory effects on histone deacetylase (HDAC) and nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B cells (NF-κB) pathways (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). This complex interplay between dysbiosis and host immunity underscores the need for immunomodulatory therapies targeting both microbial and inflammatory components. Dysbiosis compromises respiratory epithelial integrity by down-regulating tight junction proteins (e.g., claudin-1 and occludin) and mucin genes (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">MUC5AC</italic>), leading to barrier leakage and increased permeability. Impaired mucociliary clearance results in mucus accumulation, creating niches for pathogenic bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> to form biofilms. These biofilms protect bacteria from antibiotics and immune attacks, perpetuating chronic infection and local inflammation.<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> The resulting chronic bronchial inflammation and recurrent respiratory infections contribute to long COVID symptoms such as persistent cough and sputum production. In severe cases, prolonged epithelial injury may lead to remodeling and fibrotic changes, further diminishing lung function. Therapeutic strategies aiming to restore epithelial health—such as probiotics, barrier-enhancing agents, or mucolytics—may help break this cycle of inflammation and tissue damage.<fig id="fig0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Mechanisms by which gut microbes influence respiratory health. SCFAs, produced by gut flora from dietary fiber, enter the lungs via blood circulation. There, they activate GPCRs on macrophages and epithelial cells, suppress NF-κB, lower pro-inflammatory cytokines (e.g., IL-6, TNF-α), and enhance Treg differentiation. Separately, gut commensals activate ILC2s, which migrate to the lungs via S1P signaling, promoting type 2 immunity (e.g., eosinophil recruitment) and worsening allergic asthma. ATP: Adenosine triphosphate; FoxP3: Forkhead box protein P3; GPCRs: G protein-coupled receptors; HDAC: Histone deacetylase; ILC2s: Type 2 innate lymphoid cells; IL-6: Interleukin-6; IL-23: Interleukin-23; NF-κB: Nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B cells; SCFA: Short-chain fatty acid; SIP: Sphingosine-1-phosphate; Th17: T helper 17 cell; TNF-α: Tumor necrosis factor alpha; Treg: Regulatory T cell. Created with <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Biorender.com" id="interref0001">Biorender.com</ext-link>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Fig 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0002" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="para0010">The gut–lung axis serves as a critical interorgan communication pathway that influences immune responses in long COVID. SARS-CoV-2 infection can induce gut dysbiosis, reducing beneficial bacteria like <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic> that produce key immunomodulatory metabolites. These metabolites, including short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) and bile acids, are essential for maintaining immune homeostasis: SCFAs promote regulatory T cell differentiation and suppress NF-κB-mediated inflammation,<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> while bile acids modulate host immunity and oxidative stress. Their deficiency is linked to heightened pulmonary inflammation and impaired repair.<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Emerging research in long COVID confirms these mechanistic links. Studies indicate that SCFAs, particularly butyrate, are persistently reduced in patients, correlating with gut microbiota alterations and systemic inflammation. Similarly, bile acid metabolism is disrupted, with a marked decrease in beneficial secondary bile acids.<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Furthermore, elevated levels of trimethylamine N-oxide (TMAO) are associated with key long COVID mechanisms, including dysbiosis, coagulation abnormalities, and chronic inflammation.<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Critically, not all persistent microbial metabolite changes are pathogenic. The driving force behind chronic inflammation is likely the sustained loss of beneficial, anti-inflammatory metabolites (e.g., SCFAs, secondary bile acids), which disrupts immune regulation and tissue homeostasis, thereby perpetuating the pathophysiology of long COVID.</p><p id="para0011">Neurological symptoms in long COVID, such as brain fog, anxiety, and sleep disturbances, are partly mediated by microbiome imbalances through the gut–brain axis. Depletion of beneficial bacteria (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>) reduces synthesis of neurotransmitters including serotonin, gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA), and dopamine, affecting mood and cognition. Meanwhile, increased permeability of the gut barrier ("leaky gut") permits translocation of bacterial lipopolysaccharides (LPS) into systemic circulation.<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> LPS triggers Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4)-mediated activation of microglia and astrocytes, leading to neuroinflammation and neuronal dysfunction. Vagus nerve signaling, which connects gut microbial activity to central nervous system processes, may also be disrupted. These mechanisms contribute to cognitive deficits, fatigue, and autonomic dysregulation observed in long COVID.</p><p id="para0012">When it comes to current therapeutic approaches for long COVID based on the microbiome, probiotics (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> strains) and prebiotics (e.g., dietary fibers) stand out as promising means to restore microbial balance. These interventions are designed to enhance beneficial microbiota, generate immunomodulatory metabolites such as SCFAs, and strengthen epithelial barrier function. Clinical trials have demonstrated their potential in reducing the severity of respiratory symptoms and improving overall recovery trajectories.<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> As for emerging strategies, fecal microbiota transplantation (FMT) is currently under investigation as a treatment for severe, refractory dysbiosis in long COVID, though its application remains in the experimental stage. Additionally, personalized microbiome therapies, which use high-resolution metagenomic profiling and machine learning, offer a tailored approach to treatment. However, these advances must be carefully balanced against ethical considerations and potential risks, including unintended microbial shifts and the transmission of pathogens.<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref></p><p id="para0013">Collectively, much has been learned about the influence of microbiome on long COVID, while significant challenges remain in microbiome research pertaining to long COVID. Key limitations include inconsistent sampling techniques—such as the use of nasopharyngeal, oropharyngeal, or sputum samples, each with distinct biases affecting microbiome representation—as well as frequently limited sample sizes that reduce statistical power and increase error risks. Furthermore, substantial variability in study designs, including differing diagnostic criteria for long COVID, follow-up durations, and a lack of standardized laboratory and bioinformatic protocols, impedes direct comparison and synthesis of results across studies. To overcome these constraints, future research should emphasize standardization of sampling and analytical methods, alongside the adoption of larger-scale longitudinal cohorts. By establishing unified protocols and improving data transparency through shared repositories, studies can better capture temporal dynamics of microbiome changes and strengthen the evidence base for clinical and therapeutic applications.</p><p id="para0014">Summing up, the respiratory microbiome plays a central role in the pathophysiology of long COVID, particularly through mechanisms involving immune dysregulation, chronic inflammation, and epithelial compromise. While microbiome-modulating therapies offer considerable promise, robust clinical evidence is still evolving. Future research must integrate multidisciplinary approaches—combining microbiology, immunology, and clinical medicine—to develop effective interventions. By deepening our understanding of host–microbe interactions in post-COVID recovery, we can pave the way for innovative strategies that enhance respiratory health and quality of life for patients worldwide.</p><sec id="sec0001"><title>Funding</title><p id="para0015">This study was supported by the <funding-source id="gs0001">National Key Research &amp; Development Program of China</funding-source> (Nos. <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs0001">2023YFA1800900</award-id>, <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs0001">2018YFC0910502</award-id>) and <funding-source id="gs0002">the National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source> (Nos. <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs0002">32071465</award-id>, <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs0002">31871334</award-id>, <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs0002">31671374</award-id>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0001a"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="para0015a"><bold>Bo Wang:</bold> Writing – original draft, Resources, Project administration, Methodology, Investigation. <bold>Yuan Wang:</bold> Visualization, Validation, Supervision, Software. <bold>Kang Ning:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Writing – original draft, Visualization, Validation, Funding acquisition, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0001"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="para0016">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholkmann</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19, post-acute COVID-19 syndrome (PACS, ``long COVID'') and post-COVID-19 vaccination syndrome (PCVS, ``post-COVIDvac-syndrome''): Similarities and differences</article-title><source>Pathol Res Pract</source><volume>246</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">154497</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prp.2023.154497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10154064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37192595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wypych</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsland</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of the microbiome on respiratory health</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><volume>20</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41590-019-0451-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31501577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissecting the role of the human microbiome in COVID-19 via metagenome-assembled genomes</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><volume>13</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>5235</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-32991-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36068270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9446638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vitiello</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zovi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between microbiota and immune response to Sars-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Infect Dis Now</source><volume>53</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104646</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idnow.2023.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9837228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36642100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The clinical outcome of COVID-19 is strongly associated with microbiome dynamics in the upper respiratory tract</article-title><source>J Infect</source><volume>88</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">106118</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2024.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38342382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying-Jung Wu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin-Jung Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 associated mold infections: Review of COVID-19 associated pulmonary aspergillosis and mucormycosis</article-title><source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source><volume>56</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmii.2022.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36586744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9751001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotulo</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding COVID-19 in children: Immune determinants and post-infection conditions</article-title><source>Pediatr Res</source><volume>94</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41390-023-02549-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36879079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9987407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusev</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarapultsev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solomatina</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chereshnev</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2-specific immune response and the pathogenesis of COVID-19</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><volume>23</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1716</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms23031716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35163638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8835786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S.Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gut-lung axis and asthma: A historical review on mechanism and future perspective</article-title><source>Clin Transl Allergy</source><volume>14</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e12356</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/clt2.12356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11060082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38687096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JY.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of long COVID: An updated review</article-title><source>Chin M J Pulm Crit Care Med</source><volume>1</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pccm.2023.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39171285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11332859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marissen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Härtel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) and the microbiome in preterm infants: Consequences and opportunities for future therapeutics</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><volume>25</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>6684</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25126684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38928389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11203687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kritikos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernasconi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lung and gut microbiota profiling in intensive care unit patients: A prospective pilot study</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><volume>25</volume><year>2025</year><fpage>468</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-025-10825-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40188054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11972518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prolonged impairment of short-chain fatty acid and L-Isoleucine biosynthesis in gut microbiome in patients with COVID-19</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>162</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>561.e4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2021.10.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34687739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8529231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazemian</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pakpour</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fecal microbiota transplantation during and post-COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><volume>22</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>3004</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms22063004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33809421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7998826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantino-Jonapa</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Espinoza-Palacios</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Escalona-Montaño</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contribution of trimethylamine N-oxide (TMAO) to chronic inflammatory and degenerative diseases</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><volume>11</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>431</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines11020431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36830968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9952918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneja</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prochaska</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milstone</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiome dysbiosis: A modifiable state and target to prevent <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infections and other diseases in neonates</article-title><source>J Perinatol</source><volume>44</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41372-023-01810-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37904005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10842217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emadzadeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabiri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the prophylactic effects of probiotics, prebiotics, and synbiotics against COVID-19 infection: A systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>Clin Med Res</source><volume>22</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3121/cmr.2024.1865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39231625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11374498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachour</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allegretti</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on Clostridioides difficile infection and utilization of fecal microbiota transplantation</article-title><source>Therap Adv Gastroenterol</source><volume>16</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">17562848231165581</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17562848231165581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10107020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37091531</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>