<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12322159</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12322159.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12322159</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12322159</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40759992</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-11539-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">11539</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Hyperbaric oxygen therapy for long COVID: a prospective registry</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Berkel</surname><given-names initials="J">J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalieu</surname><given-names initials="RC">R. C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names initials="D">D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellemons</surname><given-names initials="M">M.</given-names></name><address><email>m.hellemons@erasmusmc.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lansdorp</surname><given-names initials="CA">C. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Eurocept Clinics, Amersfoort/Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Hyperbaric Medical Center (HGC), Rijswijk, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/018906e22</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0459 992X</institution-id><institution>Department of Pulmonary Medicine, </institution><institution>Erasmus Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478255</issue-id><elocation-id>28351</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>04</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-08-06 00:25:16.867"><day>06</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2025_Article_11539.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par6">A potential beneficial effect of hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT) on complaints of long COVID was found, leading to increased demand for this treatment despite many remaining clinical questions and lack of formal guideline recommendations and reimbursement. A registry was set up in order to gain more insight into patient characteristics and (long-term) outcomes of long COVID patients undergoing HBOT. Patient-reported outcome measures were collected at baseline, after treatment, at 3-month and 1-year follow up. This publication includes the 3-month results. The primary outcome measures were the mental and physical component score (MCS/PCS) of the SF-36 questionnaire. A clinically relevant positive or negative response was defined as a ≥ 10 point increase or decrease of in MCS and/or PCS after 3 months. Secondary outcomes included the EQ-5D, severity of complaints and ability to work. In this prospective registry, 56–63% of long term-ill patients had a clinically relevant improvement in MCS/PCS 3 months after HBOT. However, 13–19% of the patients had a clinically relevant deterioration in MCS/PCS. Symptoms that showed most improvement were predominantly in the cognitive domain. This indicates that HBOT may have a positive effect on complaints of long COVID, but alertness for worsening of the condition should be exercised.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-11539-0.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Viral infection</kwd><kwd>Outcomes research</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par7">Although the majority of people recover fully from an infection with SARS-CoV-2, 6–12% of adults develops longer lasting symptoms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. This condition, referred to as long COVID (or post COVID), was recently defined as: <italic toggle="yes">an infection-associated chronic condition that occurs after SARS-CoV-2 infection and is present for at least 3 months as a continuous</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> relapsing and remitting</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> or progressive disease state that affects one or more organ systems.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> A wide range of symptoms can occur, with the most commonly reported symptoms: fatigue, post-exertional malaise and cognitive problems. Frequently reported cognitive symptoms include memory and concentration problems, difficulty processing stimuli and brain fog<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. The condition can last for months or years or become a chronic condition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">Unsurprisingly, the impact of long COVID is substantial and leads to decreased quality of life, social functioning and has a major impact on work life<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. In the Netherlands, 18% of long COVID patients reported being unable to work and 41% had to significantly reduce their working hours<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">Research on long COVID has known a slow and difficult beginning, and there is still incomplete understanding of its complex pathophysiology. Proposed mechanisms include immune-dysregulation, microbiome disruption, autoimmunity, clotting and endothelial abnormalities, mitochondrial dysfunction, viral persistence or dysfunctional neurological signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Corresponding with the lack of understanding, treatment options for long COVID are limited; common approaches include coping strategies, activity management and symptom control<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par10">In search of an effective treatment, hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT) emerged as a promising intervention. HBOT is a medical treatment where an individual breathes near 100% oxygen intermittently while inside a hyperbaric chamber that is pressurized to greater than 2 atmosphere absolute (ATA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. HBOT is used for established indications such as diabetic foot ulcers, late radiation tissue injury and emergency indications like decompression illness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. HBOT increases tissue oxygen levels and activates genes that trigger regenerative processes, including stem-cell proliferation, anti-inflammatory responses, angiogenesis, and can benefit mitochondrial function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Furthermore, it influences cerebral blood flow and microstructure, aiding neuroplasticity and cognitive function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">Previous studies suggest improvement of long COVID symptoms after HBOT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. A sham-controlled, randomized trial showed significant improvements in cognitive symptoms, quality of life, sleep, psychological symptoms and pain after 40 sessions of HBOT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Longitudinal follow up of HBOT patients in this trial showed persistent improvement in patient-reported outcomes one year after treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Nonetheless, although effectiveness was demonstrated, the clinical relevance of its effects was questioned, and its efficacy and safety remains to be established in the more severe and longer term-ill patients, in whom spontaneous recovery is less likely.</p><p id="Par12">Based on the existing studies, the Association of Hyperbaric Medicine in the Netherlands decided the current evidence allows further exploration of HBOT for long COVID patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. In order to gain more insight into outcomes of this treatment, patients who decided to undergo (off-label) HBOT for long COVID were invited to participate in a prospective registry. In this article the 3-month follow up results from this registry are presented.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design and patient selection</title><p id="Par13">Six out of nine hyperbaric chambers in the Netherlands participated in this prospective registry. All consecutive patients that were deemed eligible for treatment between 15 February 2023 and 15 February 2024 were asked to participate in the registry and written informed consent for the acquisition of data and patient reported outcome measures (PROMS) was obtained prior to the start of treatment. Patients who were not able to provide consent or fill in questionnaires were excluded, as well as patients that were eligible for treatment but did not start the treatment. The study was approved by the Medical Ethical Review Board of Erasmus University of Rotterdam (MEC-2023-0433) and performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations. The study was documented in a trial registry (clinicaltrials.gov, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT06159309">NCT06159309</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par14">Local eligibility criteria for referral and off-label treatment in these centers were in line with previous literature: age ≥ 18 years, (primary) cognitive complaints with significant impact on everyday life for at least 3 months after initial COVID infection and with no alternative explanations for these symptoms. Initial COVID infection was preferably confirmed by PCR or antigen test or was highly probably (e.g. patients with typical COVID symptoms during the endemic phase before testing was possible). Eligibility for the treatment and contraindications were assessed by the referring specialist and the hyperbaric physician. The original study protocol is provided in the supplementary documents.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>HBO regimen</title><p id="Par15">The local protocol for off-label treatment comprised 40 daily sessions of HBOT at 2.4–2.5 ATA, with a treatment duration of 90 to 110 min with 5-minute air breaks every 20 min. All participating centers use multiplace chambers to administer 100% oxygen by mask or hood. Treatment was provided 5 days a week (excluding weekends), with a total treatment duration of 8 weeks (in the case of 40 sessions). This protocol was based on prior studies for this indication<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, and the standard protocols for established indications, such as diabetic foot wounds, late radiation tissue injury and chronic refractive osteomyelitis which encompass 30 to 60 sessions at ≥ 2.0 ATA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par16">At the discretion of the hyperbaric physician extension of the protocol was possible. Reasons for prolonging the treatment were either clinical (e.g. a subjective late response with the wish to continue treatment at the moment of response) or because of inadequate dosing at the beginning of treatment due to interruptions of the treatment schedule (e.g. due to illness).</p><p id="Par17">Regular visits with the hyperbaric physician and/or case manager were scheduled at baseline and after every 10 to 15 sessions and in the case of extension of treatment also after 50 or 60 sessions, in accordance with standard care at the facilities. During these visits the progression of the treatment and complaints were discussed, as well as any adverse events. Follow up was performed by telephone: the 3-month follow up is part of standard care of HBOT.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Outcome measures</title><p id="Par18">Patients were asked to fill out PROMS at baseline, after 20 sessions, after 40 sessions, 3 months after treatment and 1 year after treatment. In the case of extension of treatment beyond 40 sessions, PROMs were also collected directly after the extended treatment (i.e. after 50 or 60 sessions). This article includes only the 3-month results. The 1 year follow up will be published separately (expected September 2025).</p><p id="Par19">The primary outcome measure is the mental and physical component score (MCS/PCS) of the SF-36 questionnaire 3 months after treatment. Each component score measures quality-of-life on four health domains: MCS includes role limitations due to emotional problems, energy/fatigue, emotional well-being and social functioning. PCS includes general health, physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health and pain. Scores range from 0 (lowest) to 100 (highest). No minimally clinical important difference (MCID) for the SF-36 is available in literature for long COVID patients specifically, and therefore a 10 point increase in score or more is used in this study as MCID, as is in line with the national guideline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Responders after HBOT were defined as ≥ 10 points increase in MCS and/or PCS score between baseline and 3-month follow up. Patients who had a ≥ 10 points decrease of MCS and/or PCS score were defined as negative-responders. The patients who had a less than 10 points change in MCS and PCS or a mixed result (e.g. positive response in MCS, but negative in PCS) were defined as non-responders.</p><p id="Par20">Secondary outcome measures include:</p><p id="Par21">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par22">EQ-5D VAS score: The EQ-5D evaluates quality of life in 5 domains (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression) and a visual analogue scale (VAS), which measures quality of health on a scale ranging from 0 (worst imaginable health) to 100 (best imaginable health). A MCID of 7.5 points for the VAS has been reported for patients with long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par23">Questionnaire of long COVD symptoms: patients evaluated the presence and severity of 40 common long COVID symptoms. The list of symptoms was based on available literature. Patients rated the presence and severity of their symptoms on a 5-point Likert scale (not present/mild/moderate/severe/extreme) and were then further subcategorized into: no symptoms, mild-moderate and severe-extreme.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par24">Absence from work: all patients were questioned regarding absence from work and its relation to their diagnosis of long COVID, number of working hours and adjustments to the job content.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par25">Furthermore, information on adverse events of HBOT (both solicited during regular visits and unsolicited), re-infection and re-vaccination during HBOT and follow up was recorded.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data management and statistical analysis</title><p id="Par26">An external electronic data capture system (Castor EDC) was used to document and store patient information between centers. Baseline characteristics were recorded during the initial assessment by the hyperbaric physician (before the start of treatment), and included gender, age, patient body mass index, smoking, medical history, and COVID specific information including the date of infection leading to long COVID, hospital or intensive care admission, type of test (PCR or antigen) and COVID vaccination history.</p><p id="Par27">IBM SPSS Statistics 29.0.1.0 software was used to analyze all data. Missing data was excluded from the analysis (i.e. analysis was performed only on cases where the relevant variables were present). Descriptive statistics were used to describe patient baseline characteristics. Categorical data are presented as number and/or percentage. For continuous data, distribution was assessed on histograms, if normality was assumed this was tested (Kolgorov-Smirnov, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Normally distributed data is presented as a mean with a standard deviation (SE) and non-normally distributed data is presented as a median with an interquartile range (IQR). To compare groups, paired T-tests were used if data was normally distributed, Wilcoxon signed rank tests were used if data was not normally distributed. A value of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Registry</title><p id="Par28">Between February 2023 and February 2024, 239 patients were eligible for inclusion. 5 patients were excluded because they never started HBOT due to private circumstances, and 2 patients did not provide informed consent. Therefore, 232 patients were included in the final analysis. Of the 232 patients, 187 patients were treated at Eurocept Clinics (Amersfoort, Arnhem, Geldrop, Hoogeveen, Rotterdam and Waalwijk) and 45 patients at the Hyperbaric Medical Center in Rijswijk. The response rate on the primary outcome (SF-36) was 95% at baseline, 84% directly after HBO and 80% at 3-month follow up.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>PROMS collection</title><p id="Par29">Unfortunately, due to logistical challenges - particularly at one participating center that was less experienced with follow-up procedures - a substantial portion of the data at the 20 sessions time point was not collected and was lost to follow-up. As a result, these results are not included in the main analysis. However, the data 20 sessions time point (SF-36, EQ-5D, and Long COVID questionnaire) is provided in the appendix (Appendix Tables A, B and D).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Baseline characteristics</title><p id="Par30">Baseline characteristics are presented in Table 1. The median age of patients at the start of the treatment was 42 years (IQR 31–51). Most patients were female (70%) and never-smokers (76%), with only 2% patients being active smokers at the start of treatment. 118 patients had no documented medical history. Of the reported history items in the remaining 114 patients, mental complaints (12%), asthma (11%), irritable bowel syndrome (7.3%), hypertension (4.7%) and other cardiovascular disease (4.7%) were most frequently reported. Most COVID infections that lead to long COVID were confirmed by PCR (71%) or antigen testing (15%). A minority of patients (3%) had been hospitalized for their COVID infection, with none being admitted to the intensive care unit. Patients had long-term complaints before starting HBOT with a median 20 months (IQR 14–30) between SARS-CoV-2 infection and start of HBOT.</p><p id="Par31">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Age</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (32–51) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 232)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Body Mass Index<sup>i</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.2 (21.8–27.4) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 222)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Female</p><p>Male</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>162 (70%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 232)</p><p>70 (30%)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Smoking history</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Smoker</p><p>Ex-smoker</p><p>Never-smoker</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5 (2%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 231)</p><p>51 (22%)</p><p>175 (76%)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">COVID test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PCR+</p><p>Antigen+</p><p>Not confirmed by test (first wave)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>156 (71%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 220)</p><p>33 (15%)</p><p>31 (14%)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><p>Hospital admission</p><p>Intensive care admission</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6 (3%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 227)</p><p>0 (0%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 227)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Months between SARS-CoV-2 infection and start of treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (14–30) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 226)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">COVID vaccinated (received at least one)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">207 (95%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 218)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Medical history yes/no</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114 (49%)/117 (51%) </td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Mental disorders</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (11.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Asthma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (11.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Irritable bowel disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (7.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (4.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Other cardiovascular disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (4.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Auto-immune disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (4.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Infectious mononucleosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- ADHD/ADD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Other gastrointestinal disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Neurological/neuromuscular disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Burn-out</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Thyroid disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Other pulmonary disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Intestinal parasitic infection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Chronic kidney disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- ME/CFS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Immune deficiency</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (8.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Work status</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Able to work</p><p>- worked hours per week</p><p>- contracted hours per week</p><p>Not able to work due to Long COVID complaints</p><p>Not working due to other reasons</p><p>Student</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>105 (49%)(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 214)</p><p>15.1 (SD 10.2)(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 98)</p><p>37.8 (SD 8.2)(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 98)</p><p>91 (43%)</p><p>11 (5%)</p><p>9 (4%)</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Numbers are shown as <italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic>. Continuous variables are shown as means (SD) when normally distributed and median (IQR) otherwise.</p><p>IQR, interquartile range. SD, standard deviation. ADHD/ADD, Attention Deficit (Hyperactivity) Disorder. ME/CFS, chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis. <sup>i</sup> Calculated as weight/height<sup>2</sup>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>HBOT sessions</title><p id="Par32">Patients were treated with a median of 40 sessions (IQR 40–46). 15 (6%) patients terminated their treatment before 37 sessions. Reasons for early termination of the treatment were: HBOT was too exhausting with worsening of fatigue or other long COVID symptoms (10 patients), anxiety or claustrophobia during HBOT (2 patients), no treatment effect (1 patient), an unrelated illness (1 patient), and private circumstances (1 patient).</p><p id="Par33">54 patients received 48 sessions or more. 42 patients because of a (subjective) late response with the wish to extend the treatment, and 12 patients because of inadequate dosing in the beginning of treatment due to interruptions of the treatment schedule (e.g. due to illness).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Primary outcome: SF-36 questionnaire</title><p id="Par34">The median MCS of the SF-36 questionnaire improved from 45.5 (IQR 28.7–56.6) at baseline to 57.0 (IQR 46.2–71.5) at 3-month follow up. For the PCS, these scores were 36.9 (IQR 27.2–45.0), and 42.5 (IQR 32.2–52.5), respectively. The Wilcoxon Signed-Rank Test indicated a statistically significant change in median MCS and PCS from baseline to 3 months Z= −7.11, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 and Z= −4.53, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively. Subdomains that showed the largest increase in score were energy/fatigue, social functioning, emotional well-being and physical functioning (Table 2; Figs.1 and 2).</p><p id="Par35">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>SF-36<sup>i</sup> scores.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Directly after HBOT</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
<sup>*</sup>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3-month follow up</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>MCS</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.5 (28.7–56.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.5 (38.3–63.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.0 (46.2–71.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Role limitations due to emotional problems</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.0 (0.0–100.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.0 (33.3–100.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.059</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.0 (100.0–100.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Energy/fatigue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">149</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.0 (10.0–30.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.0 (15.0–45.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0 (20.0–55.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Emotional well-being</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.0 (52.0–76.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.0 (60.0–80.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.0 (60.0–84.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Social functioning</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.5 (0.0–37.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.0 (0.0–50.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.5 (12.5–62.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>PCS</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.9 (27.2–45.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.6 (29.1–53.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.5 (32.2–52.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">General health</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">143</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.0 (20.0–40.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0 (25.0–45.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.008</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0 (25.0–50.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.031</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical functioning</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0 (35.0–70.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.0 (40.0–80.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.0 (40.0–80.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Role limitations due to physical health</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">156</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0 (0.0–0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0 (0.0–0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0 (0.0–0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.5 (32.5–80.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.5 (45.0–90.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.5 (45.0–90.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.007</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Variables (non-normally distributed) are shown as median (IQR). Abbreviations: SF-36, 36-Item Short Form Survey. MCS, mental component score (range 0-100), PCS, physical component score. IQR, interquartile range.</p><p><sup>i</sup>SF-36 measures quality-of-life. The MCS quality-of-life on four health domains: role limitations due to emotional problems, energy/fatigue, emotional well-being and social functioning. The PCS includes general health, physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health and pain. Scores range from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating higher quality of life.</p><p>* Statistical significance as compared to baseline.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par36">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>SF-36 Mental component scores. Note for Fig. 1a/b: SF-36 measures quality-of-life. The MCS of the SF-36 measures quality-of-life on four health domains: role limitations due to emotional problems, energy/fatigue, emotional well-being and social functioning. The PCS includes general health, physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health and pain. Scores range from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating higher quality of life. Median scores are displayed as dots, with an interquartile range as lines, the corresponding values and significance can be found in Table 2. SF-36, 36-item Short Form Survey. PCS, physical component score. MCS, mental component score.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e905" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11539_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par37">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>SF-36 Physical component scores. Note for Fig. 1a/b: SF-36 measures quality-of-life. The MCS of the SF-36 measures quality-of-life on four health domains: role limitations due to emotional problems, energy/fatigue, emotional well-being and social functioning. The PCS includes general health, physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health and pain. Scores range from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating higher quality of life. Median scores are displayed as dots, with an interquartile range as lines, the corresponding values and significance can be found in Table 2. SF-36, 36-item Short Form Survey. PCS, physical component score. MCS, mental component score.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e915" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11539_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par38">Three months after HBOT, out of 137 patients analyzed, 76 (56%) were responders, 43 (31%) were non-responder and 18 (13%) were negative-responders. Patient characteristics for each subgroup are shown in Table 3.</p><p id="Par39">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Responder, non-responder and negative-responder patient characteristics. Note: Numbers are shown as <italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic>. Continuous variables are shown as median (IQR). Abbreviations: <italic toggle="yes">IQR</italic> interquartile range. SF-36, 36-item Short Form Survey. PCS, physical component score. MCS, mental component score. VAS, visual analogue scale. HBOT, hyperbaric oxygen therapy. <sup>i</sup> Calculated as weight/height<sup>2</sup>. <sup>ii</sup> SF-36 measures quality-of-life. The MCS of the SF-36 measures quality-of-life on four health domains: role limitations due to emotional problems, energy/fatigue, emotional well-being and social functioning. The PCS includes general health, physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health and pain. Scores range from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating higher quality of life. <sup>iii</sup> EQ-5D VAS score records the respondent’s self-rated health on a visual analogue scale from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating higher quality of life.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Responder (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 76)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Responder (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 43)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative-Responder (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (32–51) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (31–51) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (36–53) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Body Mass Index<sup>i</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.8 (22.6–28.0) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.7 (21.2–26.2) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 39)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.8 (21.2–26.7) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Female</p><p>Male</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>43 (57%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 76)</p><p>33 (43%)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>33 (77%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 43)</p><p>10 (23%)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16 (89%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</p><p>2 (11%)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking history</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Smoker</p><p>Ex-smoker</p><p>Never smoker</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0 (0%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 75)</p><p>20 (27%)</p><p>55 (73%)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0 (0%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 42)</p><p>9 (21%)</p><p>34 (79%)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0 (0%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</p><p>4 (22%)</p><p>14 (78%)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">COVID test</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>PCR+</p><p>Antigen+</p><p>Not confirmed</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>49 (69%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 72)</p><p>10 (6%)</p><p>13 (14%)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>29 (71%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 41)</p><p>3 (7%)</p><p>9 (22%)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13 (72%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</p><p>4 (22%)</p><p>1 (6%)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Hospital admission</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (5%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Months between SARS-CoV-2 infection and start of treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (15–30) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 74)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (13–34) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (14–21) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">COVID vaccinated (at least one)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (93%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (93%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 41)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (95%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 17)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Medical history, yes/no</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (47%)/40 (53%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (51%)/21 (49%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (61%)/7 (39%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Baseline work status:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 71)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 41)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 17)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Able to work</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (55%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (49%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (29%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Worked hours per week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (9–24) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (8–18) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (2–8) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Contracted hours per week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (32–40) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (32–40) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (26–40) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Not able to work due to Long COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (32%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (42%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (71%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Not working due to other reasons</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- Student</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 92%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Baseline SF-36 component scores<sup>ii</sup>:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- MCS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4 (23,3–57.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.6 (37.5–58.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.5 (42.1–59.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">- PCS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.2 (25.8–47.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.6 (28.1–44.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.3 (23.9–41.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Baseline EQ-5D VAS score <sup>iii</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (30–50) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (29–45) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (24–40) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 17)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Re-infection with SARS-CoV-2 during or after HBOT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (8%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (14%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 73)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (11%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Re-vaccination (COVID) during or after HBOT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (8%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (7%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (10%) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 17)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par40">In the patients who received an extension to 50 or 60 sessions, median MCS changed from 39.3 (IQR 19.4–53.7) at baseline, to 46.8 (IQR 38.6–55.5) directly after HBOT, to 55.1 (40.6–64.1) at 3-month follow up (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 23). For the PCS these scores were 27.5 (IQR 21.3–41.3), 32.5 (IQR 20.0–43.1), and 40.6 (IQR 26.3–48.1), respectively (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 24). Wilcoxon signed rank indicated significant change in both MCS and PCS (for MCS: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006, Z= −2.8 directly after HBOT and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002, Z-3.0 at 3-month follow up, and for PCS: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.016, Z= −2.4 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.012, Z= −2.5, respectively).</p><p id="Par41">In the extension of treatment group, out of the 32 patients analyzed, 20 (63%) were responders, 6 (19%), were non-responders, and 6 (19%) were negative-responders. In the 105 patients analyzed in 40 sessions group this was 56 (53%), 37 (35%), and 12 (11%), respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>EQ-5D</title><p id="Par42">The mean score on the visual analogue scale of the EQ-5D (EQ-5D VAS) improved from mean 37 (SD 14) at baseline to 46 (SD 20) directly after HBOT (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), to 50 (SD 19) at 3-month follow up (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), for 138 patients analyzed (Table 4).</p><p id="Par43">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>EQ-5D VAS scores (including T = 20 sessions).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Directly after HBOT</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sup>*</sup>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3-month follow up</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sup>*</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>EQ-5D VAS</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (SD 14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (SD 20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (SD 19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Variables are shown as mean (standard deviation). The EQ-5D VAS score records the respondent’s self-rated health on a visual analogue scale from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating higher quality of life.</p><p>* Statistical significance as compared to baseline.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par44">And out of 163 patients analyzed, 99 (61%) improved more than the MCID (7.5 points) at 3-month follow-up, 16 (10%) patients had a deterioration of more than the MCID, and 48 patients (29%) did not improve or deteriorate more than the MCID.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Long COVID complaints questionnaire</title><p id="Par45">Out of the 40 included complaints in the questionnaire, the complaints that were most often scored ‘severe to extreme’ at baseline were fatigue (87%), difficulty processing stimuli (80%), post-exertional malaise (75%), loss of physical fitness (71%) and concentration problems (68%). All symptoms and frequencies are shown in Figure A in the appendix.</p><p id="Par46">At 3-month follow up, for the top 5 symptoms there was a global decline in symptom burden, for example from severe-extreme symptoms to mild-moderate (Fig. 3).</p><p id="Par47">For fatigue 55/155 (35%) patients with severe-extreme symptom score had less severe complaints at 3 month follow up. On the other hand, 9/21 (43%) patients with no or mild-moderate symptoms transitioned to severe-extreme complaints at 3-month follow up. Respectively, for difficulty processing stimuli 81/146 (55%) reported improvement and 6/33 (18%) deterioration, for post-exertional malaise 45/136 (33%) reported improvement and 6/44 (14%) deterioration, for loss of physical fitness 42/123 (34%) reported improvement and 15/53 (28%) deterioration and for concentration problems 77/126 (61%) reported improvement and 5/54 (9%) deterioration.</p><p id="Par48">The most substantial decreases in symptom burden (from severe-extreme to less severe) were seen for word-finding problems (43/59 patients, 73%), irritability (44/61, 72%), memory problems (62/88, 70%), brain fog (70/103, 68%) and shortness of breath on exertion (38/68, 56%). All symptoms and frequencies over time are presented in Appendix Table C.</p><p id="Par49">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Severity of top 5 long COVID complaints at baseline and 3-month follow up. Note: Number of patients for each symptom category. Symptom severity was rated by patients on a 5-point Likert scale, and further subcategorized into; no symptoms, mild-moderate and severe-extreme.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1519" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11539_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Absence from work</title><p id="Par50">In the registry there were 214 people that were working before the onset of long COVID. Of these people, 105 (49%) were still able to work to a certain degree, and 91 people were completely unable to work due to complaints of long COVID (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 214). Of the patients who were able to work, 94 (96%) had reduced their weekly working hours to a median of 12 (IQR 8–23) hours per week or 34% (IQR 22–60) of the hours stated in their contract (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 98). Furthermore 78 (74%) working patients reported adjustments in the content of their work because of their illness (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 102).</p><p id="Par51">At 3-month follow up, 8 (11%) of patients who were not working at baseline due to long COVID were able to resume activities at work (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 72). On average, they were able to work for a median of 9 (IQR 4–32) hours per week (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 8).</p><p id="Par52">Patients who were able to work at baseline but who had reduced their working hours because of long COVID, were not able to work more hours per week at 3-month follow up (median 12 (IQR 8–20), p 0.294). Content of work was no longer adjusted in 6 (9%) of patients (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 68).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Adverse events</title><p id="Par53">In the 232 patients who received HBOT there were 24 unsolicited adverse events. The most common unsolicited adverse event was barotrauma of the middle ear (11 patients). Furthermore, 2 patients had complaints of anxiety/claustrophobia during HBOT, and 1 patient had an episode with symptoms of shortness of breath. And, as stated before, 10 patients experienced worsening of fatigue or other long COVID symptoms during HBOT and terminated treatment before completion.</p><p id="Par54">Solicited events during regular visits were fatigue (65%) and blurry vision (27%), which are common complaints associated with HBOT. These complaints were reversed at 3-month follow up, except for one patient who still experienced blurry vision. A consultation at the ophthalmologist revealed an incipient cataract, not requiring treatment at that time.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par55">Due to the observational nature of this study, a causal effect of HBOT can certainly not be established. However, the results from this registry do demonstrate that 56–63% of long COVID patients treated with HBOT report increased quality of life 3 months after HBOT. The largest improvement was seen on social functioning, energy/fatigue, and physical functioning. Furthermore, there was a major reduction of severe to extreme cognitive symptoms 3 months after treatment. Only a fraction of patients had made steps in reintegration at work at 3-month follow up.</p><p id="Par56">A deterioration of long COVID complaints at 3-month follow up was found in 13–19% of patients and was seen more frequently in the group of patients who received an extended treatment. The worsening of long COVID after HBOT was not reported in earlier research but represents an important safety signal. Given the high prevalence of post-exertional malaise and heavy symptom burden, HBOT treatment may be too exhausting for certain patients in this specific patient group, worsening their condition. The deterioration of long COVID symptoms during/after HBOT have led to adaptations in local protocols for the treatment: a minimum 4 hours of upright activity per day is now a criterion to be eligible for treatment as a proxy for sufficient resilience. Furthermore, patients are informed that an increase in fatigue, malaise or other complaints during HBOT can be a reason for early termination. Regular visits with the hyperbaric physician during the treatment, e.g. every 5 or 10 sessions, can help monitor any changes in the course of the disease.</p><p id="Par57">Other adverse events were mostly minor and reversible. Nonetheless, it should be noted that one patient was diagnosed with incipient cataracts, after complaints of blurry vision did not improve in the months after HBOT. The patient did not have problems with visual acuity before the start of HBOT. Given the nature of this study, a causal effect between HBOT and the occurrence of cataracts cannot be established nor ruled out. Induction of cataracts after HBOT has been described in literature but is associated with treatment schedules of &gt; 100 sessions. However, in a recent overview of the literature from 2024, unpublished results of an ongoing randomized HBOT trial are reported that show development of cataracts in approximately 2% of the patients receiving 20 to 40 sessions (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 120)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. This implies that the incidence of cataracts may be underestimated. For future research it is advised to inform patients about this possible side effect as part of the informed consent procedure. Furthermore, early referral for further examination should be warranted in case complaints of blurry vision do not show improvement within 10 to 12 weeks after treatment.</p><p id="Par58">Local protocol at the hyperbaric chambers was a treatment schedule of 40 sessions, in line with the study that provided the highest level of evidence that is available for this indication at this time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Individual changes in this schedule were made at the discretion of the hyperbaric physician and/or referring physician, which happened in 23% of cases, with an addition of 10 or 20 sessions being most common. The percentage of responders was higher in the group of patients who received an extended treatment (63% versus 53%), but the percentage of negative-responders was also higher in the extended-treatment group (19% versus 11%). Dose-response relationship is an interesting topic for future research, since the burden for patients and the cost of treatment is affected by more or less sessions. Some previous studies have suggested treatment protocols with lower dosage (10–15 sessions) could also be effective<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. However a recently published sham-controlled trial investigating 10 sessions of HBOT did not show a significant difference between groups. It can be argued that in this study dosage was too low (a minimum of 5 sessions was maintained for their per-protocol analysis)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Efrati et al. found a significant difference in a sham controlled trial after 40 sessions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, which is more in line with the standard protocol for established indications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par59">The findings in this study add on to previously reported results but are unique with regards to the number of patients included and the longer-term follow. Furthermore, it provides real-life insight into the current situation in the Netherlands and the type and number of patients who opt for off-label therapy when made available. Moreover, the included patients are patients with more severe symptoms and of longer duration than the earlier studies.</p><sec id="Sec18"><title>Strengths</title><p id="Par60">A strength of the current study is that it took place in a real-life, clinical setting, with a diverse group of patients. We feel the current study functions as a proof of concept for successfully treating long COVID symptoms with HBOT in patients who are able to undergo the therapy. Since the infrastructure to provide this therapy is already in place, there are no concerns for the applicability of this treatment in clinical practice. Furthermore, we have used multiple questionnaires to measure improvement in quality of life in different domains, and symptoms specifically related to long COVID. The results are maintained for at least three months, and follow up one year after treatment is planned to investigate long-term results as well. As indicated in the protocol for a systematic review by Li et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, there is a lack of evidence for the application of HBOT for long COVID syndrome. We feel the current study provides a valuable addition to the currently available, but sparse data. Especially since we included not just clinical parameters but also real-life data such a return to work.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par61">Limitations of this study are the lack of a control group, possible selection and confirmation biases and the questionnaires that were used. Given the uncontrolled nature of this study, a causal effect of HBOT on the outcomes cannot be established. A control group would have served to notice natural improvement in time and address confounders such as the Placebo/Hawthorne or sham effect. Such effects can be expected since the sham controlled studies also show improvements in the sham group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. In our study the median time from COVID infection to the start of HBOT was 20 months, which makes natural resolution of symptoms less likely; as studies suggest that recovery of long COVID appears to plateau after 6–12 months after infection, and few patients achieve full remission<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. The 1-year follow up (expected September 2025) can give more information on the Placebo/Hawthorne/sham effect, as these effects are expected to diminish over time. Nonetheless, more randomized (sham-)controlled trials are needed to establish a causal effect. A randomized controlled trial is planned in the Netherlands in which the data of this registry will serve as pilot-data.</p><p id="Par62">Furthermore, the population in this study is comprised of patients who were able to (1) undergo the therapy and (2) finance their own treatment, since it is currently applied off-label. This has undoubtedly led to a selection bias of patients with enough means and capacities for this treatment, and who are highly motivated to complete the treatment. This motivation could also lead to confirmation bias as any improvement in symptoms might get attributed to the treatment. We feel this effect is limited, since there is still a substantial amount of non- or negative responders in the population.</p><p id="Par63">Finally, in this study, standard of care patient-reported outcomes (i.e. SF-36 and EQ-5D) were used. On top of this, a specific long COVID complaints questionnaire was added, as well as questions regarding work history. Although this set gives an important impression of the disease burden and improvement over time, a more comprehensive assessment would be of interest, for example more specifically focused on other specific disease aspects of long COVID such as post-exertional malaise burden and dysautonomia features. Recently, an international core outcome set for long COVID was proposed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. For future prospective studies we aim to take such disease specific outcomes and features into account.</p><p id="Par64">In conclusion, the majority of patients who opted for HBOT reported a significant and clinically relevant increase in quality of life 3 months after treatment. However, a minority of patients reported a significant and relevant deterioration after HBOT. A high percentage of patients who experienced severe to extreme cognitive complaints at baseline reported a reduction in severity at 3 month follow-up. a small percentage of patients previously absent through sickness were able to return to work 3 months after treatment. These findings add onto previous research showing the potential of HBOT in long COVID in improving symptoms in moderate-severely affected and long-term ill patients with long COVID with sufficient resilience to undergo this intensive treatment. These registry data lay a fundament on setting up prospective clinical controlled trials for HBOT confirming the results and investigating dose-response and most likely responders.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_11539_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank all participants of the study for their contributions. Furthermore, we would like to thank the personnel of all participating hyperbaric centers for their efforts in providing their best patient care and collecting outcome data.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JB: data collection, data analysis, interpretation of data, writing the main manuscript including tables and figuresRL: data collection, interpretation of data, manuscript reviewDJ: data collection, manuscript reviewME: corresponding author, interpretation of data, manuscript reviewCL: co-writing the main manuscript, interpretation of data, manuscript review.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>An external electronic data capture system (Castor EDC) was used to document and store patient information. Data can be provided upon reasonable request from the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par65">JB, DJ, CL are employed by Eurocept Clinics and RL is employed by Hyperbaric Medical Centre Rijswijk, in which none of the authors have ownership or shares. The authors declare no personal conflict of interest or financial benefits as a result of this publication.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimated global proportions of individuals with persistent fatigue, cognitive, and respiratory symptom clusters following symptomatic COVID-19 in 2020 and 2021</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2022</year><volume>328</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1604</fpage><lpage>1615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36215063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2022.18931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9552043</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Hanson, S. W. et al. Estimated global proportions of individuals with persistent fatigue, cognitive, and respiratory symptom clusters following symptomatic COVID-19 in 2020 and 2021. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic><bold>328</bold> (16), 1604–1615 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36215063</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2022.18931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9552043</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kuang, S. et al. Experiences of Canadians with long-term symptoms following COVID-19. <italic toggle="yes">Statistics Canada</italic>. (2023). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/pub/75-006-x/2023001/article/00015-eng.htm">https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/pub/75-006-x/2023001/article/00015-eng.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Author correction: long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>408</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37069455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-023-00896-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10408714</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Davis, H. E., McCorkell, L., Vogel, J. M. &amp; Topol, E. J. Author correction: long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. <italic toggle="yes">Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</italic><bold>21</bold> (6), 408 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37069455</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-023-00896-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10408714</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fineberg</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worku</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldowitz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A long COVID definition: a chronic, systemic disease state with profound consequences</article-title><source>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, National Academies Press</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17226/27768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39110819</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Fineberg, H. V., Brown, L., Worku, T. &amp; Goldowitz, I. A long COVID definition: a chronic, systemic disease state with profound consequences. <italic toggle="yes">National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, National Academies Press</italic>10.17226/27768 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39110819</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Volberding, P. A., Chu, B. X. &amp; Spicer, C. M. Long-term health effects of COVID-19: disability and function following SARS-CoV-2 infection. <italic toggle="yes">National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, National Academies Press</italic> (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39312610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">C-support, Erasmus, M. C. &amp; Publiekssamenvatting jaar 2. (2023). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.c-support.nu/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/publiekssamenvatting-jaar-2-def.pdf">https://www.c-support.nu/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/publiekssamenvatting-jaar-2-def.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demko</surname><given-names>ZO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two-Year longitudinal study reveals that long COVID symptoms peak and quality of life Nadirs at 6–12 months postinfection</article-title><source>Open. Forum Infect. Dis.</source><year>2024</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>ofae027</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38449921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ofid/ofae027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10917418</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Demko, Z. O. et al. Two-Year longitudinal study reveals that long COVID symptoms peak and quality of life Nadirs at 6–12 months postinfection. <italic toggle="yes">Open. Forum Infect. Dis.</italic><bold>11</bold> (3), ofae027 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38449921</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ofid/ofae027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10917418</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huang, E.T. UHMS Hyperbaric Medicine Indications Manual. 15th ed. Best Publishing (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peña-Villalobos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperbaric oxygen increases stem cell proliferation, angiogenesis and wound-healing ability of WJ-MSCs in diabetic mice</article-title><source>Front. Physiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>995</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30104981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphys.2018.00995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6078002</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Peña-Villalobos, I. et al. Hyperbaric oxygen increases stem cell proliferation, angiogenesis and wound-healing ability of WJ-MSCs in diabetic mice. <italic toggle="yes">Front. Physiol.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 995 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30104981</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphys.2018.00995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6078002</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protection of mitochondrial function and improvement in cognitive recovery in rats treated with hyperbaric oxygen following lateral fluid-percussion injury</article-title><source>J. Neurosurg.</source><year>2007</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>694</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17432723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3171/jns.2007.106.4.687</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Zhou, Z. et al. Protection of mitochondrial function and improvement in cognitive recovery in rats treated with hyperbaric oxygen following lateral fluid-percussion injury. <italic toggle="yes">J. Neurosurg.</italic><bold>106</bold>, 687–694 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17432723</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3171/jns.2007.106.4.687</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Efrati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperbaric oxygen induces late neuroplasticity in post stroke patients—Randomized, prospective trial</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e53716</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23335971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0053716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3546039</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Efrati, S. et al. Hyperbaric oxygen induces late neuroplasticity in post stroke patients—Randomized, prospective trial. <italic toggle="yes">PloS One</italic>. <bold>8</bold> (1), e53716 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23335971</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0053716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3546039</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperbaric oxygen May induce angiogenesis in patients suffering from prolonged post-concussion syndrome due to traumatic brain injury</article-title><source>Restor. Neurol. Neurosci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26484702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3233/RNN-150585</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Tal, S. et al. Hyperbaric oxygen May induce angiogenesis in patients suffering from prolonged post-concussion syndrome due to traumatic brain injury. <italic toggle="yes">Restor. Neurol. Neurosci.</italic><bold>33</bold> (6), 943–951 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26484702</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3233/RNN-150585</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperbaric oxygen therapy for the treatment of long COVID: early evaluation of a highly promising intervention</article-title><source>Clin. Med.</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e629</fpage><lpage>e632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7861/clinmed.2021-0462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8806311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34862223</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Robbins, T. et al. Hyperbaric oxygen therapy for the treatment of long COVID: early evaluation of a highly promising intervention. <italic toggle="yes">Clin. Med.</italic><bold>21</bold> (6), e629–e632 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7861/clinmed.2021-0462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8806311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34862223</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaiyat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperbaric oxygen treatment for long coronavirus disease-19: a case report</article-title><source>J. Med. Case Rep.</source><year>2022</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>80</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35168680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13256-022-03287-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8848789</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Bhaiyat, A. et al. Hyperbaric oxygen treatment for long coronavirus disease-19: a case report. <italic toggle="yes">J. Med. Case Rep.</italic><bold>16</bold> (1), 80 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35168680</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13256-022-03287-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8848789</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilberman-Itskovich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperbaric oxygen therapy improves neurocognitive functions and symptoms of post-COVID condition: randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11252</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35821512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-15565-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9276805</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Zilberman-Itskovich, S. et al. Hyperbaric oxygen therapy improves neurocognitive functions and symptoms of post-COVID condition: randomized controlled trial. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>12</bold> (1), 11252 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35821512</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-15565-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9276805</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadanny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long term outcomes of hyperbaric oxygen therapy in post Covid condition: longitudinal follow-up of a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3604</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38360929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-024-53091-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10869702</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Hadanny, A. et al. Long term outcomes of hyperbaric oxygen therapy in post Covid condition: longitudinal follow-up of a randomized controlled trial. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>14</bold> (1), 3604 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38360929</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-024-53091-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10869702</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Catalogna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of hyperbaric oxygen therapy on functional and structural connectivity in post-COVID-19 condition patients: A randomized, sham-controlled trial</article-title><source>NeuroImage Clin.</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>103218</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36208548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.nicl.2022.103218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9528018</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Catalogna, M. et al. Effects of hyperbaric oxygen therapy on functional and structural connectivity in post-COVID-19 condition patients: A randomized, sham-controlled trial. <italic toggle="yes">NeuroImage Clin.</italic><bold>36</bold>, 103218 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36208548</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.nicl.2022.103218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9528018</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of hyperbaric oxygen therapy on myocardial function in post-COVID-19 syndrome patients: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9473</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37301934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-36570-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10257166</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Leitman, M. et al. The effect of hyperbaric oxygen therapy on myocardial function in post-COVID-19 syndrome patients: a randomized controlled trial. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>13</bold> (1), 9473 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37301934</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-36570-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10257166</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>García Estévez</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>López Pérez</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gómez márquez, H. Hyperbaric oxygen therapy in long-COVID-19 disease. Oxigenoterapia hiperbárica En La Enfermedad Por COVID-19 persistente</article-title><source>Med. Clin.</source><year>2023</year><volume>161</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.medcli.2023.06.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37775412</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">García Estévez, D. A. &amp; López Pérez, Á. Gómez márquez, H. Hyperbaric oxygen therapy in long-COVID-19 disease. Oxigenoterapia hiperbárica En La Enfermedad Por COVID-19 persistente. <italic toggle="yes">Med. Clin.</italic><bold>161</bold> (11), 498–499 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.medcli.2023.06.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37775412</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindenmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immediate and long-Term effects of hyperbaric oxygenation in patients with long COVID-19 syndrome using SF-36 survey and VAS score: A clinical pilot study</article-title><source>J. Clin. Med.</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>6253</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37834897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm12196253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10573231</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Lindenmann, J. et al. Immediate and long-Term effects of hyperbaric oxygenation in patients with long COVID-19 syndrome using SF-36 survey and VAS score: A clinical pilot study. <italic toggle="yes">J. Clin. Med.</italic><bold>12</bold> (19), 6253 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37834897</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm12196253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10573231</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitala</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preliminary research on the effect of hyperbaric oxygen therapy in patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome</article-title><source>J. Clin. Med.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>308</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36615108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm12010308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9821575</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Kitala, D. et al. Preliminary research on the effect of hyperbaric oxygen therapy in patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome. <italic toggle="yes">J. Clin. Med.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 308 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36615108</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm12010308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9821575</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of hyperbaric oxygen therapy on long COVID: A systematic review</article-title><source>Life (Basel Switzerland)</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>438</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38672710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/life14040438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11051078</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Wu, B. Q. et al. Effects of hyperbaric oxygen therapy on long COVID: A systematic review. <italic toggle="yes">Life (Basel Switzerland)</italic>. <bold>14</bold> (4), 438 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38672710</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/life14040438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11051078</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nerderlandse Vereniging van Hyperbare Geneeskunde. (2023). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nvvhg.nl/hyperbare-zuurstoftherapie-bij-patienten-met-long-covid/">https://nvvhg.nl/hyperbare-zuurstoftherapie-bij-patienten-met-long-covid/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UHMS HBO Indications. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.uhms.org/resources/featured-resources/hbo-indications.html">https://www.uhms.org/resources/featured-resources/hbo-indications.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Module Hyperbare zuurstoftherapie bij. langdurige klachten na COVID-19 (included in ‘Related Files’ and planned to be published soon).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Corral</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Minimal clinically important differences in EQ-5D-5L index and VAS after a respiratory muscle training program in individuals experiencing Long-Term Post-COVID-19 symptoms</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2522</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37760964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines11092522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10526144</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Del Corral, T. et al. Minimal clinically important differences in EQ-5D-5L index and VAS after a respiratory muscle training program in individuals experiencing Long-Term Post-COVID-19 symptoms. <italic toggle="yes">Biomedicines</italic><bold>11</bold> (9), 2522 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37760964</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines11092522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10526144</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bennett, M. H. &amp; Cooper, J. S. Hyperbaric Oxygen Therapy and Associated Cataracts. <italic toggle="yes">In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing</italic>. (2024). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK470454/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK470454/</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29261974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kjellberg, A. et al. Ten sessions of hyperbaric oxygen versus Sham treatment in patients with long Covid (HOT-LoCO): a randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind, phase II trial. <italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic><bold>15</bold>(4), e094386 (2025). 10.1136/bmjopen-2024-094386<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2024-094386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11997836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40228859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of hyperbaric oxygen therapy for long COVID: a protocol for systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMJ Open.</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e083868</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2024-083868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11138265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38806438</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Li, Y. et al. Efficacy and safety of hyperbaric oxygen therapy for long COVID: a protocol for systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open.</italic><bold>14</bold> (5), e083868 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2024-083868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11138265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38806438</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munblit</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PC-COS project steering committee. A core outcome set for post-COVID-19 condition in adults for use in clinical practice and research: an international Delphi consensus study</article-title><source>Lancet Respiratory Med.</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(22)00169-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9197249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35714658</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Munblit, D. et al. PC-COS project steering committee. A core outcome set for post-COVID-19 condition in adults for use in clinical practice and research: an international Delphi consensus study. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet Respiratory Med.</italic><bold>10</bold> (7), 715–724 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(22)00169-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9197249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35714658</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>