<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3819</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmccmt</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2662-7671</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12661764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12661764.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12661764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12661764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41316170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-025-05161-w</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5161</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Experiences with Qi and changes in post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC) symptoms with qigong: a qualitative analysis of participants’ experiences in a pilot clinical trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joy</surname><given-names initials="M">Monica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names initials="N">Nicole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanuck</surname><given-names initials="M">Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dossett</surname><given-names initials="ML">Michelle L.</given-names></name><address><email>mdossett@health.ucdavis.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05rrcem69</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27860.3b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9684</institution-id><institution>University of California Davis School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Sacramento, CA U.S.A. </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05rrcem69</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27860.3b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9684</institution-id><institution>Department of Internal Medicine, </institution><institution>University of California Davis, </institution></institution-wrap>Sacramento, CA U.S.A. </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04ztqy570</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430980.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0395 4002</institution-id><institution>Sacramento VA Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Mather, CA U.S.A. </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Division of General Internal Medicine, 4150 V St., Suite 2400, Sacramento, CA 95817 U.S.A. </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478408</issue-id><elocation-id>434</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-29 16:25:14.893"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12906_2025_Article_5161.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Commonly known as “long COVID”, post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC) is a chronic condition with no validated treatment that significantly impacts the quality of life of those affected. Qigong is a Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM) practice that may serve as a possible therapeutic approach for PASC. This study explored participants’ experiences with qi, and changes in PASC symptoms, following participation in a clinical trial of group-based, combined external and internal qigong for individuals with PASC.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A qualitative study of 26 individuals who participated in a pilot feasibility trial of qigong for PASC symptoms was performed. Participants engaged in six weekly, two-hour sessions of external and internal qigong delivered in a group-based format. Upon completion of the intervention, all participants were interviewed using a semi-structured interview guide. The interviews were transcribed, coded and analyzed using a conventional content analysis approach to explore participants’ perceptions and understanding of qi, qigong, and the overall impact of the sessions on their well-being and PASC symptoms.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Participants’ understanding and explanations of qi varied. Almost all participants (92%) reported feeling qi during the sessions, and a variety of different sensations associated with perception of qi were described. Approximately three-quarters of participants experienced improvement in one or more PASC symptoms, most commonly fatigue, “brain fog”, and sleep quality, and 85% reported improved well-being. Additionally, participants frequently cited the group-based nature of the intervention as a positive aspect of their experience.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The qigong intervention was well-received by participants, with the majority perceiving qi and reporting improvements in PASC-related symptoms and overall well-being. These findings suggest that many individuals may be able to perceive qi and that group-delivered combined external and internal qigong may be a beneficial complementary therapy for managing PASC symptoms. As this is a pilot study with a small sample size and a single qigong teacher, results must be interpreted cautiously. Further research is warranted to evaluate the effects of qigong in this patient population.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial registration</title><p id="Par5">Registry: ClinicalTrials.gov. Trial Registration Number: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT05675995">NCT05675995</ext-link>. Date of Registration: January 4, 2023.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Qigong</kwd><kwd>Biofield therapies</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Post-Acute COVID-19 syndrome</kwd><kwd>Qualitative research</kwd><kwd>Traditional chinese medicine</kwd><kwd>Integrative medicine</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Yanuck Family Trust</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>UC Davis Community Physicians Group</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par10">It is estimated that 6.9% of United States adults, and more than 65 million people worldwide, have suffered from post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] (PASC, commonly known as “long COVID”), a chronic condition that can affect nearly every organ system and varies in clinical presentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. PASC is defined as symptoms that persist at least 3 months following a COVID-19 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The most common symptoms associated with PASC are fatigue/post-exertional malaise, myalgias, arthralgias, depression and anxiety, “brain fog” (i.e. problems concentrating or thinking), cough, dyspnea, and sleep disturbance. There are no current validated treatments for PASC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], and prognosis is unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. With 44% of patients with PASC unable to work at all, and 51% reducing their working hours, PASC is responsible for an estimated $50 billion in lost income annually and increased medical spending of $9000 per person [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">Given the burden of disability from PASC, new therapies are urgently needed. There is growing evidence that integrative medicine approaches are beneficial for many chronic health conditions, and it has been suggested that Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM), qigong, and group-based integrative interventions may be beneficial for treating PASC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. One such therapy that has not been studied is external qigong, a biofield therapy. Biofield therapies (e.g., reiki, therapeutic touch, external qigong) are based on the premise that there is a subtle energy that permeates and surrounds the human body and can be engaged to help promote healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Despite the controversial nature of biofield therapies, some studies have shown potential benefits. For example, external qigong may reduce chronic pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Qigong works with “qi,” which is considered to be “a ubiquitous resource of nature that sustains human well-being and assists in healing disease” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Different forms of qigong, such as internal movement-based qigong (similar to Tai Chi) and external qigong (a form of non-touch energy healing) have been refined over the last 5000 years and are still practiced today. Qualitative research can provide a deeper understanding of the nuanced participant experience with qigong and the phenomenon of qi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Existing qualitative research on qigong is limited; there are few qualitative studies characterizing patients’ experiences of qi and their understanding of it. This study aims to deepen our understanding of the PASC patient experience with a group-based combined external and internal qigong intervention, the impact of this intervention on participants’ PASC symptoms and overall well-being, and to characterize participants’ understanding and experience of qi.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Participant recruitment and eligibility</title><p id="Par12">This qualitative study was embedded in a prospective randomized controlled trial approved by the UC Davis Institutional Review Board and registered on ClinicalTrials.gov (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT05675995">NCT05675995</ext-link>). The Standards for Reporting Qualitative Research (SRQR) were followed for this report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Participants were recruited from the UC Davis Pulmonary Specialty Clinic (a clinic that serves PASC patients), UC Davis-affiliated primary care clinics and federally qualified health centers, Studypages, and social media advertising. To be eligible for inclusion in the study, participants were required to be English-speaking adults with a history of a COVID-19 infection associated with lingering symptoms lasting longer than 12 weeks. Individuals with COVID-related shortness of breath and evidence of parenchymal lung damage on imaging (or FVC &lt; 80% on pulmonary function testing), dementia, a history of exposure to agent orange, an active pregnancy, active episode of psychosis, mania, or severe depression, active infection or substance abuse disorder(s), or any other condition that would make it difficult for the individual to complete questionnaires or attend the qigong sessions were excluded from the study. Upon determining eligibility, informed consent was obtained for all enrolled participants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study design and intervention</title><p id="Par13">The study intervention consisted of six weekly small group sessions of external qigong followed by a brief internal qigong practice. The qigong interventions were led by a trained practitioner (MY) who, during the external qigong practice, facilitated the release of turbid qi/retained energy of trauma with the intention of promoting healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. At the first session, all participants were provided with a brief explanation and demonstration of qi (qi tangibility exercise). During the qi tangibility exercise, participants were invited to scan about six to eight inches above the practitioner’s hand and forearm to perceive points of qi. Next, participants took turns receiving the external qigong intervention as the rest of the group observed. During the intervention, participants were stationary and situated in a comfortable seated position. External qigong was conducted while the hands of the qigong practitioner were at least six inches away from the participant’s body, starting around the participant’s head and usually moving downwards. External qigong was individualized to each person, and the specific healing movement and length of treatment varied by participant and session, depending on the practitioner’s perception of the participant’s qi status. Typically, the feeling of qi left the practitioner’s hand after several minutes, so to signal the end of the intervention. After all of the participants had received the external qigong intervention, the group was invited to participate in a brief internal qigong self-practice exercise, so that the participants would have the means to release any turbid qi on their own in-between sessions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Unlike most forms of internal qigong that involve movement, this practice involved minimal effort or exertion and was more like a meditation. The seated self-practice consisted of three phases: (1) breathing into the dantien (the vital energy center located about three inches below the navel and believed to be the body’s main storage area for qi), (2) feeling a qi ball between the palms for a few minutes, and (3) connecting with a feeling of the universal qi at the top of the head and feeling energy in the head and hands.</p><p id="Par14">The sessions were each approximately two hours long, and group size ranged from two to nine participants. Qigong sessions were held at a primary care clinic affiliated with UC Davis on Saturday mornings when no other patients or clinic staff were present.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Qualitative interviews</title><p id="Par15">Within two weeks of completing the final group qigong session, study participants underwent a semi-structured interview regarding their experience as a participant in the study. All participants who completed the intervention were interviewed. Interviews were performed by one of two investigators (NA, MJ) who received training from an experienced qualitative researcher (MD). Interviews were audio recorded and ranged from 8 to 42 min in length. Each interview included the same series of questions, with probes to seek additional information so that participants could expand on any answers and provide additional input. The interviews queried about participant understanding and experience of qi and the practice of qigong, the impact of the group qigong sessions on their PASC symptoms and overall well-being, and their subjective experience of the study as a whole (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Interview questions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">How would you describe qigong to someone who doesn’t know anything about it?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">What did you feel, if anything, in terms of qi during the sessions? Did that change over time?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Did you notice any changes in your long-COVID symptoms during this study? Please explain.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Do you think the qigong sessions affected your symptoms or sense of well-being in any way? Please explain.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Is there anything else that you would like to tell us about your experience with qigong?</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Qualitative analysis</title><p id="Par16">Interviews were transcribed and a conventional content analysis approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] was used to qualitatively analyze the semi-structured interview data in an attempt to understand participants’ experiences without any a priori guiding theory. Three team members (NA, MJ, and MD) served as the primary coders for analysis. NA is a clinical research coordinator, and MJ is a medical student. Both NA and MJ were involved in study participant recruitment and data collection and took attendance at the sessions. They were not involved in the delivery of the qigong intervention. MD is an integrative medicine researcher who has some personal experience with internal qigong and had minimal to no contact with the study participants. None of the team members had any prior experience with external qigong. During the initial phase of coding, all three study team members individually engaged in a process of iterative immersion/crystallization with the transcribed interview data, reading through portions of transcripts and pausing to reflect on participants’ experiences until patterns and themes began to emerge that could be meaningfully expressed as categories and subcategories, creating codes.</p><p id="Par17">After this process was completed independently by each of the three coders with one third of the transcribed interviews, the study team met to discuss their initial set of codes and their overall impressions of the data. Based on this discussion, the team created a collective draft of codes and returned to the next one-third of transcripts, repeating the process above and meeting once again to discuss revised codes and insights. This cycle of repeated immersion/crystallization and code revision with subsequent meetings was repeated until a final set of codes was agreed upon by all three members of the study team. Using this set of codes, NA and MJ revised and reviewed their coding, re-reading transcripts and quotes to ensure that all unique participant perspectives were captured.</p><p id="Par18">Based on the information provided in each interview, and blinded to the other’s coding, NA and MJ individually reviewed each transcript and coded whether participants reported experiencing an improvement in their PASC symptoms (overall and also regarding specific symptoms), overall well-being, and the extent to which they were able to perceive/feel qi. Any discrepancies in coding were resolved through the use of a “tie-breaker” in which MD made the final coding determination.</p><p id="Par19">Participants were also asked to self-identify their PASC symptoms (free text response on the baseline questionnaire), and these symptoms were tallied to characterize the frequencies of the various PASC symptoms within this patient cohort.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Demographics and baseline characteristics</title><p id="Par20">Twenty-six participants completed the study and agreed to complete exit interviews which were coded and included in the analysis. These 26 participants ranged from 25 to 79 years of age; 73.1% of participants were female, 84.6% White and 11.5% Hispanic (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Average duration of PASC symptoms was 24.7 months (range 4–47). The most commonly reported PASC symptoms prior to starting the study intervention were fatigue, “brain fog” (i.e. problems concentrating or thinking), and shortness of breath (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Participant demographics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participants (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 26)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, mean (SD), years</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.9 (14.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female, %</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male, %</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hispanic, %</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> White, %</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Asian, %</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> American Indian or Alaska Native, %</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Other, %</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PASC symptom duration, mean (SD), months</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.7 (11.6)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>PASC symptoms reported by participants at baseline</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PASC Symptoms</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">% Affected</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">“Brain fog” (i.e. problems concentrating or thinking)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shortness of breath</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Digestive symptoms (i.e. diarrhea, stomach pain, constipation)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Myalgias</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Palpitations/tachycardia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dizziness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sleep disturbances</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arthralgias</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-exertional malaise</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Loss of taste and/or smell</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muscle weakness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Memory loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paresthesias</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chest pain, tightness, or pressure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tinnitus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vision impairment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Impaired thermoregulation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tremor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rash</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Positional orthostatic Tachycardia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dysuria</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Depression</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cough</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Changes in Menstruation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hair Loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decreased Libido</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Understanding of qigong</title><p id="Par21">Participants were asked, “How would you describe qigong to someone who doesn’t know anything about it?” Their descriptions of qigong varied, sharing a few common themes. Qigong was commonly described as working with the energy of oneself, a practitioner, and other people to promote healing and to release energy blockages.</p><p id="Par22">
<disp-quote><p id="Par23"><italic toggle="yes">“There are energy centers in your body and you’re trying to</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> sort of like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> focus on the flow of energy through your body and</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> figure out where energy is being blocked and release that.” (ID 16)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par24">
<disp-quote><p id="Par25"><italic toggle="yes">“I describe it to people as the Chinese energy work that has been used for many</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> many years to help equalize a person’s energy level so there’s no blockages.” (ID 45)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par26">
<disp-quote><p id="Par27"><italic toggle="yes">“I would say it relates to your energy</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and someone else stepping into your energy to kind of recharge your energy and almost fix it by just connecting with you. It’s a connection.” (ID 43)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par28">Sometimes the description of qigong referenced the practitioner, Dr. Yanuck, and the explanation of qigong he provided in the first group session.</p><p id="Par29">
<disp-quote><p id="Par30"><italic toggle="yes">“Let’s say like it involves a lot of energy healing and how Dr. Yanuck explained it</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it was like releasing the retained energy of trauma</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> which made more sense like in the terms that he said.” (ID 18)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par31">
<disp-quote><p id="Par32"><italic toggle="yes">“Dr. Yanuck was connecting our energy to the universal qi</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> which is like a blueprint that our body can learn from</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> essentially releasing retained energy of prior trauma</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> whether it be emotional</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> mental</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> physical</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> as to allow our system to jumpstart back into a higher functioning state. So</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> for this study specifically</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it was addressing the multiple injuries caused by long COVID.” (ID 30)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par33">Qigong was also described as a restful and calming experience, a type of Eastern medicine and self-healing that involves connecting with a universal energy.</p><p id="Par34">
<disp-quote><p id="Par35"><italic toggle="yes">“For me</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it’s been getting me into</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> this restful state where you learn to tap into the energy of your body. And the goal is to kind of have that energy that’s stored up</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> energy from trauma</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> of which COVID has been traumatic in your body</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> to try to get that trauma out of your body.” (ID 6)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par36">
<disp-quote><p id="Par37"><italic toggle="yes">“A way of getting you to connect with the central energy forces within your body and with</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> the earth.” (ID 44)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par38">
<disp-quote><p id="Par39"><italic toggle="yes">“There is this energy force I knew about</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but never really knew how to take advantage of it</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I guess</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> or harness it in some way.” (ID 57)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par40">Some participants used metaphors to explain qigong.</p><p id="Par41">
<disp-quote><p id="Par42"><italic toggle="yes">“You live in a house</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it’s just a regular house. And then suddenly</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you open up the plank in the floor</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and there’s a diamond</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and it’s not just a diamond under the floor - suddenly it’s everywhere</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and it’s beautiful</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and it’s powerful.” (ID 23)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par43">While many participants provided explanations related to energy, a few did not know how to explain qigong at all.</p><p id="Par44">
<disp-quote><p id="Par45"><italic toggle="yes">“I don’t feel qualified to describe it</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> because I don’t think I actually really understand it.” (ID 14)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Experience of Qi</title><p id="Par46">The majority of study participants reported perceiving, or feeling, qi (92%), and their experience of qi varied across participants as well as within participants over the course of the study. Qi was often described by participants as “energy”, sometimes a ball of energy or a movement of energy felt throughout the body. Qi was perceived in themselves, in other study participants, and in the instructor, and was often felt most strongly in their own hands.</p><p id="Par47">
<disp-quote><p id="Par48"><italic toggle="yes">“I felt the warmth</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like a ball. … Ball of energy. And that was what I felt the first time. But then the subsequent sessions</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I felt that energy beyond the ball and more</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> throughout my body</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> radiating through my body. And I could feel the energy from other participants at times. Yeah</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it was just… It was really bizarre</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and it was a good feeling.” (ID 44)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par49">Descriptions of the feeling of qi included temperature changes (warmth, coolness), a breeze, tingling, static or electricity, pressure or heaviness, and magnetism.</p><p id="Par50">
<disp-quote><p id="Par51"><italic toggle="yes">“The sensations that I felt were more of like cool air</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> coming from my hands in particular</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and my arm</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I did feel that. I felt a magnetism sensation</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and I did feel some tingling on my crown</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> on the top of my head.” (ID 49)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par52">
<disp-quote><p id="Par53"><italic toggle="yes">“As we practiced each week</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I started to feel the cold … And it’s fascinating because you think it’s coming from the air on the ceiling</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but it’s really</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> what you’re feeling is in your hands … Not knowing what to expect and then actually feeling the sensations was incredible. " (ID 10)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par54">
<disp-quote><p id="Par55"><italic toggle="yes">“During the sessions</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I had a feeling of warmth</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> relaxation and tingling.” (ID 39)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par56">Some participants experienced physical sensations, a release of tension, and/or emotional experiences.</p><p id="Par57">
<disp-quote><p id="Par58"><italic toggle="yes">“We would experience a lot of physical symptoms that were interesting</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> such as our heart rates fluttering or</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I know at one time I got a little sweaty or</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I would become hot. And</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I don’t know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it’s a… I guess it was a physical manifestation of the qigong</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> is feeling it during the sessions.” (ID 12)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par59">Participants described the experience of qi as comfortable, non-painful, and relaxing.</p><p id="Par60">
<disp-quote><p id="Par61"><italic toggle="yes">“It was overall a kind of sense of overall relaxation</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> very pleasant</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and did not feel uncomfortable.” (ID 50)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Effect of qigong on PASC symptoms</title><p id="Par62">When participants were asked how their PASC symptoms changed throughout the course of the study, 73% reported experiencing some improvement in one or more PASC symptoms. For example, 72% of participants reported an overall improvement in their energy levels, 39% of participants reported improvement in “brain fog,” and 20% of participants reported improvement in sleep.</p><p id="Par63">
<disp-quote><p id="Par64"><italic toggle="yes">“It helps with pain relief</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and memory</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> brain fog. I think it helped with everything. … I felt better after each class and it has continued to help.” (ID 36)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par65">
<disp-quote><p id="Par66"><italic toggle="yes">“I’ve been actually sleeping much</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> much better. Well</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> well-rested. I had an issue with lack of energy. That’s been restored. I feel energetic</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> starting to get up at the time that I used to get up before COVID</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> which is around 5:30 or 6:00 in the morning</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and now I’m back to that kind of routine. I had some issues with concentration and kind of a brain fog kind of a thing that has mostly gone away.” (ID 21)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par67">Other PASC symptoms that participants reported improvement in were digestive symptoms, anosmia, arrhythmias, joint pain, headaches, and depression.</p><p id="Par68">
<disp-quote><p id="Par69"><italic toggle="yes">“So</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I was having arrhythmia several times a week. And it was debilitating. There were days I’d have to miss school and stuff because I could not walk. I couldn’t</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I couldn’t hardly breathe. It was just miserable. Well</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> during the month of April</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> which I was in qigong</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> the entire time</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I only had three episodes the entire month. I only had three episodes. Instead of multiple each week.” (ID 35)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par70">
<disp-quote><p id="Par71"><italic toggle="yes">“I feel better</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> meaning like the joints weren’t so achy … I noticed my smell was coming back.” (ID 17)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par72">
<disp-quote><p id="Par73"><italic toggle="yes">“I am a firm believer that it was the power of qigong</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> that healing energy that helped my heart go from being in a rapid a-fib to normal sinus rhythm.” (ID 63)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par74">
<disp-quote><p id="Par75"><italic toggle="yes">“My depression has been lessened. … I developed this rash with COVID … And I noticed on the last day of class when I looked out at my arm</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> the rash wasn’t there.” (ID 44)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par76">Of the participants who experienced symptom improvement, the degree of improvement ranged from complete resolution of symptoms to mild relief. Some participants reported symptom improvement that only lasted temporarily, some noted improvement in some PASC symptoms while other symptoms remained unaffected, and some reported no change in their symptoms at all.</p><p id="Par77">
<disp-quote><p id="Par78"><italic toggle="yes">“The POTS is 100% resolved. My oxygen is usually fluctuating anywhere between 96% and 100%. I no longer use my oxygen. I am back to work in the office full time. I’m no longer bedridden</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I do not have pain</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and my muscles do not give out</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I’m dancing with my kids again</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I’m out and about</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I’m socializing</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I’m in public</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I essentially feel as though qigong gave me like my life back. … The people closest to me say that I got the sparkle back in my eyes</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> my energy levels are higher</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I am more focused and in tune at work</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I’m knocking stuff out faster. I just feel like I woke up from a horrible nightmare. Essentially</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I feel like I’m myself again.” (ID 30)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par79">
<disp-quote><p id="Par80"><italic toggle="yes">“I do feel like I have improved from like where I was at at the beginning. … I don’t feel like it cured my long COVID unfortunately</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but I do think it helped.” (ID 9)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par81">
<disp-quote><p id="Par82"><italic toggle="yes">“I didn’t feel bad after the session by any means</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but I didn’t feel anything was changing. … I think it was good experience for me. I just</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> again</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I just don’t know whether it helped me</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> to be determined.” (ID 11)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par83">Participants’ perceptions of qi were compared to improvement in PASC symptoms (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). 79% of participants who perceived qi to some extent (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24) experienced improvement in PASC symptoms. Conversely, the two participants who reported no perception of qi did not experience any symptom improvement.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Qi Perception and PASC Symptom Improvement. Participants’ ability to feel qi and their experience of symptom improvement were based on descriptions provided in participant interviews. Symptom improvement was coded as sustained improvement in PASC symptoms that varied from partial to complete</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1165" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12906_2025_5161_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Group dynamic</title><p id="Par84">Almost every participant discussed positive aspects of the group experience in their interview. Participants described a sense of community that was formed in the study group, along with an understanding and validation of their experience living with PASC.</p><p id="Par85">
<disp-quote><p id="Par86"><italic toggle="yes">“Getting to talk about what they were going through was actually just as helpful as whatever the qigong might have done</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I think. … Knowing that other people were going through the same thing</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> what they were going through and sharing that</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> helps my mental.” (ID 8)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par87">
<disp-quote><p id="Par88"><italic toggle="yes">“Not only did some of my symptoms alleviate and I was feeling better</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but it was also like a group therapy at the same time and that was really helpful. … That we were in person</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I think was key</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and that we could all share our unfortunate journey with long COVID</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and we relate to each other.” (ID 39)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par89">A few participants shared the positive experience of meeting another person with PASC for the first time.</p><p id="Par90">
<disp-quote><p id="Par91"><italic toggle="yes">“I never met somebody else with long COVID</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> because it’s been an isolated experience. And then coming to sessions week after week</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> having folks that have gone through similar symptoms and how they’re managing it … it was just really nice to be surrounded by a group of individuals who knew what we were going through.” (ID 50)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par92">
<disp-quote><p id="Par93"><italic toggle="yes">“I just have a better understanding of what long COVID is</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and I was very relieved to talk to someone else who was also suffering from long COVID.” (ID 20)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Well-Being and a shift in mindset</title><p id="Par94">Participants were asked, “Do you think the qigong sessions affected your symptoms or sense of well-being in any way? Please explain.” Of the 26 participants, 22 reported an improvement in their well-being. The remaining four participants gave a response to the question that was unclear to coders, but no participants definitively reported that their well-being did not improve. When explaining their response, participants described different aspects of their experience in the study and the practice of qigong that may have contributed to this improvement. 40% of participants reported an increased sense of calmness or relaxation, with some describing qigong as a meditative practice.</p><p id="Par95">
<disp-quote><p id="Par96"><italic toggle="yes">“Just sort of like being forced to be there and being forced to like kind of just meditate in a chair for a couple minutes was like very calming.” (ID 16)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par97">Some participants described how they found it beneficial to continue practicing qigong by themselves, or with others, in their daily lives.</p><p id="Par98">
<disp-quote><p id="Par99"><italic toggle="yes">“And I go to it at least once a day</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> just as a practice now to try and really just for me</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> a source of like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like I said</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it’s also kind of like a meditation type of a practice for me as well.“ (ID 6)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par100">
<disp-quote><p id="Par101"><italic toggle="yes">“I’d wake up and I’d have like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> a chest pain</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> which I get periodically</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and I said</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> ‘Oh</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know what</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I’m going to go outside and do the self-guided qigong’</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and that helped. It actually helped. And so</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I’ve used that several times.” (ID 36)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par102">
<disp-quote><p id="Par103"><italic toggle="yes">“Because if I do this before bed</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> or I wake up during [the] night and can’t go back to sleep right away</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> if I do this at ten</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> this will let me go right back to sleep. … Definitely feel like I have a really valuable tool in my tool chest now. … Feeling enabled to have a non-invasive tool</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and a free tool</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> that I can do on my own to help myself and share with others who may be suffering from things like this.” (ID 57)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par104">Separate from any symptom improvement participants experienced, they described an increase in mental/emotional resilience to PASC symptoms, as well as increased resilience to everyday stress.</p><p id="Par105">
<disp-quote><p id="Par106"><italic toggle="yes">“Going through each week and noticing my energy improving</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> my resilience to stress improving</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> my stamina improving.” (ID 57)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par107">
<disp-quote><p id="Par108"><italic toggle="yes">“So</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> now</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> what happened with my symptoms is they’re there</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but I don’t – my reaction to them are not the same as they were. It’s like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> ‘Oh yeah</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> hello friend</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> let’s have some qi’</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> that kind of thing. … I’m more comfortable with what happened and what is happening with me</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and I think I know that that makes the symptoms feel less. … They’re still there</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> my reactions to them are different.” (ID 23)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par109">
<disp-quote><p id="Par110"><italic toggle="yes">“My symptoms are still here</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but they don’t bother me as much</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> or like I am not</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I don’t suffer from them quite as much</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like my attitude about them is different</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> if that makes sense. And</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like I still get winded very easily</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like if I bend down to</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> pick something up off the floor and stand back up</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> … I lose my breath</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like I’ve just ran a marathon</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know? And that still happens to me. But it’s not as distressing as it was before</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I don’t know how else to describe it. … Like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> my recovery from it is easier</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I still deal with insomnia</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but I</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> my attitude after a sleepless night is not so grim. I guess … my general outlook on everything is better.” (ID 58)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par111">Participants also described an increase in hope and positivity as a result of the study.</p><p id="Par112">
<disp-quote><p id="Par113"><italic toggle="yes">“I think our attitude about anything that’s going on with our body is real important. And this gave me</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> this study gave me acknowledgement</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it gave me hope</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and it gave me something that I can work with.” (ID 23)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par114">
<disp-quote><p id="Par115"><italic toggle="yes">“I think it gave me more of a positive outlook.” (ID 43)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par116">
<disp-quote><p id="Par117"><italic toggle="yes">“And this is the first time</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> when I could actually see like</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> being well as a real possibility. Like I’m not there yet</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> but it actually feels like it could be like a real possibility and just having that kind of hope is kind of</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it’s life changing to actually think that that’s a real possibility. Instead of</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> you know</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> like ‘Oh God</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> this is how I have to live forever and ever’. And that kind of doom that comes with it</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I don’t feel that.” (ID 58)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par118">Nested within a pilot randomized controlled trial examining qigong for PASC, we present the first qualitative study of combined external and internal qigong as a treatment for a medical condition. This study explored how patients with PASC experienced and understood qi and examined the patient perspective on how group-based qigong practice impacts PASC symptoms and overall well-being.</p><p id="Par119">Most participants were naive to qigong, yet nearly all of them were able to perceive qi, a novel finding that has not yet been described in the limited qualitative research on qigong [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Participants described external qigong in a variety of ways, including depictions of energy movement, the promotion of healing, and a calming and restful experience. A few participants had difficulty describing this form of energy healing. Participants in this study described their experiences of qi similarly to descriptions in studies on other forms of biofield therapies. In qualitative studies on therapeutic touch, Reiki, pranic healing, and Magdalena energy healing, participants reported experiences of temperature and body sensations, increased awareness, relaxation, symptom changes, post-session drowsiness, and an overall positive experience of the treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par120">In this study, 73% of participants reported some degree of symptom improvement and 85% an increase in their overall well-being. Two study participants were unable to perceive qi and also noted no improvement in symptoms. It is unclear whether the ability to perceive qi is necessary to experience benefit from this therapy, though our data suggests that qi perception itself may not be sufficient.</p><p id="Par121">The positive effect of the intervention on symptoms ranging across body systems and on overall well-being is a finding mirrored in other qualitative studies on other biofield therapies. Interestingly, 40% of participants in our study reported an increased sense of calmness or relaxation, while 68% of participants reported experiencing calmness or relaxation in a qualitative study on the subjective experience of Reiki [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. A qualitative study of energy healing for patients with irritable bowel syndrome and inflammatory bowel disease yielded mixed results with some participants reporting improvements in symptoms, while others noted no change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. A qualitative study of reiki in hospital nurses demonstrated an overall positive effect on sleep quality, though a few participants did not experience any improvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Other studies on biofield therapies have similarly demonstrated improvements in sleep quality, physical symptoms, and psychological well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Participants in two published qualitative studies on internal qigong (for cancer survivors and patients with chronic medical conditions), described improvements in physical and mental health, well-being, and social relationships [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par122">In this study, participants affirmed that the delivery of the intervention in a group setting contributed to their positive experiences, citing a sense of community, validation, and sharing of ideas for symptom management. Group-based interventions have demonstrated statistically significant improvements in pain, self-efficacy, self-care, psychological outcomes, and quality of life for patients with a variety of long-term conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Thus, the group setting in which the qigong intervention was delivered may have contributed to some of the positive outcomes observed. The generally positive effects of group-based interventions, and the relative isolation that many individuals with PASC feel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], suggest that group-based delivery of interventions for this patient population may be particularly helpful and effective.</p><p id="Par123">Limitations in the design of this pilot feasibility study include the small sample size, use of a single qigong instructor, and the multimodal nature of the intervention that makes it impossible to attribute the effects observed to any particular component (i.e., external qigong, internal qigong self-practice, and the group-based nature of the intervention). It is also possible that the intervention components interacted synergistically to facilitate participants’ improved well-being. For example, the internal qigong self-practice may have sensitized participants to benefit more from external qigong or vice versa. Variations in the descriptions of qi may, in part, be due to whether participants were referring to their experience of the external vs. internal qigong practice. Another potential limitation may be bias in that only participants who were open to receiving external qigong were included in the study. Our results may hold more positive views on the intervention for that reason. However, most participants knew little about external qigong, or reported being skeptical, prior to beginning the study. Indeed, witnessing others’ experiences of the qigong intervention may have made some participants more open to exploring it. Strengths include achievement of data saturation in our qualitative analysis. Additionally, all participants who completed the study were interviewed, and study staff who conducted the interviews and analyzed the transcripts were not involved in the intervention itself, with one of the coders abstaining from conducting interviews. Finally, the interview questions did not probe about changes in specific PASC symptoms, so our estimates of symptom-specific improvement may, in fact, be underestimates. Future studies should consider inclusion of a larger sample size with increased racial and ethnic diversity, the use of multiple qigong practitioners, and potentially blinding of participants to the intervention and/or testing individual components of the intervention (e.g., external vs. internal qigong vs. their combination).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par124">This study is one of few qualitative studies of qigong as a treatment for a medical condition. It presents a unique patient perspective on the effects of qigong, as well as insight into participants’ perception and understanding of qi. Most participants were able to perceive qi. The positive preliminary findings of this study warrant further research to evaluate the potential benefits of qigong in this patient population.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>PASC</term><def><p id="Par6">Post-Acute Sequelae of COVID-19</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCM</term><def><p id="Par7">Traditional Chinese Medicine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FVC</term><def><p id="Par8">Forced vital capacity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par9">Standard deviation</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Karen Sherman, PhD for reviewing and providing feedback on the study protocol and interview guide.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>Monica Joy (MJ) and Nicole Adams (NA) recruited study participants, ran study visits, interviewed participants, and coded the study transcripts. MJ synthesized the data and wrote the initial draft of the manuscript. Dr. Michael Yanuck (MY) and Dr. Michelle Dossett (MD) developed the study protocol. MY delivered the qigong intervention. MD developed the question guide, coded transcripts, and oversaw all aspects of the study. All authors reviewed and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was funded by a gift from the Yanuck Family Trust. The project was also supported by the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS), National Institutes of Health (NIH), through grant UL1 TR001860 and the UC Davis Community Physicians Group. The funders had no role in the study design, conduct, analysis, or reporting.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>De-identified data are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par125">This study was approved by the UC Davis Institutional Review Board. All participants provided written informed consent prior to participating in any research activities.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par126">Not required.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par127">MY is the author of a book on qigong. MLD has received royalties from UpToDate for an unrelated topic.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrnsbrak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rekito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence mounts that about 7% of US adults have had long COVID</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2024</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2024.11370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38848092</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Fang Z, Ahrnsbrak R, Rekito A. Evidence mounts that about 7% of US adults have had long COVID. JAMA. 2024;332:5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38848092</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2024.11370</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chippa V, Aleem A, Anjum F. In: StatPearls, editor. Postacute coronavirus (COVID-19) syndrome. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK570608/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK570608/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34033370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Department of Health and Human Services. Office of the assistant secretary for health. National Research Action Plan on Long COVID; 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Committee on Examining the Working Definition for Long COVID, Board on Health Sciences Policy</collab></person-group><source>Board on global health, health and medicine Division, National academies of Sciences, Engineering, and medicine. A long COVID definition: A Chronic, systemic disease state with profound consequences</source><year>2024</year><publisher-loc>Washington, D.C</publisher-loc><publisher-name>National Academies</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39110819</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="book">Committee on Examining the Working Definition for Long COVID, Board on Health Sciences Policy. Board on global health, health and medicine Division, National academies of Sciences, Engineering, and medicine. A long COVID definition: A Chronic, systemic disease state with profound consequences. Washington, D.C.: National Academies; 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39110819</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brondstater</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID management: a mini review of current recommendations and underutilized modalities</article-title><source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source><year>2024</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1430444</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2024.1430444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38947233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11211541</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Dietz TK, Brondstater KN. Long COVID management: a mini review of current recommendations and underutilized modalities. Front Med (Lausanne). 2024;11:1430444.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38947233</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2024.1430444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11211541</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The costs of long COVID</article-title><source>JAMA Health Forum</source><year>2022</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e221809</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2022.1809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36219031</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Cutler DM. The costs of long COVID. JAMA Health Forum. 2022;3:e221809.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36219031</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2022.1809</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addressing the long COVID crisis: integrative health and long COVID</article-title><source>Glob Adv Health Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>216495612110565</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/21649561211056597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8606968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34820152</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Roth A, Chan PS, Jonas W. Addressing the long COVID crisis: integrative health and long COVID. Glob Adv Health Med. 2021;10:216495612110565.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/21649561211056597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8606968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34820152</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carter ES. Acupuncture for the adjunct treatment of long COVID. AAFP. 2023;108(4). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37843933">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37843933</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37843933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Estores</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrative medicine in long COVID</article-title><source>Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am</source><year>2023</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmr.2023.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37419539</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Estores IM, Ackerman P. Integrative medicine in long COVID. Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am. 2023;34:677–88.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37419539</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pmr.2023.03.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID shared medical appointments: lifestyle and mind-body medicine with peer support</article-title><source>Ann Fam Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>383</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.2817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35443975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9328700</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Lin Y, Saper R, Patil SJ. Long COVID shared medical appointments: lifestyle and mind-body medicine with peer support. Ann Fam Med. 2022;20:383.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35443975</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1370/afm.2817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9328700</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">O N JCPBBC. P S, S D. A potential therapeutic approach according to traditional Thai medicine theory for Post-COVID-19 syndrome treatment: an observational Retrospective Clinical Study. PubMed.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38518168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kierkegaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeitelhofer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A call to use the multicomponent exercise Tai Chi to improve recovery from COVID-19 and long COVID</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>827645</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.827645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35296042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8918505</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Castro JP, Kierkegaard M, Zeitelhofer M. A call to use the multicomponent exercise Tai Chi to improve recovery from COVID-19 and long COVID. Front Public Health. 2022;10:827645.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35296042</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2022.827645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8918505</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuchman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denninger</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fricchione</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Qigong for the prevention, treatment, and rehabilitation of COVID-19 infection in older adults</article-title><source>Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year><volume>28</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jagp.2020.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32425471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7227578</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Feng F, Tuchman S, Denninger JW, Fricchione GL, Yeung A. Qigong for the prevention, treatment, and rehabilitation of COVID-19 infection in older adults. Am J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2020;28(8):812–9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32425471</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jagp.2020.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7227578</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">J L, J W, X L, H S. The Role of Traditional Chinese Medicine in COVID-19: Theory, Initial Clinical Evidence, Potential Mechanisms, and Implications. PubMed.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34653019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Matos LC, Machado JP, Monteiro FJ, Greten HJ. Perspectives, measurability and effects of Non-Contact Biofield-Based practices: A Narrative Review of Quantitative Research. 2021;18(12):6397. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34199174/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34199174/</ext-link>. 10.3390/ijerph18126397.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph18126397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8296239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34199174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pittler</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>External qigong for pain conditions: a systematic review of randomized clinical trials</article-title><source>J Pain</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2007.05.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17690012</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Lee MS, Pittler MH, Ernst E. External qigong for pain conditions: a systematic review of randomized clinical trials. J Pain. 2007;8:827–31.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17690012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpain.2007.05.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effects of qigong for adults with chronic pain: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am J Chin Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1525</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S0192415X15500871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26621441</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Bai Z, Guan Z, Fan Y, Liu C, Yang K, Ma B, et al. The effects of qigong for adults with chronic pain: systematic review and meta-analysis. Am J Chin Med. 2015;43:1525–39.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26621441</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1142/S0192415X15500871</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahnke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larkey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Etnier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive review of health benefits of qigong and Tai Chi</article-title><source>Am J Health Promot</source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>e1</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4278/ajhp.081013-LIT-248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20594090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3085832</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Jahnke R, Larkey L, Rogers C, Etnier J, Lin F. A comprehensive review of health benefits of qigong and Tai Chi. Am J Health Promot. 2010;24:e1–25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20594090</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4278/ajhp.081013-LIT-248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3085832</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warber</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruyere</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weintrub</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A consideration of the perspectives of healing practitioners on research into energy healing</article-title><source>Glob Adv Health Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1suppl</issue><fpage>gahmj2015014suppl</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7453/gahmj.2015.014.suppl</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4654782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26665045</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Warber SL, Bruyere RL, Weintrub K. A consideration of the perspectives of healing practitioners on research into energy healing. Glob Adv Health Med. 2015;4(1suppl):gahmj2015014suppl.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7453/gahmj.2015.014.suppl</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4654782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26665045</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Standards for reporting qualitative research: a synthesis of recommendations</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACM.0000000000000388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24979285</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">O’Brien BC, Harris IB, Beckman TJ, Reed DA, Cook DA. Standards for reporting qualitative research: a synthesis of recommendations. Acad Med. 2014;89:1245–51.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24979285</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ACM.0000000000000388</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yanuck M, BioEnerQi. Bioenergy Publishing; 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>H-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three approaches to qualitative content analysis</article-title><source>Qual Health Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732305276687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16204405</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Hsieh H-F, Shannon SE. Three approaches to qualitative content analysis. Qual Health Res. 2005;15:1277–88.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16204405</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1049732305276687</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CDC, Signs, Symptoms of Long COVID. COVID-19. 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/covid/long-term-effects/long-covid-signs-symptoms.html">https://www.cdc.gov/covid/long-term-effects/long-covid-signs-symptoms.html</ext-link>. Accessed 10 Sep 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deleemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberoi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piedalue</surname><given-names>K-A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phenomenological qualitative exploration of mind-body therapy use and effectiveness among young, middle, and older adult cancer survivors</article-title><source>Integr Cancer Ther</source><year>2024</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>15347354241253847</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15347354241253847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38767143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11107309</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Singh S, Nguyen T, Deleemans J, Oberoi D, Piedalue K-A, Carlson LE. A phenomenological qualitative exploration of mind-body therapy use and effectiveness among young, middle, and older adult cancer survivors. Integr Cancer Ther. 2024;23:15347354241253847.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38767143</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/15347354241253847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11107309</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fix</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VanDeusen Lukas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elwy</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bokhour</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biopsychosocial benefits of movement-based complementary and integrative health therapies for patients with chronic conditions</article-title><source>Chronic Illn</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1742395318782377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29914264</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Bolton RE, Fix GM, VanDeusen Lukas C, Elwy AR, Bokhour BG. Biopsychosocial benefits of movement-based complementary and integrative health therapies for patients with chronic conditions. Chronic Illn. 2020;16:41–54.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29914264</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1742395318782377</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soundy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingstone</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experiences of healing therapy in patients with irritable bowel syndrome and inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-015-0611-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4391663</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Soundy A, Lee RT, Kingstone T, Singh S, Shah PR, Roberts L. Experiences of healing therapy in patients with irritable bowel syndrome and inflammatory bowel disease. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2015;15:106.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888247</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12906-015-0611-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4391663</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of the subjective experience of receiving reiki: qualitative results from a pragmatic effectiveness study</article-title><source>J Integr Complement Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jicm.2022.0477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35613402</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Dyer NL, Ali A, Baldwin AL, Kowalski S, Rand WL. An evaluation of the subjective experience of receiving reiki: qualitative results from a pragmatic effectiveness study. J Integr Complement Med. 2022;28:739–48.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35613402</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/jicm.2022.0477</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mb MB, Kkk MSN, Sn S. J. Understanding pranic energy experiences: A qualitative approach. Adv Mind Body Med. 2023;37.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37119543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brueggemann</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekwonye</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perceived benefits of Magdalena energy healing sessions: an exploratory study of clients’ perspectives</article-title><source>Healthcare</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>3087</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/healthcare11233087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38063655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10871104</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Brueggemann AD, Ekwonye AU. Perceived benefits of Magdalena energy healing sessions: an exploratory study of clients’ perspectives. Healthcare. 2023;11:3087.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38063655</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/healthcare11233087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10871104</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jrd C, Ss M, Rg N, Fhde S, Dr P, Sg O et al. Reiki for promotion of health and sleep quality in hospital nursing professionals. PubMed. 2022. 10.1590/0034-7167-2021-0535<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/0034-7167-2021-0535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35976274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Branton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of biofield energy therapy as complementary and alternative medicine in human health care system: a narrative review and potential mechanisms</article-title><source>J Complement Integr Med</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jcim-2024-0027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38563780</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Trivedi MK, Branton A, Trivedi D, Mondal S, Jana S. The use of biofield energy therapy as complementary and alternative medicine in human health care system: a narrative review and potential mechanisms. J Complement Integr Med. 2024. 10.1515/jcim-2024-0027.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38563780</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1515/jcim-2024-0027</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Facilitated group work for people with long-term conditions: a systematic review of benefits from studies of group-work interventions</article-title><source>Br J Gen Pract</source><year>2019</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>e363</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3399/bjgp19X702233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30962225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6478458</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Jackson M, Jones D, Dyson J, Macleod U. Facilitated group work for people with long-term conditions: a systematic review of benefits from studies of group-work interventions. Br J Gen Pract. 2019;69:e363-72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30962225</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3399/bjgp19X702233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6478458</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Portman</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carthy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowlands</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batchelor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Psychosocial aspects of the lived experience of long COVID: a systematic review and thematic synthesis of qualitative studies</article-title><source>Health Expect</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/hex.70071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39445819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11500211</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Eberhardt J, Gibson B, Portman RM, Carthy N, Rowlands S, Batchelor R, et al. Psychosocial aspects of the lived experience of long COVID: a systematic review and thematic synthesis of qualitative studies. Health Expect. 2024. 10.1111/hex.70071.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39445819</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/hex.70071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11500211</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>