<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">35</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcimm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2172</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12577001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12577001.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12577001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12577001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41174473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12865-025-00769-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">769</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Investigating apoptosis in peripheral blood mononuclear cells among the elderly in the post-COVID-19 era</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0739-9654</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Abiri</surname><given-names initials="E">Elaheh</given-names></name><address><email>elahe.abiri71@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmatian</surname><given-names initials="N">Najmeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03v4m1x12</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411973.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0611 8472</institution-id><institution>Department of Cellular and Molecular Biology, School of Biology, Institute of Biological Sciences, </institution><institution>Damghan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Damghan, Iran </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05y44as61</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.486769.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0384 8779</institution-id><institution>Food and Drug Administration, </institution><institution>Semnan University of Medical Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Semnan, Iran </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478646</issue-id><elocation-id>86</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-02 08:25:16.383"><day>02</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12865_2025_Article_769.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background and aim</title><p id="Par1">The COVID-19 pandemic has left a lasting imprint on immune function, particularly in the elderly—a population already vulnerable to immunosenescence. While acute and long-COVID immune responses have been widely studied, the long-term apoptotic behavior of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) remains underexplored. This study aims to investigate the legacy of SARS-CoV-2 on PBMC apoptosis in elderly individuals during the post-COVID era, shedding light on potential persistent immune dysregulation.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="Par2">In this cross-sectional study, PBMCs were isolated from peripheral blood samples of elderly individuals (&gt; 65 years old) with a documented history of COVID-19 infection at least six months prior. Using multiparametric flow cytometry, we quantified early and late apoptosis markers (Annexin V/PI), mitochondrial membrane potential disruption (ΔΨm), and expression of pro-apoptotic (Bax, Caspase-3) and anti-apoptotic (Bcl-2) proteins. Statistical analyses were performed to assess intergroup differences and correlations with clinical history. This study was conducted in 2025.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Elderly post-COVID individuals exhibited a significantly elevated proportion of apoptotic PBMCs compared to controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), particularly within the CD4 + and CD8 + T-cell subsets. Mitochondrial depolarization and increased Bax/Bcl-2 ratios indicated a shift toward intrinsic apoptotic pathways. Caspase-3 activation was also heightened in the post-COVID group. Notably, apoptotic burden correlated with time since infection and severity of initial illness.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par4">Our findings suggest a prolonged apoptotic signature in the immune cells of elderly individuals following recovery from COVID-19. These alterations may reflect a sustained immune exhaustion or maladaptive remodeling of lymphocyte populations, potentially contributing to impaired immunosurveillance and increased vulnerability to secondary infections or chronic inflammatory conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par5">COVID-19 may cast a long immunological shadow in the elderly, with persistent PBMC apoptosis representing a novel facet of post-viral immune dysregulation. Flow cytometry reveals a unique apoptotic phenotype that could serve as a biomarker for long-term immune health and guide post-pandemic clinical management strategies for aging populations.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Post-COVID syndrome</kwd><kwd>Elderly immunity</kwd><kwd>Apoptosis</kwd><kwd>PBMCs</kwd><kwd>Flow cytometry</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background and aim</title><p id="Par8">The COVID-19 pandemic, while largely transitioning into an endemic phase, has left behind more than clinical memories—it has potentially rewritten immune landscapes, especially in the elderly. Aging is intrinsically associated with immunosenescence and altered apoptotic responses, rendering older individuals more susceptible not only to severe SARS-CoV-2 infection but also to long-term immune dysfunction [15-]. While acute-phase immune alterations in COVID-19 have been well characterized, the long-term apoptotic behavior of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) in elderly survivors remains a largely uncharted territory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Emerging evidence suggests that viral infections, particularly those as systemic as COVID-19, may induce sustained immune reprogramming, including persistent activation or exhaustion of immune cells. Yet, it is unclear whether this leads to an enhanced apoptotic tendency in key immune populations months after recovery—potentially weakening the immune defense or contributing to post-viral syndromes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. This study aims to explore the enduring impact of COVID-19 on PBMC apoptosis in elderly individuals during the post-pandemic era. By employing high-resolution flow cytometry, we assess not only the presence of apoptosis but its qualitative and quantitative characteristics across immune cell subsets. Our objective is to uncover whether SARS-CoV-2 leaves a pro-apoptotic footprint in aged immune systems—and if so, to what extent this could inform future strategies for monitoring immune resilience or dysfunction in the elderly post-COVID population. The COVID-19 pandemic has fundamentally altered global health, but its most enduring impact may be on the human immune system—particularly in the older individuals. Older adults, already burdened by immunosenescence, were disproportionately affected during the pandemic, experiencing higher morbidity and mortality rates. Although many have since recovered, there is growing concern that SARS-CoV-2 may leave lasting imprints on the immune system, even after the virus is no longer detectable. The post-COVID era presents a critical opportunity to investigate these potential long-term effects and to understand how immune function in elderly individuals may have been irreversibly shaped by the pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs)—which include lymphocytes and monocytes—play a central role in orchestrating immune responses. Apoptosis, or programmed cell death, is a crucial regulatory mechanism that maintains immune homeostasis. Within the context of the immune system, lymphocytes play a vital role as they are responsible for identifying and eliminating pathogens. However, a misfit arises when apoptosis becomes excessive or dysregulated among lymphocyte populations. This dysregulation can lead to significant consequences, such as compromising overall immunity. As a result, individuals may experience chronic inflammation, an increased susceptibility to infections, or the development of autoimmune disorders, where the immune system mistakenly attacks the body’s own tissues. Understanding these dynamics is essential for addressing the impacts of aberrant apoptosis on immune health. In elderly individuals recovering from COVID-19, such disruptions may be amplified due to age-related vulnerabilities, yet this area remains underexplored [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Most current studies on post-COVID immunology focus on antibody persistence or cytokine profiles, with relatively little attention paid to cellular apoptosis. Moreover, few have specifically targeted the elderly—a demographic that not only bore the brunt of the pandemic but may now face hidden consequences in the form of subtle immune decay. Understanding whether COVID-19 has initiated a sustained apoptotic phenotype in PBMCs could reveal a previously unrecognized mechanism of immune deterioration in aging populations. To address this knowledge gap, the present study investigates the apoptotic behavior of PBMCs in elderly individuals with a history of COVID-19, compared to age-matched uninfected controls. Utilizing advanced flow cytometry techniques, we assess key markers of apoptosis, including Annexin V binding, propidium iodide uptake, mitochondrial membrane potential (ΔΨm), and the expression of pro- and anti-apoptotic proteins such as Bax, Bcl-2, and Caspase-3. By mapping these apoptotic patterns, we aim to identify whether COVID-19 acts as a long-term modulator of immune cell fate and function in the elderly. The central aim of this study is to uncover whether a legacy of enhanced or altered apoptosis persists in the immune systems of elderly individuals post-COVID-19, and to determine the potential implications for immune resilience, vulnerability to future infections, and age-related immune health.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design and participants</title><p id="Par9">This cross-sectional observational study aimed to evaluate the apoptotic profiles of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) in elderly individuals with a prior history of COVID-19 infection. Participants were recruited from outpatient clinics and community health centers in Damghan, Iran, between [2024] and [2025]. Two groups were included: Post-COVID Group: Elderly individuals (≥ 65 years) who had laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection at least six months prior to enrollment and had fully recovered. Control Group: Age- and sex-matched elderly individuals with no history of COVID-19, confirmed via negative serology and absence of symptoms or PCR confirmation during the pandemic. Exclusion criteria included current infections, autoimmune diseases, malignancies, immunosuppressive therapy, or recent vaccinations (within the last 3 months). Informed consent was obtained from all participants, and the study was approved by the Institutional Ethics Committee [IR.IAU.DAMGHAN.REC.1400.005], with all procedures performed according to the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Vaccination status of donors</title><p id="Par10">Vaccination records were obtained from official health documentation and participant interviews. For each donor, the following data were recorded: vaccination status (vaccinated or unvaccinated), vaccine type (Sinopharm [BBIBP-CorV], AstraZeneca [ChAdOx1 nCoV-19], or Sputnik V), number of doses received (1–3), and the interval between last vaccination and blood sampling. A summary of vaccination characteristics for all donors is provided in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, detailing vaccination type, dose number, and time elapsed since last vaccination.</p><p id="Par11">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Vaccination details</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Donor No.</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaccinated</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary Vaccine</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Doses (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Booster Vaccine</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interval last vaccine → sampling (months)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sputnik V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Vaccination status is based on official health records and participant interviews</p><p><italic toggle="yes">NA</italic> Not applicable</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sample collection and PBMC isolation</title><p id="Par12">Peripheral blood samples (10 mL) were collected in EDTA-coated tubes. PBMCs were isolated within 2 h of collection using density gradient centrifugation with Ficoll-Paque™ PLUS (GE Healthcare, Cat# 17–1440-03). Briefly, blood samples were diluted 1:1 with PBS and carefully layered over Ficoll in a 15 mL conical tube, followed by centrifugation at 400 g for 30 min at room temperature with the brake off. After centrifugation, the distinct PBMC layer (buffy coat) located at the plasma–Ficoll interface was carefully aspirated using a sterile Pasteur pipette. The harvested cells were transferred to a new tube, washed three times with PBS (300 g, 10 min each) to remove platelets and Ficoll residues, and finally resuspended in RPMI-1640 medium (Gibco, Cat# 11875-093) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco, Cat# 10082147). Cell viability was assessed using Trypan Blue (Sigma, Cat# T8154) exclusion, and viable cells were counted using a hemocytometer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Apoptosis assessment by flow cytometry</title><p id="Par13">Early and late apoptosis were measured using the Annexin V-FITC Apoptosis Detection Kit (BioLegend, Cat# 640914) following the manufacturer’s protocol. Specifically, 1 × 10^6 PBMCs were stained with Annexin V-FITC (Clone AV38) and propidium iodide (PI, Sigma Cat# P4170), then analyzed within 1 h. Mitochondrial depolarization was assessed with JC-1 dye (Thermo Fisher, Cat# T3168). For intracellular apoptotic markers, cells were fixed and permeabilized using the Cytofix/Cytoperm™ kit (BD Biosciences, Cat# 554714) and stained with: Anti-Bax (Clone 2D2, BD Biosciences, Cat# 556467, PE-conjugated). Anti-Bcl-2 (Clone 100, BD Biosciences, Cat# 556357, FITC-conjugated). Anti-active Caspase-3 (Clone C92-605, BD Biosciences, Cat# 550821, Alexa Fluor<sup>®</sup> 647-conjugated).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Flow cytometry acquisition and analysis</title><p id="Par14">Samples were run on a BD FACSCanto™ II. At least 10,000 events were acquired per sample. Compensation controls and fluorescence-minus-one (FMO) controls were applied. Data were analyzed using FlowJo™ v10. Apoptosis was quantified as the percentage of Annexin V⁺/PI⁻ (early) and Annexin V⁺/PI⁺ (late) cells. Median fluorescence intensity (MFI) was used for Bax, Bcl-2, and Caspase-3.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Gating strategy for flow cytometry analysis</title><p id="Par15">Specifically, CD3, CD4, and CD8 antibodies were utilized to identify T cell populations. Initially, live cells were gated using a viability dye to exclude dead cells from the analysis. Following this, CD3 + populations were selected to distinguish T cells, with subsequent gating on CD4 + and CD8 + T cells for functional assays. Dead cells were excluded using a fixable viability dye (BioLegend, Cat# 423107). CD3 (Clone UCHT1, BioLegend Cat# 300415), CD4 (Clone RPA-T4, BioLegend Cat# 300507), and CD8 (Clone RPA-T8, BioLegend Cat# 301007) were used to identify T cell subsets.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par16">Data were tested for normality using the Shapiro-Wilk test. Between-group comparisons were conducted using the independent t-test or Mann-Whitney U test, as appropriate. Correlation analyses were performed using Pearson or Spearman methods based on data distribution. A p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism, version 9.5.1 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Graphical representation</title><p id="Par17">Graphical representations were generated using GraphPad Prism software. Bar graphs were constructed to illustrate the differences in apoptotic profiles between groups, with individual data points overlaid on each bar to represent the variability among participants (one dot per patient).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Participant characteristics</title><p id="Par18">A total of 60 elderly participants were enrolled, including 30 post-COVID individuals and 30 age- and sex-matched controls. The mean age was 72.4 ± 4.8 years, with a male-to-female ratio of 1:1.1. There were no statistically significant differences in baseline demographics (age, sex, BMI, comorbidities) between the two groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05), ensuring comparability.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Participant vaccination characteristics</title><p id="Par19">Overall vaccination coverage was high across both groups; unvaccinated donors were present in both the post-COVID and control cohorts. Vaccine platforms were predominantly inactivated (BBIBP-CorV) with additional use of adenoviral vector vaccines (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 and Sputnik V). The interval between last vaccination and sampling was ≥ 4 months for all vaccinated donors. Full per-donor details (platform, doses, and interval) are reported in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Immunological and comorbidity profiles</title><p id="Par20">The most common comorbidities across both groups were hypertension (42% overall) and type 2 diabetes mellitus (35% overall). A smaller proportion of participants reported ischemic heart disease (18%) or chronic respiratory disease (10%). The prevalence of comorbidities did not differ significantly between the post-COVID and control groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05), suggesting appropriate matching.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Apoptosis in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs)</title><p id="Par21">Flow cytometric analysis revealed a significantly higher percentage of apoptotic PBMCs in the post-COVID group compared to controls. Early apoptosis (Annexin V⁺/PI⁻) was observed in 22.6% ± 6.1% of PBMCs in post-COVID individuals vs. 11.3% ± 4.2% in controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Late apoptosis (Annexin V⁺/PI⁺) was elevated at 18.9% ± 5.8% in post-COVID subjects vs. 9.4% ± 3.7% in controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). When stratified by cell subset, CD4⁺ T cells and CD8⁺ T cells showed significantly increased apoptosis in the post-COVID group (both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), suggesting a lymphocyte-specific vulnerability. The strategy of FACS (flow cytometry) analysis is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of apoptosis in COVID-19 patients in post-COVID-19: significant difference in different flow cytometric levels of apoptosis in the two control and test groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1264" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12865_2025_769_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Strategy figure from FACS (flow cytometry) analysis</title><p id="Par22">The percentage of apoptosis of peripheral blood lymphocytes in the clinical stage of COVID-19 patients was significantly increased compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). According to the results of this study, the percentage of apoptotic cells increases in post-COVID-19 patients. Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the Annexin V-FITC/PI fluorescence intensity in post-COVID-19 patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The data are presented based on Annexin V-FITC fluorescence intensity units and the number of cells counted. Row Q1 represents necrotic cells, Q2 is considered for late apoptosis, Q3 is considered for early apoptosis, and row Q4 identifies non-apoptotic cells as Annexin V-FITC negative populations in each analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Mitochondrial dysfunction in PBMCs</title><p id="Par23">Assessment of mitochondrial membrane potential using JC-1 dye demonstrated increased mitochondrial depolarization in the post-COVID group: The green/red fluorescence ratio (indicative of loss of ΔΨm) was significantly higher in post-COVID individuals (2.4 ± 0.5) compared to controls (1.3 ± 0.3, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), confirming activation of the intrinsic apoptotic pathway.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Expression of Apoptosis-Related proteins</title><p id="Par24">Intracellular staining showed altered expression of key apoptotic regulators in PBMCs from post-COVID participants: Bax expression (pro-apoptotic): Elevated MFI in post-COVID group (1,825 ± 240) vs. controls (1,130 ± 180, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Bcl-2 expression (anti-apoptotic): Decreased in post-COVID group (790 ± 150) compared to controls (1,220 ± 200, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Bax/Bcl-2 ratio was significantly higher in post-COVID subjects, suggesting a strong pro-apoptotic shift. Active Caspase-3 levels were also significantly increased in the post-COVID group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), indicating execution-phase apoptosis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Correlation with COVID-19 severity and time since infection</title><p id="Par25">Among post-COVID participants, higher apoptotic indices were positively correlated with: Severity of initial infection (mild, moderate, severe): <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.61, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. Shorter time since recovery (&lt; 9 months): <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = − 0.45, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03, suggesting partial normalization over time in some individuals. These findings indicate a persistently altered apoptotic profile in PBMCs of elderly individuals who have recovered from COVID-19, especially those who experienced moderate to severe illness. Early and late apoptosis in PBMCs are compared in Fig. 2, and Fig. 3 shows the assessment of mitochondrial membrane depolarization by JC-1 assay. The expression levels of pro-apoptotic and anti-apoptotic proteins in PBMCs are shown in Fig. 4. The demographic and clinical characteristics of the donors are listed in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p> Comparison of early and late apoptosis in PBMCs. This bar graph presents a professional-grade analysis of early and late apoptosis percentages in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) from elderly individuals who have recovered from COVID-19 and their age-matched controls. The results indicate a significantly higher proportion of both early and late apoptotic cells in the post-COVID elderly group compared to controls, highlighting the impact of prior SARS-CoV-2 infection on apoptotic processes. Significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) between mild and severe cases are indicated by an asterisk (*,…). Col: one-way ANOVA</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12865_2025_769_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p> Mitochondrial membrane depolarization assessment via JC-1 Assay. This figure illustrates the results of the JC-1 assay, which measures mitochondrial membrane potential by analyzing the green/red fluorescence ratio. The graph shows a significantly higher green/red fluorescence ratio in the post-COVID group, indicating greater mitochondrial depolarization. This finding serves as a clear indicator of intrinsic apoptotic pathway activation following COVID-19 infection. Significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) between mild and severe cases are indicated by an asterisk (*,…). Col: one-way ANOVA</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12865_2025_769_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Expression levels of pro-apoptotic and anti-apoptotic proteins in PBMCs. This graph compares the expression levels of Bax (pro-apoptotic) and Bcl-2 (anti-apoptotic) proteins in PBMCs from post-COVID individuals and matched controls. The data reveal a marked increase in Bax expression and a significant reduction in Bcl-2 levels in the post-COVID group, strongly suggesting a pro-apoptotic shift and providing key evidence for the activation of intrinsic apoptosis pathways. Col: Significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) between mild and severe cases are indicated by an asterisk (*,…). Col: one-way ANOVA</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12865_2025_769_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par26">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Donor demographics and clinical characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Donor No.</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time since symptom onset (months)*</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization (Yes/No)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">…</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Time from symptom onset was calculated only for the post-COVID group</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Sex-based analyses of PBMC apoptosis</title><p id="Par27">Post-COVID group: Female donors demonstrated a modest but statistically significant increase in early apoptosis (Annexin V⁺/PI⁻) in CD4⁺ T cells compared to male donors (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.04). No significant sex differences were observed in late apoptosis (Annexin V⁺/PI⁺) or mitochondrial depolarization. Control group: No significant sex-based differences were observed in apoptosis profiles. Apoptotic markers (Bax, Bcl-2, Caspase-3): Female post-COVID donors showed higher Bax/Bcl-2 ratios than males, suggesting a greater pro-apoptotic tendency, though this did not reach statistical significance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.08). These findings suggest a subtle but detectable sex-related variation in post-COVID apoptotic responses, consistent with broader literature on sex-based immune regulation. Gender-based analyses of PBMC apoptosis are shown in Fig. 5.<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p> Sex-based analyses of PBMC apoptosis. Col: Significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) between mild and severe cases are indicated by an asterisk (*,…). one-way ANOVA</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12865_2025_769_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par28">This study provides novel insights into the enduring impact of COVID-19 on the immune systems of elderly individuals, revealing a sustained pro-apoptotic phenotype in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) months after viral recovery. A key strength of our study is the deliberate exclusion of individuals with ongoing long COVID symptoms. This distinction is essential because immune dysregulation and chronic inflammation have been reported in symptomatic long COVID cohorts, which could confound interpretation of apoptosis-related findings. By focusing on elderly donors who had clinically recovered from COVID-19 and remained asymptomatic for at least six months, our results demonstrate that a sustained pro-apoptotic phenotype in PBMCs can persist even in the absence of long COVID. Thus, our findings highlight that COVID-19 may induce durable immunological “scars” in the elderly, independent of ongoing symptomatic sequelae. By employing multiparametric flow cytometry, we demonstrated that elderly post-COVID individuals exhibit significantly increased levels of apoptosis, mitochondrial dysfunction, and altered expression of key apoptotic regulators compared to age-matched controls. These findings unveil a previously underappreciated layer of immune dysregulation that may contribute to the complex post-COVID syndrome and immunosenescence in aging populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Our observations of elevated early and late apoptosis in PBMCs, particularly within CD4 + and CD8 + T lymphocytes, reinforce conclusions drawn in prior studies, indicating that SARS-CoV-2 infection leaves a lasting imprint on the adaptive immune system. Increased apoptosis may underlie impaired T cell function and reduced immune surveillance capacity, potentially explaining the heightened susceptibility of elderly post-COVID patients to secondary infections and vaccine hyporesponsiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The marked mitochondrial depolarization and increased Bax/Bcl-2 ratio further indicate activation of the intrinsic apoptotic pathway, reinforcing the concept of mitochondrial involvement in long-term immune cell dysfunction following COVID-19, consistent with findings in other respiratory infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Our results extend previous research focused primarily on acute immune responses and cytokine storms by revealing long-term alterations in cellular fate. The positive correlation between levels of apoptosis and initial COVID-19 severity aligns with clinical observations regarding profound immune exhaustion in severe cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Additionally, the inverse relationship with time since infection suggests some level of partial recovery; however, it also raises concerns about persistent immune vulnerability in certain individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The urgency for longitudinal monitoring of immune cell viability and function in elderly COVID-19 survivors is underscored by our findings. Persistent apoptosis could serve as a biomarker for identifying patients at risk of immune decline, providing vital information to guide interventions such as immunomodulatory therapies or tailored vaccination strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Furthermore, this apoptotic signature may reflect broader mechanisms of age-related immune remodeling accelerated by viral insult, thus opening avenues for targeted research into therapies aimed at restoring mitochondrial health and apoptotic balance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. While this study primarily focuses on the elderly, the implications for other vulnerable groups and chronic viral infections warrant further investigation. Future studies should explore the mechanistic links between persistent apoptosis, inflammation, and clinical outcomes in post-COVID populations, reinforcing the need for a more comprehensive literature review encompassing recent studies on the long-term effects of COVID-19 on immunity. Our findings contribute a crucial piece to the evolving puzzle of COVID-19’s long-term immunological legacy and highlight the importance of safeguarding immune resilience in aging societies. In our study, we primarily focused on the intrinsic apoptotic pathway to characterize the persistent apoptosis observed in T cells (CD4 + and CD8+) among elderly individuals following COVID-19 recovery. This focus is justified given the established role of mitochondrial dysfunction and the dysregulation of pro-apoptotic and anti-apoptotic proteins in the intrinsic pathway, which has been shown to significantly impact T cell functionality and survival. However, the extrinsic apoptotic pathway, activated through death receptors such as Fas (CD95) and TRAIL receptors, also plays a crucial role in regulating apoptosis in immune cells, including T lymphocytes. The extrinsic pathway is particularly significant in the context of viral infections, where immune cell activation and subsequent apoptosis are necessary to resolve infection and maintain immune homeostasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. While our study did not directly assess the extrinsic apoptotic pathway, the findings of increased apoptosis in T cells could suggest its involvement, especially considering the immune dysregulation associated with COVID-19. The release of inflammatory cytokines and damage-associated molecular patterns (DAMPs) during severe infection could lead to upregulation of death receptors on T cells, potentially triggering extrinsic apoptosis as a response to heightened immune activation or infection-induced cell stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Previous studies have identified increased expression of death receptors in T cells following viral infections, which may provide indirect evidence supporting the hypothesis that the extrinsic pathway contributes to the enhanced apoptosis noted in our findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In future studies, incorporating additional flow cytometry panels or functional assays to quantitate the expression levels of relevant death receptors and ligands will be critical for elucidating the potential role of the extrinsic pathway in T cell apoptosis. This inclusive approach will enhance our understanding of immune dysregulation in post-viral syndromes and inform the development of targeted interventions aimed at restoring effective immune responses in affected populations. Through this broadened perspective, we aim to contribute to the evolving field of immunology concerning COVID-19 and its long-term impacts on immune function, particularly in vulnerable populations such as the elderly.</p><sec id="Sec22"><title>Limitations of the study</title><p id="Par29">The study involved a relatively small sample size, which may limit statistical power and the ability to generalize findings to a broader population. Larger studies are necessary to confirm the observed effects and to enhance the robustness of the conclusions drawn. Although rigorous techniques for FACS analysis and data interpretation were employed, the exclusive focus on T cell populations may not fully capture the complexities of the immune response during and after COVID-19 infection. Future studies should consider a more comprehensive approach that includes other immune cell types to better understand the interplay among various immune populations. Participants in this study were predominantly elderly individuals who had recovered from COVID-19. Consequently, the findings may not be fully applicable to younger populations or those with different comorbidities. Further research in diverse cohorts is essential to validate the implications of these results across different demographic groups and clinical backgrounds.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par30">This study reveals that COVID-19 leaves a lasting pro-apoptotic footprint on peripheral blood mononuclear cells in elderly individuals, characterized by enhanced lymphocyte apoptosis, mitochondrial dysfunction, and dysregulated apoptotic protein expression. These persistent changes suggest that SARS-CoV-2 infection accelerates immune cell aging and compromises immune resilience long after clinical recovery. Monitoring apoptosis in post-COVID elderly patients could serve as a valuable biomarker for immune health and guide personalized interventions to mitigate long-term immune dysfunction. Our findings highlight the urgent need for focused strategies to restore immune homeostasis in aging populations affected by the pandemic’s legacy.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par6">Coronavirus Disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SARS-CoV-2</term><def><p id="Par7">Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>E.A. and N.H. conceived the original idea and designed the project, and participated in the design and executed the experiments.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This project did not receive any financial support from any non-profit, government, or for-profit financial institutions. Financial support for this research was provided by Dr. Elaheh Abiri.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets generated and/or analyzed during this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par31">All procedures performed in the study involving human participants were conducted according to the ethical standards of the institutional and national research committee and of the 1975 Helsinki Declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards. This study was approved by the Biomedical Research Ethics Committee of Damghan Islamic Azad University, which issued the study’s code of ethics (IR.IAU. DAMGHAN.REC.1400.005). Before data collection, written informed consent was obtained from all subjects participating in the study. To comply with ethical considerations, all medical record information was kept confidential. The names and surnames of participants were not used for data collection, and data collection was carried out after obtaining the code of ethics from Damghan Islamic Azad University.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par32">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Clinical trial number</title><p id="Par33">Not applicable.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gimenez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Monocytic reactive oxygen species–induced T-cell apoptosis impairs cellular immune response to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2025.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39800264</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Gimenez S, et al. Monocytic reactive oxygen species–induced T-cell apoptosis impairs cellular immune response to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2025. 10.1016/j.jaci.2025.01.003.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39800264</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaci.2025.01.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahrizi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeed</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lymphopenia associated with survivin and its downstream pathway in COVID-19 serving as a potential route in COVID-19 pathogenesis</article-title><source>Adv Med Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>69</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.advms.2024.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38521459</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Kahrizi M, Saeed, et al. Lymphopenia associated with survivin and its downstream pathway in COVID-19 serving as a potential route in COVID-19 pathogenesis. Adv Med Sci. 2024;69(1):190–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38521459</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.advms.2024.03.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cezar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>T4 apoptosis in the acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection predicts long COVID</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1335352</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1335352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38235145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10791767</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Cezar R, et al. T4 apoptosis in the acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection predicts long COVID. Front Immunol. 2024;14:1335352.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38235145</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1335352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10791767</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wroński</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Beyond interferon gamma-decreased cellular response to COVID-19 vaccination booster in patients with autoimmune inflammatory rheumatic diseases</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2025</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1568439</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1568439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40226625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11986637</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Wroński J, et al. Beyond interferon gamma-decreased cellular response to COVID-19 vaccination booster in patients with autoimmune inflammatory rheumatic diseases. Front Immunol. 2025;16:1568439.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40226625</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1568439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11986637</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of coinhibitory receptors in B cell dysregulation in SARS-CoV-2–infected individuals with severe disease</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2024</year><volume>212</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1540</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.2300783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38517295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11075007</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Saito S, et al. The role of coinhibitory receptors in B cell dysregulation in SARS-CoV-2–infected individuals with severe disease. J Immunol. 2024;212(10):1540–52.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38517295</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.2300783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11075007</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alenzi</surname><given-names>FQB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survivin: a key apoptosis inhibitor in COVID-19 infection and its implication for treatment protocol</article-title><source>Saudi J Biol Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>31</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>104021</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2024.104021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38831893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11145386</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Alenzi FQB. Survivin: a key apoptosis inhibitor in COVID-19 infection and its implication for treatment protocol. Saudi J Biol Sci. 2024;31(7):104021.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38831893</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.sjbs.2024.104021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11145386</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasiri</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact understanding of exosome therapy in COVID-19 and preparations for the future approaches in dealing with infectious diseases and inflammation</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5724</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-56334-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38459174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10924089</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Nasiri Z, et al. The impact understanding of exosome therapy in COVID-19 and preparations for the future approaches in dealing with infectious diseases and inflammation. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):5724.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38459174</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-024-56334-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10924089</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valderrábano</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dysregulated nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide metabolome in patients hospitalized with COVID-19</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><year>2024</year><volume>23</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e14326</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acel.14326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39354697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11634700</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Valderrábano RJ, et al. Dysregulated nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide metabolome in patients hospitalized with COVID-19. Aging Cell. 2024;23(12):e14326.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39354697</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/acel.14326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11634700</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heydari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNAs in biomarking COVID-19: a machine learning-based approach</article-title><source>Virol J</source><year>2024</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>134</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12985-024-02408-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38849961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11161961</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Heydari R, et al. Long non-coding RNAs in biomarking COVID-19: a machine learning-based approach. Virol J. 2024;21(1):134.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38849961</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12985-024-02408-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11161961</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanaliha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analyzing the expression pattern of the noncoding RNAs (HOTAIR, PVT-1, XIST, H19, and miRNA‐34a) in PBMC samples of patients with COVID‐19, according to the disease severity in Iran during 2022–2023: a cross‐sectional study</article-title><source>Health Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e1861</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hsr2.1861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38332929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10850438</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Khanaliha K, et al. Analyzing the expression pattern of the noncoding RNAs (HOTAIR, PVT-1, XIST, H19, and miRNA‐34a) in PBMC samples of patients with COVID‐19, according to the disease severity in Iran during 2022–2023: a cross‐sectional study. Health Sci Rep. 2024;7(2):e1861.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38332929</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hsr2.1861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10850438</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E-S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory risk contributes to post-COVID endothelial dysfunction through anti-ACKR1 autoantibody</article-title><source>Life Sci Alliance</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26508/lsa.202402598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11091471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38740432</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Lee E-S, et al. Inflammatory risk contributes to post-COVID endothelial dysfunction through anti-ACKR1 autoantibody. Life Sci Alliance. 2024;7:7.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.26508/lsa.202402598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11091471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38740432</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huminiecki</surname><given-names>Łukasz</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bulk and single-cell RNA sequencing elucidate the etiology of severe COVID-19</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3280</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25063280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38542251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10970417</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Huminiecki Łukasz. Bulk and single-cell RNA sequencing elucidate the etiology of severe COVID-19. Int J Mol Sci. 2024;25(6):3280.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38542251</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms25063280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10970417</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ghosh S, Chatterjee A, Maitra A. An insight into COVID-19 host immunity at single-cell resolution. Int Rev Immunol. 2024;43:1–16.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/08830185.2024.2443420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39707914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal single cell atlas identifies complex Temporal relationship between type I interferon response and COVID-19 severity</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>567</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-44524-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38238298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10796319</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Lin QX, Xuan, et al. Longitudinal single cell atlas identifies complex Temporal relationship between type I interferon response and COVID-19 severity. Nat Commun. 2024;15(1):567.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38238298</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-023-44524-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10796319</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spriņģe ML, et al. Unveiling the immune landscape of COVID-19 and prolonged Long-COVID through Single-Cell RNA Sequencing. BioRxiv. 2025:2025–03.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bispo</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iseke</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunomodulatory effect of IFN-γ licensed adipose-mesenchymal stromal cells in an in vitro model of inflammation generated by SARS-CoV-2 antigens</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>24235</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-75776-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39415027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11484699</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Bispo EC, Iseke, et al. Immunomodulatory effect of IFN-γ licensed adipose-mesenchymal stromal cells in an in vitro model of inflammation generated by SARS-CoV-2 antigens. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):24235.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39415027</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-024-75776-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11484699</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cetinkaya</surname><given-names>Pınar</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gur</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plasma extracellular vesicles derived from pediatric COVID-19 patients modulate monocyte and T cell immune responses based on disease severity</article-title><source>Immunol Investig</source><year>2024</year><volume>53</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08820139.2024.2385992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39115924</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Cetinkaya Pınar, Gur, et al. Plasma extracellular vesicles derived from pediatric COVID-19 patients modulate monocyte and T cell immune responses based on disease severity. Immunol Investig. 2024;53(7):1141–75.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39115924</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/08820139.2024.2385992</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D’Onofrio</surname><given-names>Valentino</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sékaly</surname><given-names>Rafick Pierre</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The immune–endocrine interplay in sex differential responses to viral infection and COVID-19</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.it.2024.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39562265</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">D’Onofrio Valentino, Sékaly Rafick Pierre. The immune–endocrine interplay in sex differential responses to viral infection and COVID-19. Trends Immunol. 2024. 10.1016/j.it.2024.10.004.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39562265</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.it.2024.10.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ćwilichowska-Puślecka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Understanding the long-term interplay of SARS-CoV-2 immune and inflammatory responses with proteases in COVID-19 recovery: a longitudinal study</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2025</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1517933</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1517933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40557167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12185401</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Ćwilichowska-Puślecka N, et al. Understanding the long-term interplay of SARS-CoV-2 immune and inflammatory responses with proteases in COVID-19 recovery: a longitudinal study. Front Immunol. 2025;16:1517933.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40557167</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1517933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12185401</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbati</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The glycan ectodomain of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein modulates cytokine production and expression of CD206 mannose receptor in PBMC cultures of pre-COVID-19 healthy subjects</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>497</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v16040497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38675840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11054381</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Barbati C, et al. The glycan ectodomain of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein modulates cytokine production and expression of CD206 mannose receptor in PBMC cultures of pre-COVID-19 healthy subjects. Viruses. 2024;16(4):497.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38675840</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/v16040497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11054381</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal dynamic single-cell mass cytometry analysis of peripheral blood mononuclear cells in COVID-19 patients within 6 months after viral RNA clearance</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>567</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-024-09464-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38844850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11157885</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Zhou D, et al. Longitudinal dynamic single-cell mass cytometry analysis of peripheral blood mononuclear cells in COVID-19 patients within 6 months after viral RNA clearance. BMC Infect Dis. 2024;24(1):567.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38844850</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-024-09464-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11157885</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gavriilidis GI, et al. APNet, an explainable sparse deep learning model to discover differentially active drivers of severe COVID-19. Bioinformatics. 2025:btaf063.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btaf063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11897427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39921901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunological characterization and comparison of children with COVID-19 from their adult counterparts at single-cell resolution</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1358725</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2024.1358725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39148728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11325098</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Jia R, et al. Immunological characterization and comparison of children with COVID-19 from their adult counterparts at single-cell resolution. Front Immunol. 2024;15:1358725.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39148728</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2024.1358725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11325098</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jana S. Role of apoptosis in viral infections with special reference to COVID-19: therapeutic targets and Strategies. In: apoptosis and human health: Understanding mechanistic and therapeutic potential. Singapore: Springer Nature Singapore; 2024. p. 325–39.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>Pedro RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of a pro-resolving drug in COVID‐19: preclinical studies to a randomized, placebo‐controlled, phase Ib/IIa trial in hospitalized patients</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2024</year><volume>181</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>4750</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bph.17322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39159951</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Almeida Pedro RJ, et al. Effects of a pro-resolving drug in COVID‐19: preclinical studies to a randomized, placebo‐controlled, phase Ib/IIa trial in hospitalized patients. Br J Pharmacol. 2024;181(23):4750–65.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39159951</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bph.17322</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 lung injury: unique and familiar aspects of pathophysiology</article-title><source>Appl Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>11048</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app142311048</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Hall S, Berger G, Lehmann C. COVID-19 lung injury: unique and familiar aspects of pathophysiology. Appl Sci. 2024;14:11048.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial dysfunction and the aging immune system</article-title><source>Biology</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biology8020026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31083529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6627503</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">McGuire PJ. Mitochondrial dysfunction and the aging immune system. Biology. 2019;8(2):26.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31083529</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biology8020026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6627503</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elesela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>W. Lukacs</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of mitochondria in viral infections</article-title><source>Life</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>232</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life11030232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33799853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7998235</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Elesela S, Nicholas W. Lukacs. Role of mitochondria in viral infections. Life. 2021;11(3):232.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33799853</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/life11030232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7998235</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitophagy: a promising therapeutic target for neuroprotection during ageing and age-related diseases</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2023</year><volume>180</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1542</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bph.16062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36792062</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Mishra E. Mitophagy: a promising therapeutic target for neuroprotection during ageing and age-related diseases. Br J Pharmacol. 2023;180(12):1542–61.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36792062</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bph.16062</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee Y, Haeng et al. Targeting mitochondrial oxidative stress as a strategy to treat aging and age-related diseases. Antioxidants 12.4 (2023):934.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox12040934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10136354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37107309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Navigating the post-COVID-19 immunological era: understanding long COVID-19 and immune response</article-title><source>Life</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2121</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life13112121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38004261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10672162</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Mohan A, et al. Navigating the post-COVID-19 immunological era: understanding long COVID-19 and immune response. Life. 2023;13(11):2121.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38004261</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/life13112121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10672162</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multidisciplinary recommendations for the management of CAR-T recipients in the post-COVID-19 pandemic era</article-title><source>Exp Hematol Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>66</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40164-023-00426-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37501090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10375673</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Zhang T, et al. Multidisciplinary recommendations for the management of CAR-T recipients in the post-COVID-19 pandemic era. Exp Hematol Oncol. 2023;12(1):66.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37501090</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40164-023-00426-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10375673</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tappe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 patients share common, corticosteroid-independent features of impaired host immunity to pathogenic molds</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>954985</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.954985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36052094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9427195</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Tappe B, et al. COVID-19 patients share common, corticosteroid-independent features of impaired host immunity to pathogenic molds. Front Immunol. 2022;13:954985.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36052094</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2022.954985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9427195</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shevela</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ya</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intranasal immunotherapy with M2 macrophage soluble factors in post-COVID hyposmia: a pilot study</article-title><source>Int Immunopharmacol</source><year>2024</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>111260</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2023.111260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38000231</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Shevela E, Ya, et al. Intranasal immunotherapy with M2 macrophage soluble factors in post-COVID hyposmia: a pilot study. Int Immunopharmacol. 2024;126:111260.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38000231</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.intimp.2023.111260</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibodies as a therapeutic strategy against multidrug-resistant bacterial infections in a post-COVID-19 era</article-title><source>Life</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>246</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life14020246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38398755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10890110</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Chen H-C, et al. Monoclonal antibodies as a therapeutic strategy against multidrug-resistant bacterial infections in a post-COVID-19 era. Life. 2024;14(2):246.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38398755</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/life14020246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10890110</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavda</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A global picture: therapeutic perspectives for COVID-19</article-title><source>Immunotherapy</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/imt-2021-0168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35187954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8884157</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Chavda VP, et al. A global picture: therapeutic perspectives for COVID-19. Immunotherapy. 2022;14(5):351–71.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35187954</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2217/imt-2021-0168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8884157</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The multifaceted nature of IL-10: regulation, role in immunological homeostasis and its relevance to cancer, COVID-19 and post-COVID conditions</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1161067</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1161067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37359549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10287165</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Carlini V, et al. The multifaceted nature of IL-10: regulation, role in immunological homeostasis and its relevance to cancer, COVID-19 and post-COVID conditions. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1161067.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37359549</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1161067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10287165</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global collaboration research strategies for sustainability in the post COVID-19 era: analyzing virology-related national-funded projects</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>6561</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su12166561</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Lee D, Kang J, Kim K. Global collaboration research strategies for sustainability in the post COVID-19 era: analyzing virology-related national-funded projects. Sustainability. 2020;12(16):6561.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>