<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">574</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jcardiomagnres</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1097-6647</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-429X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12182812</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12182812.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12182812</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12182812</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40185235</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocmr.2025.101890</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1097-6647(25)00052-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101890</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Abnormal coronary vascular response in patients with long COVID syndrome – a case‐control study using oxygenation‐sensitive cardiovascular magnetic resonance</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weberling</surname><given-names initials="LD">Lukas D.</given-names></name><email>Lukas.Weberling@Med.Uni-Heidelberg.de</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names initials="E">Elizabeth</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names initials="MG">Matthias G.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahlten</surname><given-names initials="M">Marc</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names initials="N">Norbert</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name name-style="western"><surname>André</surname><given-names initials="F">Florian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steen</surname><given-names initials="H">Henning</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Department of Cardiology, Angiology and Pneumology, Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>DZHK (German Centre for Cardiovascular Research), Partner Site Heidelberg/Mannheim, Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Division of Experimental Medicine, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</aff><aff id="aff0020"><label>d</label>Division of Cardiology, Departments of Medicine and Diagnostic Radiology, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. <email>Lukas.Weberling@Med.Uni-Heidelberg.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Summer</season><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478369</issue-id><elocation-id>101890</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-09-19 13:25:40.253"><day>19</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="ab0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Following the worldwide coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, many patients reported ongoing severe cardiovascular symptoms after the acute phase. This multisystemic condition has been named long COVID syndrome. While cardiovascular magnetic resonance (CMR) imaging is the gold standard to diagnose acute myocardial damage, no specific changes have been shown in long COVID patients. However, endothelial dysfunction has been hypothesized to contribute to its pathogenesis. Oxygenation-sensitive CMR during breathing exercise is a simple, non-invasive, and accurate test to objectify vascular function, which has not been applied to long COVID patients yet.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>After receiving approval from the local ethics committee, this prospective observational case-control study enrolled (i) patients reporting symptoms for ≥6 weeks following an acute COVID-19 infection or vaccination, and (ii) healthy volunteers with neither symptoms nor history of cardiovascular disease. Participants completed a questionnaire, point-of-care testing of cardiac biomarkers, a standard non-contrast CMR, and an oxygenation-sensitive CMR. Heart rate response and breathing-induced myocardial oxygenation reserve (B-MORE) were assessed during metronome-paced hyperventilation and apnea.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Thirty-one patients (17 female; age 39.4 [30.3; 51.6] years) and 27 controls (12 female; age 33.3 [27.3; 46.8] years) were included with comparable demographics and cardiovascular risk factors between groups. Laboratory testing and standard CMR did not reveal any pathologies in either of the groups. Indexed left ventricular stroke volume was significantly lower in patients (44.5 mL [41.2; 46.6] vs 55.9 mL [49.2; 59.2]; p &lt; 0.001), while ejection fraction and longitudinal strain of both ventricles were comparable (p &gt; 0.05 for all). Vasoactive breathing exercises induced a significant increase in heart rate (+35/min [21; 45]) and B-MORE (9.8% [4.3; 17.2]) in controls. In patients, however, heart rate increase was blunted (+15/min [7; 26]; p &lt; 0.001) and B-MORE was significantly lower (7.3% [3.4; 10.4], p = 0.044).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This pilot study is the first to show a blunted hemodynamic and myocardial oxygenation response to vasoactive breathing maneuvers during oxygenation-sensitive CMR in long COVID patients. This simple, non-invasive test may be the first to objectify complaints of affected patients and indicates evidence for the crucial role of the endothelium in the pathophysiology of long COVID.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="ab0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="fig0025" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><alt-text id="at0045">ga1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0025" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ga1.jpg"/></fig></p></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>CMR</kwd><kwd>Cardiovascular imaging</kwd><kwd>OS-CMR</kwd><kwd>Oxygenation-sensitive CMR</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Long COVID syndrome</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term id="key0010">B-MORE</term><def><p>Breathing-induced Myocardial Oxygenation Reserve</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key0020">CMR</term><def><p>Cardiovascular magnetic resonance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key0030">COVID</term><def><p>Coronavirus disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key0040">EF</term><def><p>Ejection fraction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key0050">GLS</term><def><p>Global longitudinal strain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key0060">hsTnI</term><def><p>High-sensitivity Troponin I</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key0070">LV</term><def><p>Left ventricular</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key0080">OS-CMR</term><def><p>Oxygenation-sensitive CMR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key0090">RV</term><def><p>Right ventricular</p></def></def-item></def-list></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Background</title><p id="p0010">The unprecedented spread of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) has challenged the limits of global health care systems with currently over 775 million cases and over 7 million deaths <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. COVID-19 is a multisystemic disease affecting respiratory and in particular cardiovascular systems <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Affected patients experience different clinical courses ranging from asymptomatic infections to a potentially life-threatening illness, with the latter occurring less common since the introduction of COVID-19 vaccinations <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. In a minority of patients, symptoms persist &gt;4 or &gt;12 weeks after the acute phase of infection with shortness of breath, fatigue, chest pain, brain fog, and myalgia being the most common complaints. This symptom complex has been summarized as long COVID syndrome and may also, to a much lesser extent, occur after COVID-19 vaccination <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. It also occurs in initially asymptomatic or mild infections and does not correlate with myocardial injury assessed by cardiovascular magnetic resonance (CMR) imaging <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Furthermore, vaccination has been shown to only partly protect from long COVID syndrome <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Therefore, despite a high individual symptom burden and decreased quality of life, it has proven challenging to identify underlying causes and to provide potential targets for therapies. Suggested mechanisms involve persisting tissue damage or virus particles, coagulopathies, and metabolic or autoimmune disorders <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Recent research indicates a crucial role of the endothelium in the pathogenesis of the disease <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>.</p><p id="p0015">In the assessment of the cardiovascular autonomic and endothelial function, combining oxygenation-sensitive CMR (OS-CMR) with breathing maneuvers is highly reproducible and has been established in patients with coronary artery disease, obstructive sleep apnea, myocardial infarction with non-obstructive coronary arteries, heart failure and in heart transplant recipients <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Hyperventilation is a stressor superior to adenosine and substantially increases heart rate, specifically in healthy individuals <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. OS-CMR makes use of the different relaxation of oxygenated versus deoxygenated hemoglobin measurable through signal alterations in the highly perfused myocardium <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. In a standardized breathing sequence including hyperventilation followed by a breath-hold, CO<sub>2</sub> induces a coronary vasoconstriction followed by a vasodilation <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. These endothelium-dependent breathing effects induce specific changes of oxygenation in the myocardium, which can be assessed through OS-CMR and which have been standardized as breathing-induced myocardial oxygenation reserve (B-MORE) <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>.</p><p id="p0020">The aim of this study was to assess the myocardial vascular and autonomous function in long COVID patients using OS-CMR during standardized breathing maneuvers.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Study population and design</title><p id="p0025">This prospective observational case-control study was approved by the ethics committee of the University of Heidelberg, Germany (S-361/2022). Participants were included through public announcements and social media posts. A full written informed consent was obtained from all participants. Between September 2022 and January 2024, two groups of participants (patients and controls) were prospectively included at two participating sites in Hamburg and Hannover, Germany. For the patients, inclusion criteria were either <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> the persistence of symptoms, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> the new onset of symptoms, or <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> a worsening of symptoms with a significant negative influence on daily activities and quality of life for at least 6 weeks after an acute COVID-19 illness (with positive polymerase chain reaction or rapid antigen testing) or a COVID-19 vaccination in accordance to the long/post-COVID guidelines <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. A group of healthy volunteers without the presence of any cardiovascular symptoms but with a history of COVID-19 vaccination or infection at least 6 weeks before inclusion served as controls. Exclusion criteria for both groups involved known cardiac pathologies (such as heart failure, coronary artery disease) or a COVID-19 infection or vaccination in the last 6 weeks before the examination. Of note, participants with cardiovascular risk factors or isolated atrial fibrillation were not excluded. <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> shows a flow diagram of the patient recruitment. The study involved a questionnaire covering pre-existing conditions, cardiovascular risk factors, and current complaints, a medical consultation (in person or via telephone), point-of-care testing of cardiac biomarkers (high-sensitivity troponin I [hsTnI] and N-terminal pro-hormone brain natriuretic peptide [NTproBNP], Quidel Triage, San Diego, California, USA), a standard CMR and a vascular function assessment using breathing maneuvers with OS-CMR.<fig id="fig0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of recruitment, inclusion, and examination of both long COVID cases and healthy controls. <italic toggle="yes">COVID</italic> coronavirus disease, <italic toggle="yes">CMR</italic> cardiovascular magnetic resonance, <italic toggle="yes">OS-CMR</italic> oxygenation-sensitive cardiovascular magnetic resonance</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0005" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>2.2</label><title>CMR acquisition protocol</title><p id="p0030">CMR acquisitions were executed on clinical CMR scanners of the manufacturer Siemens Healthineers (Erlangen, Germany) at either 1.5T (site in Hannover, Magnetom™ Aera) or 3T (site in Hamburg, Magnetom™ Skyra). Cine images were obtained with a steady-state free precession sequence (time of repetition 38.4 ms; time of echo 1.24–1.4 ms; field of view 301 × 360/174 × 208 mm; slice thickness 8.0 mm) using retrospective electrocardiographic gating in at least three long-axis planes (two-, three-, and four-chamber views), as well as a short-axis stack of the whole left ventricle (LV) (during breath-hold with 25 phases per cardiac cycle). T1 maps were acquired using a standard modified look-locker inversion recovery 5s(3s)3s T1-native sequence in 3–5 short-axis views (time of repetition 280.6–312.6 ms; time of echo 1.12–1.33 ms; field of view 360 × 306/384 × 327 mm; slice thickness 8.0 mm). T2 maps were acquired using a T2 FLASH sequence in 3–5 short-axis views (time of repetition 222.8–280.6 ms; time of echo 1.12 ms; field of view 360 × 306/384 × 327 mm; slice thickness 8.0 mm). OS-CMR was executed using a modified balanced steady-state free precession sequence (time of repetition 40.7 ms; time of echo 1.7 ms; field of view 320 × 380/162 × 192 ms; slice thickness 10 mm) in two short-axis slices (basal and midventricular) as previously described <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. The standard OS-CMR imaging protocol assessing vascular function was deployed as previously described and involved a baseline OS-CMR image acquisition, followed by 60 s of metronome-paced hyperventilation at 30 breaths/min, and then by a voluntary maximal breath-hold at expiration <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. OS-CMR images were acquired continuously during breath-hold. Oxygen saturation, blood pressure, and heart rate were noted before initiation of hyperventilation. Participants received a minimum of three repetitions of exact instructions for the breathing maneuvers (with the first one through a standardized video) and did at least one test hyperventilation before the scan. During hyperventilation, the maximum heart rate measured by electrocardiogram and pulse oximeter was noted. Heart rate response was calculated by subtracting the baseline heart rate from the maximum heart rate. Patient compliance, breathing depth, and breathing rate were monitored visually and with a respiration belt and rated as excellent, good, acceptable, or poor. Side effects experienced by the patients were noted. <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> illustrates the OS-CMR protocol. No contrast agent was administered during the CMR acquisition.<fig id="fig0010" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Study protocol to assess myocardial vascular function using oxygenation-sensitive CMR. <italic toggle="yes">B-MORE</italic> breathing-induced myocardial oxygenation reserve, <italic toggle="yes">SI</italic> signal intensity, <italic toggle="yes">CMR</italic> cardiovascular magnetic resonance, <italic toggle="yes">OS-CMR</italic> oxygenation-sensitive cardiovascular magnetic resonance</p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0010" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Image analysis</title><p id="p0035">Image analysis was performed using cvi42 (versions 5.13.8 and 6.0.2, Circle Cardiovascular Imaging, Calgary, Alberta, Canada), including the research module OxySense by a researcher (L.D.W.) with &gt;4 years and &gt;1500 clinical CMR cases of experience, who was blinded to all clinical data. Endocardial and epicardial borders of both the LV and right ventricle (RV), the left and right atrium (LA, RA), and both RV insertion points throughout the cardiac cycle were automatically detected and manually corrected, if necessary, to derive volume, myocardial mass, ejection fraction (EF) and longitudinal strain of both ventricles and atria and to measure global T1 and T2 values. Global oxygenation (B-MORE) was measured at the end of hyperventilation (0 s, at the beginning of breath-hold) and at 30 s during the breath-hold. For these measurements, end-systolic images of each cardiac cycle were identified and endocardial and epicardial contours were drawn using the automated processing tool of the OxySense module, which were manually corrected if needed. The global B-MORE was calculated by the formula B-MORE (%) = <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M1" altimg="si0001.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SI</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>30</mml:mn><mml:mi>sec</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SI</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>sec</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SI</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>sec</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0040">The R language and environment for statistical computing (version 4.2.1, R Foundation for Statistical Computation, Vienna, Austria) with the R studio user interface (version 2023.06.0+421) was deployed for the statistical analyses <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p id="p0045">Normal distribution was assessed by using the Shapiro-Wilk test. Parametric variables are given as mean ± standard deviation, nonparametric variables as median with interquartile range. The Student’s t-test was used for the comparison of two groups, when parameters were distributed normally. The nonparametric Wilcoxon rank-sum test tested not normal distributed variables for differences. The Fisher’s exact test was used to test for group differences of categorical variables. Potential correlations between two variables were assessed using the Pearson or Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient, as applicable. To test the influence of the potential confounders sex, age, hypertension, and asthma, an analysis of covariance was used.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0035"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec0040"><label>3.1</label><title>Study population</title><p id="p0050">Fifty-eight participants (27 controls; 31 patients) were included in this study. Both patients and controls were at a young age and distribution among genders was balanced. The presence of cardiovascular risk factors was scarce with hypertension and a smoking habit being most frequent in both patients and controls. None of the controls and 14 of the patients had known comorbidities. These involved a thyroid disorder (3), asthma (3), celiac disease (2), iron deficiency, polycystic ovary syndrome, testosterone deficiency, prior Lime disease, prior pulmonary embolism, atrial fibrillation, and obstructive sleep apnea (1 each). Only a fraction of both controls and patients were on a vasoactive medication. Five controls were non-professional endurance athletes, while the rest of the controls had ordinary levels of physical activity (&lt;5 h/week). Baseline characteristics are given in <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of cases and controls.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Controls<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Long COVID<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 27</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 31</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age [years]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[27.3; 46.8]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[30.3; 51.6]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Body mass index [kg/m²]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[21.9; 29.2]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[21.0; 27.3]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex [male/female]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiovascular risk factors</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hypertension</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.9%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.5%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hypercholesterinemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.5%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.4%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Diabetes mellitus</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Smoking habit</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Family history</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.9%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">On vasoactive medication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.4%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Calcium antagonists</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.5%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Beta blocker</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.9%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Laboratory testing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> hsTnI [ng/L]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5<xref rid="tbl1fnStar" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[1.6; 3.5]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[0.3; 2.5]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> NTproBNP [ng/L]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24<xref rid="tbl1fnStar" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[20; 45]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[20; 67]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0030"><p><italic toggle="yes">COVID</italic> coronavirus disease, <italic toggle="yes">NTproBNP</italic> N-terminal pro-hormone brain natriuretic peptide, <italic toggle="yes">hsTnI</italic> high-sensitivity troponin I</p></fn><fn id="sp0035"><p>Continous values are given as median (Interquartile range). Binary values are given as percentages with numerator and denominator.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fnStar"><label>*</label><p id="ntp0005">Laboratory testing was available for 8 healthy controls</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0055">Patients were highly symptomatic at the time of enrollment with angina pectoris, dyspnea, and fatigue being the most common complaints. Brain fog, myalgia, anxiety, or depression were also common among patients. The prevalence of symptoms was similar between patients who developed long COVID following infection versus vaccination. Details of the present complaints are displayed in <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The laboratory testing revealed normal levels of hsTnI and NTproBNP in all study participants.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Present complaints of the long COVID groups.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0030">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">All cases</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Post COVID-19</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Post vaccination</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group difference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 31</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 14</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p =</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Angina pectoris</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>27</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>87.1%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>11</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>78.6%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>16</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>94.1%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.607</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Typical</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.8%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.4%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.4%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Atypical</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.3%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.1%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.7%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>21</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.7%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>9</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>64.3%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>12</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>70.6%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.814</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> On exertion</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.9%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.7%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.1%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> At rest and on exertion</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.8%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.6%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brain fog</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.5%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.1%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.6%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.478</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Myalgia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.3%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.1%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.7%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.724</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.4%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.4%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.4%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.670</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety or depression</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.6%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.7%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.8%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.198</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of complaints [d]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">559</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[277; 663]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">227</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[125;599]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[555; 769]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.018</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0045"><p><italic toggle="yes">COVID-19</italic> coronavirus disease 2019</p></fn><fn id="sp0050"><p>Significant group differences are highlighted in bold.</p></fn><fn id="sp0055"><p>Continous values are given as median (Interquartile range). Binary values are given as percentages with numerator and denominator.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><label>3.2</label><title>Standard CMR</title><p id="p0060">For the CMR scan, 51 participants were scanned at 3T, while 7 participants (4 controls, 3 patients) were scanned at 1.5T. There were no wall motion abnormalities in any of the participants. LV- and RV-EF were normal in both controls (median LV-EF 61.0%; RV-EF 56.0%) and patients (LV-EF 59.7%; RV-EF 55.4%) and were similar between groups. Equally, left and right global longitudinal strain (GLS) were normal in both controls (median LV-GLS −19.4%; RV-GLS −24.0%) and patients (−18.5%; −22.7%) and were comparable between groups. Controls had higher volumes (indexed to body surface area) of both the LV (controls 89.7 mL; patients 72.9 mL) and the RV (96.7 mL; 78.3 mL) and showed higher indexed stroke volumes of both the LV (55.9 mL vs 44.5 mL) and the RV (53.7 mL vs 45.6 mL). This difference remained significant even after excluding athletic controls (n = 5) from the control group. The maximum wall thickness of the LV was normal and similar between controls (median 9 mm) and patients (8 mm). Global T1 and T2 times were all within scanner-specific normal value ranges and values at 3T were comparable between controls (median T1 1232 ms; median T2 41 ms) and patients (T1 1232 ms, T2 40 ms). T1 values at 1.5T showed a significant difference (p = 0.042) between cases (1009 ms) and controls (1092 ms), which is however underpowered due to the small sample size at 1.5T (4 controls, 3 patients) and was not significant after adjustment for confounders. The adjustment for the confounders age, sex, hypertension, and asthma for all other previous analyses did not alter the results. <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the CMR results of both groups and both unadjusted and adjusted group differences.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0015" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Results derived from the standard contrast-free CMR in cases and controls.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0035">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Group difference<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Controls</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Long COVID</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted<xref rid="tbltbl0015fn8457" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 27</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p =</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p =</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">LV-EDV (indexed, mL/m²)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[83.1; 95.2]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[69.1; 83.9]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">LV-ESV (indexed, mL/m²)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[31.1; 38.8]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[25.9; 34.8]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.053</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.019</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">LV-EF (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[57.5; 64.0]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[56.1; 62.6]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.384</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.350</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">LV-GLS (-%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[17.7; 20.6]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[17.7; 20.0]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.647</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.616</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">LV-SV (indexed, mL/m²)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[49.2; 59.2]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[41.2; 46.6]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Max. wall thickness LV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[8; 11]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[8; 11]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.541</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.198</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">RV-EDV (indexed, mL/m²)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[88.5; 102.3]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[70.5; 92.5]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">RV-ESV (indexed, mL/m²)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[35.8; 49.0]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[30.0; 41.8]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.030</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">RV-EF (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[52.2; 60.4]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[51.9; 58.7]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.467</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.448</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">RV-GLS (-%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[20.8; 26.5]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[19.9; 25.5]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.807</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.806</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">RV-SV (indexed, mL/m²)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[50.5; 57.3]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[41.1; 48.6]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">LA volume</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[59; 80]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[43; 67]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.012</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.018</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">LA longitudinal strain (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[30.9; 46.8]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[28.8; 42.8]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.192</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.154</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">RA volume</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[73; 96]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[59; 80]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.009</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">RA longitudinal strain (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[27.1; 51.1]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[31.4; 48.3]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.579</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.560</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Global T1 times (ms, 1.5T)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1092</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[1070; 1098]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1009</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[992; 1022]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.042</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.159</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Global T1 times (ms, 3T)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1232</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[1212; 1246]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1232</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[1204; 1256]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.544</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.499</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Global T2 times (ms, 1.5T)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[48; 50]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[46; 48]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.079</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Global T2 times (ms, 3T)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[39; 42]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[38; 42]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.194</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.179</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0065"><p><italic toggle="yes">LV</italic> left ventricular, <italic toggle="yes">EDV</italic> end-diastolic volume, <italic toggle="yes">ESV</italic> end-systolic volume, <italic toggle="yes">EF</italic> ejection fraction, <italic toggle="yes">GLS</italic> global longitudinal strain, <italic toggle="yes">SV</italic> stroke volume, <italic toggle="yes">RV</italic> right ventricular, <italic toggle="yes">LA</italic> left atrial, <italic toggle="yes">RA</italic> right atrial, <italic toggle="yes">COVID</italic> coronavirus disease, <italic toggle="yes">CMR</italic> cardiovascular magnetic resonance</p></fn><fn id="sp0070"><p>The local reference values for the mapping sequences are:</p></fn><fn id="sp0075"><p>1.5T: 1010 ms [910–1110] for T1 and 48 ms [44–52] for T2</p></fn><fn id="sp0080"><p>3T: 1180 ms [1116–1244] for T1 and 38 ms [32–44] for T2</p></fn><fn id="sp0085"><p>Values are given as median (Interquartile range).</p></fn><fn id="sp0090"><p>Significant group differences are highlighted in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbltbl0015fn8457"><label>*</label><p id="ntp0010">Adjusted for age, sex, hypertension, and asthma</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0050"><label>3.3</label><title>Vasoactive breathing maneuver</title><p id="p0065">At rest, patients and controls had a normal resting heart rate as well as inconspicuous oxygen saturation and blood pressure. During metronome-paced hyperventilation, a similar portion of controls and patients experienced temporary side effects (55.6% vs 64.5%). Vital parameters and side effects are detailed in <xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. Patient compliance, breathing depth, and breathing rate were excellent (26/31 patients [83.9%]; 23/27 controls [85.2%]) or good (5/31 [16.1%]; 4/27 [14.8%]) in all participants. Field strength was not associated with B-MORE results (p = 1.0). In contrast, the heart rate response was significantly different between patients and controls (p &lt; 0.001) with an increase of 35/min [21; 45] in controls and 15/min [7; 26] in patients, illustrated in <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. After adjustment for age, sex, arterial hypertension, and asthma, the heart rate response remained significant (p &lt; 0.001), while only age (p = 0.021) and asthma (p = 0.036) revealed a significant correlation with the heart rate response (p &gt; 0.05 for the rest). The B-MORE was 9.8% in controls [4.3; 17.2] and 7.3% in patients [3.4; 10.4] with a significant difference between the groups (p = 0.044). After adjusting for age, sex, arterial hypertension, and asthma, B-MORE remained significant (p = 0.049), while none of the confounders were significantly associated with B-MORE (p &gt; 0.05 for all). <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> show B-MORE results for both groups and detail unadjusted and adjusted group differences. Both heart rate response and B-MORE were not correlated with NTproBNP levels, presence and severity of shortness of breath, left ventricular EF, volume, or GLS (p &gt; 0.05 for all). In controls, neither heart rate response nor B-MORE was different between athletic and non-athletic participants (p = 0.827; p = 0.542). In a subgroup analysis of the patient group, there was no statistical difference in heart rate response (p = 0.372) or B-MORE (p = 0.834) between those after COVID illness versus those after vaccination. The full subgroup analysis can be found in <xref rid="sec0090" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0020" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Results from the hyperventilation stress between cases and controls.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0040">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Group difference<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Controls</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Long COVID</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted<xref rid="tbltbl0020fn5047" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 27</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">n = 31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p =</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Length of breath-hold at expiration (s)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥60</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.2%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.9%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.551</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.318</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.9%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Side effects during hyperventilation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.6%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.5%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tingling sensation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.0%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.5%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dizziness</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.5%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.1%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other<xref rid="tbltbl0020fn2038" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Blood pressure at rest (mmHg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Systolic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">131</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[120; 141]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">125</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[116; 135]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.080</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.066</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diastolic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[72; 83]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[72; 84]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.380</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.388</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Oxygen saturation at rest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[95; 99]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[96; 99]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.539</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.646</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR at rest (/min)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[56; 74]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[62; 74]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.578</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.575</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peak HR during hyperventilation (/min)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">97</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[83; 125]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[72; 92]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Heart rate difference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[21; 45]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[7; 26]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">B-MORE (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[4.3; 17.2]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[3.4; 10.4]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.044</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.049</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0100"><p><italic toggle="yes">HR</italic> heart rate, <italic toggle="yes">B-MORE</italic> Breathing-induced myocardial oxygenation reserve, <italic toggle="yes">COVID</italic> coronavirus disease</p></fn><fn id="sp0105"><p>Significant group differences are highlighted in bold.</p></fn><fn id="sp0110"><p>Continous values are given as median (Interquartile range). Binary values are given as percentages with numerator and denominator.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbltbl0020fn5047"><label>*</label><p id="ntp0015">Adjusted for age, sex, hypertension, and asthma</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbltbl0020fn2038"><label>†</label><p id="ntp0020">Headache, dry mouth, palpitations. No serious side effects occurred. All side effects ceased within 30 s</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig0015" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Individual heart rate response in controls (A) and cases (B) before and during a 60-s metronome-paced hyperventilation. (C) Displays the heart rate increase between groups. The heart rate response was blunted (p &lt; 0.001) in cases as opposed to controls</p></caption><alt-text id="at0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0015" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig0020" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Breathing-induced myocardial oxygenation reserve (B-MORE) in cases and controls</p></caption><alt-text id="at0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0020" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0055"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0070">This present study is the first to show a potential benefit of using OS-CMR and breathing maneuvers in the assessment of long COVID patients. In contrast to a group of controls indifferent concerning age, gender, body mass index, and cardiovascular risk factors, the hyperventilation-induced heart rate increase was blunted in long COVID cases (15/min vs 35/min, p &lt; 0.001). Additionally, OS-CMR revealed a significant difference in B-MORE between controls (B-MORE 9.8%) and cases (B-MORE 7.3%, p = 0.044), which remained significant after adjusting for age, sex, hypertension, and asthma (p = 0.049). Taken together, these results might suggest an impaired vascular responsiveness and presence of endothelial dysfunction.</p><p id="p0075">CMR may be the current gold standard to assess structural pathologies and has proven valuable in diagnosing acute myocardial inflammation following COVID-19 infection or vaccination <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. However, its role in the assessment of long-term myocardial changes is less established. In the literature, a mild vaccine- or infection-related long-term myocardial injury has been described <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. However, assessed parameters such as LV-EF, GLS, and T1/T2 times were still within normal range and detected changes did not correlate with clinical symptoms <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Similarly, the standard CMR sequences in the present study did not reveal any significant cardiac pathologies. Consistent with previous literature, indexed stroke volumes of patients were lower when compared with controls, but still within normal range <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. It remains unlikely that these deviations in stroke volume and previously found mild myocardial tissue abnormalities alone are responsible for the clinical presentation of long COVID, leaving the pathophysiology of long COVID unanswered. Here, our study may provide a new link pointing toward the endothelium as a critical structure in the development of long COVID. Hyperventilation is a natural stressor inducing an endothelium-dependent vasoconstriction mediated through low CO<sub>2</sub> levels, while the post-hyperventilation breath-hold leads to an increase in CO<sub>2</sub> and subsequent vasodilation <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Coronary vasodilation in healthy individuals results in a “luxury perfusion” with increased coronary blood flow without an associated increase of demand, which decreases the proportion of deoxygenated hemoglobin in the myocardium. In OS-CMR images, this leads to a myocardial signal intensity increase, which can be semi-quantitatively expressed with the B-MORE <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Hyperventilation, however, also activates the neuro-humoral axis and increases the rate-pressure product, which increases demand. This triggers a heart rate increase that is reduced in patients with heart disease <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Since both B-MORE and heart rate increase are diminished in long COVID patients when compared to controls in our study, a crucial role of the endothelium seems likely. This is in accordance with extensive literature on the pathophysiology of long COVID, although this study is the first to apply this to the heart and test it clinically <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. The inability to adequately react to external or internal stress on top of a decreased stroke volume despite a structurally inconspicuous heart might explain many of the symptoms described by long COVID patients <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. This study is only a first step toward a potential implementation of OS-CMR with vasoactive breathing maneuvers into the standard assessment of long COVID patients, as the protocol currently still faces obstacles. Specifically, the overlap between cases and controls leaves a level of uncertainty for the individual patient. However, previous studies have demonstrated that the heterogeneity of myocardial oxygenation might play a significant role <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Normal (or even elevated) segments can coexist with pathologically reduced ones, potentially masking abnormalities in the global signal despite high levels of abnormalities. Furthermore, the introduction of machine learning-enhanced analysis of the whole cardiac cycle may significantly improve the signal-to-noise ratio. The measurements of B-MORE in the control group in the present study were comparable to previous measurements of healthy individuals in other studies <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Interestingly, a recent study did not find any perfusion deficits in a cohort of long COVID patients, which might seem in contrast to our study’s findings <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. However, previous studies comparing both perfusion and oxygenation in the same patients indicated that these are overlapping but distinct phenomena <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><label>5</label><title>Limitations</title><p id="p0080">Our study has several limitations. First, as a hypothesis-generating case-control study, the case number is limited, and results may not apply to other populations. Specifically, the indifference between the post vaccination and post COVID subgroups might not hold in a larger study group. Future studies and larger case numbers are needed to confirm the described observations and to apply them to other organ systems as well. Second, it remains possible that the differences between the two groups were caused by different levels of compliance with the breathing maneuvers. To address this, all participants were instructed to follow a highly standardized protocol and practice hyperventilation. Furthermore, patient compliance was ensured both visually and automatically and the derived rating scale revealed an excellent or good compliance in all cases. Since the breath-hold was at expiration, its length of &gt;35 s in all participants and ≥60 s in 83.9% of the participants points toward a significant effect of hyperventilation. Otherwise, a breath-hold of that length would be hardly achievable at expiration. Ultimately, the rate of hyperventilation-induced side effects did not differ between patients and controls. Thus, a significant bias is highly unlikely. Third, an objective assessment of physical activity of both patients and controls would have been valuable for correlating with the study’s findings. Fourth, the analysis of late gadolinium enhancement images would have certainly been of interest to achieve better comparability to previous studies. However, we believe that the risk of missing these mild changes of unknown clinical significance is outweighed by the benefit of the fast and needle-free CMR protocol that saves both time and resources. Fifth, an underlying lung pathology may have contributed to the results as it may limit the peak oxygen uptake. However, this cannot explain the blunted heart rate response and patients did not have any known lung comorbidity. Sixth, the inclusion of both patients post COVID vaccination and post COVID illness into one study group assumes that both entities are clinically comparable. However, research especially for the pathophysiology of symptoms after COVID vaccination is scarce and the disease is not yet well understood <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. In this study, however, apart from length of symptoms, a detailed subgroup analysis (<xref rid="sec0090" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table 1</xref>) did not reveal any statistical differences between both subgroups, neither concerning clinical presentation nor cardiac biomarkers, standard CMR, or hyperventilation stress OS-CMR.</p></sec><sec id="sec0065"><label>6</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0085">In conclusion, the current study introduces breathing maneuvers and OS-CMR as new tools in the assessment of long COVID patients that may extend the diagnostic capabilities of CMR and highlight a potential role of the endothelium in the pathophysiology of long COVID. The results indicate an impaired hemodynamic and myocardial oxygenation responsiveness, possibly reflecting an altered coronary vasoreactivity and a direct impact of COVID-19 on coronary vascular integrity. However, this should be confirmed in larger trials and correlated to symptoms and objectifiable functional capacity.</p></sec><sec id="sec0070"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0090">For the analysis of the OS-CMR images, the authors were provided with one free research license by Circle Cardiovascular Imaging. L.D.W. was supported by the Rotation Grand (<award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">D.10021788</award-id>) of the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100010447</institution-id><institution>DZHK</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (German Centre for Cardiovascular Research). Circle Cardiovascular Imaging and the DZHK did not have any influence on design, analysis, or interpretation of the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec0075"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0095"><bold>Lukas D. Weberling:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Writing – original draft, Visualization, Supervision, Project administration, Methodology, Investigation, Funding acquisition, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Matthias G. Friedrich:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Supervision, Software. <bold>Elizabeth Hillier:</bold> Writing – original draft, Supervision, Methodology. <bold>Norbert Frey:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Resources. <bold>Marc Zahlten:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Methodology, Investigation, Data curation. <bold>Henning Steen:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Writing – original draft, Supervision, Resources, Project administration, Investigation, Funding acquisition, Conceptualization. <bold>Florian André:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Supervision.</p></sec><sec id="sec0080"><title>Ethics approval and consent</title><p id="p0100">This study was approved by the ethical committee of our university (S-361/2022) and carried out in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent was given by all patients and controls.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0005"><title>Declaration of competing interests</title><p id="p0105">The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Lukas D. Weberling reports equipment, drugs, or supplies were provided by Circle Cardiovascular Imaging Inc. Lukas D. Weberling reports article publishing charges were provided by German Research Foundation. Lukas D. Weberling reports financial support was provided by German Center for Cardiovascular Disease. Matthias G. Friedrich and Elizabeth Hillier report a relationship with Area 19 Medical Inc. that includes consulting or advisory. The other authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibliog0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="othref0005">World Health Organization. WHO COVID-19 dashboard; 2024. Updated August 8, 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int" id="ir0010">https://covid19.who.int</ext-link> (accessed 8 August 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleine-Weber</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krüger</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erichsen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 cell entry depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and is blocked by a clinically proven protease inhibitor</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>181</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>280.e8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32142651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polack</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitchin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Absalon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurtman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety and efficacy of the BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 vaccine</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>383</volume><issue>27</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>2603</fpage><lpage>2615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33301246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa2034577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7745181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholkmann</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19, post-acute COVID-19 syndrome (PACS, “long COVID”) and post-COVID-19 vaccination syndrome (PCVS, “post-COVIDvac-syndrome”): similarities and differences</article-title><source>Pathol Res Pract</source><volume>246</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">154497</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.prp.2023.154497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10154064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37192595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doeblin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahnke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Tabatabaee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goetze</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CMR findings after COVID-19 and after COVID-19-vaccination-same but different?</article-title><source>Int J Cardiovasc Imaging</source><volume>38</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>2057</fpage><lpage>2071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37726611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10554-022-02623-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9097142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postacute sequelae of COVID-19 at 2 years</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>29</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>2347</fpage><lpage>2357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37605079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-023-02521-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10504070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uusitalo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaara</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmström</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuorinen</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heliö</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiac magnetic resonance -detected myocardial injury is not associated with long-term symptoms in patients hospitalized due to COVID-19</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0282394</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0282394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9994679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36888600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoubkhani</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bermingham</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pouwels</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nafilyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaccardi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trajectory of long covid symptoms after covid-19 vaccination: community based cohort study</article-title><source>Bmj</source><volume>377</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e069676</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj-2021-069676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9115603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35584816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reis Carneiro</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helbok</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sellner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Struhal</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical presentation and management strategies of cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction following a COVID-19 infection - a systematic review</article-title><source>Eur J Neurol</source><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1528</fpage><lpage>1539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36694382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ene.15714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Appelman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlton</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerkhoff</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breedveld</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noort</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Muscle abnormalities worsen after post-exertional malaise in long COVID</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38177128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-023-44432-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10766651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Libby</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lüscher</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 is, in the end, an endothelial disease</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><volume>41</volume><issue>32</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>3038</fpage><lpage>3044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32882706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurheartj/ehaa623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7470753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>K.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimmeler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 induced vascular endothelial dysfunction: direct or indirect effects?</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><volume>120</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38159046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cvr/cvad191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaskamp</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roubal</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sotzny</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kedor</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum of post-COVID-19 syndrome patients with or without ME/CFS differentially affects endothelial cell function in vitro</article-title><source>Cells</source><volume>11</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>2376</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35954219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cells11152376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9367589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iannino</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hafyane</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mongeon</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myocardial vascular function assessed by dynamic oxygenation-sensitive cardiac magnetic resonance imaging long-term following cardiac transplantation</article-title><source>Transplantation</source><volume>105</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1347</fpage><lpage>1355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32804801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/TP.0000000000003419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaji</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luescher</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Tengg-Kobligk</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Feasibility of cardiovascular magnetic resonance to detect oxygenation deficits in patients with multi-vessel coronary artery disease triggered by breathing maneuvers</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</source><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29730991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12968-018-0446-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5937049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roubille</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guensch</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tardif</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of hyperventilation and apnea on myocardial oxygenation in patients with obstructive sleep apnea - an oxygenation-sensitive CMR study</article-title><source>J Cardiol</source><volume>69</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27256216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jjcc.2016.03.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guensch</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Tengg-Kobligk</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannetti</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insights into myocardial oxygenation and cardiovascular magnetic resonance tissue biomarkers in heart failure with preserved ejection fraction</article-title><source>Circ Heart Fail</source><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e008903</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCHEARTFAILURE.121.008903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35038887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Covone</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The reproducibility of breathing maneuvers as a vasoactive stimulus in the heart: an oxygenation-sensitive resonance imaging study</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</source><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">81</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12968-023-00983-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10753842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38151725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elharram</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heydari</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regional heterogeneity in the coronary vascular response in women with chest pain and nonobstructive coronary artery disease</article-title><source>Circulation</source><volume>143</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33587662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.120.052520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential of oxygenation-sensitive CMR in heart failure</article-title><source>Curr Heart Fail Rep</source><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34378154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11897-021-00525-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guensch</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of myocardial oxygenation to breathing manoeuvres and adenosine infusion</article-title><source>Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Imaging</source><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25336541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ehjci/jeu202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Covone</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxygenation-sensitive cardiac MRI with vasoactive breathing maneuvers for the non-invasive assessment of coronary microvascular dysfunction</article-title><source>J Vis Exp</source><issue>186</issue><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3791/64149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36062996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koczulla</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ankermann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrends</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlit</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Böing</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>German S1 guideline long-/post-COVID</article-title><source>Pneumologie</source><volume>76</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36479679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/a-1946-3230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>R Core Team</surname></name></person-group><part-title>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</part-title><comment>07.0/548 ed.</comment><year>2022</year><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez Tijmes</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thavendiranathan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Udell</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanneman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiac MRI assessment of nonischemic myocardial inflammation: state of the art review and update on myocarditis associated with COVID-19 vaccination</article-title><source>Radiol Cardiothorac Imaging</source><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e210252</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1148/ryct.210252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8686006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34934954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fronza</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thavendiranathan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karur</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Udell</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wald</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Myocardial injury pattern at MRI in COVID-19 vaccine–associated myocarditis</article-title><source>Radiology</source><volume>304</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35166587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1148/radiol.212559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8856022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafiee</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MRI of cardiac involvement in COVID-19</article-title><source>Br J Radiol</source><volume>97</volume><issue>1160</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38656976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bjr/tqae086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11256941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>V.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plein</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raisi-Estabragh</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular magnetic resonance for evaluation of cardiac involvement in COVID-19: recommendations by the Society for Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</source><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>21</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36973744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12968-023-00933-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10041524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puntmann</surname><given-names>VO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carerj</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieters</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arendt</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Outcomes of cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging in patients recently recovered from coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)</article-title><source>JAMA Cardiol</source><volume>5</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>1273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32730619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamacardio.2020.3557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7385689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puntmann</surname><given-names>V.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shchendrygina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ka</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giokoglu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term cardiac pathology in individuals with mild initial COVID-19 illness</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>28</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>2117</fpage><lpage>2123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36064600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-022-02000-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9556300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moravsky</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weitsman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amsalem</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bar-Sheshet Itach</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Algur</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A prospective study on myocardial injury after BNT162b2 mRNA COVID-19 fourth dose vaccination in healthy persons</article-title><source>Eur J Heart Fail</source><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36097844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ejhf.2687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9538001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guensch</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinco</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadeshalingham</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperventilation-induced heart rate response as a potential marker for cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">17887</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-019-54375-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6884614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31784617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teuwen</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geldhof</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pasut</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmeliet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19: the vasculature unleashed</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32439870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41577-020-0343-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7240244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salatzki</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochs</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weberling</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahlten</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whayne</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Absence of cardiac impairment in patients after severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus type 2 infection: a long-term follow-up study</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</source><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101124</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jocmr.2024.101124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11663758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39549839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michelen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkheir</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dagens</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterising long COVID: a living systematic review</article-title><source>BMJ Glob Health</source><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e005427</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjgh-2021-005427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8478580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34580069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorecka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jex</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thirunavukarasu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhary</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corrado</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging and spectroscopy in clinical long-COVID-19 syndrome: a prospective case-control study</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</source><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">50</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12968-022-00887-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9464490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36089591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamitsos</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhamra-Ariza</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Myocardial oxygenation in coronary artery disease: insights from blood oxygen level-dependent magnetic resonance imaging at 3 tesla</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><volume>59</volume><issue>22</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1954</fpage><lpage>1964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22624835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jacc.2012.01.055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamitsos</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leccisotti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Recio-Mayoral</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhamra-Ariza</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howells</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between regional myocardial oxygenation and perfusion in patients with coronary artery disease: insights from cardiovascular magnetic resonance and positron emission tomography</article-title><source>Circ Cardiovasc Imaging</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19920032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCIMAGING.109.860148</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec0090" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary material</title><p id="p0120"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary material</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0005"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="p0005">The datasets used and analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0110">The authors would like to thank Silke Morgenstern, Ute Pfeiffer, and the other members of the CMR team at the sites in Hannover and Hamburg for their outstanding support in the conduction of this study. Also, the authors would like to acknowledge the help of Maggie Leo in setting up this study.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="sec0085" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0115">Supplementary data associated with this article can be found in the online version at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jocmr.2025.101890" id="ir0005">doi:10.1016/j.jocmr.2025.101890</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>