<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Allergy Clin Immunol Glob</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Allergy Clin Immunol Glob</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4505</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jacig</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology: Global</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2772-8293</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12803966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12803966.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12803966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12803966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41550084</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacig.2025.100620</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2772-8293(25)00221-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100620</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 mRNA revaccination is safe and well tolerated in individuals with previous adverse reactions to the vaccine and/or long COVID</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slack</surname><given-names initials="IF">Ian F.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>islack@med.umich.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Shea</surname><given-names initials="KM">Kelly M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freigeh</surname><given-names initials="GE">George E.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names initials="LM">Lea M.</given-names></name><degrees>BS, MS</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaafar</surname><given-names initials="S">Sara</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuler</surname><given-names initials="CF">Charles F.</given-names><suffix>IV</suffix></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names initials="JR">James R.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of Allergy and Clinical Immunology, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Mary H. Weiser Food Allergy Center, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Division of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology, Department of Pediatrics, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Michigan Nanotechnology Institute for Medicine and Biological Sciences, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author: Ian F. Slack, MD, Division of Allergy and Clinical Immunology, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Michigan, 24 Frank Lloyd Wright Dr, Lobby H, Ste H2100, Ann Arbor, MI 48106. <email>islack@med.umich.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">504152</issue-id><elocation-id>100620</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-19 15:25:12.797"><day>19</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Vaccine safety is a primary concern among those with a history of adverse reactions to coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) mRNA vaccines. Retrospective data and cohorts of individuals with severe previous reactions suggest that revaccination is safe and well tolerated. However, prospective data are limited.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p>We sought to prospectively assess safety and tolerability of COVID-19 mRNA vaccines in individuals with a history of adverse vaccine reactions and in individuals with long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Adults with a self-reported adverse reaction to COVID-19 mRNA vaccination and/or long COVID underwent COVID-19 mRNA revaccination at the University of Michigan with 30-minute observations. Participants were contacted by telephone after 7 days to review interval adverse events.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 103 participants received COVID-19 mRNA revaccination—91 with history of adverse vaccine reaction, 20 with long COVID, and 8 with both. Mean age at enrollment was 41.8 years, and women were 67% of the cohort. Five individuals (4.9%) developed immediate symptoms with revaccination. All 5 events were mild (Consortium for Food Allergy Research severity level 1). Vital signs were assessed prevaccination and 30 minutes postvaccination. At 7-day follow-up, 77% of participants reported at least 1 adverse event, with fatigue (33.7%), headache (29.7%), and muscle pain (28.7%) most commonly reported. No follow-up reactions were severe. Five of the 103 participants had incidentally elevated baseline serum tryptase. None of these participants experienced immediate symptoms with revaccination.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Revaccination with COVID-19 mRNA vaccines was safe and well tolerated among individuals with previous adverse COVID-19 mRNA vaccine reaction and/or long COVID.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Key words</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>mRNA vaccine</kwd><kwd>adverse reaction</kwd><kwd>revaccination</kwd><kwd>tryptase</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><def-list><title>Abbreviations used</title><def-item><term id="kwrd0045">AE</term><def><p>Adverse event</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0055">CoFAR</term><def><p>Consortium for Food Allergy Research</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0065">COVID-19</term><def><p>Coronavirus disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0075">mRNA</term><def><p>Messenger RNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></front><body><p id="p0010">Initial use of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) messenger RNA (mRNA) vaccines during the pandemic was accompanied by concerns for systemic allergic reactions following dosing.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Global efforts to assess real-world safety of these vaccines estimated rates of COVID-19 vaccine anaphylaxis at 7.9 events per million doses.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Although anaphylaxis is quite rare with COVID-19 mRNA vaccines, other adverse reactions including pain, fever, and fatigue are expected side effects due to the induction of immunity and affect most patients following administration.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Both severe and mild adverse reactions can drive vaccine hesitancy, and vaccine safety is frequently cited as a concern in this context.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Vaccine hesitancy can persist even after receiving COVID-19 immunization.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></p><p id="p0015">Despite this, the benefits of COVID-19 vaccination include a significantly decreased risk of COVID-19–related emergency room visits, hospitalizations, and deaths.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> The improved outcomes are particularly prominent among those with risk factors for severe COVID-19 infection, including older age and multiple medical comorbidities.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Vaccination appears to decrease the risk of subsequent development of long COVID syndrome; however, data are mixed on the effects of vaccination on existing long COVID, although some reports note potential benefit.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Despite the potential benefits of vaccination to those experiencing long COVID, varied perspectives on COVID-19 vaccination have been noted, essentially reflecting vaccine perspectives of the general population.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref></p><p id="p0020">Because safety concerns continue to present a barrier to ongoing COVID-19 vaccination, we conducted a single-arm clinical trial providing COVID-19 mRNA vaccinations. This study assessed individuals with a history of adverse reactions to COVID-19 mRNA vaccines as well as those with a history of long COVID to prospectively assess symptoms associated with subsequent vaccination.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Methods</title><p id="p0025">This prospective cohort study was performed at the University of Michigan and funded by a grant from the Wallace Foundation (award no. 019850). The University of Michigan Institutional Review Board approved the study (HUM00206480). All participants provided written informed consent.</p><p id="p0030">Participants 18 years or older with a history of adverse reaction to a previous COVID-19 mRNA vaccine or documented history of long COVID as per symptom report were eligible for enrollment. Patients with long COVID were primarily recruited from a multidisciplinary long COVID clinic at the University of Michigan. All participants received either a COVID-19 vaccine primary series or booster dosing in the study as per the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention recommendations.</p><p id="p0035">Exclusion criteria included the following: individuals with self-reported COVID-19 infection within 21 days or convalescent plasma within 90 days of vaccination appointment, pregnant individuals, those with immunocompromised status, a history of malignancy with recent chemotherapy, use of biologic therapeutic agents, participants with chronic kidney disease stage 3 or higher, and/or a history of significant pulmonary compromise. Individuals with physician-diagnosed anaphylaxis to the COVID-19 mRNA vaccine were also excluded, because package inserts specifically recommend against vaccination in this population.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p id="p0040">Participants were recruited from clinic populations, including the University of Michigan multidisciplinary long COVID clinic. Additional recruitment occurred through social media ads, print and digital flyers, and mass emails to students and institutional employees. Previous vaccination status was reviewed with participants, and participants were asked whether their initial symptoms with COVID-19 mRNA vaccination were immediate (&lt;2 hours of vaccination) or delayed (&gt;2 hours following vaccination). Baseline laboratory data including COVID spike antibody status, complete metabolic panel, complete blood cell count with differential, serum pregnancy testing, serum tryptase level, and urinalysis were obtained and reviewed before vaccination.</p><p id="p0045">Initially, participants received the same COVID-19 vaccine to which they experienced adverse symptoms—either Pfizer-BioNTech or Moderna—as authorized under the Food and Drug Administration emergency use authorization or approval. Beginning in August 2023, participants received the Pfizer-BioNTech vaccine regardless of their vaccination history. This update in protocol occurred because of vaccine sourcing and availability changes through the University of Michigan pharmacy system.</p><p id="p0050">At the study visit, baseline vital signs were obtained and a physical examination done before vaccination. Following vaccination in the deltoid muscle, all participants were monitored for a minimum of 30 minutes postvaccination and queried for any immediate adverse events (AEs). AEs were graded on the Consortium for Food Allergy Research (CoFAR) Grading Scale for Systemic Allergic Reactions version 3.0.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Vital signs were obtained again before discharge at least 30 minutes following vaccination. Study coordinators contacted participants by telephone 7 days following vaccination to elicit any additional AEs in the interval period. Individuals were asked to report symptom quality, timing of onset and offset, and any additional medications or health care utilization required to manage the symptoms. Investigators reviewed the AEs and graded severity using the same CoFAR Grading Scale for Systemic Allergic Reactions version 3.0.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Data were stored and analyzed using Research Electronic Data Capture (Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tenn), and additional descriptive statistics were generated in Microsoft Excel (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, Wash) and GraphPad Prism (GraphPad Software, San Diego, Calif). Two-tailed paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used to compare prevaccination and postvaccination vital signs and long COVID outcomes by subgroup.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><p id="p0055">A total of 137 individuals consented for the study, of whom 103 received a study vaccination with a COVID-19 mRNA vaccine (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). Seven-day follow-up for delayed AE review was completed for 101 participants; 2 were lost to follow-up. Most of the participants (81.6%) had completed their primary COVID-19 vaccine series and had received at least 1 booster dose (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table I</xref>). A total of 91 participants (88.3%) noted at least 1 AE with previous COVID-19 mRNA vaccination, whereas 20 participants (18.4%) reported a long COVID diagnosis. Eight participants (7.8%) reported both long COVID diagnosis and adverse reaction to the COVID-19 mRNA vaccine (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table I</xref>).<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig 1</label><caption><p>Consort diagram of study participants.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table I</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total (N = 103)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (y), mean ± SD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.8 ± 15.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex, n (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (67.0)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (31.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Undisclosed</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race, n (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> White</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 (69.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Asian</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (15.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Black</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Other and/or multiple races</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unknown</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethnicity, n (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Non-Hispanic</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97 (94.2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hispanic</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (3.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unknown</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Previous COVID-19 vaccine status, n (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Single dose</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (7.8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Two doses</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (10.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> At least 1 booster dose</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (81.6)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Long COVID diagnosis, n (%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (19.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Physician diagnosis</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (14.6)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Self-diagnosis</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">COVID-19 vaccine adverse reaction history, n (%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (88.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78 (75.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Moderna</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (50.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Both</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (30.1)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0060">Five participants (4.9%) developed immediate symptoms within 30 minutes of COVID-19 vaccination (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table II</xref>). All 5 participants had a history of immediate symptoms with their first COVID-19 mRNA vaccination. Three of the 5 reported pruritus without rash. One individual noted subjective sensation of lip swelling. The final participant experienced a flare of preexisting migraine headache disorder. All reactions were graded CoFAR level 1 severity, and no participant required treatment with epinephrine or respiratory therapies. Of note, a participant who had experienced symptoms of immediate chest tightness, bronchospasm, cough, and tongue swelling on 3 previous vaccinations with both Pfizer-BioNTech and Moderna COVID-19 mRNA vaccines subsequently tolerated their booster dose with no immediate symptoms. In addition, 3 participants with history of immediate symptoms but not physician-documented anaphylaxis with previous COVID-19 mRNA vaccination tolerated their subsequent dose in the study without immediate symptom report as well. All participants without a history of immediate AEs with previous vaccination did not experience an immediate AE in the study.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table II</label><caption><p>Subjects with immediate vaccine reactions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Historical adverse reactions<hr/></th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Immediate adverse reactions with revaccination<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subject</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaccine</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dose</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptoms</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaccine</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptoms</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CoFAR severity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dizziness</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hives, jaw pain, hypertension</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lip swelling</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cetirizine 20 mg</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Facial pruritus, lip swelling</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pruritus</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cetirizine 20 mg</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderna</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Throat tightness, acral swelling</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderna</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Migraine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acetaminophen, aspirin, caffeine, rimegapant</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderna</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hives, facial pruritus, mouth itching, dyspnea</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderna</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pruritus</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cetirizine 20 mg</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech and Moderna</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 3, 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea, chest tightness, cough, tongue swelling</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderna</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea, chest tightness, throat tightness</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea, wheeze, flushing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech and Moderna</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1, 2, 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Throat tightness, rash</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer-BioNTech</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pruritus</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cetirizine 10 mg</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">NA</italic>, Not applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0065">Vital signs were measured prevaccination and at least 30 minutes postvaccination to assess for objective signs of COVID-19 mRNA vaccine reaction (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Respiratory rate, systolic and diastolic blood pressures, and blood oxygen saturation were not significantly changed for vaccine recipients. There was a statistically significant decrease in heart rate postvaccination (mean decrease of 1.7 beats/min; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .03), although the small magnitude was not clinically significant.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig 2</label><caption><p><bold>A-E</bold>, Stable vital signs prevaccination and postvaccination: pairwise analysis of heart rate (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>), respiratory rate (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>), systolic blood pressure (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>), diastolic blood pressure (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>), and blood oxygen saturation (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>). Postvaccination vital signs were taken at least 30 minutes after vaccination. ∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> ≤ .05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0070">The 91 participants with adverse COVID-19 mRNA vaccine reaction reported a total of 1420 symptom events with historical vaccination (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>). Fatigue (87.8%), headache (63.3%), and muscle pain (60.0%) were the most commonly reported symptoms within the adverse reaction cohort. Nine participants reported symptom onset within 2 hours of vaccination (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table III</xref>). Six of these 9 participants had noted symptoms occurring with their initial COVID-19 mRNA vaccine. Symptoms included hives and pruritus, soft tissue swelling, dyspnea, and hypertension. Two individuals reported their immediate symptoms occurring reproducibly with multiple vaccine doses.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig 3</label><caption><p><bold>A</bold>, Symptoms reported with previous COVID-19 mRNA vaccination. <bold>B,</bold> Symptoms reported at 7-day postvaccination follow-up, stratified by history of adverse reaction to mRNA vaccine and long COVID history.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE III</label><caption><p>Participants with incidentally elevated tryptase</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participants</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline tryptase (ng/mL)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adverse reaction history</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Long COVID</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Immediate symptoms with vaccination</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delayed symptoms with vaccination</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea with second dose</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lost to follow-up</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fever with second dose</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue, muscle pain</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diarrhea with first dose</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache, diarrhea</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Joint pain, chills, and headache with second and third doses</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0075">A total of 101 participants completed the 1-week follow-up for delayed AE report, of whom 78 participants (77.2%) reported 173 symptom events (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). Injection-site pain was the most commonly reported symptom (34.7%). Fatigue (33.7%), headache (29.7%), and muscle pain (28.7%) were the next most commonly experienced AEs. These symptoms correspond to common historical symptom report, although these were noted less frequently in the study (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). Seven-day AEs were generally rare in the long COVID cohort, with the most common symptom of injection-site reaction occurring in 4.0% of participants (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). AE rates reported at 7 days postvaccination were not significantly different between individuals with self-diagnosed and those with physician-diagnosed long COVID (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .5017; see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig E1</xref> in this article’s Online Repository at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jaci-global.org" id="intref0010">www.jaci-global.org</ext-link>).</p><p id="p0080">Baseline serum tryptase was collected on all study participants and did not affect inclusion or exclusion from the trial. Five of the 103 participants (4.9%) had elevated baseline tryptase ranging from 12.9 to 20.2 ng/mL (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table III</xref>). Four of these participants had experienced adverse reaction to previous vaccination and 3 carried long COVID diagnoses. None of the 5 participants experienced immediate symptoms with revaccination. Two of the 5 reported mild delayed symptoms inconsistent with IgE-mediated hypersensitivity, and 1 individual was lost to follow-up.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0085">More than 75% of individuals receiving initial COVID-19 mRNA vaccination report at least 1 AE.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> With vaccine safety cited as a top concern for those with COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy,<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> it is essential to have accurate, prospective data regarding the safety of subsequent COVID-19 vaccination after an initial AE. This single-site prospective study reinforces the safety of COVID-19 mRNA revaccination in individuals with a history of adverse reaction to COVID-19 mRNA vaccine and/or a diagnosis of long COVID.</p><p id="p0090">This study concords with 1 retrospective study and 1 very focused prospective study demonstrating the safety of COVID-19 vaccination after a previous AE.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> Our inclusion of any previously experienced adverse reaction to the COVID-19 mRNA vaccine allowed us to evaluate a larger cohort of 90 individuals for revaccination. Among these, 28% experienced no AEs with revaccination. Symptoms that were experienced with revaccination were mild and occurred at lower frequency than with historical vaccinations. We also included a cohort of 20 individuals with long COVID symptoms who also tolerated revaccination. Eight of these 20 (40.0%) had no symptoms with subsequent vaccination, with the remainder experiencing mild AEs inconsistent with IgE-mediated symptoms. Measurement of vital signs prevaccination and postvaccination demonstrated no evidence of objective reaction to the COVID-19 mRNA vaccines.</p><p id="p0095">The safety profile of COVID-19 mRNA revaccination also applies to participants with incidentally elevated serum tryptase levels. Previous retrospective work has suggested COVID-19 mRNA vaccine safety in patients with mast cell disorders.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Prospective investigations of vaccination in the setting of mast cell disorders also demonstrate safety, although generally in the setting of mast cell–directed premedication.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Our cohort contained 5 individuals with incidentally elevated serum tryptase levels. These participants did not premedicate before vaccination, and all 5 tolerated revaccination without evidence of mast cell–mediated symptoms.</p><p id="p0100">The findings presented here are subject to limitations. This was a single-center study. Adverse reaction history and long COVID symptomatology were dependent on participants’ report. Although baseline laboratory evaluation was obtained, laboratory data were not collected on participants during the vaccination visit to distinguish participants experiencing IgE-mediated symptoms versus immunization stress–related responses.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> The study enrollment spanned several years of the COVID-19 pandemic; as such, multiple seasonal or variant-focused versions of the COVID-19 mRNA vaccines were administered to participants as time passed. Finally, study follow-up was limited to 1 week; it is possible that participants may have experienced other AEs beyond this timeline that the study did not capture, although patients were asked for this follow-up and no reactions were reported.</p><p id="p0105">Recent work by Khalid et al<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> demonstrated a significant presence of immunization stress–related responses in individuals experiencing immediate symptoms with COVID-19 mRNA vaccination. Our experience supports the notion that IgE-mediated reactions are exceedingly rare to these vaccines. Five participants experienced immediate symptoms with revaccination, with pruritus as the most common symptom. No participant experienced objective signs of reaction either by examination or by vital sign changes, and no one required epinephrine for the treatment of symptoms. Given that the use of the mRNA vaccine platform continues after the COVID-19 pandemic and is being expanded to other pathogens, it is critical that the medical community characterizes the risk of ongoing vaccination among individuals with adverse reactions to both the vaccine and the virus in the form of long COVID. With this information available, medical professionals can provide better shared decision making for optimal vaccine usage in all eligible individuals.</p><p id="p0110">This prospective study strongly suggests that COVID-19 vaccination is safe in individuals with a previous mRNA vaccine reaction. COVID-19 vaccination is also safe in those with long COVID syndrome. It is expected that these data will provide a model for objective evaluations of future vaccines with respect to potentially allergic AEs.<boxed-text id="dtbox1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Clinical implications</title></caption><p id="p0185">The risk of severe reaction to COVID-19 mRNA revaccination is low even in the setting of previous adverse vaccine reaction or long COVID.</p></boxed-text></p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Disclosure Statement</title><p id="p0120">This work was supported by a grant from the Wallace Foundation (award no. 019850). It was also supported by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases of the National Institutes of Health (award no. U01AI181882-01 to I.F.S., K.M.O., L.M.F., S.J., C.F.S., and J.R.B. and award no. K23AI162661 to C.F.S.).</p><p id="p0120a">Disclosure of potential conflict of interest: The authors declare that they have no relevant conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CDC COVID-19 Response Team, Food and Drug Administration</collab></person-group><article-title>Allergic reactions including anaphylaxis after receipt of the first dose of Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 vaccine—United States, December 14-23, 2020</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>70</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33444297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm7002e1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7808711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenhawt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The risk of allergic reaction to SARS-CoV-2 vaccines and recommended evaluation and management: a systematic review, meta-analysis, GRADE assessment, and international consensus approach</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</source><volume>9</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>3546</fpage><lpage>3567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34153517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaip.2021.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8248554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref3"><source>Comirnaty (COVID-19 mRNA vaccine)</source><year>2025</year><publisher-name>Pfizer-BioNTech</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref4"><source>SPIKEVAX (COVID-19 mRNA vaccine)</source><year>2025</year><publisher-name>Moderna Tx, Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Troiano</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccine hesitancy in the era of COVID-19</article-title><source>Public Health</source><volume>194</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33965796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.puhe.2021.02.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7931735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegler</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luisi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopman</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trajectory of COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy over time and association of initial vaccine hesitancy with subsequent vaccination</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>4</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2126882</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.26882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8463937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34559232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stenehjem</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grannis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naleway</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of Covid-19 vaccines in ambulatory and inpatient care settings</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>385</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1355</fpage><lpage>1371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34496194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa2110362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8451184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammerman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sergienko</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peretz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Netzer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BNT162b2 vaccine booster and mortality due to Covid-19</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>385</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>2413</fpage><lpage>2420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34879190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa2115624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8728797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiegand</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adjemian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimating the early impact of the US COVID-19 vaccination programme on COVID-19 cases, emergency department visits, hospital admissions, and deaths among adults aged 65 years and older: an ecological analysis of national surveillance data</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>399</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34741818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02226-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8565933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Havers</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anglin</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19-associated hospitalizations among vaccinated and unvaccinated adults 18 years or older in 13 US states, January 2021 to April 2022</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><volume>182</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36074486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2022.4299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9459904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Notarte</surname><given-names>K.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catahay</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastrana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ver</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pangilinan</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of COVID-19 vaccination on the risk of developing long-COVID and on existing long-COVID symptoms: a systematic review</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><volume>53</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101624</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9417563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36051247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwagami</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuhara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuno</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of COVID-19 vaccination against long COVID syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><volume>41</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>1783</fpage><lpage>1790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36774332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vaccine.2023.02.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9905096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byambasuren</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stehlik</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcorn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of covid-19 vaccination on long covid: systematic review</article-title><source>BMJ Med</source><volume>2</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e000385</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjmed-2022-000385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9978692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36936268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoubkhani</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bermingham</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pouwels</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nafilyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaccardi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trajectory of long covid symptoms after covid-19 vaccination: community based cohort study</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>377</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e069676</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj-2021-069676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9115603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35584816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacEwan</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahurkar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarver</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaughan</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schamess</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 vaccination perspectives among patients with long COVID: a qualitative study</article-title><source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source><volume>20</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2327663</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/21645515.2024.2327663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10978020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38532547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chinthrajah</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sicherer</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shreffler</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanser</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Updating the CoFAR Grading Scale for Systemic Allergic Reactions in food allergy</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><volume>149</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2166</fpage><lpage>21670.e1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35026206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaci.2021.12.789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9177543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krantz</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwah</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerji</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety evaluation of the second dose of messenger RNA COVID-19 vaccines in patients with immediate reactions to the first dose</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><volume>181</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1530</fpage><lpage>1533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34309623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2021.3779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8314170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puxkandl</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bangerl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanfstingl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guenova</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoetzenecker</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altrichter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Second-dose COVID-19 vaccines are well tolerated in patients with allergic reactions to the first dose—a single center experience</article-title><source>World Allergy Organ J</source><volume>15</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100654</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.waojou.2022.100654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9120131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35611049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaakati</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khokhar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety of COVID-19 vaccination in patients with mastocytosis and monoclonal mast cell activation syndrome</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</source><volume>9</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>3198</fpage><lpage>3199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34033981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaip.2021.05.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8141687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannetti</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godwin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicoloro-SantaBarbara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonadonna</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Outcomes of COVID-19 vaccination in 323 patients with clonal and non-clonal mast cell activation disorders</article-title><source>Allergy</source><volume>78</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35962620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/all.15476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9538600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rama</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castells</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mRNA COVID-19 vaccine is well tolerated in patients with cutaneous and systemic mastocytosis with mast cell activation symptoms and anaphylaxis</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><volume>147</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33485650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaci.2021.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7816615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarinis</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossios</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gulen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 vaccination in the setting of mastocytosis-Pfizer-BioNTech mRNA vaccine is safe and well tolerated</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</source><volume>10</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1377</fpage><lpage>1379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35123098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaip.2022.01.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8810433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMurtry</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heininger</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menning</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunization stress-related response—redefining immunization anxiety-related reaction as an adverse event following immunization</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><volume>38</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>3015</fpage><lpage>3020</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32131975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.02.046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zektser</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Utoh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A randomized double-blinded trial to assess recurrence of systemic allergic reactions following COVID-19 mRNA vaccination</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><volume>153</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>1634</fpage><lpage>1646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38460680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaci.2024.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11162316</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0125">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplemental Material</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>