<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Kidney Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Kidney Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3900</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">kme</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Kidney Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2590-0595</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12311507</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12311507.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12311507</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12311507</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40746934</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xkme.2025.101039</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2590-0595(25)00075-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101039</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Renal Long COVID: A Scoping Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frediani</surname><given-names initials="MM">Marcella M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">∗</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names initials="HS">Heitor S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">∗</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Busatto</surname><given-names initials="GF">Geraldo F.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names initials="CRR">Carlos R.R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burdmann</surname><given-names initials="EA">Emmanuel A.</given-names></name><email>burdmann@usp.br</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Laboratório de Investigação 12, Hospital das Clinicas HCFMUSP, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Departamento e Instituto de Psiquiatria, Hospital das Clinicas HCFMUSP, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Divisão de Pneumologia, Instituto do Coração, Hospital das Clinicas HCFMUSP, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label><bold>Address for Correspondence:</bold> Emmanuel A. Burdmann, MD, PhD, Laboratório de Investigação (LIM) 12, Serviço de Nefrologia, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, 01246-903, Brazil. <email>burdmann@usp.br</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>∗</label><p id="ntpara0015">M.M.F. and H.S.R. contributed equally to this work and share first authorship.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">493980</issue-id><elocation-id>101039</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-08-01 17:25:20.260"><day>01</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Rationale &amp; Objective</title><p>Whether long coronavirus disease (long COVID) affects the kidneys remains to be understood. In this scoping review, we described the evidence of renal long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Study Design</title><p>A scoping review was conducted according to the Joanna Briggs Institute and Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews guidelines by searching MEDLINE, Embase, and other databases from inception until February 2025.</p></sec><sec><title>Setting &amp; Study Populations</title><p>We included evidence on kidney-related outcomes in adult survivors of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) with data on long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Selection Criteria for Studies</title><p>Cohorts from all settings.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Extraction</title><p>We extracted data related to longitudinal kidney outcomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Analytical Approach</title><p>Data were synthesized and presented in tables and figures.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We screened 6,203 studies and included 37 in this review (38 reports), comprising 1,308,265 individuals with follow-up data. The majority were retrospective (61%) and from Europe (37%). All reports included hospitalized patients and 34% also included the community setting. Acute kidney injury (AKI) during acute COVID-19 phase was assessed in 58% of the reports. Chronic kidney disease (CKD) development was assessed in 29% of the reports, with wide variation in its frequency, ranging from 0.4%-45%. Progression of CKD (7 studies, 18%) ranged from 8%-49%. Studies reporting higher frequencies of AKI found larger rates of renal long COVID. Overall, there was high heterogeneity in how kidney-related outcomes were reported during follow-up. Most studies presented data on crude kidney function biomarkers (eg, serum creatinine or estimated glomerular filtration rate), while a few (13%) reported major adverse kidney events. Data on proteinuria or urinary biomarkers were scarce.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>Lack of studies with pre-COVID-19 data.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>This scoping review highlighted that renal long COVID, characterized by CKD development and/or progression, may occur. Available evidence suggests that AKI may be associated with renal long COVID. Therefore, long-term kidney function monitoring is advisable after COVID-19 recovery to enable early diagnosis and timely intervention for CKD.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="plain-language-summary" id="abssec0055"><title>Plain-Language Summary</title><p>Kidney complications may persist after coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) recovery, but their long-term impact remains unclear. Our review analyzed data from over 1 million patients and found that those who experienced acute kidney injury during COVID-19 had a higher risk of developing or worsening chronic kidney disease. However, the studies showed significant variation in how often renal long COVID occurred, highlighting the need for more research. Given these findings, regular kidney function monitoring after COVID-19 recovery is essential for early detection and intervention to prevent long-term complications. This study underscores the importance of recognizing renal long COVID as a potential consequence in the post-COVID era.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Index Words</title><kwd>Chronic kidney disease</kwd><kwd>end-stage kidney disease</kwd><kwd>kidney replacement therapy</kwd><kwd>nephrology</kwd><kwd>post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection, had catastrophic repercussions worldwide. In addition to challenges related to acute infection, health care institutions face the burden of late sequelae in previously infected individuals. The term “long COVID” or “post-COVID-19” encompasses signs and symptoms associated with COVID-19 that develop or continue 3 months after the initial SARS-CoV-2 infection and persist for &gt;2 months, according to the World Health Organization.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p><p id="p0015">Long COVID can involve pulmonary and extrapulmonary manifestations, including fatigue, sleep disturbances, and neuropsychiatric, kidney, gastrointestinal, and cardiovascular dysfunction, among others.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> The mechanisms of long COVID are not yet completely understood. Overall, various hypotheses have been proposed, including the persistence of SARS-CoV-2 reservoirs in tissues, immune system dysregulation, autoimmunity, and endothelial dysfunction leading to microvascular blood clotting. Regarding immune dysregulation, studies have reported T cell alterations, highly activated innate immune cells, and elevated expression of type I and type III interferons.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></p><p id="p0020">Postulated risk factors for long COVID include severe acute pulmonary disease requiring invasive mechanical ventilation, female sex, obesity, socioeconomic deprivation, and pre-existing comorbid conditions.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Data about renal long COVID are scarce and still a matter of debate, with contradictory findings.<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> The risk factor that has been most frequently associated with renal long COVID is acute kidney injury (AKI), which is common in acute SARS-CoV-2 infection. Previous studies have reported that ≤28% of hospitalized patients develop AKI, and 9% require kidney replacement therapy (KRT).<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Possible mechanisms for AKI development include direct effects of the infection on the kidney, such as endothelial damage from viral entry, complement activation, local inflammation with tubular injury, and collapsing glomerulopathy. In addition, indirect mechanisms such as sepsis, systemic inflammation, use of nephrotoxic drugs, and hypercoagulability may play a role in COVID 19-associated AKI.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref></p><p id="p0025">In individuals who have not contracted COVID-19, a significant association between AKI and the development or progression of late chronic kidney disease (CKD) has been demonstrated.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> However, whether there is an association between AKI-associated COVID-19 in the acute phase of infection and renal long COVID is unknown.</p><p id="p0030">Overall, a better understanding of the post-COVID-19 impact on CKD development and/or progression is mandatory to help and guide the development and implementation of health care strategies for survivors of COVID-19. The aim of this scoping review is to describe the effects of long COVID on kidney function and kidney-related outcomes, here named as renal long COVID. We hypothesize that COVID-19 may be associated with a late decline in kidney function, which may evolve to CKD development and/or progression.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec1.1"><title>Registration and Protocol</title><p id="p0035">The protocol of this scoping review was previously published.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> In brief, it was conducted in accordance with the Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) methodology for scoping reviews<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> and the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> (PRISMA-ScR; <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Item S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.2"><title>Search Strategy</title><p id="p0040">We designed a search strategy to mainly locate published evidence that underwent peer review. A full search strategy for MEDLINE, Embase, and LILACS databases was developed (see Item S2). Databases were searched from inception until August 9, 2023, and search was updated on February 10, 2025. The reference lists of all the included sources of evidence were screened for additional studies. We did not apply language restrictions.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.3"><title>Selection Criteria</title><p id="p0045">Eligibility criteria based on the PCC framework (Participants; Concept; Context) adopted in the scoping review are shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. All types of cohort study designs (eg, retrospective, prospective, etc.) were considered, whereas reviews, commentaries, abstracts, and letters to the editor were not included.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>PCC (Participants; Concept; Context) framework for the selection criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Definition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participants</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Long-term (≥3 mo) adult survivors of COVID-19</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Concept</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Renal long COVID (eg, development and/or progression of CKD)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Context</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">All settings and designs, including in-hospital and community</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: CKD, chronic kidney disease; COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec1.4"><title>Evidence Selection</title><p id="p0050">All identified citations were collated and uploaded into EndNote X9 (Clarivate). Duplicates were removed for the screening process by Covidence systematic review software (Veritas Health Innovation). The titles and abstracts were screened by 2 independent reviewers (MMF and HSR) for assessment against the inclusion criteria. The full text of selected evidence was assessed in detail by the same independent reviewers. Any disagreements between the reviewers were resolved through discussion or with an additional reviewer (EAB).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.5"><title>Data Extraction</title><p id="p0055">Relevant data were extracted from the studies included in the scoping review by the main reviewer (MMF) and checked by a second (HSR). The extracted data included specific details about comorbid conditions, race/ethnicity, diagnosis of COVID-19, clinical outcomes during hospital stay, follow-up time for prolonged symptoms, kidney function assessment, and kidney-related outcomes. If necessary, the authors of the studies were contacted to request missing or additional data (reply rate = 45%).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.6"><title>Methodological Assessment</title><p id="p0060">Methodological quality assessment of the included studies was conducted by 1 reviewer with previous experience (HSR) using the JBI Critical Appraisal Checklist.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> The JBI tool consists of 9 items with 4 possible responses (Yes, No, Unclear, or Not applicable). For this review, we considered only 5 items due to the characteristics of the research question (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S1</xref>). The greater the number of “Yes” responses, the better the quality of the study. Doubts were solved with a second reviewer (EAB). We arbitrarily categorized studies into “≤3” or “4 or 5” quality criteria by adopting the “Yes” answer.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.7"><title>Data Synthesis and Analysis</title><p id="p0065">Data were synthesized and presented in tables and figures along with a narrative summary. We calculated absolute and relative frequencies (percentages) or median and interquartile range (IQR) for the characteristics of the reports included. Statistical analysis was performed using the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (version 29.0, IBM Corp).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Literature Search</title><p id="p0070">We screened 6,203 studies, of which 37 were included in this review,<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> comprising 38 reports. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows the flow diagram with the selected evidence.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of the literature search.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Characteristics of the Evidence</title><p id="p0075"><xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> describes the characteristics of the reports included in the review (see Item S3 for the characteristics of each report). <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> shows that reports were mostly from Europe (n = 14; 36.8%) and Asia (n = 13; 34.2%), while only 2 were from Latin America (5.3%)<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref> and none from Africa. Most of the cohort designs were retrospective (n = 23; 60.5%). Evidence came mainly from high-income (n = 25; 65.8%) and upper-middle-income countries (n = 11; 28.9%), with only 1 (2.6%) study from a lower-middle-income country (India).<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> Most reports (n = 19; 50.0%) were from the pre-vaccine COVID-19 period.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the Included Reports (N = 38)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Design</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (60.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (26.3%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Ambidirectional</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (7.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Setting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> In-hospital only</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (65.8%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ICU only</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Ward only</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (2.6%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Ward and ICU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (44.7%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Community only</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Both hospital and community</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (34.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohort period<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Pre-vaccine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (52.6%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Post-vaccine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (23.7%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Not reported</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (26.3%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney function cohort characterization</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Patients with pre-existing CKD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (57.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Only patients with CKD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (21.1%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Only kidney transplant patients</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (10.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Only patients with AKI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcomes during hospitalization</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> AKI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (57.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Use of KRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (44.7%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney function assessment at follow-up</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Serum creatinine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (81.6%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> eGFR</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (57.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Serum cystatin C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (5.3%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ICD codes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (10.5%%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney outcomes at follow-up</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> CKD development</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (28.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> CKD progression</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> KRT dependence</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (15.8%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> MAKEs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (13.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up time<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>, mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (39.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 4 to 6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (36.8%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 7 to 11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (34.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quality criteria</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≤3 (Yes)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (66.7%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 4 or 5 (Yes)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (33.3%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: AKI, acute kidney injury; CKD, chronic kidney disease; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate; ICD, International Classification of Diseases; ICU, intensive care unit; KRT, kidney replacement therapy; MAKE, major adverse kidney event.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0020">A report could have &gt;1 option and sum may be &gt;100%.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Geographical heatmap of the included evidence on renal long COVID.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0080">All reports included patients that required hospital admission; 13 (34.2%) also included the community setting, and 7 (2.6%) only included patients with intensive care unit admission. None of the reports included patients treated exclusively in community settings. Seven (14.4%) of the reports only included patients who developed AKI during SARS-CoV-2 infection. Twenty-two (57.9%) reports included patients with underlying CKD, 4 (10.5%) only included kidney transplant recipients, and 4 (10.5%) excluded patients with underlying CKD.</p><p id="p0085">The diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection was confirmed mainly by reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction (n = 27; 71.1%). Regarding the follow-up time, 15 (39.5%) reports had 3 months of follow-up whereas 13 (34.2%) had ≥12 months. Most studies (n = 22; 57.9%) met ≤3 of 5 quality criteria with a “Yes” answer (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S1</xref> for each study).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Characteristics of the Patients</title><p id="p0090">A total of 1,400,875 patients were included in the review. The mean age of the included patients ranged from 38 (IQR, 28-56) to 69 (IQR, 59-77) years, and most were men. Regarding race/ethnicity, White was the most reported, ranging from 14%-100%. Kidney disease prevalence ranged from 1.5%-38.3% (excluding reports with 0% or 100%). Antibiotics were the most common drug therapy used, administered in 13 (34.2%) studies. While some studies (n = 15, 39.5%) were able to follow-up all included patients, the median follow-up rate was 90% (IQR, 37-100), comprising 1,308,265 individuals with follow-up data.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Kidney Function</title><sec id="sec2.4.1"><title>Assessment at Baseline and Follow-up</title><p id="p0095"><xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows that the most used biomarker for baseline kidney function assessment was serum creatinine (Scr) (n = 25; 65.8%). Twenty (52.6%) reports used estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR), and 2 (5.3%) used serum cystatin C (Scys).<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> At follow-up, kidney function was assessed mostly by Scr (n = 31; 81.6%), and 2 studies (5.3%) used Scys.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref>
<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref><xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> describe each study individually divided into their respective settings.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Kidney Function Features of the Reports From Hospital Setting (n = 18)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohort Sample (N and Characteristics)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohort Design</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney Function Markers and Time Points</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AKI During Hospital Stay</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney Function Outcomes at Follow-up</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CKD Development and/or Progression</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">KRT at Follow-up</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aklilu et al<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref> (2024)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">987 (only hospitalized patients with COVID-19 AKI)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>10 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 100%<break/>Stage 1: 72%<break/>Stage 2: 19%<break/>Stage 3: 9% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR change −6.79 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> (95% CI, −7.93 to −5.64)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR decline by ≥25% from discharge: 19.5% in 6 mo<break/>28.7% in 1 y<break/>34.4% in 2 y<break/>MAKEs<break/>32.7% in 1 y<break/>39.2% in 2 y<break/>MAKEs were lower for the COVID-19 AKI than the other AKI groups (HR, 0.67; 95% CI, 0.59-0.75; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001)<break/>MAKE: composite of worsened kidney function (defined as eGFR decline by ≥25% or ICD-10 code for ESKD) or death.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bansode et al<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53 (only AKI patients)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage 1: 18%<break/>Stage 2: 14%<break/>Stage 3: 68% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49% of eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> or a decline &gt;25% for patients with underlying CKD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bento et al<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (only AKI patients)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bidirectional</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>Albuminuria<break/>16 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage 1: 10%<break/>Stage 2: 15%<break/>Stage 3: 75% (AKIN)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr 1.2 mg/dL eGFR 66 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>Albuminuria in 32% of patients defined as UACR &gt;30 mg/g</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45% of eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Boruga et al<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> (2024)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (only patients without CKD at baseline)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>Albuminuria<break/>6 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 17% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr 90.4 μmol/L eGFR 70.6 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>Albuminuria 38.8 mg/g (compared to admission 52.4, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Continuous eGFR decline &lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>: 23.9%<break/>Risk factors: BMI, COVID-19 severity, smoking, AKI, creatinine increase, UACR increase, and SUN increase</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chan et al<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> (2021)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">591</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>5 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 4%<break/>Stage 1: 59%<break/>Stage 2: 14%<break/>Stage 3: 27% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR decline in AKI patients: 7.5 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>eGFR decline in non-AKI patients: 1.1 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Darcis et al<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> (2021)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">199</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 11%<break/>Stage 1: 33%<break/>Stage 2: 19%<break/>Stage 3: 48% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 of 199 patients: sCr 0.9 mg/dL eGFR<break/>83.7 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Defelice et al<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (only kidney transplant patients)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>Proteinuria<break/>3-6 and 9-12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">At 3-6 mo: Scr 1.8 mg/dL and eGFR 47 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>;<break/>Incident proteinuria: 0%<break/>At 9-12 mo: Scr 1.9 mg/dL and eGFR 48.0 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>;<break/>Incident proteinuria: 0%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Filev et al<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> (2024)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70 (only patients with underlying CKD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>36 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 23%<break/>Stage 1: 59%<break/>Stage 2: 14%<break/>Stage 3: 27% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr decline of −4.39 μmol/L compared with baseline<break/>Albuminuria decline of −0.47 g/L compared with baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gu et al<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,734</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bidirectional</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR<break/>11 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 6% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR decline:<break/>Overall 7.2% (2.2-14.3)<break/>AKI group 19.8% (11.5-26.5)<break/>Non-AKI group 6.7% (2.0-13.3)<break/><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 for comparison</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR decline ≥25% from baseline: 8%<break/>AKI severity was associated with greater eGFR decline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Huang et al<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,733</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bidirectional</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR<break/>6 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR &lt;90 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>: 479/1,378 (35%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Li et al<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">155</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3, 12, and 24 mo<break/>Proteinuria<break/>24 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr 69.8 μmol/L eGFR 102.8 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>eGFR declined from 3 to 12 mo but not from 12 to 24 mo<break/>Proteinuria 7% at 24 months</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lu et al<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,296 (only AKI patients stratified in early, delayed, and prolonged recovery; AKI defined by ADQI)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not described</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 and 12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">At 12 mo<break/>Early recovery: Scr 1.6 mg/dL eGFR 61 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>Delayed recovery: Scr 1.7 mg/dL eGFR 58.1 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>Prolonged recovery: Scr 4.4 mg/dL eGFR 35.5 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">At 3 mo<break/>1,215/3,296 patients analyzed for CKD incidence (eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> or &gt;25% decrease)<break/>Early recovery: 20%<break/>Delayed recovery: 29%<break/>Prolonged recovery 36%<break/>90-d MAKE incidence for all groups: 23% (MAKE was defined as a composite of dialysis dependence, death, or eGFR decline ≥25%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Morin et al<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> (2021)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">478</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>4 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2/177 patients displayed a persistent alteration of kidney function</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Strohbehn et al<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> (2021)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,091</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR<break/>10 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 23%<break/>Stage 1: 44%<break/>Stage 2: 26%<break/>Stage 3: 30% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14% of eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>11% of eGFR decline ≥25%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sun et al<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,338 (only AKI survivors analyzed at follow-up)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR<break/>12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 41%<break/>Stage 1: 54%<break/>Stage 2: 25%<break/>Stage 3: 21% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">161/1,338 patients: 16% of incident or progressive CKD<break/>“incident” defined as eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> if the patient had no history of CKD and “progressive” as eGFR &lt;60 and Scr 10% above baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tan et al<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,891</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 51%<break/>Stage 1: 69%<break/>Stage 2: 17%<break/>Stage 3: 14% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39% of non-recovery of kidney function (recovery defined by ≤125% of baseline Scr)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Teng et al<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (hospitalized patients without CKD before COVID 19 diagnosis)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>6 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr 68.3 μmol/L eGFR 99.8 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhou et al<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89 (only hospitalized patients with severe COVID-19)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>Scys eGFR (based on Scr and Scys)<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR 76.8 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abnormal eGFR (&lt;90 mL/min/m<sup>2</sup>): 77.5%<break/>Risk factors: age (OR, 1.26; 95% CI, 1.08-147)<break/>BMI (OR, 1.97; 95% CI, 1.20-3.22)<break/>Scys (OR, 1.22; 95% CI, 1.07-1.39)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: ADQI, Acute Disease Quality Initiative; AKI, acute kidney injury; AKIN, Acute Kidney Injury Network; BMI, body mass index; SUN, serum urea nitrogen; CKD, chronic kidney disease; COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate; ESKD, end-stage kidney disease; HR, hazard ratio; KDIGO, Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes; KRT, kidney replacement therapy; MAKE, major adverse kidney event; OR, odds ratio; Scr, serum creatinine; Scys, serum cystatin C; UACR, urinary albumin-creatinine ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Kidney Function Features of the Reports from the Intensive Care Unit Setting (n = 7)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohort Sample (N and Characteristics)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohort Design</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney Function Markers and Time Points</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AKI During Hospital Stay</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney Function Outcomes at Follow-up</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CKD Development and/or Progression</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">KRT at Follow-up</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Andrade et al<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref> (2025)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">360 (only patients with severe AKI)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%<break/>Stage 1: 4%<break/>Stage 2: 5%<break/>Stage 3: 91% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72% of patients dialysis-free<break/>In 25/37 of the patients, mean eGFR was significantly lower than that at baseline (65.9 vs 85.5 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37/360 patients: 14%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">El Mouhayyar et al<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">459</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 and 6 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 80%<break/>Stage 1: 28%<break/>Stage 2: 25%<break/>Stage 3: 47% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12/459 patients<break/>At 3 mo: 46%<break/>At 6 mo: 36%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lumlertgul et al<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> (2021)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">313</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 77%<break/>Stage 1: 26%<break/>Stage 2: 17%<break/>Stage 3: 57% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">158/313 patients: Scr 79.0 μmol/L<break/>90-d MAKEs occurred in 42% of all patients (n = 313) and comprised non-recovery AKI, dialysis dependence, or death<break/>91% of the survivors (n = 194) had kidney recovery at 3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17% of eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Melero et al<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (only AKI patients requiring CRRT divided into survivors and deceased)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR<break/>6 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100% of AKI stage 3 (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9/11 survivors had a mean eGFR decline of 44.0 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rousseau et al<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> (2021)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr 1.0 mg/dL</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28% of eGFR &lt;60 ml/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ruault et al<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">266</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 32%<break/>Stage 1: 50%<break/>Stage 2: 20%<break/>Stage 3: 30% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">90-d MAKEs occurred in 43% of 244 patients, and comprised death, dialysis dependence, or eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> 90 d after ICU admission</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11% of eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">244/266 patients: 0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yang et al<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">171 (only critically ill patients)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scys<break/>3, 6, and 12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18% of AKI used KRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">At 3 mo<break/>81/171 patients: Scys 1.1 mg/dL<break/>At 6 mo<break/>63/171 patients: Scys 1.0 mg/dL<break/>At 12 mo<break/>65/171 patients: Scys 1.0 mg/dL</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: AKI, acute kidney injury; CKD, chronic kidney disease; CRRT, continuous renal replacement therapy; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate; ICU, intensive care unit; KDIGO, Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes; KRT, kidney replacement therapy; MAKE, major adverse kidney event; Scr, serum creatinine; Scys, serum cystatin C.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Kidney Function Features of the Reports From Hospital and Community Settings (n = 13)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohort Sample (N and Characteristics)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohort Design</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney Function Markers and Time Points</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AKI During Hospital Stay</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney Function Outcomes at Follow-up</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CKD Development and/or Progression</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">KRT at Follow-up</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Atiquzzaman et al<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,212</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR<break/>Albuminuria<break/>3, 6, and 12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">At 3 mo eGFR 86.7 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>At 6 mo<break/>1,076/2,212 patients: eGFR 84.3 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>At 12 mo<break/>685/2,212 patients: eGFR 84.0 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>Annual eGFR change (mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>)<break/>Hospitalized: −5.7<break/>Non-hospitalized: 2.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Huang et al<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> (2024)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (only patients with pulmonary embolism)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5/9 patients: sCr 0.72 mg/dL</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hui et al<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> (2024)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">181 (only patients with IgA nephropathy)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>10 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR change of 3.81 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> (95% CI, 1.60-6.03)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Karadag et al<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">173 (only CKD non-dialysis-dependent)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total: 55%<break/>Stage 1: 58%<break/>Stage 2: 28%<break/>Stage 3: 15% (KDIGO)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr 1.9 mg/dL eGFR 28.9 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kemeç &amp; Akgül<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,008 (patients without AKI, need for MV or VADs)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>6 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr 0.7 mg/dL eGFR 97.8 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lam et al<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">535,186 (Hong Kong cohort)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ICD-9-CM, ICD-10, and ICD-10-WHO codes<break/>5 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESKD 0.14 (95% CI, 0.12-0.16) per 1,000 person-years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lam et al<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,400 (United Kingdom cohort)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ICD-9-CM, ICD-10, and ICD-10-WHO codes<break/>8 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESKD 1.75 (95% CI, 1.60-1.92) per 1,000 person-years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mahalingasivam et al<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> (2024)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">134,565</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not reported</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR<break/>11 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59,267/134,565 patients eGFR mean annual decline: 3.4% (95% CI, 3.2%-3.5%), increasing to 5.4% (95% CI, 5.2%-5.6%) among those hospitalized<break/>COVID-19 group annual eGFR decline 1.0 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> (95% CI, 0.7-1.2) faster than the pneumonia group</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR decline of 25%: 0.8%<break/>HR for eGFR decline: 1.19 (95% CI, 1.07-1.34) for the COVID-19 vs pneumonia group</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Malinowska et al<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> (2022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (only kidney transplant patients)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>6 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr 1.3 mg/dL eGFR 58.0 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Malinowska et al<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">112 (only kidney transplant patients)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr<break/>12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Higher increase in Scr level in males (0.41 mg/dL; 95% CI, 0.11-0.70, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.007) but not in females (0.17 mg/dL, 95% CI, −0.18 to 0.52, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.33), when compared to same-sex patients observed after mild COVID-19<break/>Mean change in eGFR of −2.32 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> (95% CI, −4.05 to −0.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.009)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mathew et al<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">683,958 (only patients without CKD before COVID-19 diagnosis)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ICD-10 codes<break/>3 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2%<break/>ICD-10 codes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moein et al<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">188 (only kidney transplant patients divided into 2 groups: reduction of IMS and no reduction of IMS during COVID-19)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR<break/>3, 6, and 12 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">At 3 mo<break/>Reduction of IMS: eGFR 55.3 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>No reduction of IMS: eGFR 56.1 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>At 6 mo<break/>Reduction of IMS: eGFR 51.2 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>No reduction of IMS: eGFR 55.3 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>At 12 mo<break/>Reduction of IMS: eGFR 51.7 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>No reduction of IMS: eGFR 59.6 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obrişcă et al<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> (2023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">104 (only patients with biopsy-proven kidney diseases)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scr eGFR<break/>30 mo</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">eGFR 51.9 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup><break/>eGFR change of 0.31 (95% CI, −2.72 to 3.35); mean difference of −3.34 (95% CI, −7.03 to 0.34) compared with controls</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">eGFR decline &gt;30%: 23.8%<break/>ESRD (dialysis, transplant, or eGFR &lt;15 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>): 21.8%<break/>Combined endpoint: 26.7%<break/>Risk factors: eGFR at baseline, male sex, and COVID-19</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: AKI, acute kidney injury; CI, confidence interval; CKD, chronic kidney disease; COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate; ESKD, end-stage kidney disease; HR, hazard ratio; ICD-9-CM, <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification</italic>; ICD-10, <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases, Tenth Revision</italic>; ICD-10-WHO, <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases, Tenth Revision, World Health Organization</italic>; IMS, immunosuppression; KDIGO, Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes; KRT, kidney replacement therapy; MV, mechanical ventilation; Scr, serum creatinine; VAD, vasoactive drug.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0100">Yang et al<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> conducted a prospective study involving only critically ill patients, in which they analyzed Scys levels among survivors. They reported that 20.5% (17/83) of patients had elevated Scys levels at 3 months post-discharge. This proportion declined over time, with 17.5% in 6 months and 10.8% in 12 months.</p><p id="p0105">Zhou et al<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> conducted a prospective analysis of hospitalized patients with severe COVID-19, assessing eGFR calculated using both Scr and Scys. At 3 months post-discharge, 77.5% of patients exhibited abnormal eGFR (&lt;90 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>). Independent risk factors for reduced eGFR following discharge included older age, body mass index, and Scys levels.</p><p id="p0110">Glomerular filtration rate was estimated in 22 (57.9%) reports, mainly through the Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration (CKD-EPI) 2009 equation by using Scr (n = 12; 31.6%). A single study assessed eGFR with combined sCr-sCys.<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> Four (10.5%) studies described kidney outcomes based on <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases</italic> (ICD) codes. Lam et al<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> adopted the <italic toggle="yes">ICD, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification,</italic> the <italic toggle="yes">ICD, Tenth Revision</italic>, and the <italic toggle="yes">ICD, Tenth Revision</italic> World Health Organization codes for end-stage kidney disease, CKD, and chronic kidney failure. Mathew et al<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> adopted the <italic toggle="yes">ICD, Tenth Revision</italic> codes for CKD and end-stage kidney disease. No study objectively measured glomerular filtration rate.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4.2"><title>Kidney Outcomes During Hospitalization</title><p id="p0115">Among kidney-related outcomes during hospitalization, 22 (57.9%) reports found an AKI development ranging from 1.8%-80.1% (excluding reports with 0% or 100%). The Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) guideline was the most used for AKI diagnosis (n = 20; 52.6%). Seventeen reports (44.7%) described the use of KRT, with rates ranging from 0.7%-87.2% (excluding reports with 0% or 100%).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4.3"><title>Renal Long COVID</title><sec id="sec2.4.3.1"><title>CKD Development and/or Progression</title><p id="p0120">During the follow-up period, 11 (28.9%) reports provided data on CKD development, and 7 (18.4%) on CKD progression. CKD development was mainly defined as an eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> and CKD progression was mostly defined as an eGFR decline &gt;25% for patients with underlying CKD. Bansode et al<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> and Bento et al<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> studied only patients that developed AKI during hospitalization and found the highest rates of CKD development and/or progression, with an incidence of 49% and 45%, respectively. On the other hand, Mathew et al<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> assessed community and in-hospital patients, with an AKI incidence of 2%, and found a CKD development of 0.4%.</p><p id="p0125">Five (13.2%) studies reported data on major adverse kidney events, although different definitions and follow-up periods were applied. Lu et al<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> only included patients who developed AKI during hospitalization in their study. Among these patients, 23% experienced major adverse kidney event, which was defined as a composite of dialysis dependence, death, or a ≥25% eGFR decline. In contrast, the study by Lumlertgul et al<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> identified major adverse kidney events in 42% of patients, using a definition that included non-recovery of AKI, dialysis dependence, or death.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4.3.2"><title>KRT Dependence</title><p id="p0130">Six (15.8%) reports detailed KRT dependence, while 7 (18.4%) described AKI recovery rates. El Mouhayyar et al<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> studied 459 patients, of whom 80% were diagnosed with AKI during their hospital stay. At 6 months of follow-up, 36% were KRT dependent. On the other hand, Ruault et al<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> studied 266 patients with an AKI incidence of 32% during hospitalization, and none of the patients were KRT dependent at 3 months of follow-up.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4.3.3"><title>Other Kidney Outcomes</title><p id="p0135">Five (13.2%) studies reported albuminuria. The study by Bento et al<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> found albuminuria, defined as urinary albumin/creatinine ratio &gt;30 mg/g, in 31.6% of patients. Eight (21.1%) reports investigated proteinuria. Li et al<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> reported proteinuria (but did not describe albuminuria) in 6.9% of patients at 2 years of follow-up.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.4.4"><title>Factors Associated With Renal Long COVID</title><p id="p0140">Although most of the included studies reported ≥1 adverse kidney outcome during follow-up, only 5 (13.2%) provided analysis of the factors associated with renal long COVID. In the study by Matthew et al,<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> among the SARS-CoV-2-positive cohort, older age (≥60 years compared with 18-29 years), male sex, African American race/ethnicity, diabetes, AKI, and intensive care unit admission were associated with subsequent CKD development. Obrişcă et al<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> found that eGFR at baseline, male sex, and SARS-CoV-2 infection were risk factors for the combined endpoint of eGFR decline &gt;30% and/or ESKD.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Main Findings</title><p id="p0145">In this scoping review, we investigated the available evidence of long-term kidney outcomes in COVID-19 survivors and found that renal long COVID, characterized by CKD development, progression, and/or long-term KRT dependence, may occur. Most of the studies that investigated these long-term outcomes were those that focused on AKI occurrence during hospitalization. Studies with higher frequencies of AKI reported greater rates of renal long COVID during follow-up. Our findings are consistent with a recently published meta-analysis that reported significant KRT dependence in patients with AKI-associated COVID-19.<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Long COVID and Kidney Outcomes</title><p id="p0150">This scoping review summarized the available evidence on long-term kidney outcomes in COVID-19 survivors. Previous evidence mainly focused on AKI-associated COVID-19 and was limited to hospital settings, whereas our study also included findings from survivors who were not hospitalized. We found a high heterogeneity of kidney function outcomes at follow-up. This heterogeneity may be attributed to variations in AKI frequency across studies, differences in the use of KRT during hospitalization, and disparities in baseline comorbid conditions, particularly the presence of CKD.</p><p id="p0155">The available evidence mainly assessed eGFR using Scr. The reduction in muscle mass frequently observed in COVID-19 patients who were hospitalized may lead to an overestimation of eGFR when Scr is used as the primary marker.<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref> Thus, the actual decline in eGFR reported in the evidence reviewed may be even greater than that observed. Moreover, other markers of kidney function beyond eGFR were poorly investigated, with only 2 studies reporting on proteinuria and none addressing urinary biomarkers of tubular injury.</p><p id="p0160">There are very scarce data about the pathophysiology of renal long COVID. Ramamoorthy et al<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref> investigated the long-term post-infection pathologic changes in mice. The results showed the development of edema and inflammation of the kidney parenchyma, severe acute tubular necrosis, and infiltration of macrophages and lymphocytes. These findings point to the potential development of kidney fibrosis in the long term.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>Clinical Applicability and Public Policies</title><p id="p0165">Regular kidney function monitoring post-COVID-19 is likely essential for patients who experienced AKI during the acute phase of infection, who underwent KRT during hospitalization, and those with pre-existing comorbid conditions, especially CKD. Potential interventions may include closely monitoring high-risk patients, managing well-established risk factors for CKD, such as hypertension, diabetes, and obesity, and avoiding nephrotoxic agents. Among the interventions that may slow CKD progression, lifestyle changes, which include adequate nutrition, regular physical activity, and healthy sleep habits, should be considered.<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> These strategies might be potentially beneficial in preventing the development and/or progression of CKD.<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref> Notably, our findings demonstrated that the majority of the evidence came from high-income countries in the Global North. This highlights the need for greater attention in regions where the COVID-19 pandemic may have been underreported.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>Implications for Future Research</title><p id="p0170">It is essential to standardize the diagnosis of AKI during acute SARS-CoV-2 infection, mainly by adopting the KDIGO guideline.<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref> Furthermore, it is important to avoid adapting or altering well-established definitions of abnormal kidney function, as this can lead to misdiagnosis and lack of adequate assistance. We also recommend assessing kidney function through markers other than Scr, which is notably influenced by the frequent muscle mass loss during COVID-19-associated hospitalization. These additional markers primarily include Scys and albuminuria. The routine use of composite outcomes, including major adverse kidney events, as reported in some studies, should be encouraged, as it enables a more comprehensive evaluation of kidney dysfunction without relying exclusively on hard endpoints such as the development of CKD. Also, longer follow-up periods are necessary to provide insights into the long-term trends of kidney outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>Strengths and Limitations</title><p id="p0175">For conducting this scoping review, we followed well-established guidelines (JBI and PRISMA-ScR). Additionally, the review protocol was previously published and is freely available.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Finally, we did not impose language or date restrictions and adopted a comprehensive search strategy across multiple databases. Despite these strengths, relevant limitations are worth mentioning. First, almost all the evidence included came from Asia, Europe, and North America, whereas only 2 studies were from Latin America and none from Africa. Second, the studies exhibited high heterogeneity in kidney function outcomes at follow-up. These limitations were expected, as scoping reviews aim to gather all available evidence and shed light on implications for future research.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0180">This scoping review highlighted that renal long COVID, characterized by CKD development, progression, and/or long-term KRT dependence, may occur in survivors of COVID-19. Studies reporting higher frequencies of AKI demonstrated greater rates of long-term adverse kidney outcomes, indicating AKI as a potential risk factor for renal long COVID. However, the high heterogeneity and low methodological quality of the studies limit robust conclusions, and further research is needed.</p><p id="p0185">Therefore, it may be essential to conduct regular assessments of kidney function during post-COVID-19 follow-up in high-risk patients, especially those who developed AKI during the acute phase of infection and those with pre-existing comorbid conditions such as CKD. This approach can help identify individuals with kidney function decline who are at risk of CKD development and/or progression, enabling timely interventions and treatment.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group><article-title>Post COVID-19 condition (Long COVID)</article-title><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition" id="intref0015">https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition</ext-link><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID or post-COVID-19 syndrome: putative pathophysiology, risk factors, and treatments</article-title><source>Infect Dis (Lond)</source><volume>53</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34024217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/23744235.2021.1924397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8146298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>PHOSP-COVID Collaborative Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics with inflammation profiling of long COVID and association with 1-year recovery following hospitalisation in the UK: a prospective observational study</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><volume>10</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35472304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(22)00127-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9034855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nirantharakumar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symptoms and risk factors for long COVID in non-hospitalized adults</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>28</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1706</fpage><lpage>1714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35879616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-022-01909-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9388369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optMaqkoTsu2X"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burdmann</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Renal long COVID-19: an ongoing debate requiring robust evidence</article-title><source>J Bras Nefrol</source><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2025E001</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/2175-8239-JBN-2025-E001en</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11864787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40009792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaubien-Souligny</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of acute kidney injury in patients hospitalized with COVID-19 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Kidney Med</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>98.e1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33319190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.xkme.2020.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7723763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadim</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forni</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19-associated acute kidney injury: consensus report of the 25th Acute Disease Quality Initiative (ADQI) Workgroup</article-title><source>Nat Rev Nephrol</source><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33060844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41581-020-00356-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7561246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of acute kidney injury in chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>Semin Nephrol</source><volume>36</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27475659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.semnephrol.2016.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4979984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frediani</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Busatto</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>C.R.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burdmann</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><collab>HCFMUSP COVID-19 Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Long COVID and kidney function: a scoping review protocol</article-title><comment>Preprint</comment><source>medRxiv</source><volume>2024</volume><year>Published February 29, 2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.02.29.24303559</pub-id><comment>2024.02.29.24303559</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M.D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marnie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Updated methodological guidance for the conduct of scoping reviews</article-title><source>JBI Evid Synth</source><volume>18</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>2119</fpage><lpage>2126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33038124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.11124/JBIES-20-00167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M.D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recommendations for the extraction, analysis, and presentation of results in scoping reviews</article-title><source>JBI Evid Synth</source><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36081365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.11124/JBIES-22-00123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillie</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PRISMA Extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><volume>169</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M18-0850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munn</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moola</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riitano</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tufanaru</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methodological guidance for systematic reviews of observational epidemiological studies reporting prevalence and cumulative incidence data</article-title><source>Int J Evid Based Healthc</source><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26317388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/XEB.0000000000000054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The pattern of cytokines expression and dynamic changes of renal function at 6 months in patients with Omicron COVID-19</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><volume>95</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e28477</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jmv.28477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36609778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognosis and antibody profiles in survivors of critical illness from COVID-19: a prospective multicentre cohort study</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><volume>128</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34980470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bja.2021.11.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8616737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thankachan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dvorai</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saidi</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunosuppression regimen modification during COVID-19 infection in kidney transplant recipients</article-title><source>Transpl Immunol</source><volume>80</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101883</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.trim.2023.101883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37433396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malinowska</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heleniak</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muchlado</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in kidney graft function in COVID-19 convalescents</article-title><source>Transplant Proc</source><volume>54</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>884</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35501173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.transproceed.2022.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8923994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Healthy outcomes of patients with COVID-19 two years after the infection: a prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>2680</fpage><lpage>2688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36215047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/22221751.2022.2133639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9639507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>R.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olatosi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence of chronic kidney disease following acute coronavirus disease 2019 based on South Carolina statewide data</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><volume>38</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1911</fpage><lpage>1919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37045985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-023-08184-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10097447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melero</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mijaylova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez-Benítez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García-Prieto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cedeño</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goicoechea</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality and renal long-term outcome of critically ill COVID-19 patients with acute kidney failure, continuous renal replacement therapy and invasive mechanical ventilation</article-title><source>Med Clin (Barc)</source><volume>159</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.medcle.2022.02.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9259468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35818456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumlertgul</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirondini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute kidney injury prevalence, progression and long-term outcomes in critically ill patients with COVID-19: a cohort study</article-title><source>Ann Intensive Care</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>123</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34357478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13613-021-00914-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8343342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boparai</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term outcomes of COVID-19 survivors with hospital AKI: association with time to recovery from AKI</article-title><source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source><volume>38</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>2160</fpage><lpage>2169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36702551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ndt/gfad020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strohbehn</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seethapathy</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute kidney injury incidence, recovery, and long-term kidney outcomes among hospitalized patients with COVID-19 and influenza</article-title><source>Kidney Int Rep</source><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>2565</fpage><lpage>2574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34307971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ekir.2021.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruault</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philipponnet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sapin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and outcome of early-onset acute kidney injury and recovery in critically ill COVID-19 patients: a retrospective analysis</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1001</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37189619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines11041001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10135848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Annadi</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhri</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Short- and long-term recovery after moderate/severe AKI in patients with and without COVID-19</article-title><source>Kidney360</source><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35373118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.34067/KID.0005342021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8967640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savale</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Four-month clinical status of a cohort of patients after hospitalization for COVID-19</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>325</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1525</fpage><lpage>1534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33729425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2021.3331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7970386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rousseau</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minguet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-intensive care syndrome after a critical COVID-19: cohort study from a Belgian follow-up clinic</article-title><source>Ann Intensive Care</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34324073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13613-021-00910-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8319705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>I.F.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>O.T.Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mass screening is associated with low rates of acute kidney injury among COVID-19 patients in Hong Kong</article-title><source>Am J Nephrol</source><volume>52</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33765681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000514234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Defelice</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giusti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Killackey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paramesh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijay</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short and long-term outcomes of kidney transplant recipients diagnosed with COVID-19 infection: a single-center observational study</article-title><source>Cureus</source><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e31375</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.31375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9744398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36523681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>B.W.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>B.W.Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>A.L.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term kidney function recovery and mortality after COVID-19-associated acute kidney injury: an international multi-centre observational cohort study</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><volume>55</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">01724</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9640184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36381999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darcis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouquegneau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term clinical follow-up of patients suffering from moderate-to-severe COVID-19 infection: a monocentric prospective observational cohort study</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><volume>109</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34273510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.07.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8278829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bansode</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swami</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute kidney injury in COVID-19: clinical profile and outcome</article-title><source>Indian J Nephrol</source><volume>32</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35967529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/ijn.IJN_21_21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9364999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bento</surname><given-names>G.A.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>V.L.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaz</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daher</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduction of estimated glomerular filtration rate after COVID-19-associated acute kidney injury</article-title><source>J Bras Nefrol</source><volume>45</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>488</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37311051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/2175-8239-JBN-2022-0179en</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10726661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemeç</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akgül</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are patients with COVID-19 at risk of long-term chronic kidney disease?</article-title><source>Niger J Clin Pract</source><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37056110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/njcp.njcp_382_22</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karadag</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arici</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 outcomes of non-dialysis dependent chronic kidney disease patients: a national, multicenter, controlled study</article-title><source>Int Urol Nephrol</source><volume>55</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35951255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11255-022-03329-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9366804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>I.C.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C.K.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 infection: a retrospective, multi-database cohort study in Hong Kong and the UK</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><volume>60</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102000</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.102000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10173760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37197226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Mouhayyar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrales</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with severity of acute kidney injury and adverse outcomes in critically ill patients with COVID-19</article-title><source>Nephron</source><volume>146</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35675790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000524657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9393776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>6-month consequences of COVID-19 in patients discharged from hospital: a cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>401</volume><issue>10393</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>e21</fpage><lpage>e33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37321233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00810-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10258565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atiquzzaman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term effect of COVID-19 infection on kidney function among COVID-19 patients followed in post-COVID-19 recovery clinics in British Columbia, Canada</article-title><source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source><volume>38</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>2816</fpage><lpage>2825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37349962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ndt/gfad121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boruga</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Septimiu-Radu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nandarge</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kidney function tests and continuous eGFR decrease at six months after SARS-CoV-2 infection in patients clinically diagnosed with post-COVID syndrome</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>950</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38790912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines12050950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11117851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahalingasivam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faucon</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjölander</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kidney function decline after COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>7</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2450014</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.50014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11672154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39724377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obrişcă</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mocanu</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vornicu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of SARS-CoV-2 infection on renal function in patients with biopsy-proven kidney diseases</article-title><source>PLOS One</source><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0296168</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0296168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10745175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38134019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of mild and moderate COVID-19 infection on the progression of kidney dysfunction in patients with IgA nephropathy</article-title><source>Clin Kidney J</source><volume>17</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">sfae157</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ckj/sfae157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11229029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38979107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malinowska</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruszkowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muchlado</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of COVID-19 on kidney graft function one year after onset</article-title><source>Medicina (Kaunas)</source><volume>60</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38256287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/medicina60010026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11154522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Filev</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyubomirova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogov</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-Acute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 Infection (PASC) for patients—3-year follow-up of patients with chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>1259</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38927466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines12061259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11201278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of acute kidney injury with 1-year outcome of kidney function in hospital survivors with COVID-19: a cohort study</article-title><source>EBioMedicine</source><volume>76</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103817</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ebiom.2022.103817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8776508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35074630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in glomerular filtration rate and metabolomic differences in severely ill coronavirus disease survivors 3 months after discharge</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta Mol Basis Dis</source><volume>1868</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">166289</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbadis.2021.166289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8516480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34656797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 condition and pulmonary embolism</article-title><source>J Multidiscip Healthc</source><volume>17</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>6153</fpage><lpage>6159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39741525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/JMDH.S492159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>J.A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinerz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute kidney injury in critically ill COVID-19 patients in a tertiary hospital: short and long-term kidney and patient outcomes</article-title><source>J Bras Nephrol</source><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e20240107</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/2175-8239-JBN-2024-0107en</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11726861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39792860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aklilu</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nugent</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19−associated acute kidney injury and longitudinal kidney outcomes</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><volume>184</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38407862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.8225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10897825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term renal outcomes of patients with COVID-19: a meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title><source>J Nephrol</source><volume>36</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>2441</fpage><lpage>2456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37787893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40620-023-01731-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of cystatin C and creatinine in the assessment of measured kidney function during critical illness</article-title><source>Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</source><volume>18</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37256861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2215/CJN.0000000000000203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10564373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramamoorthy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravelo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kidney damage in long COVID: studies in experimental mice</article-title><source>Biology (Basel)</source><volume>12</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1070</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37626956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biology12081070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10452084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) CKD Work Group</collab></person-group><article-title>KDIGO 2024 clinical practice guideline for the evaluation and management of chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>Kidney Int</source><volume>105</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>S117</fpage><lpage>S314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38490803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.kint.2023.10.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mafra</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardozo</surname><given-names>L.F.M.F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and nutrition: focus on chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>J Ren Nutr</source><volume>33</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>S118</fpage><lpage>S127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37632513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.jrn.2023.01.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantuária</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inda-Filho</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 rehabilitation: a special look at chronic kidney disease patients</article-title><source>Ren Replace Ther</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34150334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s41100-021-00355-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8205208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optRWeAtynPJk"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarca</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lightfoot</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prescribing physical activity and exercise for people with chronic kidney disease: A practical guide by the Global Renal Exercise Network</article-title><source>Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</source><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2025</year><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40085159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2215/CJN.0000000708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12160954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO)</collab></person-group><article-title>KDIGO clinical practice guideline for acute kidney injury</article-title><source>Kidney Int Suppl</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>138</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><p id="p0225">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary File (PDF)</title><p>Items S1-S2; Table S1.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary File (XLSX)</title><p>Item S3.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Article Information</title><sec id="sec4"><title>Authors’ Full Names and Academic Degrees</title><p id="p0190">Marcella M. Frediani, MD∗, Heitor S. Ribeiro, PhD∗, Geraldo F. Busatto, MD, PhD, Carlos R.R. Carvalho, MD, PhD, and Emmanuel A. Burdmann, MD, PhD</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Authors’ Contributions</title><p id="p0195">Research ideas and study design: MMF, HSR, and EAB; Data acquisition, analysis, and interpretation: MMF and HSR; Statistical analysis: HSR; Supervision: EAB, GFB, and CRRC. Each author contributed important intellectual content during article drafting or revision and accepts accountability for the overall work by ensuring that questions pertaining to the accuracy or integrity of any portion of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. MMF and HSR contributed equally and share first authorship.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Support</title><p id="p0200">This study received funding from the <italic toggle="yes">Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</italic> (<funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001807</institution-id><institution>FAPESP</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>; grant <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">22/01769-5</award-id>). EAB received a research grant (<italic toggle="yes">Bolsa de Produtividade em Pesquisa</italic>, 304743/2017-8) from The <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003593</institution-id><institution>National Council for Scientific and Technological Development</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>. HSR received a postdoctoral scholarship from FAPESP (24/04564-0). FAPESP had no role in the study design.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Financial Disclosure</title><p id="p0205">The authors declare that they have no relevant financial interests.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Data Sharing</title><p id="p0210">All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this article and available in the Supplementary Material. Further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Declaration of generative AI and AI-assisted technologies in the writing process</title><p id="p0215">During the preparation of this work, the authors used OpenAI’s GPT-4 architecture to aid in the English-language writing process. After using this tool, the authors reviewed and edited the content as needed and take full responsibility for the content of the publication.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Peer Review</title><p id="p0220">Received December 9, 2024. Evaluated by 2 external peer reviewers, with direct editorial input from the Editor-in-Chief. Accepted in revised form April 18, 2025.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn id="d36e1921"><p id="ntpara0010">Complete author and article information provided before references.</p></fn><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="p0230">
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.xkme.2025.101039" id="intref0010"><bold>Supplementary File (PDF)</bold></ext-link>
</p><p id="p0235"><bold>Item S1:</bold> Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses Extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMA-ScR) Checklist.</p><p id="p0240"><bold>Item S2:</bold> Search strategy.</p><p id="p0245"><bold>Item S3:</bold> Characteristics of each included report.</p><p id="p0250"><bold>Table S1:</bold> Methodological Quality Assessment of the Included Studies.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>