<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1754</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontimmu</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Immunol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-3224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11955459</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11955459.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11955459</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11955459</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40165957</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1575669</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Long COVID and brain inflammation: unravelling mechanisms and potential therapies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb Sharif-Askari</surname><given-names initials="F">Fatemeh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/960411"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raber</surname><given-names initials="J">Jacob</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/48178"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alzoubi</surname><given-names initials="KH">Karem H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2025955"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Research Institute for Medical and Health Science, University of Sharjah</institution>, <addr-line>Sharjah</addr-line>, <country>United Arab Emirates</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Department of Pharmacy Practice and Pharmacotherapeutics, College of Pharmacy, University of Sharjah</institution>, <addr-line>Sharjah</addr-line>, <country>United Arab Emirates</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>Departments of Behavioral Neuroscience, Neurology, and Radiation Medicine, Division of Neuroscience, Oregon National Primate Research Center (ONPRC), Oregon Health &amp; Science University</institution>, <addr-line>Portland, OR</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and Reviewed by: Pietro Ghezzi, Brighton and Sussex Medical School, United Kingdom</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Fatemeh Saheb Sharif-Askari, <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:fsharifaskari@sharjah.ac.ae">fsharifaskari@sharjah.ac.ae</email>; Jacob Raber, <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:raberj@ohsu.edu">raberj@ohsu.edu</email>
</corresp><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn003"><p>†These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480569</issue-id><elocation-id>1575669</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-01 09:25:14.673"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025 Saheb Sharif-Askari, Raber and Alzoubi</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Saheb Sharif-Askari, Raber and Alzoubi</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fimmu-16-1575669.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/55492"/><kwd-group><kwd>long Covid</kwd><kwd>neuroinflammation</kwd><kwd>immune dysregulation</kwd><kwd>cognitive dysfunction</kwd><kwd>preclinical mice models</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>Office of Dietary Supplements
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000063</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. FSSA is supported by the Seed Research Projects (No. 2401110399) from the University of Sharjah. JR is partially supported by R21 AG079158-01A1.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="3"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="925"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Inflammation</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Patients with Long COVID often experience persistent brain-related symptoms, including brain fog, mood changes, and dizziness (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), likely driven by neuroinflammation even after the virus is cleared. Imaging studies have shown structural and functional changes that indicate ongoing inflammation in the Long COVID brain. The biological mechanisms underlying these symptoms are still not fully understood, and research continues to identify effective therapies to improve both the physical and mental health of those affected (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>In this Research Topic, we explore research on Long COVID and its investigation through preclinical animal models.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1450853" ext-link-type="uri">Missailidis et al.</ext-link> conducted RNA-Seq analysis of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) from individuals with Long COVID and those who had fully recovered COVID-19. Their findings revealed upregulation of ICOS and S1PR1, suggesting a persistent pro-inflammatory state (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure 1A</bold>
</xref>), as these genes are involved in immune cell survival and signaling. They also observed downregulation of LILRB1 and LILRB2, highlighting immune dysregulation as a distinguishing feature of Long COVID.</p><fig position="float" id="f1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Neurological consequences of Long COVID. <bold>(A)</bold> In Long COVID, persistent neuroinflammation and mitochondrial dysfunction are implicated in ongoing neurodegeneration. <bold>(B)</bold> Certain populations, particularly females, are more susceptible due to hormonal and immune factors. <bold>(C)</bold> Preclinical models, including mice exposed to virus-like particles (VLPs), are being used to investigate the effects of Long COVID on the nervous system. These studies have linked neuroinflammation to behavioral disruptions, highlighting the need for further research into the neurological impacts of viral infections, particularly in Long COVID.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fimmu-16-1575669-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1290523" ext-link-type="uri">Lee et al.</ext-link> analyzed the expression of long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) in the brains of COVID-19 patients, identifying hundreds of differentially expressed lncRNAs compared to age- and sex-matched uninfected controls. Many of these lncRNAs correlated with cognitive decline and increased inflammation, aligning with cognitive dysfunction observed in Long COVID. These findings suggest a potential role for lncRNAs in the neurological effects of COVID-19, highlighting a key area for further research.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2023.1275001" ext-link-type="uri">Noonong et al.</ext-link> proposed that mitochondrial dysfunction may play a crucial role in Long COVID, linking it to diabetes and oxidative stress (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure 1A</bold>
</xref>). Their hypothesis highlights mitochondria’s role in inflammation and metabolic homeostasis, suggesting broader systemic implications for viral recovery and chronic symptoms.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1332776" ext-link-type="uri">Hanafy and Jovin</ext-link> emphasized the role of chronic inflammation in exacerbating neurological symptoms commonly seen in patients with Long COVID, such as brain fog, extreme fatigue (asthenia), and depression- a condition they refer as “Brain FADE syndrome” (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure 1A</bold>
</xref>). They advocate for an integrated treatment approach that targets both inflammatory pathways and associated mental health challenges.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2023.1281310" ext-link-type="uri">Gu et al.</ext-link> investigated sex differences in COVID-induced autoimmunity and neurological effects, highlighting how female sex hormones and X-chromosome factors may increase women’s susceptibility to Long COVID (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure 1B</bold>
</xref>). They proposed that COVID-19 may disturb immune tolerance, leading to autoantibodies infiltration into the central nervous system. They also suggested that COVID-19 could disrupt the female microbiome, contributing to neural damage, including demyelination, neuroinflammation, and neurodegeneration. Understanding these sex differences could help develop strategies to mitigate COVID-related neurological injuries.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnint.2024.1417856" ext-link-type="uri">Bustamante et al.</ext-link> explored risk factors for developing Long COVID, including a history of severe illness and intensive care. Using preclinical animal models, they examined the involvement of the nervous system in inflammation through the psychoneuroimmunoendocrine axes. They proposed that Long COVID involves peripheral and central sensitization, leading to dysregulation and chronic inflammation, and discussed therapeutic strategies to modulate these inflammation responses.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1521029" ext-link-type="uri">Dai et al.</ext-link> reviewed the utility of preclinical animal models in understanding Long COVID. They highlighted key features replicated in these models, including lung fibrosis, hyperglycemia, and neurological sequelae, while acknowledging limitations such as restricted genetic diversity and challenges in modeling Long COVID pathology. To improve translational relevance, they proposed incorporating genetically diverse populations, conducting longitudinal studies, and aligning animal findings with clinical data.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1384516" ext-link-type="uri">Singh et al.</ext-link> investigated the Long COVID implications of the Delta variant using K18-hACE2 mice. They found robust inflammatory responses linked to neuropsychiatric symptoms and motor behavior changes during acute infections, with persistent immune activation post-infection. Post-acute infection, the brain showed no detectable viral RNA and minimal residential immune cell activation in surviving mice. However, transcriptome analysis revealed persistent activation of immune pathways, including humoral responses, complement, phagocytosis, along with gene expression linked to ataxia telangiectasia, impaired cognitive function, and neuronal dysfunction. Surviving mice exhibited strong neutralizing antibodies against both Delta and Omicron variants, months after the infection.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1473366" ext-link-type="uri">O’Niel et al.</ext-link> used virus-like particles (VLPs) expressing SARS-CoV-2 structural proteins (nucleocapsid (N), membrane (M), envelope (E) and spike (S), in human apolipoprotein E (apoE)-targeted replacement mice (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure 1C</bold>
</xref>). The study found apoE isoform-dependent effects on behavioral measures, with E2 mice more affected than E3 or E4 mice, despite E2 being linked to a lower Alzheimer’s disease risk. VLPs also caused behavioral and circadian disruptions independent of apoE isoform, even in the absence of viral replication. Increased susceptibility in E2 mice was associated with elevated hippocampal CCL11, similar to CCL11 elevations seen in humans with cognitive symptoms after COVID-19 exposure. The authors emphasize the need for further research to better understand and treat neurological conditions associated with viral infections, especially as many continue to struggle with Long COVID.</p><p>The ongoing research discussed in this Research Topic reveals significant progress toward understanding the biological mechanisms of Long COVID. As we continue to uncover the complexities of the condition, further preclinical and clinical studies are critical for improving the well-being and brain function of those affected by Long COVID and other related neurological conditions.</p></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The guest editors would like to express their gratitude to all the authors and reviewers for their invaluable contributions to this Research Topic.</p></ack><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>FS: Writing – original draft, Writing – review &amp; editing. JR: Writing – original draft, Writing – review &amp; editing. KA: Writing – review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s3"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p><p>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="s4"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Generative AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s5"><title>Publisher’s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bobak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorney</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacevich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaelber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preexisting psychiatric conditions as risk factors for diagnosed long COVID-19 syndrome within aggregated electronic health record data</article-title>. <source>Psychomat Med</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<page-range>132–6</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0000000000001280</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11001529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38193771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Sharif-Askari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali Hussain Alsayed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Sharif-Askari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saddik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Sayed Hussain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halwani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors and early preventive measures for long COVID in non-hospitalized patients: analysis of a large cohort in the United Arab Emirates</article-title>. <source>Public Health</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>230</volume>:<fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2024.02.031</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38574425</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Sharif-Askari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali Hussain Alsayed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Sharif-Askari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Sayed Hussain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Muhsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halwani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nirmatrelvir plus ritonavir reduces COVID-19 hospitalization and prevents long COVID in adult outpatients</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>25901</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-76472-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39472619</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11522512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>