<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Commun Med (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Commun Med (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4189</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">commsmed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Communications Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2730-664X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11978816</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11978816.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11978816</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11978816</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40199960</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43856-025-00759-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">759</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A nationwide study of risk factors for long COVID and its economic and mental health consequences in the United States</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8907-6420</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="D">Daniel</given-names></name><address><email>d.kim@northeastern.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04t5xt781</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.261112.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2173 3359</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Health and Health Sciences, School of Community Health and Behavioral Sciences, </institution><institution>Northeastern University, </institution></institution-wrap>Boston, MA USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04t5xt781</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.261112.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2173 3359</institution-id><institution>School of Public Policy and Urban Affairs, </institution><institution>Northeastern University, </institution></institution-wrap>Boston, MA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478325</issue-id><elocation-id>104</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-10 16:25:37.327"><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="43856_2025_Article_759.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">In the United States, concerns have been increasingly raised over the future public health and economic burden of long COVID including disability and declines in labor force participation. However, only a handful of U.S. studies have explored sociodemographic or socioeconomic characteristics that put people at risk of long COVID or have investigated its economic and mental health sequelae.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Using repeated cross-sectional data on over 375,000 adults including nearly 50,000 adults with long COVID pooled from U.S. nationally-representative Household Pulse Survey data collected between September and November 2022 and between August and October 2023, I fit age- and gender-adjusted and multivariable modified Poisson regression models to examine multiple sociodemographic and socioeconomic factors as predictors of long COVID. I further estimate the risks of unemployment, financial hardship, and anxiety and depression among working-aged adults and adults with current long COVID symptoms, and estimate the economic burden of lost wages due to long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Nearly one in seven adults (~35 million) and working-aged adults (~30 million) reported having a history of long COVID by late 2022 and late 2023. In age- and gender-adjusted models and fully-adjusted multivariable models, I find several factors predict long COVID including lower household income, and being Hispanic, female, gay/lesbian or bisexual. I also find having long COVID is linked to higher risks of recent unemployment, financial hardship, and anxiety and depressive symptomatology, with evidence of dose-response relationships.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Overall, an estimated 24 million working-aged adults with long COVID had been or may still be at risk of adverse socioeconomic and mental health outcomes. The lost earnings due to long COVID among working-aged adults are estimated to total $211 billion in 2022 and $218 billion in 2023. These findings highlight the substantial public health and economic implications of long COVID among Americans.</p></sec></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="plain-language-summary"><title>Plain Language Summary</title><p id="Par5">Long COVID is a long-term health problem in people with a history of likely or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection (the virus that causes COVID-19). U.S. Census Bureau data on over 375,000 adults were used to identify risk factors for long COVID and its harmful effects. Nearly one in every seven adults reported a history of long COVID in late 2023, months after the emergency phase of the pandemic was declared over. Those with lower income and who are Hispanic, female, and gay/lesbian or bisexual are at higher risk of long COVID. Long COVID is also linked to higher risks of job loss, financial hardship, and anxiety and depression. Overall, 24 million working-aged adults with long COVID were at risk of these negative outcomes. Lost earnings due to long COVID among working-aged adults totaled $218 billion in 2023. These findings show the important public health and economic consequences of long COVID among Americans.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs3" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par6">Kim identifies risk factors for long COVID and links long COVID to higher instances of job loss, financial hardship, and anxiety and depressive symptoms. Lost earnings due to long COVID among working-aged adults are estimated to total $218 billion in 2023, indicating long COVID’s substantial public health and economic consequences among Americans.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Epidemiology</kwd><kwd>Public health</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par7">As the number of confirmed cases of COVID-19 has well exceeded 100 million in the United States and continues to accrue<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, concerns have been increasingly raised over the future public health and economic burden of long COVID including disability and concomitant declines in labor force participation. Long COVID (also known as post-COVID-19 condition or post-acute sequelae of COVID-19) is a condition characterized by long-term health problems in individuals with a history of probable or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, usually 3 months from the onset of COVID-19 with symptoms that last for at least 2 months and cannot be explained by an alternative diagnosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. By yielding symptoms affecting daily functioning, long COVID can plausibly affect one’s ability to work, leading to loss of employment income and inducing financial strain. Through impacting physical and mental functioning<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>, long COVID can contribute to mental health disorders including anxiety and depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Yet only a handful of US population-based studies have explored sociodemographic and socioeconomic predictors of long COVID and economic and health sequelae, and such studies remain primarily limited to relatively small samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">The present study was undertaken to use nationally-representative data from the US Census Bureau’s Household Pulse Survey (HPS) on over 375,000 adults including nearly 50,000 adults with long COVID to investigate key sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics as risk factors for long COVID among adults, to explore the associations of long COVID with unemployment, financial hardship, and mental health outcomes, and to estimate the economic burden of lost wages from long COVID in the United States, both in 2022 and 2023 to investigate trends over time. Those with lower income and who are Hispanic, female, and gay/lesbian or bisexual are at higher risk of long COVID. Long COVID is linked to higher risks of job loss, financial hardship, and anxiety and depression, and lost earnings due to long COVID among working-aged adults totaled $211 billion in 2022 and $218 billion in 2023, indicating the substantial public health and economic consequences of long COVID among Americans.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par9">Repeated cross-sectional data were pooled from nationally-representative HPS surveys in data collection Phase 3.6 administered from September 14—November 14, 2022 and pooled data from HPS surveys in Phase 3.10 administered from August 23—October 30, 2023<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. The HPS used the Census Bureau’s Master Address File as the source of sampled housing units. The HPS was conducted online by Qualtrics, with survey response rates ranging from 3.9 to 5.6% in Phase 3.6 and from 6.4 to 7.3% in Phase 3.10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The study population consisted of US adults aged 18+ years. Analyses of employment and financial hardship as outcomes were limited to adult participants of working age (aged 18–64 years). For the primary sample analyzed in multivariable models, data were available on 154,430 adults including 113,192 working-aged adults (representative of 197 million American adults) surveyed in late 2022 and 220,664 adults surveyed in late 2023.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Outcomes</title><p id="Par10">The first set of models examined the risks of 1) long COVID in the full samples; 2) long COVID among those with confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection based on a positive rapid point-of-care test, self-test, or laboratory test for COVID-19 or being told by a doctor or other health care provider of having COVID-19; and 3) confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection in the full sample. The risk of long COVID is a function of the risk of becoming infected with COVID and the risk of progressing from acute infection to long COVID. Long COVID was defined in the HPS as reporting any symptoms lasting 3 months or longer that were not present prior to having COVID-19 including fatigue, difficulty concentrating and forgetfulness, “brain fog”, shortness of breath, joint or muscle pain, heart palpitations, changes to taste/smell, and inability to exercise<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">The second set of models examined 4 recent outcomes in the full sample and among those still reporting long COVID symptoms: whether the respondent was employed in the past week; experienced financial hardship, defined as household difficulty (somewhat/very difficult vs. not at all/a little difficult) to pay for usual household expenses including food, rent/ mortgage, and loans, within the previous week; and the frequency of experiencing anxiety symptoms and depressive symptoms (using the 2-item Generalized Anxiety Disorder-2 (GAD-2) and Patient Health Questionnaire-2 (PHQ-2)) over the previous 2 weeks, with scores of 3–6 vs 0–2 being employed previously to screen for anxiety and depressive disorders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Based on a cut-off score of ≥3, the GAD-2 demonstrated optimal sensitivity and specificity (sensitivity = 0.71, specificity = 0.69), and the PHQ-2 exhibited peak sensitivity and adequate specificity (sensitivity = 0.64, specificity = 0.85). Internal consistency reliability has been demonstrated to be high for both measures (Cronbach’s α = 0.81 and 0.83 for the GAD-2 and PHQ-2 scales, respectively)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Predictors</title><p id="Par12">The first set of models included the following predictors: age group, gender (male, female, transgender, other), sexual orientation (straight, gay/lesbian, bisexual, other), race and Hispanic ethnicity (Hispanic, non-Hispanic White, Black, Asian, and Other), marital status, education, household income in 2021, household size, presence of children in the household, receipt of a COVID-19 vaccine (either primary series or booster in the 2022 surveys, and either vaccine receipt within the past year or earlier in the 2023 surveys), and health insurance status<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par13">In the second set of models, the main predictors were long COVID status (yes, no) in the full sample and the extent to which current long COVID symptoms reduced the ability to carry out day-to-day activities (a lot, a little, not at all) compared to before having COVID-19.</p><p id="Par14">All fully-adjusted models further controlled for state of residence and self-reported non-receipt of the COVID-19 booster due to a COVID-19 infection (the latter in the 2022 surveys only).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par15">Using data from Phase 3.6, age- and gender-adjusted and multivariable modified Poisson regression models (that can approximate yet circumvent issues with log-binomial models) controlling for all predictors simultaneously (“fully-adjusted models”) were fit to estimate adjusted PRs from generalized estimating equations that accounted for survey weights and repeated measures within individuals in order to provide robust standard errors based on sandwich estimators<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Multiple imputation using 25 multiply imputed datasets and the MCMC algorithm without rounding under a missing at random assumption<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> was used to handle missing data on predictor variables, which ranged from 0.6% for marital status, 0.8% for vaccination receipt, 1.1% for gender, 1.4% for sexual orientation, 18.0% for household income, to 20.9% for health insurance status. For outcome variables, multiple imputation was not able to be implemented using the MCMC algorithm; data were missing in 0.33% for long COVID, 2.4% for unemployment, 5.6% for financial hardship, 11.0% for anxiety, and 11.1% for depression. The first set of multivariable-adjusted models of predictors of long COVID were then estimated using survey data from Phase 3.10.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Estimation of economic burden of lost wages</title><p id="Par16">The estimated economic burden of long COVID from lost wages was calculated in part by adopting a similar approach to others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, with the components used in the calculation shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> for the survey phases in 2022 and 2023. The 2021 Bureau of Labor Statistics labor force participation rate for those aged 18–64 y was derived using age group-specific labor force participation rates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> and applied to the HPS-derived estimated number of adults aged 18–64 y with long COVID who still reported having long COVID symptoms, disaggregated by household income category. From the HPS data, I also employed estimates of the distribution of adults not working due to long COVID by income category. I used published 2021 U.S. national survey estimates of work time being reduced by 25.9% due to long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, and for each income category combined the estimated FTEs of lost work due to reduced working time with the lost FTEs for the HPS-derived number of adults choosing not to work recently because of long COVID, under the assumption that the distribution of reduced working hours with long COVID by income mirrored the distribution of not working at all due to long COVID by income. For each income category, the estimated total FTE of lost work was then multiplied by the midpoint of income for the corresponding income category below $200k/year and by the estimated median income of $275k/year in the $200k+/year income bracket, and then summed across income categories to yield an annual estimate of lost earnings due to long COVID in both late 2022 and late 2023 (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Estimated lost earnings due to long COVID among U.S. adults aged 18–64 years in 2022 and 2023</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Component</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">HPS Phase 3.6</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">HPS Phase 3.10</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Data source</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Sept. 14—Nov. 14 2022</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Aug. 23—Oct. 30, 2023</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">Estimated total # and % distribution of adults aged 18–64 y with current long COVID symptoms</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">a: 14,508,809</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">a: 10,914,616</td><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">Household Pulse Survey sample data</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">% distribution by income</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">% distribution by income</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.54%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.84%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.04%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.66%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.20%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.63%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.47%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.51%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.33%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.49%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.81%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.07%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.21%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.60%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.40%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.20%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Estimated labor force participation rate aged 18–64 y</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">b: 76.15%</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">b: 76.15%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (2021 estimate)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">Estimated total number and % distribution of adults not working due to long COVID</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">c: 435,473</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">c: 246,970</td><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">Household Pulse Survey sample data</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">% distribution by income</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">% distribution by income</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.02%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.54%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.30%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.35%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.98%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.73%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.70%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.63%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.84%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.15%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.20%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.73%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.11%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.06%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.85%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.81%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">Estimated number of adults working with long COVID</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">d: (a × b) – c = 10.6 million</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">d: (a × b) – c = 8.1 million</td><td rowspan="10" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Freq. distribution by income</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Freq. distribution by income</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,157,150</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">779,193</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">923,966</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">615,768</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,167,720</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">857,081</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,879,028</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,416,592</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,544,467</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,159,702</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,927,288</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,548,710</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">783,406</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">700,140</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,229,960</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">987,322</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average % reduced work time due to long COVID</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">e: 25.92% [CI: 18.09%, 35.65%]</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">e: 25.92% [CI: 18.09%, 35.65%]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Understanding America Study COVID-19 Survey (mid-2021)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">Estimated total FTEs of lost work time</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">f: (d × e) + c = 3.19 million [CI: 2.4 million, 4.2 million]</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">f: (d × e) + c = 2.34 million [CI: 1.7 million, 3.1 million]</td><td rowspan="10" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Freq. distribution by income</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Freq. distribution by income</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">860,947</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">363,179</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">551,127</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">195,074</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">509,314</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">250,809</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">372,791</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">365,426</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">281,609</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">424,308</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">293,195</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">344,301</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99,243</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">141,586</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">218,133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">252,607</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">Annual income</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">g: Average salary within income category</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">g: Average salary within income category</td><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">*2022 estimate based on income percentiles derived from the U.S. Census Bureau Annual Social and Economic (ASEC) Supplement by the University of Minnesota Population Center<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$12.5k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;$25k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$12.5k</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$30k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$25k–34,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$30k</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$42.5k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$35k–49,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$42.5k</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$62.5k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50k–74,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$62.5k</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$87.5k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$75k–99,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$87.5k</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$125k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$100k–149,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$125k</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$175k</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$150k–199,999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$175k</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$275k*</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$200k+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$275k*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Estimated annual lost earnings due to long COVID</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>f × g: $210.9 billion</p><p>[CI: $155.9 billion, $279.2 billion]</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>f × g: $218.3 billion</p><p>[CI: $159.3 billion, $291.6 billion]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par17">All analyses were conducted using SAS (version 9.4; SAS Institute, Cary, NC). All data were publicly available and anonymized and after the author sought ethics approval were deemed exempt by the Institutional Review Board at Northeastern University from ethical compliance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Reporting summary</title><p id="Par18">Further information on research design is available in the <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">Nature Portfolio Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Characteristics of the full samples</title><p id="Par19">Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> shows the unweighted and weighted characteristics of the full samples aged 18+ years alongside characteristics for the U.S. general population. The composition of the unweighted HPS samples were generally older, more educated, and White compared to the U.S. population. With weighting, these differences were attenuated (e.g., for geographic region) but not eliminated (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Risk of long COVID in the full sample in 2022 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 154,430)</title><p id="Par20">In the age- and gender-adjusted model, compared to those aged 18–29 years, adults aged 30–39 years and 40–49 years had 7–12% higher risks of long COVID, while adults aged 65+ years had 41–57% lower risks (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Higher risks were also observed among those with any (vs. no) children in the household, of Hispanic and other (vs. White non-Hispanic) race/ethnicity, of lower income, in larger households, and who were divorced/separated (vs. married), gay/lesbian or bisexual (vs. straight), and female (60% higher risk), transgender (67% higher risk), or other gender (vs. male) (all age and gender-adjusted prevalence ratios, PRs = 1.07–2.08; nearly all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Black and Asian adults and never married adults were at 20–43% lower risk and 7% lower risk than White adults and married adults, respectively (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Individuals who had completed the primary vaccination series plus a booster against COVID-19 exhibited a 14% lower risk than the unvaccinated group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Age- and gender-adjusted risks of long COVID according to sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics among 154,430 adults, 2022.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, September–November 2022. The figure shows the associations between various sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics and the risk of long COVID among adults in the study population, taking into account age and gender. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. ‘Partial’ refers to receipt of one dose of a two-shot primary vaccine series. ‘Complete’ refers to completion of the primary vaccine series (2 doses of a two-shot series or a single dose series).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e844" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">In the fully-adjusted multivariable model, similar overall patterns were generally observed although some estimates were attenuated compared to estimates from the age- and gender-adjusted model. Compared to those aged 18–29 years, adults aged 30–39 years and 40–49 years had 18–21% higher risks of long COVID, while adults aged 65+ years had 31–46% lower risks (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Higher risks were also observed among those with any (vs. no) children in the household, of Hispanic and other (vs. White non-Hispanic) race/ethnicity, of lower income, in larger households, and who were divorced/separated (vs. married), gay/lesbian or bisexual (vs. straight), and female (52% higher risk), transgender (42% higher risk), or other gender (vs. male) (all multivariable-adjusted prevalence ratios, PRs = 1.07–1.81; nearly all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Black and Asian adults and never married adults were at 21–36% lower risk and 8% lower risk than White adults and married adults, respectively (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). No vaccinated groups exhibited lower risks than the unvaccinated group (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Multivariable-adjusted risks of long COVID according to sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics among 154,430 adults, 2022.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, September–November 2022. The figure shows the associations between various sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics and the risk of long COVID among adults in the study population, taking into account all of these characteristics. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. All models were also adjusted for state of residence and non-receipt of a COVID-19 vaccine booster due to COVID-19 infection. ‘Partial’ refers to receipt of one dose of a two-shot primary vaccine series. ‘Complete’ refers to completion of the primary vaccine series (2 doses of a two-shot series or a single dose series).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e870" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Risk of long COVID in the full sample in 2023 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 220,664)</title><p id="Par22">In the fully-adjusted multivariable model using the most recent HPS data in late 2023, similar overall patterns were generally observed as in 2022. Compared to those aged 18–29 years, adults aged 30–39 years and 40–49 years had 13–22% higher risks of long COVID, while adults aged 65+ years had 31–40% lower risks (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Higher risks were also observed among those with any (vs. no) children in the household, of Hispanic and other (vs. White non-Hispanic) race/ethnicity, of lower income, in larger households, gay/lesbian or bisexual (vs. straight), and female (51% higher risk), transgender (46% higher risk), or other gender (vs. male) (all multivariable-adjusted prevalence ratios, PRs = 1.05–1.59; nearly all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Black and Asian adults and never married adults were at 26–36% lower risk and 7% lower risk than White adults and married adults, respectively (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Unlike the associations observed for 2022, those who were divorced/separated (vs. married) had a weaker elevated risk of long COVID, and vaccinated groups had higher risks than the unvaccinated group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Multivariable-adjusted risks of long COVID according to sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics among 220,664 adults, 2023.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, August–October 2023. The figure shows the associations between various sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics and the risk of long COVID among adults in the study population, taking into account all of these characteristics. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. All models were also adjusted for state of residence. ‘Vaccinated, no booster’ refers to receipt of a vaccine more than a year ago. ‘Vaccinated, booster’ refers to receipt of a vaccine within the past year.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e902" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Risk of long COVID among those with diagnosed COVID-19 infection in 2022 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 72,882)</title><p id="Par23">Modeling the risk of long COVID among those confirmed/diagnosed with COVID-19 infection in both the age- and gender-adjusted model and the fully-adjusted multivariable model showed similar patterns (e.g., with females having 37–49% higher risks than males; Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), with a few exceptions: Having a child in the household was not associated with long COVID, whereas inverse associations between educational attainment and long COVID were consistently observed. Being widowed was linked to 13–30% higher risks, and no association was observed for never being married in the fully-adjusted model. Those who completed their primary vaccination series but did not receive a booster had 11–14% higher risks than the unvaccinated (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), while in the age- and gender-adjusted model those who received a booster had a 12% lower risk than the unvaccinated (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Age- and gender-adjusted risks of long COVID according to sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics among 72,882 adults with COVID-19 infection, 2022.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, September–November 2022. The figure shows the associations between various sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics and the risk of long COVID among adults with confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection, taking into account age and gender. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. ‘Partial’ refers to receipt of one dose of a two-shot primary vaccine series. ‘Complete’ refers to completion of the primary vaccine series (2 doses of a two-shot series or a single dose series).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e937" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Multivariable-adjusted risks of long COVID according to sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics among 72,882 adults with COVID-19 infection, 2022.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, September–November 2022. The figure shows the associations between various sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics and the risk of long COVID among adults with confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection, taking into account all of these characteristics. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. All models were also adjusted for state of residence and non-receipt of a COVID-19 vaccine booster due to COVID-19 infection. ‘Partial’ refers to receipt of one dose of a two-shot primary vaccine series. ‘Complete’ refers to completion of the primary vaccine series (2 doses of a two-shot series or a single dose series.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e945" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Risk of confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection in the full sample in 2022 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 154,430)</title><p id="Par24">Modeling the risk of confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection in both the age- and gender-adjusted model and the fully-adjusted multivariable model exhibited analogous patterns to the risk of long COVID (Figs. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). However, being older more consistently predicted a lower risk of COVID-19, and lower education and income were associated with lower risks rather than higher risks. For gender, only females showed an elevated risk of confirmed/diagnosed infection than males. All vaccinated groups had 3–16% lower risks than unvaccinated adults (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Age- and gender-adjusted risks of COVID-19 infection according to sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics among 154,430 adults, 2022.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, September–November 2022. The figure shows the associations between various sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics and the risk of confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection among adults in the study population, taking into account account age and gender. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. ‘Partial’ refers to receipt of one dose of a two-shot primary vaccine series. ‘Complete’ refers to completion of the primary vaccine series (2 doses of a two-shot series or a single dose series).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e977" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Multivariable-adjusted risks of COVID-19 infection according to sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics among 154,430 adults, 2022.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, September–November 2022. The figure shows the associations between various sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics and the risk of confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection among adults in the study population, taking into account all of these characteristics. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. All models were also adjusted for state of residence and non-receipt of a COVID-19 vaccine booster due to COVID-19 infection. ‘Partial’ refers to receipt of one dose of a two-shot primary vaccine series. ‘Complete’ refers to completion of the primary vaccine series (2 doses of a two-shot series or a single dose series).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e985" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Risks of unemployment, financial hardship, and anxiety and depression among working-aged adults (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 113,192) and among adults with current long COVID symptoms in 2022 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10,348)</title><p id="Par25">Those who reported having long COVID had a higher likelihood of not being employed, experiencing financial hardship, and reporting recent anxiety or depressive symptoms (PRs ranging from 1.20–1.71 in the age- and gender-adjusted model and 1.05–1.52 in the fully-adjusted model; all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 except for current employment in the fully-adjusted model; Figs. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> and <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). Among those with current symptoms, there was evidence of dose-response relationships, with those reporting the highest (vs. no) impact on daily functioning having a more than two-fold higher risk of recent depressive symptoms (age-and gender-adjusted PR = 2.59; 95% = 2.21–3.04, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>; fully-adjusted PR = 2.21; 95% = 1.88–2.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>).<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><title>Age- and gender-adjusted risks of unemployment, financial hardship, and anxiety and depressive symptomatology according to long COVID status and according to impact of long COVID symptoms on daily functioning during the COVID-19 pandemic, 2022.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, September–November 2022. The figure shows the risks of unemployment, financial hardship, and anxiety and depressive symptomatology among 154,430 adults and according to the impact of long COVID symptoms on daily functioning among 10,388 adults with symptoms in the study population, taking into account age and gender. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. The analyses of unemployment and financial hardship were restricted to 113,192 working-aged adults (aged 18–64 years). The impact of long COVID symptoms variable measured the extent to which current symptoms reduced the ability to carry out day-to-day activities compared with the period before having COVID-19.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1026" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig8_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><title>Multivariable-adjusted risks of unemployment, financial hardship, and anxiety and depressive symptomatology according to long COVID status and according to impact of long COVID symptoms on daily functioning during the COVID-19 pandemic, 2022.</title><p>Data were collected from the U.S. Census Bureau Household Pulse Survey, September–November 2022. The figure shows the risks of unemployment, financial hardship, and anxiety and depressive symptomatology among 154,430 adults and according to the impact of long COVID symptoms on daily functioning among 10,388 adults with symptoms in the study population, taking into account age, gender, race and Hispanic ethnicity, education, household income in 2021, sexual orientation, children in the household, household size, receipt of a COVID-19 vaccine, health insurance coverage, state of residence, and non-receipt of a vaccine booster due to COVID-19 infection. All estimates shown correspond to prevalence ratio point estimates with 95% confidence intervals. The analyses of unemployment and financial hardship were restricted to 113,192 working-aged adults (aged 18–64 years). The impact of long COVID symptoms variable measured the extent to which current symptoms reduced the ability to carry out day-to-day activities compared with the period before having COVID-19.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1034" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_Fig9_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Estimated population at risk and economic burden of lost wages</title><p id="Par26">Based on the study sample, 14.8% of US adults aged 18+ years (35.22 million; 95% CI = 34.29–36.15 million) and 15.1% of working-aged adults aged 18–64 years (30.65 million; 95% CI = 29.75–31.53 million) had developed long COVID by November 2022. An estimated 14.3% of US adults aged 18+ years (35.03 million; 95% CI = 34.23–35.83 million) and 14.8% of working-aged adults aged 18–64 years (29.93 million; 95% CI = 29.20–30.66 million) had a history of long COVID by November 2023. The estimated percentages of those with long COVID still experiencing symptoms and reporting a modest to considerable impact on daily functioning were 55.3% and 24.6%, respectively. Assuming the same percentages in those no longer experiencing symptoms, this translates into an estimated 28 million adults aged 18+ years and 24 million working-aged adults with long COVID who had been or may still be at risk of adverse outcomes. Given that cases of COVID from new infections and re-infections continue to accrue, these numbers of susceptible individuals will only escalate over time.</p><p id="Par27">An estimated 14.5 million adults aged 18+ years and 10.9 million adults aged 18–64 years with long COVID still had current symptoms in the fall of 2022 and fall of 2023, respectively. Assuming a 76.15% labor force participation rate, while accounting for 435,473 adults in 2022 and 246,970 adults in 2023 that reported not working recently because of long COVID, an estimated 10.6 million adults and 8.1 million adults were working with long COVID in late 2022 and late 2023, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The total full-time equivalents (FTEs) of lost work either due to not working at all or 25.9% (CI: 18.1–35.6%) reduced working hours because of long COVID amounted to 3.2 million (CI: 2.4 million—4.2 million) FTE and 2.3 million (CI: 1.7 million—3.1 million), respectively. Using the reported household income of respondents in 2021, this translated into an estimated $211 billion (CI: $156 billion—$279 billion) and $218 billion (CI: $159 billion—$292 billion) annually in lost earnings due to long COVID for American adults aged 18–64 years in the fall of 2022 and 2023, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>)—considerably higher than a previous $168 billion estimate for adults aged 16–64 years<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par28">To the author’s knowledge, this study represents one of the largest multivariable analyses to date using U.S. nationally-representative data to explore key sociodemographic and socioeconomic predictors and mental health and economic sequelae and to estimate the economic burden of lost wages from long COVID as well as to examine trends in these estimates over time. The large sample size enabled a comprehensive examination of potential risk factors including marital status and gender and the discovery of novel associations such as for sexual orientation. Several characteristics predicted greater long COVID risks including being aged 30–49 years, of lower education and household income, living in a larger household, and being Hispanic, female, gay/lesbian or bisexual, and divorced/separated. Receipt of a COVID-19 vaccine (with or without a booster) was linked to lower risks of infection. Overall, similar patterns for predictive relationships were observed in the age- and gender-adjusted models and fully-adjusted models, and similar associations with long COVID were identified in fully-adjusted models in 2022 vs. 2023, supporting the generalisability of the findings over time.</p><p id="Par29">Other epidemiologic studies of risk factors for long COVID have observed associations that are generally consistent with these findings. For example, adults aged 65+ years (vs. those aged 25–34 years) were similarly characterized by lower risk of long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Four studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> likewise found that females were at higher risk of long COVID than males, and two studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> identified similar patterns of inverse associations between socioeconomic position (measured by either income or educational attainment) and long COVID. Consistent with the present study, three studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> found that Black and Asian non-Hispanic (vs. White non-Hispanic) Americans were at lower risks of long COVID, and three studies linked Hispanic ethnicity to a higher risk of long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, while another study observed that Hispanic Americans had lower risks of long COVID than White non-Hispanic Americans but was based on age- and sex-adjusted models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Like in the current study, having health insurance was linked to a higher risk of long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, whereas being unvaccinated was associated with higher risks of long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Notably, while two other large studies on long COVID also employed data from the Household Pulse Survey<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, those analyses relied on a more limited list of predictor variables that were co-adjusted and did not control for several key factors including household income<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> or both education and income<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par30">The lack of an apparent association between COVID-19 vaccination and long COVID from the fully-adjusted multivariable model in the present study seems inconsistent with the study’s finding of an inverse association between vaccination and confirmed/diagnosed COVID-19 infection. Nonetheless, it is possible that selection bias may have contributed to the former findings—for example, if those who received the COVID-19 vaccine were more likely to have uncontrolled characteristics (e.g., COVID-19 re-infections) that put them at higher risk of long COVID. Meanwhile, in the age- and gender-adjusted model, having received a full primary series and booster for the COVID-19 vaccine predicted a lower risk of long COVID. It is possible that the fully-adjusted model had associated bias towards the null due to its control for factors along the causal pathway between COVID-19 vaccination and long COVID and/or due to the introduction of collider bias.</p><p id="Par31">Future studies to further explore these findings and delineate any underlying bias are warranted. The higher associations of long COVID among those with health insurance (vs. no insurance) might also be explained by selection based on a higher likelihood of insured individuals being confirmed with COVID-19 through a test at point-of-care and diagnosed by a health care provider.</p><p id="Par32">Potential mechanisms to explain why females may be at higher risk of long COVID than males have been proposed. These mechanisms include biological differences (e.g., lower production of pro-inflammatory interleukin-6 after viral infection) and higher levels of psychological stress in females brought on by the COVID-19 pandemic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, with recent evidence that psychological distress is linked to post-COVID conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Likewise, higher stress levels experienced by those who are divorced/separated (vs. married)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> or transgender (vs. male)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> might help to account for their associated higher risks of long COVID.</p><p id="Par33">Furthermore, treatment with nirmatrelvir-ritonavir (Paxlovid) has been linked to large reductions in risks of long COVID such as neuro-cognitive and psychiatric complications of COVID-19<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. If those of lower socioeconomic position, who are of Hispanic ethnicity, transgender, or of gay/lesbian or bisexual orientation are less likely to seek and receive such treatment, this could explain the linkages between these characteristics and higher risks of long COVID.</p><p id="Par34">Even after accounting for sociodemographic and socioeconomic factors, the current study found that having long COVID predicted higher risks of recent unemployment, financial hardship, and anxiety and depressive symptomatology using 2-item validated scales. For all of these outcomes, there were stronger relationships at higher levels of impacts of symptoms on daily functioning, compatible with causal relationships. Previous U.S. population-based studies have likewise found long COVID to predict a lower odds of employment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> and higher risk of anxiety<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par35">Limitations of this study include its cross-sectional design, which precludes the ability to draw causal inferences due to bias from reverse causation or residual confounding by factors such as comorbid conditions and reinfections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Due to this inability to draw causal inferences, the models would more aptly be described as prediction models, although the majority of the predictor variables are relatively time-invariant in nature (e.g., educational attainment) and hence are unlikely to have led to confounding that would require temporal considerations. While adjustment was made for receipt of a vaccine booster due to a COVID-19 infection, confounding by indication could explain the null and positive associations between vaccination and long COVID. The measure of being vaccinated and boosted in late 2023 was also limited by the survey item asked then, such that differential misclassification is possible and could explain in part the positive associations with long COVID among those vaccinated (vs. unvaccinated). Although sampling weights accounted for non-response and there is evidence that weighting adjustments mitigated non-response bias<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, such bias could have led to bias towards or away from the null. Because some weighted sample characteristics (e.g., old age, high educational attainment) that differed from the U.S. general population were found to predict lower risks of long COVID, prevalence estimates may be more conservative and represent underestimates. Finally, the estimated costs associated with lost work from long COVID underestimates the total economic burden of long COVID because it does not account for reductions in quality of life or health care costs associated with long COVID and its physical and mental health sequelae, which could be in excess of $500 billion annually<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par36">The findings from this study highlight the anticipated substantial health and economic burden of long COVID among American adults. Notably, while the estimated total number of working-aged adults reporting currently having long COVID symptoms was sizably lower in the fall of 2023 than in the fall of 2022, the estimated economic burdens were comparable. This may be attributed to the fact that long COVID appeared to increasingly affect higher income groups by the fall of 2023. Should these estimates be confirmed in longitudinal studies, future efforts should focus on identifying biological and social explanations and mediating pathways, and on targeting risk stratification and risk reduction in those at higher risk of long COVID. The scale of long COVID and its sequelae necessitates large-scale governmental funding to address long COVID research priorities and a robust and coordinated policy response strategy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, as well as ongoing national surveillance of the prevalence and health and economic burden of long COVID, despite the emergency phase of the COVID-19 pandemic being declared over. Candidate public health interventions to mitigate adverse sequelae of long COVID could include enhanced uptake by higher-risk groups of COVID-19 vaccines and non-pharmaceutical interventions including mask-wearing and improved ventilation to reduce the risk of acute infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, and expanded access to paid sick leave and disability insurance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="43856_2025_759_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Reporting Summary</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s43856-025-00759-0.</p></sec><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>D.K. was responsible for conceptualization, methodology, formal analysis, data curation, acquisition of resources, project administration, and writing (original draft preparation, review, and editing).</p></notes><notes notes-type="peer-review"><title>Peer review</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Peer review information</title><p id="Par37"><italic toggle="yes">Communications Medicine</italic> thanks Denis Nash and the other, anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work.</p></sec></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data used are available in a public, open access repository through the United States Census Bureau (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/household-pulse-survey/data.html">https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/household-pulse-survey/data.html</ext-link>).</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par38">The author declares no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mathieu, E. et al. Coronavirus pandemic (COVID-19). (2024). Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus">https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Soriano, J. B., Murthy, S., Marshall, J. C., Relan, P. &amp; Diaz, J. V. Group WC. A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet Infecti. Dis.</italic><bold>22</bold>, e102–e107 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lau, B. et al. Physical and mental health disability associated with long-COVID: Baseline results from a US nationwide cohort. medRxiv. (2022). Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.12.07.22283203v1">https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.12.07.22283203v1</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjmed.2023.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10924070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37690503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bautista-Rodriguez, E. et al. Stress, anxiety, depression and long COVID symptoms. <italic toggle="yes">Fatigue</italic><bold>11</bold>, 35–54 (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ailshire</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crimmins</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID and symptom trajectory in a representative sample of Americans in the first year of the pandemic</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35804058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-15727-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9264749</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Wu, Q., Ailshire, J. A. &amp; Crimmins, E. M. Long COVID and symptom trajectory in a representative sample of Americans in the first year of the pandemic. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1–1 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35804058</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-15727-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9264749</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Robertson, M. M. et al. The epidemiology of long COVID in US adults. <italic toggle="yes">Clin. Infect. Dis</italic>. <bold>76</bold>, 1636–1645 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cid/ciac961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36542514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perlis</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and correlates of long COVID symptoms among US adults</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open.</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e2238804</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.38804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36301542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9614581</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Perlis, R. H. et al. Prevalence and correlates of long COVID symptoms among US adults. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw. Open.</italic><bold>5</bold>, e2238804 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36301542</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.38804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9614581</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Durstenfeld</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with long COVID symptoms in an online cohort study</article-title><source>Open Forum Infect. Dis.</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>ofad047</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofad047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36846611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9945931</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Durstenfeld, M. S. et al. Factors associated with long COVID symptoms in an online cohort study. <italic toggle="yes">Open Forum Infect. Dis.</italic><bold>10</bold>, ofad047 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36846611</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ofid/ofad047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9945931</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchflower</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID in the United States</article-title><source>PLOS One.</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>e0292672</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0292672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37917610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10621843</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Blanchflower, D. G. &amp; Bryson, A. Long COVID in the United States. <italic toggle="yes">PLOS One.</italic><bold>18</bold>, e0292672 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37917610</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0292672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10621843</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Racial, ethnic, and sex disparities in the incidence and cognitive symptomology of long COVID-19</article-title><source>J. Natl Med Assoc.</source><year>2023</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36792456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jnma.2023.01.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9923441</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Jacobs, M. M., Evans, E. &amp; Ellis, C. Racial, ethnic, and sex disparities in the incidence and cognitive symptomology of long COVID-19. <italic toggle="yes">J. Natl Med Assoc.</italic><bold>115</bold>, 233–243 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36792456</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jnma.2023.01.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9923441</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudenstine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-COVID and comorbid depression and anxiety two years into the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res.</source><year>2022</year><volume>317</volume><fpage>114924</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2022.114924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37732865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9597528</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Rudenstine, S. et al. Long-COVID and comorbid depression and anxiety two years into the COVID-19 pandemic. <italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res.</italic><bold>317</bold>, 114924 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37732865</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.psychres.2022.114924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9597528</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. Census Bureau. Household Pulse Survey: Measuring social and economic impacts during the coronavirus pandemic. (2024). Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/household-pulse-survey.html">https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/household-pulse-survey.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. Census Bureau. Household Pulse Survey technical documentation. (2024). Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/household-pulse-survey/technical-documentation.html">https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/household-pulse-survey/technical-documentation.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Psychometric properties and clinical utility of brief measures of depression, anxiety, and general distress: The PHQ-2, GAD-2, and K-6</article-title><source>Gen. Hospital Psychiatry</source><year>2019</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2018.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30508772</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Staples, L. G. et al. Psychometric properties and clinical utility of brief measures of depression, anxiety, and general distress: The PHQ-2, GAD-2, and K-6. <italic toggle="yes">Gen. Hospital Psychiatry</italic><bold>56</bold>, 13–18 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2018.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30508772</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blizzard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stankovich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosmer</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Be wary of using Poisson regression to estimate risk and relative risk</article-title><source>Biostatistics Biometrics Open Access J.</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Zhu, C., Blizzard, L., Stankovich, J., Wills, K. &amp; Hosmer, D. W. Be wary of using Poisson regression to estimate risk and relative risk. <italic toggle="yes">Biostatistics Biometrics Open Access J.</italic><bold>4</bold>, 1–3 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imputation of categorical variables with PROC MI</article-title><source>SUGI 30 Proc.</source><year>2005</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Allison, P. D. Imputation of categorical variables with PROC MI. <italic toggle="yes">SUGI 30 Proc.</italic><bold>113</bold>, 1–4 (2005).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bach, K. New data shows long COVID is keeping as many as 4 million people out of work. August 24, 2022. Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.brookings.edu/research/new-data-shows-long-COVID-is-keeping-as-many-as-4-million-people-out-of-work/">https://www.brookings.edu/research/new-data-shows-long-COVID-is-keeping-as-many-as-4-million-people-out-of-work/</ext-link> (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics. Labor force and employment status of the civilian population 16 years and over by sex and age: 2021. (2021). Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www2.census.gov/programs-surveys/demo/tables/age-and-sex/2021/age-sex-composition/2021agesex_table7.xlsx">https://www2.census.gov/programs-surveys/demo/tables/age-and-sex/2021/age-sex-composition/2021agesex_table7.xlsx</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ham, D. I. Long-haulers and labor market outcomes. Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis; 2022 Jul 7. Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.minneapolisfed.org/institute/working-papers-institute/iwp60.pdf">https://www.minneapolisfed.org/institute/working-papers-institute/iwp60.pdf</ext-link> (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-de-Las-Peñas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Female sex is a risk factor associated with long-term post-COVID related-symptoms but not with COVID-19 symptoms: the LONG-COVID-EXP-CM multicenter study</article-title><source>J. Clin. Med.</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>413</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm11020413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35683388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9181377</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Fernández-de-Las-Peñas, C. et al. Female sex is a risk factor associated with long-term post-COVID related-symptoms but not with COVID-19 symptoms: the LONG-COVID-EXP-CM multicenter study. <italic toggle="yes">J. Clin. Med.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 413 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35054108</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm11020413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8778106</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations of depression, anxiety, worry, perceived stress, and loneliness prior to infection with risk of post–COVID-19 conditions</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><year>2022</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2022.2640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36069885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9453634</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Wang, S. et al. Associations of depression, anxiety, worry, perceived stress, and loneliness prior to infection with risk of post–COVID-19 conditions. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Psychiatry</italic><bold>79</bold>, 1081–1091 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36069885</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2022.2640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9453634</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sareen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhyani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychological aspects of widowhood and divorce</article-title><source>Mens. Sana Monogr.</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0973-1229.40648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21836778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3151454</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Trivedi, J. K., Sareen, H. &amp; Dhyani, M. Psychological aspects of widowhood and divorce. <italic toggle="yes">Mens. Sana Monogr.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 37 (2009).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21836778</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/0973-1229.40648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3151454</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smalley</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barefoot</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychological well-being among transgender and genderqueer individuals</article-title><source>Int. J. Transgenderism.</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15532739.2016.1216344</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Warren, J. C., Smalley, K. B. &amp; Barefoot, K. N. Psychological well-being among transgender and genderqueer individuals. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Transgenderism.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 114–123 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of nirmatrelvir-ritonavir on the long-term risk of neuropsychiatric sequelae following COVID-19</article-title><source>J. Med. Virol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>e28951</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.28951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37436873</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Liu, T. H., Wu, J. Y., Huang, P. Y., Tsai, Y. W. &amp; Lai, C. C. The effect of nirmatrelvir-ritonavir on the long-term risk of neuropsychiatric sequelae following COVID-19. <italic toggle="yes">J. Med. Virol.</italic><bold>95</bold>, e28951 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37436873</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jmv.28951</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and postacute sequelae associated with SARS-CoV-2 reinfection</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2398</fpage><lpage>2405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02051-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9671810</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Bowe, B., Xie, Y. &amp; Al-Aly, Z. Acute and postacute sequelae associated with SARS-CoV-2 reinfection. <italic toggle="yes">Nat. Med.</italic><bold>28</bold>, 2398–2405 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357676</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-022-02051-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9671810</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Peterson, S., Toribio, N., Farber, J. &amp; Hornick, D. Non-response bias report for the 2020 Household Pulse Survey, Version 1.0. U.S. Census Bureau. (2020). Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www2.census.gov/programs-surveys/demo/technical-documentation/hhp/2020_HPS_NR_Bias_Report-final.pdf">https://www2.census.gov/programs-surveys/demo/technical-documentation/hhp/2020_HPS_NR_Bias_Report-final.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cutler, D. The Economic Cost of Long COVID: An Update. (2022). Accessed at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/files/cutler/files/long_covid_update_7-22.pdf">https://scholar.harvard.edu/files/cutler/files/long_covid_update_7-22.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long COVID science, research and policy</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><year>2024</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2148</fpage><lpage>2164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-024-03173-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39122965</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Al-Aly, Z. et al. Long COVID science, research and policy. <italic toggle="yes">Nat. Med.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 2148–2164 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39122965</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-024-03173-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tildesley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccination and non-pharmaceutical interventions for COVID-19: a mathematical modelling study</article-title><source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00143-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33743847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7972312</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Moore, S., Hill, E. M., Tildesley, M. J., Dyson, L. &amp; Keeling, M. J. Vaccination and non-pharmaceutical interventions for COVID-19: a mathematical modelling study. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet Infect. Dis.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 793–802 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33743847</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00143-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7972312</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morawska</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>How can airborne transmission of COVID-19 indoors be minimised?</article-title><source>Environ. Int.</source><year>2020</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>105832</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32521345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7250761</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Morawska, L. et al. How can airborne transmission of COVID-19 indoors be minimised? <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Int.</italic><bold>142</bold>, 105832 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32521345</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7250761</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Flood, S. et al. <italic toggle="yes">Integrated Public Use Microdata Series, Current Population Survey: Version 10.0</italic>. Minneapolis, MN (IPUMS, 2022).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>