<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12618668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12618668.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12618668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12618668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41238605</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-22050-x</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">22050</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dual use of combustible and heated tobacco products associates persistent symptoms with a history of COVID-19: a JASTIS 2023 cross‑sectional study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toyokura</surname><given-names initials="E">Erika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names initials="K">Kazuhiro</given-names></name><address><email>k.yamada@omu.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asai</surname><given-names initials="K">Kazuhisa</given-names></name><address><email>kazuasai@omu.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names initials="M">Masaya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names initials="T">Takahiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names initials="K">Kaho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuichiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names initials="A">Atsushi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names initials="M">Misako</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names initials="K">Kanako</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names initials="T">Tetsuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names initials="T">Takahiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names initials="T">Tomoya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.518217.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0005 0893 4200</institution-id><institution>Osaka City University, </institution></institution-wrap>Osaka, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01hvx5h04</institution-id><institution>Osaka Metropolitan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Osaka, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00v053551</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.416948.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1764 9308</institution-id><institution>Osaka City General Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Osaka, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01dq60k83</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.69566.3a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2248 6943</institution-id><institution>Tohoku University Graduate School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Sendai, Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478255</issue-id><elocation-id>38659</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-16 00:25:13.030"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2025_Article_22050.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Multiple reports have identified smoking as a risk factor for long COVID; however, few have distinguished among tobacco product types. We conducted a cross-sectional study using data from an internet-based survey administered in February 2023 to examine the association between 12 persistent symptoms and smoking status in participants with a history of COVID-19. A total of 28,250 participants were included, of whom 5,068 had a history of COVID-19. Among current tobacco users with a history of COVID-19, the odds ratios for persistent symptoms were significantly elevated for four symptoms—arthralgia, chest pain, dyspnea, and dysosmia—compared to never smokers. For subgroup analysis, current tobacco users were categorized into three groups: combustible cigarette (CC), heated tobacco product (HTP), and dual users. Among dual users, the odds ratios were significantly elevated for five symptoms: arthralgia, chest pain, dyspnea, dysgeusia, and dysosmia. CC users showed significantly higher odds for chest pain, dyspnea, and fatigue, while HTP users for dyspnea and sexual dysfunction. Smoking in individuals with a history of COVID-19 associates the prevalence of persistent symptoms, and its impact may vary by smoking type. Separately analyzing smoking subgroups allows for a more accurate understanding of the relationship between persistent symptoms and smoking behavior.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-22050-x.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Epidemiology</kwd><kwd>Viral infection</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>JP23K07631</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Tetsuya</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par9">Since the onset of COVID-19, individuals adopted preventive measures to avoid infection, and the government launched a vaccination campaign to limit case numbers in Japan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. However, following the pandemic, personal behaviors shifted, and infections became more common, resulting in a rise in cases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. This increase has introduced new challenges: the long-term effects of SARS-CoV-2 infection, known as long COVID. Long COVID, also referred to by the WHO as “post-COVID-19 condition,” is defined as symptoms usually beginning within 3 months of SARS-CoV-2 infection and lasting for at least 2 months<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. More recently, U.S. guidance has characterized it as a chronic condition persisting for ≥ 3 months as a continuous, relapsing-remitting, or progressive disease affecting one or more organ systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Reported symptoms include fatigue, dyspnea, cough, chest pain, palpitations, fever, memory impairment, difficulty concentrating, dysgeusia, anosmia, hair loss, and arthralgia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. These prolonged symptoms have significantly affected the quality of life (QOL) of individuals recovering from COVID-19, often continuing for extended periods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Survey data suggest that over 60 million globally including Japan have experienced long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, and investigations into associated risk factors have continued since the start of the pandemic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par10">Combustible cigarette (CC) use is a well-established risk factor for numerous respiratory and cardiovascular diseases and exerts complex effects on the central nervous system. In COVID-19 research, CC use has been identified as a potential risk factor, with studies indicating that smokers may be more likely to develop long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Recently, alternative tobacco products such as heated tobacco products (HTPs) and electronic cigarettes have gained popularity worldwide. In Japan, HTP use has rapidly expanded, accounting for approximately one-third of the tobacco prevalence data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Given the high prevalence of HTP use, it is essential to investigate the relationship between COVID-19 and tobacco exposure, including both CCs and HTPs, particularly in countries like Japan. However, few comprehensive studies have examined both products.</p><p id="Par11">HTPs heat tobacco without combustion, generating an aerosol that generally contains lower levels of harmful substances compared with the smoke produced by CCs. While many levels are lower than in cigarettes, some are comparable or higher and some are unique to HTPs. Thus, reduced toxicant levels do not necessarily translate into reduced health risk, long-term effects remain uncertain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Considering these differing exposure profiles, associations between long COVID, CC users, HTP users, and dual users may differ. Our previous study found that HTP and dual use were associated with a higher likelihood of SARS-CoV-2 infection compared with never use, whereas no significant association was identified for CC use alone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. This finding suggests that tobacco-related analyses should distinguish between product types. To date, evidence regarding their respective impacts on long COVID remains limited. In this study, we examined the association between persistent symptoms with a history of COVID-19 and smoking status in Japan’s general population, grouping all CC, HTP, and dual users together. We also explored how this association varies among CC, HTP, and dual users.</p><sec id="Sec50"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec51"><title>Study design and participants</title><p id="Par14">We conducted a cross-sectional study using data from the Japan “Society and New Tobacco” Internet Survey (JASTIS), an internet-based, self-reported survey. JASTIS aimed to assess the impact of new tobacco products in Japan [Study profile is shown in a previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Participants were recruited from a large survey panel managed by a major nationwide internet research agency, Rakuten Insight, which maintains a pool of 2.3 million panelists covering all census-defined social categories, such as education, housing tenure, and marital status in Japan. This study used data from the JASTIS 2023 study (conducted in February 2023). A follow-up survey (February 6–27, 2023), for all 44,681 participants of the 2015–2023 survey who could be contacted, and 28,437 responses were received (response rate, 63.6%). An additional 5,563 participants completed a new survey (February 25–27, 2023) using the same questionnaire. These were combined with the follow-up responses for a total of 34,000 participants in the JASTIS 2023 dataset. For this analysis, 2,963 participants were excluded due to inconsistent responses. Of the remaining 31,037 participants, 1,635 and 1,047 participants with a history of COVID-19 within the past 2 months and &gt; 1 year prior to the survey date, respectively, were excluded. We also excluded 105 participants who gave contradictory responses regarding their smoking status. The final analysis included 28,250 participants. This study was conducted in accordance with the Ethical Guidelines for Life Science and Medical Research Involving Human Subjects. All study protocols were reviewed and approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the Osaka International Cancer Institute (No. 20084-8). Informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec52"><title>Definition of variables</title><sec id="Sec53"><title>Tabacco use</title><p id="Par17">Smoking status was determined based on participants’ responses to questions regarding the use of various tobacco products. CCs included both factory-made cigarettes and roll-your-own tobacco. HTPs comprised IQOS, Ploom Tech, Ploom S, Ploom X, glo, and lil HYBRID—brands available in Japan as of February 2023. Participants were classified into three categories according to their smoking status over the past year: current users, defined as individuals who used tobacco within the past year; former users, who had ceased tobacco use for one year or more; and never users, who had never used any tobacco products. Current users were further subdivided into three groups: dual users (those using both CCs and HTPs), CC users (exclusive users of combustible cigarettes), and HTP users (exclusive users of heated tobacco products).</p></sec><sec id="Sec530"><title>COVID-19 history</title><p id="Par19">COVID-19 history was categorized based on the time of infection relative to the survey date: within 2 months, 2–6 months, 6 months to 1 year, and &gt; 1 year prior. Participants with infections within the previous 2 months were excluded because such cases may not adequately reflect long COVID. Similarly, those with infections &gt; 1 year prior were excluded, as post-infection smoking cessation could alter smoking status, potentially leading to misclassification. To assess the association between smoking status and persistent symptoms with a history of COVID-19 accurately, the main analysis focused on participants with COVID-19 infections occurring 2–6 months or 6 months to 1 year before the survey.</p></sec><sec id="Sec54"><title>Persistent symptoms</title><p id="Par21">Based on prior research related to long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, 12 symptoms were selected for analysis: arthralgia, headache, chest pain, dyspnea, fatigue, dysgeusia, dysosmia, memory impairment, loss of concentration, hair loss, sexual dysfunction, and cough. The questionnaire used in this study was not specifically designed to evaluate long COVID19, it asked whether participants experienced symptoms lasting more than two months, regardless of their COVID-19 history. To evaluate the association between persistent symptoms and COVID-19, the interaction between COVID-19 history and smoking status was evaluated for each persistent symptom.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par22">We conducted multivariate logistic regression analysis to examine the association between symptoms persisting for &gt; 2 months (outcome variable) and explanatory variables including COVID-19 history and smoking status. The models included an interaction term between COVID-19 history and smoking status, along with covariates such as age, sex, BMI, vaccine status (≥ 2 doses vs. &lt;2 doses), and number of comorbidities (none, one, or ≥ 2). Comorbidities included 20 conditions: diabetes, dyslipidemia, pneumonia, asthma, atopic dermatitis, allergic rhinitis, periodontal disease, dental caries, angina pectoris, stroke, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic kidney disease, chronic liver disease, immunodeficiency, malignant tumors, chronic pain syndrome, depression, alcoholism, and other mental disorders. Details of comorbidities are shown in the Supplementary Material, Table S1. Adjusted odds ratios (aORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated, with p-values &lt; 0.05 considered statistically significant. To assess the interaction between smoking and COVID-19 history, an interaction term was incorporated into the model. Variance inflation factors (VIFs) were calculated for each covariate to evaluate multicollinearity; VIF &lt; 5 was considered to indicate non-linearity. Population bias from the internet-based design was addressed using inverse probability weighting (IPW)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, based on a nationally representative sample from the Comprehensive Survey of Living Conditions of People on Health and Welfare (CSLCPHW)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. JASTIS and CSLCPHW data were combined, and logistic regression adjusted for background factors (residence, education, housing tenure, and health status) was used to estimate the probability of “being a respondent in an internet survey,” i.e., propensity score. Details on IPW have been reported previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Participant numbers in the text and tables reflect weighted values; unweighted numbers are shown in Supplementary Tables. All statistical analyses were conducted using EZR Version 1.54 (Jichi Medical University, Saitama, Japan), a graphical interface for R (The R Foundation for Statistical Computing)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec60"><title>Participant characteristics</title><p id="Par24">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents the weighted characteristics of all participants. Unweighted characteristics are shown in the Supplementary Material, Table S2. A total of 28,250 participants were included in the study, of whom 5,068 (17.9%) had a history of COVID-19. Participants with a history of COVID-19 tended to be younger, with a median age of 38 years. The prevalence of current users was 27.5% among those with a history of COVID-19 and 22.5% among those without a history of COVID-19. The prevalence of CC use was 9.6% among those infected and 11.7% among those not infected; for HTP use, 4.4% and 3.4%, respectively; and for dual use, 13.5% and 7.3%, respectively. Participants with a history of COVID-19 were more likely to use dual tobacco products. The proportion of former users was lower among those infected (14.6%) than among those not infected (18.8%). Never users accounted for 57.9% of those infected and 58.7% of those not infected.</p><p id="Par25">Participants who had received the SARS-CoV-2 vaccine no or one time accounted for 11.4% of those infected and 12.0% of not infected. Participants who had received the vaccine two times or more accounted for 86.0% of those infected and 87.5% of those not infected. Among all participants, 24.7% had one comorbidity and 35.7% had two or more, with no significant differences based on COVID-19 history. The median BMI was 21.8 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, with no significant differences based on COVID-19 history. No significant differences were found in educational background, although infected participants tended to report higher incomes.</p><p id="Par26">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of participants (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 28,250) (weighted).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Previous history of COVID-19</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28,250</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,182</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5068</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, median (IQR) years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 [34, 63]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 [35, 66]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 [28, 48]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Sex, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,988 (49.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,354 (49.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2634 (52.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,262 (50.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,828 (51.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2434 (48.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Smoking status, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Current user</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6604 (23.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5208 (22.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1396 (27.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Only CCs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3207 (11.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2720 (11.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">487 (9.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Only HTPs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1009 (3.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">786 (3.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (4.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dual tobacco products</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2388 (8.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1702 (7.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">686 (13.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Former user</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5102 (18.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4364 (18.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">738 (14.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Never user</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,544 (58.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,610 (58.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2934 (57.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">SARS-CoV-2 vaccination status, n(%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No or one time</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3367 (11.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2789 (12.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">578 (11.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Two times or more</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24,642 (87.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,286 (87.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4356 (86.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Comorbidities*, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> One comorbidity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6977 (24.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5744 (24.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1234 (24.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Two or more</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,088 (35.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8443 (36.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1646 (32.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> BMI, median (IQR) kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.80 [19.72, 24.22]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.80 [19.74, 24.22]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.72 [19.72, 24.12]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Education, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Junior high school/high school</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,358 (54.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,785 (55.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2573 (50.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> University/technical school or more</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,891 (45.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,397 (44.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2495 (49.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Income over 4 million yen, n (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,803 (45.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9826 (42.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2977 (58.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Symptom lasting more than two months</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Arthralgia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4979 (17.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4239 (18.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">740 (14.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Headache</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3066 (10.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2425 (10.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">641 (12.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Chest pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">733 (2.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">535 (2.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">198 (3.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Cough</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1182 (4.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">956 (4.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">226 (4.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dyspnea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1664 (5.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1349 (5.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">315 (6.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dysgeusia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">268 (0.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (1.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dysosmia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">313 (1.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">229 (1.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Memory impairment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1421 (5.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1153 (5.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">268 (5.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Loss of concentration</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2640 (9.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2165 (9.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">475 (9.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hair loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1586 (5.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1303 (5.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">283 (5.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Sexual dysfunction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1642 (5.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1416 (6.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">226 (4.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Fatigue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2665 (9.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2196 (9.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">469 (9.2)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Comorbidities include the following 20 diseases: diabetes, dyslipidemia, pneumonia, asthma, atopic dermatitis, allergic rhinitis, periodontal disease, dental caries, angina pectoris, stroke, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic kidney disease, chronic liver disease, immunodeficiency, malignant tumors, chronic pain syndrome, depression, alcoholism, and other mental disorders.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec65"><title>Association between each persistent symptom and smoking</title><p id="Par29">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the results of the analysis examining the associations of COVID-19 history, overall smoking status (combining dual, CC, and HTP users), and their interaction with each persistent symptom. In this analysis, never users and those without a history of COVID-19 were used as the reference group. The interaction term between COVID-19 history and smoking status (current or former users) highlights the influence of smoking on persistent symptoms. Among current users with a history of COVID-19, aORs significantly increased for arthralgia, chest pain, dyspnea, and dysosmia. In contrast, aORs for dysgeusia, memory impairment, and loss of concentration did not show significant increases. Among former users with a history of COVID-19, aOR significantly increased for arthralgia and headache, but decreased for dyspnea and dysosmia. These results suggest stronger associations between persistent symptoms and both current and former users with a history of COVID-19, compared to never users with a history of COVID-19. In Japan, the use of HTPs has rapidly increased since their introduction as products marketed to contain fewer harmful components than CCs. HTP or dual use, as opposed to exclusive CC use, may be associated with different long COVID risks. Therefore, we further analyzed the associations between persistent symptoms and each tobacco use category—dual, CC, and HTP users.</p><p id="Par30">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Association between smoking status and history of COVID-19 in each symptom persistent for more than two months.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Symptom</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-<break/>COVID-19<break/>history</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">COVID-19<break/>history</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never user</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current user</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former user</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current user ×<break/>COVID-19<break/>history<break/>(Interaction)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former user ×<break/>COVID-19 history<break/>(Interaction)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(reference)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(reference)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arthralgia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.97</p><p>(0.85–1.11)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.27 **</p><p>(1.15–1.39)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.24**</p><p>(1.13–1.37)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.37 **</p><p>(1.12–1.69)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.44**</p><p>(1.14–1.82)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.94</p><p>(0.83–1.07)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.30**</p><p>(1.16–1.46)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.28**</p><p>(1.13–1.45)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.02</p><p>(0.81–1.28)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.58 **</p><p>(1.20–2.07)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chest pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.17</p><p>(0.90–1.53)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.10</p><p>(0.87–1.38)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.39**</p><p>(1.10–1.74)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.34**</p><p>(1.60–3.44)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.39</p><p>(0.87–2.23)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cough</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.59**</p><p>(1.28–1.98)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.45**</p><p>(1.23–1.72)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.16</p><p>(0.97–1.38)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.77</p><p>(0.55–1.09)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.80</p><p>(0.53–1.21)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.23</p><p>(1.00-1.52)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.42**</p><p>(1.22–1.66)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.21**</p><p>(1.92–2.55)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.81**</p><p>(1.35–2.43)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.66*</p><p>(0.46–0.95)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.97</p><p>(0.87–1.08)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.32**</p><p>(1.21–1.44)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.11*</p><p>(1.00-1.22)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.01</p><p>(0.84–1.20)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.43**</p><p>(1.15–1.78)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dysgeusia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.14**</p><p>(1.47–3.11)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.68</p><p>(0.45–1.03)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.82</p><p>(0.55–1.21)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.78</p><p>(0.96–3.30)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.64</p><p>(0.84–3.21)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dysosmia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.86 **</p><p>(1.24–2.80)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.25</p><p>(0.89–1.75)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.28</p><p>(0.92–1.80)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.88*</p><p>(1.08–3.29)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.40*</p><p>(0.16–0.98)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Memory impairment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.31*</p><p>(1.06–1.60)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.30**</p><p>(1.10–1.52)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.54**</p><p>(1.32–1.80)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.10</p><p>(0.80–1.51)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.88</p><p>(0.61–1.27)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Loss of concentration</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.99</p><p>(0.85–1.14)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.18**</p><p>(1.05–1.33)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.45**</p><p>(1.29–1.64)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.92</p><p>(0.72–1.19)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.18</p><p>(0.89–1.56)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hair loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.03</p><p>(0.84–1.25)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.26**</p><p>(1.09–1.46)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.33**</p><p>(1.14–1.54)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.21</p><p>(0.89–1.63)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.02</p><p>(0.71–1.46)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sexual dysfunction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.18</p><p>(0.91–1.52)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.68**</p><p>(1.45–1.95)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.51**</p><p>(1.30–1.76)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.73</p><p>(0.52–1.03)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.67</p><p>(0.46-1.00)</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>†</sup>AOR = adjusted odds ratio. Estimated using multivariable logistic regression modeling with adjustment for the following variables: age, sex, BMI, vaccine status (categorized as two doses or more vs. fewer than two doses), the number of comorbidities (none, one, or two or more), smoking status, COVID-19 history, and interaction term. CI = confidence interval. Values of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec66"><title>Association between each symptom and different tobacco products use</title><p id="Par33">Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents a re-analysis examining the effects of COVID-19 history and smoking status on individual symptoms. Current users were classified into three categories: dual users, CC users, and HTP users. The interaction term between COVID-19 history and smoking status (dual, CC, HTP, or former users) indicates the influence of smoking status on persistent symptoms. Among dual users with a history of COVID-19, aORs for five persistent symptoms—arthralgia, chest pain, dyspnea, dysgeusia, and dysosmia—were significantly elevated, whereas the aOR for one persistent symptom, sexual dysfunction, was significantly decreased. Among CC users with a history of COVID-19, aORs for three persistent symptoms—chest pain, dyspnea, and fatigue—were significantly increased. Among HTP users with a history of COVID-19, aORs for two persistent symptoms—dyspnea and sexual dysfunction—were significantly increased. Overall, dual users with a history of COVID-19 exhibited more persistent symptoms than CC and HTP users with a history of COVID-19. Furthermore, dual users with a history of COVID-19 showed a significant association with the most frequently reported long COVID symptoms: arthralgia, chest pain, dyspnea, dysgeusia, and dysosmia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par34">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Association between smoking status subdivided into combustible tobacco/ HTPs and history of COVID-19 in each symptom persistent for more than two months.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Symptom</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-COVID-19<break/>history　<break/>(reference)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">COVID-19<break/>history</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never user<break/>(reference)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dual user</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CC user</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HTP user</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former user</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dual user ×<break/>COVID-19<break/>history<break/>(Interaction)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CC user ×<break/>COVID-19<break/>history<break/>(Interaction)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HTP user ×<break/>COVID-19<break/>history<break/>(Interaction)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former user ×<break/>COVID-19<break/>history<break/>(Interaction)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(reference)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(reference)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR<sup>†</sup><break/>(95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arthralgia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.97</p><p>(0.85–1.11)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.40**</p><p>(1.21–1.63)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.24**</p><p>(1.11–1.39)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.13</p><p>(0.92–1.38)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.24**</p><p>(1.13–1.37)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.33*</p><p>(1.01–1.75)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.31</p><p>(0.99–1.75)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.45</p><p>(0.94–2.24)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.44**</p><p>(1.14–1.81)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.95</p><p>(0.83–1.08)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.56**</p><p>(1.32–1.84)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.08</p><p>(0.92–1.26)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.48**</p><p>(1.18–1.87)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.27**</p><p>(1.12–1.44)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.83</p><p>(0.62–1.12)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.40</p><p>(1.00-1.96)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.71</p><p>(0.42–1.21)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.58**</p><p>(1.20–2.07)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chest pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.19</p><p>(0.92–1.55)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.33</p><p>(0.95–1.84)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.88</p><p>(0.65–1.21)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.41</p><p>(0.91–2.18)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.38**</p><p>(1.10–1.73)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.53**</p><p>(1.57–4.07)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.84*</p><p>(1.00-3.38)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.43</p><p>(0.65–3.17)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.38</p><p>(0.86–2.22)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cough</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.58**</p><p>(1.27–1.96)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.30</p><p>(0.99–1.70)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.74**</p><p>(1.44–2.10)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.71</p><p>(0.44–1.12)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.17</p><p>(0.98–1.39)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.99</p><p>(0.63–1.57)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.73</p><p>(0.46–1.15)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.46</p><p>(0.14–1.51)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.80</p><p>(0.53–1.21)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.23</p><p>(1.00-1.52)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.45**</p><p>(1.14–1.84)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.62**</p><p>(1.36–1.94)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.65</p><p>(0.42–1.02)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.22**</p><p>(1.93–2.56)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.89**</p><p>(1.29–2.78)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.73**</p><p>(1.18–2.54)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.45*</p><p>(1.19–5.05)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.66*</p><p>(0.46–0.95)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.94</p><p>(0.81–1.09)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.47**</p><p>(1.24–1.75)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.14</p><p>(0.98–1.33)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.30*</p><p>(1.02–1.67)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.23**</p><p>(1.08–1.39)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.77</p><p>(0.55–1.07)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.55*</p><p>(1.10–2.17)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.07</p><p>(0.63–1.80)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.06</p><p>(0.78–1.44)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dysgeusia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.20**</p><p>(1.51–3.20)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.80</p><p>(0.43–1.51)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.54*</p><p>(0.31–0.96)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.04</p><p>(0.48–2.26)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.81</p><p>(0.55–1.21)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.60*</p><p>(1.17–5.74)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.71</p><p>(0.20–2.53)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.22</p><p>(0.02–2.10)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.62</p><p>(0.83–3.17)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dysosmia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.90**</p><p>(1.27–2.87)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.22</p><p>(0.71–2.08)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.27</p><p>(0.85–1.91)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.36</p><p>(0.68–2.74)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.29</p><p>(0.92–1.82)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.19**</p><p>(1.57–6.52)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.97</p><p>(0.41–2.27)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.36</p><p>(0.06–2.15)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.39*</p><p>(0.16–0.97)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">memory impairment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.31*</p><p>(1.07–1.60)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.44**</p><p>(1.13–1.83)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.33**</p><p>(1.10–1.61)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.91</p><p>(0.62–1.35)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.54**</p><p>(1.32–1.80)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.09</p><p>(0.72–1.65)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.01</p><p>(0.64–1.60)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.28</p><p>(0.62–2.67)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.88</p><p>(0.61–1.27)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">loss of concentration</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1(</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.99</p><p>(0.85–1.15)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.37**</p><p>(1.16–1.64)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.11</p><p>(0.95–1.29)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.02</p><p>(0.78–1.33)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.45**</p><p>(1.29–1.64)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.73</p><p>(0.52–1.03)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.09</p><p>(0.76–1.58)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.07</p><p>(0.62–1.87)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.18</p><p>(0.89–1.55)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hair loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.03</p><p>(0.84–1.26)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.52**</p><p>(1.24–1.88)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.20*</p><p>(1.00-1.44)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.99</p><p>(0.71–1.38)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.33**</p><p>(1.14–1.54)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.14</p><p>(0.78–1.66)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.08</p><p>(0.69–1.69)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.37</p><p>(0.71–2.65)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.01</p><p>(0.70–1.46)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sexual dysfunction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.20</p><p>(0.93–1.54)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.36**</p><p>(1.94–2.86)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.48**</p><p>(1.25–1.77)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.14</p><p>(0.83–1.56)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.49</p><p>(1.28–1.74)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.50**</p><p>(0.33–0.76)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.62</p><p>(0.37–1.03)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.91*</p><p>(1.05–3.47)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.67</p><p>(0.45-1.00)</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>†</sup>AOR = adjusted odds ratio. Estimated using multivariable logistic regression modeling with adjustment for the following variables: age, sex, BMI, vaccine status (categorized as two doses or more vs. fewer than two doses), the number of comorbidities (none, one, or two or more), smoking status, COVID-19 history, and interaction term. CI = confidence interval. Values of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par36">Each stratified analysis yielded associations distinct from those in the overall smokers’ analysis. For dysgeusia, no significant association was observed in the interaction between overall smokers and COVID-19 history; however, a significant increase in the aOR was noted among dual users with a history of COVID-19. Regarding sexual dysfunction, interaction effects differed between overall smoking status and COVID-19 history and between individual smoking categories and COVID-19 history. These findings suggest that combining data from dual, CC, and HTP users may obscure specific associations.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par37">The number and type of persistent symptoms with a history of COVID-19 vary by smoking type: dual users, CC users, and HTP users. Dual users with a history of COVID-19 were significantly associated with the most commonly reported long COVID symptoms: arthralgia, chest pain, dyspnea, dysgeusia, and dysosmia. CC users with a history of COVID-19 were associated with chest pain, dyspnea, and fatigue, while HTP users with a history of COVID-19 were associated with dyspnea and sexual dysfunction. Dual users with a history of COVID-19 exhibited a greater number of associations with persistent symptoms compared to CC or HTP users with a history of COVID-19.</p><p id="Par38">A detailed analysis of tobacco product types provides more precise insight than analyses treating smokers as a homogeneous group. Although the association between smoking and long COVID has been examined in previous studies, results have been inconsistent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. These discrepancies may stem from differences in sex, race, study populations (e.g., outpatients vs. hospitalized patients), or—critically—the varying prevalence of smoking types across studies. The rapid rise in HTP and e-cigarette use<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, coupled with differing regulatory environments, may also contribute to inconsistent findings. Our results revealed differing interaction effects for persistent symptoms depending on smoking type, highlighting the importance of collecting detailed smoking-type data. Based on these findings, future studies should assess smoking status by product type.</p><p id="Par39">CCs contain a complex mixture of over 7,000 chemicals, many of which are toxic and carcinogenic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. HTPs are marketed as reducing exposure to harmful substances. Overall, the content of toxic chemicals in HTP aerosol appears to be lower than in CC. However, the concentrations of more than twenty harmful and potentially harmful constituents have been reported to be higher in HTP aerosol than in CC. Further, several toxic compounds not detected in cigarette smoke are also reported in HTP aerosol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. These chemical differences indicate that HTPs and CCs have distinct exposure profiles and could have different effects on health. However, the health implications of these differences remain unclear. In our study, HTP users with a history of COVID-19 reported fewer persistent symptoms than dual users or CC-only users with a history of COVID-19. Dual users with a history of COVID-19 exhibited a greater number of associations with persistent symptoms than exclusive CC or HTP users with a history of COVID-19. In Japan, HTP adoption among dual users is often motivated by health concerns, protecting bystander health, or avoiding issues related to smell<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. If dual use were less harmful than exclusive CC use, one might expect fewer persistent symptoms among dual users. However, our findings showed that dual users with a history of COVID-19 had more significant associations with persistent symptoms, suggesting that dual use may negate any risk reduction expected from HTP use alone.</p><p id="Par40">In general, HTPs have lower levels of many toxicants than CCs. However, emissions from HTPs such as IQOS contain higher levels of several substances compared with combustible cigarettes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. An in vitro study demonstrated that dual exposure significantly increased oxidative stress and disrupted mitochondrial homeostasis compared with exposure to either CCs or HTPs alone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. These findings suggest that concurrent use of CCs and HTPs may exert a synergistic effect, potentially exacerbating persistent symptoms related to COVID-19 infection.</p><p id="Par41">Another possible explanation for the greater number of associations with persistent symptoms among dual users with a history of COVID-19 is that their total tobacco consumption may exceed that of individuals using only CCs or HTPs. Dual users often adopt HTPs to reduce tobacco consumption due to health concerns or other factors, such as issues with the smell of CCs, workplace restrictions, or fewer limitations on home use. In Japan, CC sales have notably declined since the introduction of HTPs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>, whereas HTP sales have markedly increased following their launch<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. This trend raises concerns that dual users may increase their overall tobacco consumption. Two studies reported that initiating HTP use among CC users can lead to increased overall tobacco use<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. In a systematic review of dual users of e-cigarettes and CCs, most continued cigarette use through sustained dual or exclusive CC use<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. However, the increase in total consumption was modest, with an average rise of fewer than five units per day. Therefore, an increase in total consumption alone may not be sufficient to explain the greater number of associations with persistent symptoms among dual users with a history of COVID-19.</p><p id="Par42">Beyond potential synergistic biological effects and increased total consumption, other unmeasured demographic factors that we could not incorporate into our analysis may also explain why dual users with a history of COVID-19 exhibited the greater number of associations with persistent symptoms. Further research is needed to clarify the health effects of dual use.</p><p id="Par43">Former users with a history of COVID-19 demonstrated a different pattern of symptom associations. Specifically, they had a higher likelihood of experiencing headache and joint pain. However, unlike dual users, CC, and HTP, former users with a history of COVID-19 did not show increased rates of symptoms commonly reported in long COVID, such as chest pain, dysgeusia, or dysosmia. Additionally, former users with a history of COVID-19 exhibited a lower likelihood of dyspnea and dysosmia. Taken together, these results suggest that smoking cessation is associated with a lower risk of characteristic long COVID symptoms including dysgeusia, dysosmia, and chest pain. Headache and joint pain—commonly reported as nicotine withdrawal symptoms—may reflect increased pain sensitivity following smoking cessation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. Smoking cessation can be accompanied by symptoms such as headache and arthralgia. However, our findings and previous reports showing smoking as a risk factor of long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>, suggest smoking cessation could confer overall protective effects against long COVID. We recommend smoking cessation to reduce the risk of long COVID.</p><p id="Par44">This study has several limitations. First, this is a cross-sectional study, and the questionnaires were not specifically developed to identify long COVID. The analysis of interaction effects between smoking status and COVID-19 infection suggests, but does not establish, the associations between persistent symptoms and COVID-19 infection.</p><p id="Par45">Second, because the quantity and duration of tobacco use were not assessed, dual users in our study may have ranged from predominantly CC use to predominantly HTP use, and some may have been heavy smokers. These heterogeneity may bias results. Future studies should collect detailed data on the consumption of each tobacco product.</p><p id="Par46">Third, because this was a questionnaire-based survey, both COVID-19 history and the presence of persistent symptoms were self-reported, which may have introduced recall and misclassification bias.</p><p id="Par47">Fourth, we conducted a survey for persistent symptoms lasting &gt; 2 months. Several reports studied persistent symptoms lasting &gt; 2 months as long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, following the initial WHO definition of long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. However, long COVID is now characterized as a chronic condition that emerges after SARS-CoV-2 infection and persists for at least three months<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. This change in definition could influence our results.</p><p id="Par48">Prospective studies are needed to assess the joint effects of smoking status and COVID-19 infection on long COVID under the updated definition and with detailed information on tobacco product consumption.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par49">Smoking in individuals with a history of COVID-19 associates the prevalence of persistent symptoms, with effects varying by smoking type—dual, CC, or HTP use. Dual users with a history of COVID-19 exhibited the greater number of associations with persistent symptoms, although the causal role of dual use remains uncertain.</p><p id="Par50">Disaggregating smoking subgroups offers more accurate insights into the association between smoking behaviors and COVID-19. Smoking cessation should be promoted to reduce the risks associated with long COVID.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_22050_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank all researchers involved in the data accumulation and all participants of JASTIS 2023, and Editage (www.editage.jp) for English language editing.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>T.T. had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data. Study concept and design: K.A.; acquisition of data: T.T., K.A.; statistical analysis and interpretation of data: E.T., K.Y.; drafting of the manuscript: E.T.; critical revision of the manuscript intellectual content: all authors; and study supervision: K.Y., K.A., and T.K.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data are not publicly available due to privacy restrictions, but available from Takahiro Tabuchi (E-mail: [tabuchitak@gmail.com] (mailto: tabuchitak@gmail.com)) on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par51">Kazuhisa Asai reports receiving lecture fees from AstraZeneca, GlaxoSmithKline and Sanofi; Tetsuya Watanabe, receiving lecture fees from AstraZeneca, GlaxoSmithKline and Sanofi; Takahiro Tabuchi receiving financial support for research, (consulting fees and lecture fees) from Daiichi Sankyo Healthcare Co., Ltd., Johnson and Johnson K. K., Data Seed Inc. and Workout-Plus LLC, and grants from the Ministry of Health Labour and Welfare, and Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Odani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of COVID-19 vaccine intake with Diagnosis, Hospitalization, and Oxygenation/Ventilation: A longitudinal Analysis, 2021–2022, Japan</article-title><source>Vaccines (Basel)</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines12111264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39591166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11598305</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Odani, S., Honda, H. &amp; Tabuchi, T. Association of COVID-19 vaccine intake with diagnosis, hospitalization, and oxygenation/ventilation: A longitudinal Analysis, 2021–2022, Japan. <italic toggle="yes">Vaccines</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1264. 10.3390/vaccines12111264 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39591166</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vaccines12111264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11598305</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 vaccination benefits in preventing severe disease in mild-to-moderate cases: an analysis in the first specialized hospital for COVID-19 in Japan</article-title><source>Respir Investig</source><year>2023</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resinv.2022.12.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36774816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9892338</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Kobayashi, K. et al. COVID-19 vaccination benefits in preventing severe disease in mild-to-moderate cases: An analysis in the first specialized hospital for COVID-19 in Japan. <italic toggle="yes">Respir. Investig.</italic><bold>61</bold>, 230–239 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36774816</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.resinv.2022.12.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9892338</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takamatsu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in personal behaviors during and after the COVID-19 pandemic: A nationwide Three-Year longitudinal study in Japan</article-title><source>Asia Pac. J. Public. Health</source><year>2025</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/10105395241305929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39688023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Takamatsu, A. et al. Changes in personal behaviors during and after the COVID-19 pandemic: A nationwide three-year longitudinal study in Japan. <italic toggle="yes">Asia Pac. J. Public Health</italic><bold>37</bold>, 108–115 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39688023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/10105395241305929</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of individual behaviors with infection prevention measures and COVID-19 development: A Japanese Cross-Sectional study</article-title><source>Asia Pac. J. Public. Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines12111264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38600739</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Honda, H. et al. Association of individual behaviors with infection prevention measures and COVID-19 development: A Japanese cross-sectional study. <italic toggle="yes">Asia Pac. J. Public Health</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1264. 10.3390/vaccines12111264 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/10105395241245496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38600739</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lipscy, P. Y. Japan’s Response to the COVID-19 Pandemic in <italic toggle="yes">Japan Decides 2021</italic> (ed. Pekkanen, R. J. et al. ) 239–254 (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Buckell, J. et al. COVID-19 vaccination, risk-compensatory behaviours, and contacts in the UK. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic>10.1038/s41598-023-34244-2 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-34244-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10209557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37231004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. A clinical case definition of post COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-Post_COVID-19_condition-Clinical_case_definition-2021.1">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-Post_COVID-19_condition-Clinical_case_definition-2021.1</ext-link> (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ely</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fineberg</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long covid defined</article-title><source>N Engl. J. Med.</source><year>2024</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>1746</fpage><lpage>1753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsb2408466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39083764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687645</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Ely, E. W., Brown, L. M., Fineberg, H. V &amp; The National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine Committee on Examining the Working Definition for Long Covid. Long covid defined. <italic toggle="yes">N. Engl. J. Med.</italic><bold>391</bold>, 1746–1753 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39083764</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsb2408466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687645</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nalbandian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01283-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8893149</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Nalbandian, A. et al. Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome. <italic toggle="yes">Nat. Med.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 601–615 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753937</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-021-01283-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8893149</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlile</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of long COVID on health-related quality-of-life: an opensafely population cohort study using patient-reported outcome measures (OpenPROMPT)</article-title><source>Lancet Reg. Health Eur.</source><year>2024</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>100908</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanepe.2024.100908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38689605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11059448</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Carlile, O. et al. Impact of long COVID on health-related quality-of-life: An opensafely population cohort study using patient-reported outcome measures (OpenPROMPT). <italic toggle="yes">Lancet Reg. Health Eur.</italic><bold>40</bold>, 100908. 10.1016/j.lanepe.2024.100908 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38689605</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lanepe.2024.100908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11059448</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prolonged symptoms after COVID-19 in japan: A nationwide survey of the symptoms and their impact on patients’ quality of life</article-title><source>Am. J. Med.</source><year>2025</year><volume>138</volume><issue>e4</issue><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2023.04.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37236416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10208656</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Honda, H. et al. Prolonged symptoms after COVID-19 in Japan: A nationwide survey of the symptoms and their impact on patients’ quality of life. <italic toggle="yes">Am. J. Med.</italic><bold>138</bold>(e4), 98–107. 10.1016/j.amjmed.2023.04.040 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37236416</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjmed.2023.04.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10208656</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takamatsu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and trends in persistent symptoms following COVID-19 in japan: A nationwide cross-sectional survey</article-title><source>J. Infect. Chemother.</source><year>2024</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2024.02.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38346670</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Takamatsu, A. et al. Prevalence and trends in persistent symptoms following COVID-19 in Japan: A nationwide cross-sectional survey. <italic toggle="yes">J. Infect. Chemother.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 725–733 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38346670</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jiac.2024.02.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID prevalence and impact on quality of life 2 years after acute COVID-19</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>11207</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-36995-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37433819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10336045</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Kim, Y., Bae, S., Chang, H. &amp; Kim, S. Long COVID prevalence and impact on quality of life 2 years after acute COVID-19. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 11207. 10.1038/s41598-023-36995-4 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37433819</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-36995-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10336045</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Davis, H. E. et al. Long COVID: Major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. <italic toggle="yes">Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 133–146 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Imoto, W. et al. A cross-sectional, multicenter survey of the prevalence and risk factors for long COVID. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic>10.1038/s41598-022-25398-6 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-25398-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9793373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36575200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors for persistent symptoms after COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Infect.</source><year>2024</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2023.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37866679</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Luo, D. et al. Prevalence and risk factors for persistent symptoms after COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic toggle="yes">Clin. Microbiol. Infect.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 328–335 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37866679</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cmi.2023.10.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Müller, S. A. et al. Prevalence and risk factors for long COVID and post-COVID-19 condition in Africa: A systematic review. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet Glob. Health</italic><bold>11</bold>, e1713-e1724 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2214-109X(23)00384-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37858583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perlis</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and correlates of long COVID symptoms among US adults</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open.</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e2238804</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.38804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36301542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9614581</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Perlis, R. H. et al. Prevalence and correlates of long COVID symptoms among US adults. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw. Open.</italic><bold>5</bold>, e2238804. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.38804 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36301542</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.38804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9614581</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID health-related quality of life and somatic symptoms: A National survey in Japan</article-title><source>Am. J. Med. Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjms.2023.04.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37120076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10140465</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Kamata, K. et al. Post-COVID health-related quality of life and somatic symptoms: A National survey in Japan. <italic toggle="yes">Am. J. Med. Sci.</italic><bold>366</bold>, 114–123 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37120076</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjms.2023.04.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10140465</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antigona Carmen Trofor</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Looking at the data on smoking and Post-COVID-19 Syndrome-A literature review</article-title><source>J. Pers. Med.</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>97</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jpm14010097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38248798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10821354</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Antigona Carmen Trofor, A. C. et al. Looking at the data on smoking and Post-COVID-19 Syndrome-A literature review. <italic toggle="yes">J. Pers. Med.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 97. 10.3390/jpm14010097 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38248798</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jpm14010097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10821354</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomar</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and its long-term sequelae: what do we know in 2023?</article-title><source>Pol. Arch. Intern Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>16402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20452/pamw.16402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36626183</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Lippi, G., Gomar, F. S. &amp; Henry, B. M. COVID-19 and its long-term sequelae: What do we know in 2023? <italic toggle="yes">Pol. Arch. Intern. Med.</italic><bold>133</bold>, 16402. 10.20452/pamw.16402 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36626183</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.20452/pamw.16402</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology, symptomatology, and risk factors for long COVID symptoms: population-based, multicenter study</article-title><source>JMIR Public. Health Surveill</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e42315</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/42315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36645453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9994465</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Wong, M. C. Epidemiology, symptomatology, and risk factors for long COVID symptoms: Population-based, multicenter study. <italic toggle="yes">JMIR Public Health Surveill.</italic><bold>9</bold>, e42315. 10.2196/42315 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36645453</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2196/42315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9994465</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinjo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heated tobacco product smokers in Japan identified by a Population-Based survey</article-title><source>J. Epidemiol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2188/jea.JE20190199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31787705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7661338</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Kinjo, A. et al. Heated tobacco product smokers in Japan identified by a population-based survey. <italic toggle="yes">J. Epidemiol.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 547–555 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31787705</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2188/jea.JE20190199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7661338</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Odani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and denial of current tobacco product use: combustible and heated tobacco products, Japan, 2022</article-title><source>Prev. Med. Rep.</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>102031</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.102031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36531095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9747627</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Odani, S. &amp; Tabuchi, T. Prevalence and denial of current tobacco product use: Combustible and heated tobacco products, Japan, 2022. <italic toggle="yes">Prev. Med. Rep.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 102031 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36531095</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.102031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9747627</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heated tobacco products: insights into composition and toxicity</article-title><source>Toxics</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>667</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxics11080667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37624172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10459283</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Upadhyay, S. et al. Heated tobacco products: Insights into composition and toxicity. <italic toggle="yes">Toxics</italic><bold>11</bold>, 667. 10.3390/toxics11080667 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37624172</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/toxics11080667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10459283</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Helen</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iii</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardone</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benowitz</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IQOS: examination of Philip Morris international’s claim of reduced exposure</article-title><source>Tob. Control</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>s30</fpage><lpage>s36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2018-054321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30158205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6252487</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Helen, G. S., Iii, P. J., Nardone, N. &amp; Benowitz, N. L. IQOS: Examination of Philip Morris international’s claim of reduced exposure. <italic toggle="yes">Tob. Control</italic><bold>27</bold>, s30–s36. 10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2018-054321 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30158205</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2018-054321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6252487</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biomarkers of exposure to nicotine and selected toxicants in individuals who use alternative tobacco products sold in Japan and Canada from 2018 to 2019</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol. Biomarkers Prev.</source><year>2025</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-24-0836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39636163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11799835</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Miller, C. R. et al. Biomarkers of exposure to nicotine and selected toxicants in individuals who use alternative tobacco products sold in Japan and Canada from 2018 to 2019. <italic toggle="yes">Cancer Epidemiol. Biomark. Prev.</italic><bold>34</bold>, 298–307 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39636163</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-24-0836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11799835</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Heated tobacco products: Information sheet. Report No.: WHO/HEP/HPR/2020.2. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/331297">https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/331297</ext-link> (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of combustible cigarettes and heated tobacco products use with SARS-CoV-2 infection and severe COVID-19 in japan: a JASTIS 2022 cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1120</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-28006-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36732559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9894839</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Nishimura, M. et al. Association of combustible cigarettes and heated tobacco products use with SARS-CoV-2 infection and severe COVID-19 in Japan: A JASTIS 2022 cross-sectional study. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 1120. 10.1038/s41598-023-28006-3 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36732559</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-28006-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9894839</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Study profile: the Japan society and new tobacco internet survey (JASTIS): A longitudinal internet cohort study of Heat-Not-Burn tobacco products, electronic Cigarettes, and conventional tobacco products in Japan</article-title><source>J. Epidemiol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2188/jea.JE20180116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30318495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6776477</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Tabuchi, T. et al. Study profile: The Japan society and new tobacco internet survey (JASTIS): A longitudinal internet cohort study of Heat-Not-Burn tobacco products, electronic Cigarettes, and conventional tobacco products in Japan. <italic toggle="yes">J. Epidemiol.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 444–450 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30318495</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2188/jea.JE20180116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6776477</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perlowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolich</surname><given-names>JŽ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: a clinical update</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2024</year><volume>404</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01136-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39096925</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Greenhalgh, T., Sivan, M., Perlowski, A. &amp; Nikolich, J. Ž. Long COVID: A clinical update. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic><bold>404</bold>, 707–724 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39096925</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01136-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</article-title><source>Eur. Respir Rev.</source><year>2022</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>210185</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0185-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35264409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8924706</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Montani, D. et al. Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome. <italic toggle="yes">Eur. Respir. Rev.</italic><bold>31</bold>, 210185. 10.1183/16000617.0185-2021 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35264409</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/16000617.0185-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8924706</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schonlau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soest</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapteyn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection bias in web surveys and the use of propensity scores</article-title><source>Sociol. Methods Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>291</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0049124108327128</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Schonlau, M., Soest, A., Kapteyn, A. &amp; Couper, M. Selection bias in web surveys and the use of propensity scores. <italic toggle="yes">Sociol. Methods Res.</italic><bold>37</bold>, 291. 10.1177/0049124108327128 (2009).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Japan Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare. Overview of the 2016 Comprehensive Survey of Living Condition of the People on Health and Welfare. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei/saikin/hw/k-tyosa/k-tyosa16/index.html">https://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei/saikin/hw/k-tyosa/k-tyosa16/index.html</ext-link>. Accessed 19 Dec 2022 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Awareness and use of electronic cigarettes and heat-not-burn tobacco products in Japan</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2016</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>706</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.13231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26566956</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Tabuchi, T. et al. Awareness and use of electronic cigarettes and heat-not-burn tobacco products in Japan. <italic toggle="yes">Addiction</italic><bold>111</bold>, 706–713 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26566956</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/add.13231</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the freely available easy-to-use software ‘EZR’ for medical statistics</article-title><source>Bone Marrow Transpl.</source><year>2013</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bmt.2012.2442013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3590441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23208313</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Kanda, Y. Investigation of the freely available easy-to-use software ‘EZR’ for medical statistics. <italic toggle="yes">Bone Marrow Transpl.</italic><bold>48</bold>, 452–458. 10.1038/bmt.2012.2442013 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/bmt.2012.244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3590441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23208313</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiyegbusi</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symptoms, complications and management of long COVID: a review</article-title><source>J. R Soc. Med.</source><year>2021</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01410768211032850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8450986</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Aiyegbusi, O. L. et al. Symptoms, complications and management of long COVID: A review. <italic toggle="yes">J. R. Soc. Med.</italic><bold>114</bold>, 428–442 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265229</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/01410768211032850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8450986</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symptoms and risk factors for long COVID in non-hospitalized adults</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1706</fpage><lpage>1714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01909-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35879616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9388369</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Subramanian, A. et al. Symptoms and risk factors for long COVID in non-hospitalized adults. <italic toggle="yes">Nat. Med.</italic><bold>28</bold>, 1706–1714 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35879616</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-022-01909-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9388369</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinato</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and impact of COVID-19 sequelae on treatment and survival of patients with cancer who recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection: evidence from the OnCovid retrospective, multicentre registry study</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1669</fpage><lpage>1680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(21)00573-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34741822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8565932</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Pinato, D. J. et al. Prevalence and impact of COVID-19 sequelae on treatment and survival of patients with cancer who recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection: Evidence from the OnCovid retrospective, multicentre registry study. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet Oncol.</italic><bold>22</bold>, 1669–1680 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34741822</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1470-2045(21)00573-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8565932</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pre-existing conditions associated with post-acute sequelae of COVID-19</article-title><source>J. Autoimmun.</source><year>2023</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>102991</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaut.2022.102991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36634460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9816074</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Jacobs, E. T. et al. Pre-existing conditions associated with post-acute sequelae of COVID-19. <italic toggle="yes">J. Autoimmun.</italic><bold>135</bold>, 102991. 10.1016/j.jaut.2022.102991 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36634460</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaut.2022.102991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9816074</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>HQM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of olfactory dysfunction and quality of life in hospitalised patients 1 year after SARS-CoV-2 infection: a cohort study</article-title><source>BMJ Open.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e054598</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-054598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35078845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8795927</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Tan, H. Q. M. et al. Prevalence of olfactory dysfunction and quality of life in hospitalised patients 1 year after SARS-CoV-2 infection: A cohort study. <italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic><bold>12</bold>, e054598. 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-054598 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35078845</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-054598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8795927</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunugita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid increase in heated tobacco product (HTP) use from 2015 to 2019: from the Japan ‘Society and new tobacco’ internet survey (JASTIS)</article-title><source>Tob. Control</source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>474</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2020-055652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32503900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8237184</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Hori, A., Tabuchi, T. &amp; Kunugita, N. Rapid increase in heated tobacco product (HTP) use from 2015 to 2019: From the Japan ‘Society and new tobacco’ internet survey (JASTIS). <italic toggle="yes">Tob. Control</italic><bold>30</bold>, 474–475 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32503900</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2020-055652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8237184</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion (US). Office on Smoking and Health. The Health Consequences of Smoking—50 Years of Progress: A Report of the Surgeon General (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (US), 2014). Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK179276/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK179276/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24455788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayaka</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>[Why people use heated tobacco products in Japan]</article-title><source>J. Dent. Hlth</source><year>2021</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5834/jdh.71.1_11</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Ayaka et al. Why people use heated tobacco products in Japan. <italic toggle="yes">J. Dent. Health</italic><bold>71</bold>, 11–18. 10.5834/jdh.71.1_11 (2021). (in Japanese).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Helen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St., Lii</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardone</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benowitz</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IQOS: examination of Philip Morris international’s claim of reduced exposure</article-title><source>Tob. Control</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>s30</fpage><lpage>s36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2018-054321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30158205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6252487</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Helen, G., St., Lii, P. J., Nardone, N. &amp; Benowitz, N. L. IQOS: Examination of Philip Morris international’s claim of reduced exposure. <italic toggle="yes">Tob. Control</italic><bold>27</bold>, s30–s36. 10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2018-054321 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30158205</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2018-054321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6252487</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effects of dual IQOS and cigarette smoke exposure on airway epithelial cells: implications for lung health and respiratory disease pathogenesis</article-title><source>ERJ open. Res.</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>00558</fpage><lpage>2022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00558-2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37260462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10227640</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Saha, P. et al. The effects of dual IQOS and cigarette smoke exposure on airway epithelial cells: Implications for lung health and respiratory disease pathogenesis. <italic toggle="yes">ERJ Open Res.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 00558–2022. 10.1183/23120541.00558-2022 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37260462</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/23120541.00558-2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10227640</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The National Health and Nutrition Survey in Japan. Available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/seisakunitsuite/bunya/kenkou_iryou/kenkou/eiyou/r1-houkoku_00002.html">https://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/seisakunitsuite/bunya/kenkou_iryou/kenkou/eiyou/r1-houkoku_00002.html</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nahhas</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweanor</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is accounting for the rapid decline in cigarette sales in japan?</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3570</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17103570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32443663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7277739</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Cummings, K. M., Nahhas, G. J. &amp; Sweanor, D. T. What is accounting for the rapid decline in cigarette sales in Japan? <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</italic><bold>17</bold>, 3570. 10.3390/ijerph17103570 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32443663</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph17103570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7277739</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chu, S. et al. Impact of heating conventional cigarettes with a novel device on Health-related biomarkers and cigarette use patterns among Chinese adult smokers unwilling to quit: A pilot randomized controlled trial. <italic toggle="yes">Nicotine Tob. Res.</italic>. 10.1093/ntr/ntae177 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ntr/ntae177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39021120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cigarettes, heated tobacco products and dual use: exhaled carbon monoxide, saliva cotinine and total tobacco consumed by Hong Kong tobacco users</article-title><source>Tob. Control</source><year>2024</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tc-2022-057598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36693724</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Zhang, X. et al. Cigarettes, heated tobacco products and dual use: Exhaled carbon monoxide, saliva cotinine and total tobacco consumed by Hong Kong tobacco users. <italic toggle="yes">Tob. Control</italic><bold>33</bold>, 457–463 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36693724</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/tc-2022-057598</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamoud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review investigating the impact of dual use of E-Cigarettes and conventional cigarettes on smoking cessation</article-title><source>ERJ Open. Res. Preprint at.</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00902-2024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12053992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40337339</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Hamoud, J. et al. A systematic review investigating the impact of dual use of E-Cigarettes and conventional cigarettes on smoking cessation. <italic toggle="yes">ERJ Open. Res.</italic>10.1183/23120541.00902-2024 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/23120541.00902-2024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12053992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40337339</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al’Absi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nicotine withdrawal and Stress-Induced changes in pain sensitivity: A Cross-sectional investigation between abstinent smokers and nonsmokers</article-title><source>Psychophysiology</source><year>2014</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>1022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/psyp.12241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24934193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4165762</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Nakajima, M. &amp; Al’Absi, M. Nicotine withdrawal and Stress-Induced changes in pain sensitivity: A cross-sectional investigation between abstinent smokers and nonsmokers. <italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiology</italic><bold>51</bold>, 1015–1022 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24934193</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/psyp.12241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4165762</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barthélémy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smoking increases the risk of post-acute COVID-19 syndrome: results from a French community-based survey</article-title><source>Tob. Induc. Dis.</source><year>2022</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18332/tid/1502952022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35799625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9204712</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Barthélémy, H. et al. Smoking increases the risk of post-acute COVID-19 syndrome: Results from a French community-based survey. <italic toggle="yes">Tob. Induc. Dis.</italic><bold>20</bold>, 59. 10.18332/tid/1502952022 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35799625</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18332/tid/150295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9204712</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takakura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koido</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical features, therapeutic outcomes, and recovery period of long COVID</article-title><source>J. Med. Virol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>e28316</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.28316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10108287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36412057</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Takakura, K., Suka, M., Kajihara, M. &amp; Koido, S. Clinical features, therapeutic outcomes, and recovery period of long COVID. <italic toggle="yes">J. Med. Virol.</italic><bold>95</bold>, e28316. 10.1002/jmv.28316 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jmv.28316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10108287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36412057</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buonsenso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-Acute COVID-19 sequelae in a working population at one year Follow-Up: A wide range of impacts from an Italian sample</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>11093</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph191711093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36078808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9518581</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Buonsenso, D. et al. Post-Acute COVID-19 sequelae in a working population at one year follow-up: A wide range of impacts from an Italian sample. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</italic><bold>19</bold>, 11093. 10.3390/ijerph191711093 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36078808</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph191711093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9518581</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fancourt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health behaviours the month prior to COVID-19 infection and the development of self-reported long COVID and specific long COVID symptoms: a longitudinal analysis of 1581 UK adults</article-title><source>BMC Public. Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1716</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-14123-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36085055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9462889</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Paul, E. &amp; Fancourt, D. Health behaviours the month prior to COVID-19 infection and the development of self-reported long COVID and specific long COVID symptoms: A longitudinal analysis of 1581 UK adults. <italic toggle="yes">BMC Public. Health</italic><bold>22</bold>, 1716. 10.1186/s12889-022-14123-7 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36085055</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-022-14123-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9462889</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistent symptoms after SARS-CoV-2 infection: Long-term implications for health and quality of life</article-title><source>Lancet Reg. Health Eur.</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>100373</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanepe.2022.100373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35373172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8964312</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">So, M. K., Chu, A. M. &amp; Tiwai, A. Persistent symptoms after SARS-CoV-2 infection: Long-term implications for health and quality of life. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet Reg. Health Eur.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 100373 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35373172</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lanepe.2022.100373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8964312</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>