<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Pharm Anal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Pharm Anal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3328</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jpa</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Pharmaceutical Analysis</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-1779</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2214-0883</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Xi'an Jiaotong University</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12398817</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12398817.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12398817</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12398817</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40893436</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpha.2025.101342</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2095-1779(25)00159-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101342</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quantifying compatibility mechanisms in traditional Chinese medicine with interpretable graph neural networks</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names initials="J">Jingqi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaobin</given-names></name><email>jiaxiaobin2015@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>School of Traditional Chinese Pharmacy, China Pharmaceutical University, Nanjing, 211198, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>State Key Laboratory of Natural Medicines, China Pharmaceutical University, Nanjing, 211198, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. School of Traditional Chinese Pharmacy, China Pharmaceutical University, Nanjing, 211198, China. <email>jiaxiaobin2015@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">495058</issue-id><elocation-id>101342</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-09-03 12:25:26.497"><day>03</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) features complex compatibility mechanisms involving multi-component, multi-target, and multi-pathway interactions. This study presents an interpretable graph artificial intelligence (GraphAI) framework to quantify such mechanisms in Chinese herbal formulas (CHFs). A multidimensional TCM knowledge graph (TCM-MKG; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/records/13763953" id="intref0010">https://zenodo.org/records/13763953</ext-link>) was constructed, integrating seven standardized modules: TCM terminology, Chinese patent medicines (CPMs), Chinese herbal pieces (CHPs), pharmacognostic origins (POs), chemical compounds, biological targets, and diseases. A neighbor-diffusion strategy was used to address the sparsity of compound-target associations, increasing target coverage from 12.0% to 98.7%. Graph neural networks (GNNs) with attention mechanisms were applied to 6,080 CHFs, modeled as graphs with CHPs as nodes. To embed domain-specific semantics, virtual nodes medicinal properties, i.e., therapeutic nature, flavor, and meridian tropism, were introduced, enabling interpretable modeling of inter-CHP relationships. The model quantitatively captured classical compatibility roles such as “monarch-minister-assistant-guide,” and uncovered TCM etiological types derived from diagnostic and efficacy patterns. Model validation using 215 CHFs used for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) management highlighted <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">Rhizoma Phragmitis</italic> as a high-attention herb pair. Mass spectrometry (MS) and target prediction identified three active compounds, i.e., methylinissolin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside, corydalin, and pingbeinine, which converge on pathways such as neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction, xenobiotic response, and neuronal function, supporting their neuroimmune and detoxification potential. Given their high safety and dietary compatibility, this herb pair may offer therapeutic value for managing long COVID-19. All data and code are openly available (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ZENGJingqi/GraphAI-for-TCM" id="intref0015">https://github.com/ZENGJingqi/GraphAI-for-TCM</ext-link>), providing a scalable and interpretable platform for TCM mechanism research and discovery of bioactive herbal constituents.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><alt-text id="alttext0010">Image 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ga1.jpg"/></fig></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>•</label><p id="p0010">A TCM-MKG was developed by integrating traditional and biomedical data.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>•</label><p id="p0015">Virtual nodes were introduced to enhance the modeling of herbal compatibility.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>•</label><p id="p0020">Open-source data, models, and code were provided to support TCM research.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><label>•</label><p id="p0025">Key herbal roles in COVID-19 management were systematically quantified.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Traditional Chinese medicine</kwd><kwd>Graph neural networks</kwd><kwd>Knowledge graph</kwd><kwd>Compatibility mechanism</kwd><kwd>Artificial intelligence</kwd><kwd>Coronavirus disease 2019</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">Traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) is characterized by a holistic philosophy and emphasis on dynamic balance, focusing on the interplay between an individual's constitution, disease state, and physiological systems. A central principle of TCM is the rational compatibility of herbal medicines, which aims to enhance therapeutic efficacy while minimizing toxicity [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This approach has demonstrated clinical advantages in treating complex diseases. For instance, Lianhua Qingwen capsules have been shown to alleviate symptoms and shorten hospitalization duration in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Similarly, PHY906, an investigational drug based on the traditional Huangqin decoction and developed by Yale University, has improved treatment outcomes in colorectal cancer as a chemotherapy adjuvant [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p id="p0035">With the rapid advancement of artificial intelligence (AI), new opportunities have emerged to investigate the complex mechanisms underlying TCM [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. AI excels in multidimensional data processing and modeling intricate relationships, thereby enabling a transition from experience-driven to data-driven research in traditional medicine [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>]. In particular, graph AI (GraphAI), which integrates knowledge graphs, graph computation, and graph neural networks (GNNs), offers powerful tools for representing and analyzing complex network-structured data [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>]. The inherent complexity of TCM compatibility, characterized by multi-herb, multi-target, and multi-pathway interactions, makes it an ideal application scenario for GraphAI, whose strengths align naturally with the layered and relational structure of TCM knowledge systems.</p><p id="p0040">Despite these advancements, current data-driven approaches in TCM face several critical challenges. First, existing models lack sufficient interpretability to explain complex herbal interactions, limiting mechanistic understanding. Second, many computational frameworks do not adequately incorporate core TCM theories, resulting in a disconnect between traditional principles and modern algorithms. Third, the absence of high-quality, multidimensional, and openly shared datasets hampers interdisciplinary collaboration and innovation.</p><p id="p0045">To address these challenges, we propose a GraphAI-based framework that integrates traditional TCM theories with modern AI techniques to quantify herbal compatibility. We constructed a comprehensive TCM multidimensional knowledge graph (TCM-MKG), incorporating hierarchical information across chemical compositions, target interactions, biological pathways, compatibility rules, and diagnostic knowledge. Using TCM-MKG, we modeled Chinese herbal pieces (CHPs) as fundamental units and integrated their medicinal properties and diagnostic attributes. GNNs with attention mechanisms were employed to analyze 6,080 Chinese herbal formulas (CHFs), enabling interpretable modeling of compatibility roles within complex prescriptions. Our method was validated using 215 CHFs employed in COVID-19 treatment in China between 2019 and 2021, revealing synergistic effects and compatibility patterns. These findings demonstrate the potential of our approach to modernize TCM theory, advance data-driven research, and support drug discovery and clinical decision-making.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>TCM terminology module</title><p id="p0050">The TCM terminology module formed the semantic foundation of TCM-MKG. Systematic categorization and standardization ensured semantic consistency across modules. This module was based on the World Health Organization (WHO) International Standard Terminologies on Traditional Medicine (2022 edition<bold>)</bold> and comprised 1,810 core TCM terms [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], including key concepts such as etiology, pathogenesis, therapeutic principles, and treatments. These terminologies provided theoretical support for cross-module data interconnectivity. The standard, published by the WHO, is accessible at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240042322" id="intref0020">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240042322</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Chinese patent medicine (CPM) module</title><p id="p0055">The module integrated data on 8,977 CPMs, including formula composition, dosage forms, efficacy, indications, and links to modern medical diseases. The primary data sources included the Chinese Pharmacopoeia (2020 edition) [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and the China Medical Information Platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dayi.org.cn" id="intref0025">www.dayi.org.cn</ext-link>). In addition, CPM indications were mapped to the International Classification of Diseases, 11th Revision (ICD-11) codes using the coding tool (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://icd11.pumch.cn" id="intref0030">https://icd11.pumch.cn</ext-link>) to align the traditional Chinese and modern medical systems.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>CHP module</title><p id="p0060">The CHP module documented 6,207 CHPs, encompassing essential information such as medicinal properties, biological sources, and chemical compositions. This module supported the systematic investigation of the mechanisms of action and chemical characteristics of CHPs. Key data sources included the Chinese Pharmacopoeia (2020 edition) [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], the China Medical Information Platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dayi.org.cn" id="intref0035">www.dayi.org.cn</ext-link>), and the U.S. National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Taxonomy (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy" id="intref0040">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], which standardizes Latin species names.</p><p id="p0065">Chemical composition data were integrated from authoritative databases and lab-curated sources, including: Traditional Chinese Medicine Integrated Database (TCMID) V2.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://47.100.169.139/tcmid" id="intref0045">http://47.100.169.139/tcmid</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], Traditional Chinese Medicine Bank (TCMbank) V1.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tcmbank.cn" id="intref0050">https://tcmbank.cn</ext-link>); [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], Symptom Mapping database (SymMap) V2.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.symmap.org" id="intref0055">http://www.symmap.org</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], Herbal Ingredients' Targets Platform (HIT) V2.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hit2.badd-cao.net" id="intref0060">http://hit2.badd-cao.net</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], HERB V2.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://47.92.70.12" id="intref0065">http://47.92.70.12</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], Encyclopedia of Traditional Chinese Medicine (ETCM) V2.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tcmip.cn/ETCM2" id="intref0070">http://www.tcmip.cn/ETCM2</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and Traditional Chinese Medicine Systems Pharmacology Database and Analysis Platform (TCMSP) V1.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.tcmsp-e.com/" id="intref0075">https://www.tcmsp-e.com/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Pharmacognostic origin (PO) module</title><p id="p0070">This module documented 4,810 POs, providing comprehensive information on their biological sources, chemical compositions, and related properties. This module formed a systematic foundation for studying POs in TCM and supported research on their pharmacological effects and molecular mechanisms of action. Data primarily originated from the NCBI Taxonomy [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], ensuring the precise classification of POs (e.g., family, genus, and species). The shared chemical composition data linked the PO and CHP modules. Additional information was obtained from the Collective Molecular Activities of Useful Plants (CMAUP) database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bidd.group/CMAUP/index.html" id="intref0080">https://www.bidd.group/CMAUP/index.html</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. POs identified as CHPs were mapped using CHP-PO associations. Chemical composition data for products recorded as natural substances (e.g., plants or fungi identified by Latin names) were compiled independently.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Chemical compounds module</title><p id="p0075">The chemical compound module systematically recorded information on 123,647 chemical compounds, including their structural data, target associations, and cross-database mappings. This module served as a robust foundation for investigating the molecular mechanisms and pharmacological activities of TCMs. All chemical compounds were standardized using RDKit (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rdkit.org/" id="intref0085">https://www.rdkit.org/</ext-link>), with International Chemical Identifier Key (InChIKey) as a unique identifier to ensure data consistency and traceability. Core data included simplified molecular-input line-entry system (SMILES), InChI, and Molecular_formula, whereas molecular descriptors (e.g., molecular weight, log<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>, and topological polar surface area) generated by RDKit supported the structural and efficacy analyses.</p><p id="p0080">To classify chemical structures, NPClassifier V1.5 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://npclassifier.ucsd.edu/" id="intref0090">https://npclassifier.ucsd.edu/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] was used for three-tier classification (pathway, superclass, and class), and to annotate IsGlycoside information to identify glycoside compounds. This classification system highlighted the biological characteristics and pharmacological activities of these compounds. Chemical compound-target association data were integrated from multiple authoritative sources: DrugBank V5.1.12 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://go.drugbank.com" id="intref0095">https://go.drugbank.com</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], Therapeutic Target Database (TTD) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://db.idrblab.net/ttd/" id="intref0100">https://db.idrblab.net/ttd/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], STITCH V5.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://stitch.embl.de" id="intref0105">http://stitch.embl.de</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and BindingDB (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bindingdb.org" id="intref0110">https://www.bindingdb.org</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. All targets were standardized using EntrezID and restricted to human-specific targets to ensure accuracy. In addition to chemical compounds derived from CHPs and POs, the module also included all compounds from DrugBank and TTD, as well as compound-target associations from STITCH with a confidence score above 700. This ensured the availability of high-quality training data for target prediction.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Target module</title><p id="p0085">The target module in TCM-MKG included 20,053 standardized human targets and 6,879,008 protein-protein interaction (PPI) records, providing a systematic foundation for TCM target research and network biology analysis. Target data were standardized using multiple identifiers, including EntrezID, UniProtID, GeneSymbol, and ENSGID, to ensure compatibility and traceability. Target symbols and sequence information were obtained from Ensembl GRCh37.p13 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://grch37.ensembl.org/Homo_sapiens/Info/Index" id="intref0115">http://grch37.ensembl.org/Homo_sapiens/Info/Index</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and UniProt Release 2024_02 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.uniprot.org/" id="intref0120">https://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Each target entry include multiple standard identifiers and detailed protein sequence data.</p><p id="p0090">PPI data were integrated from the following authoritative resources: Search Tool for the Retrieval of Interacting Genes/Proteins (STRING) V12.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cn.string-db.org/" id="intref0125">https://cn.string-db.org/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], SIGNOR V3.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://signor.uniroma2.it/" id="intref0130">https://signor.uniroma2.it/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], The Molecular INTeraction (MINT) database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mint.bio.uniroma2.it/" id="intref0135">https://mint.bio.uniroma2.it/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], IntAct (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/home" id="intref0140">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/home</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and BioGRID V4.4.233 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://thebiogrid.org/" id="intref0145">https://thebiogrid.org/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. These databases provided extensive information on direct PPIs and causal relationships, facilitating an in-depth analysis of TCM-related targets.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Disease module</title><p id="p0095">The disease module in the TCM-MKG integrated core data from the 2024 Chinese and English versions of ICD-11, extending it through standardized mappings to multiple authoritative databases, including the Unified Medical Language System (UMLS) and Medical Subject Headings (MeSH), both accessible via <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://uts.nlm.nih.gov/uts/umls" id="intref0150">https://uts.nlm.nih.gov/uts/umls</ext-link> [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and Disease Ontology Identifier (DOID) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://disease-ontology.org/do" id="intref0155">https://disease-ontology.org/do</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. This module included multi-layered mappings between ICD-11 codes and the corresponding UMLS Concept Unique Identifiers (CUIs), MeSH identifiers, and DOIDs, covering 12 semantic types such as diseases, syndromes, neoplastic processes, signs or symptoms, and injuries or poisoning.</p><p id="p0100">These mappings enabled standardized disease data management and cross-platform queries. Disease-target association data were integrated from multiple authoritative databases, including: DisGeNET V7.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.disgenet.org/" id="intref0160">https://www.disgenet.org/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], providing 575,153 CUI-classified disease-target associations; Comparative Toxicogenomics Database (CTD) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ctdbase.org/" id="intref0165">https://ctdbase.org/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], contributing 24,097,586 MeSH-classified disease-target associations; and Diseases V2.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://diseases.jensenlab.org/" id="intref0170">https://diseases.jensenlab.org/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], offering 6,522,131 DOID-classified disease-target associations. These comprehensive datasets supported the integration of traditional TCM theories with modern biomedical frameworks, enabling cross-disciplinary research and advanced network analyses.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Neighbor-diffusion strategy for prediction of compound-target associations</title><p id="p0105">We used RDKit to convert SMILES strings into molecular graphs, representing atoms as nodes and bonds as edges. Each compound was encoded with three types of features: 197 physicochemical descriptors, 2,048-bit Morgan fingerprints (radius = 2), and graph embeddings generated by graph convolutional network (GCN), graph attention network (GAT), and graph autoencoder (GAE). All features were reduced to two dimensions using uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) to facilitate similarity search. A neighbor-diffusion approach was applied to predict potential targets. For each compound, the top K most similar compounds were retrieved using the get.knnx function from the fast nearest neighbor (FNN) package. Targets of the most similar neighbor were assigned to the query compound, excluding those with the same InChIKey to avoid self-matching. Predicted associations were validated using the physicochemical GNN model, which estimates binding affinity based on compound structure and protein sequence [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Binding affinity was measured using p<italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>i</sub> (−log10<italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>i</sub>), where higher values indicate stronger interactions. Pairs with p<italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>i</sub> &gt;5.0 were retained as high-confidence predictions.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Encoding medicinal properties of CHPs and network construction</title><p id="p0110">The medicinal properties of CHPs were systematically encoded and analyzed using standardized processing and graph-intelligence methods. The medicinal properties included the therapeutic nature, medicinal flavor, and meridian tropism, which were organized into a hierarchical classification to build a medicinal property knowledge graph. To quantify the relationships among these attributes, an undirected network model was constructed, where nature, flavor, and meridian tropism were represented as nodes, and the edge weights reflected the strength of their associations.</p><p id="p0115">The initial network layout was based on the logical framework of the medicinal property theory and subsequently optimized using the ForceAtlas2 algorithm for enhanced visual clarity. The key parameters included an edge weight influence of 1.0, jitter tolerance of 0.1, Barnes-Hut optimization setting of 1.2, and activation of a strong-gravity mode (gravity value: 5.0). To identify potential functional modules within the network, the Louvain method was applied for community detection, grouping nodes into distinct communities based on edge weights, with the modular distribution visually represented through color coding.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>Encoding and clustering of TCM diagnostic terms</title><p id="p0120">To analyze the multidimensional relationships among TCM diagnostic terms, the Node2Vec algorithm was applied, embedding diagnostic features such as etiology, pathogenesis, treatment principles, and therapeutic methods into a 32-dimensional (32D) vector space. A graph model was constructed using the equations and their diagnostic features as nodes, and their relationships were represented as edge weights. The high-dimensional feature embeddings were reduced to a 2D space using UMAP to reveal potential relationships among the diagnostic terms.</p><p id="p0125">Hierarchical clustering was subsequently performed on the 32D feature vectors to classify the diagnostic terms into six categories, with the proportions of etiology, pathogenesis, treatment principles, and therapeutic methods calculated for each category. Owing to the small sample size of category six, the analysis focused on the five primary categories. The core features of each category were extracted using centroid vectors to support naming.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><label>2.11</label><title>Graph encoding of CHFs and message passing mechanisms</title><p id="p0130">To quantify the complex relationships between CHPs and the medicinal properties of CHFs, a graph-encoding method was designed using virtual nodes. This method integrated the core concepts of TCM theory with modern GNN techniques for the hierarchical and quantitative analysis of formula compatibility. The graph structure consisted of real and virtual nodes. Real nodes represent CHPs, with attributes including 91 feature variables (90 describing characteristics such as efficacy and origin, and one for dosage, set to zero if unknown). Virtual nodes represented medicinal property categories, including “therapeutic nature”, “medicinal flavor”, and “meridian tropism,” with initial attributes calculated as the weighted mean of all connected real node attributes. Edge attributes quantified the relationship between CHPs and medicinal properties using 2D encoding.</p><p id="p0135">To represent the complex relationships more comprehensively within the formulas, the virtual node attributes were dynamically updated based on the attributes of the connected real nodes, calculated as the weighted mean of all linked node attributes. Edge attributes between virtual nodes were determined by averaging the attributes of all connected real node edges, reflecting the potential relationships among the medicinal property categories. Through virtual nodes connecting multiple real nodes, this design established a hierarchical hypergraph structure for the CHF, facilitating the discovery of complementary and interactive relationships among CHPs.</p><p id="p0140">After constructing the graph structure, three GNN models were constructed to capture the multidimensional relationships within the CHF. The graph transformer network (GTN) captured long-range interactions using a global attention mechanism between nodes with a single-layer hidden design which balanced the complexity and computational efficiency. The hypergraph neural network (HGNN) leveraged hyperedges to organize high-order structural relationships between virtual and real nodes using two hidden layers to enhance information aggregation. The GAT dynamically adjusted message-passing weights through edge attention mechanisms, focusing on key interactions among CHPs. This network featured a three-layer hidden structure captures multilevel node interactions. This design ensures that every node in the model interacted attentively with others, achieving high interpretability while improving the modeling efficiency and stability.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><label>2.12</label><title>Data preparation and model hyperparameter optimization</title><p id="p0145">This study employed a comprehensive methodology encompassing data selection and grouping, hyperparameter optimization, and model interpretability analysis. A dataset of 6,080 CHF samples categorized into five major disease types, i.e., metabolic and circulatory imbalance, organ aging and immune deficiency, lifestyle and environmental impacts, psychological stress and external stimuli, and internal pathological changes with infectious factors, was partitioned into calibration (4,256 samples), validation (1,222 samples), and testing (602 samples) sets in a 7:2:1 ratio. The model performance was assessed using precision, recall, F1 score, area under the curve (AUC), accuracy, and specificity.</p><p id="p0150">For the three GNN models (GTN, HGNN, and GAT), a two-stage grid search combined with five-fold cross-validation was conducted on the full dataset. In the first stage, the structural parameters, including the hidden layer dimensions (32, 64, 96, and 128), number of attention heads (2, 4, 8, and 16), and dropout rates (0.1, 0.3, 0.4, and 0.5), were tuned by evaluating the average validation loss, with the configuration yielding the lowest loss selected. The second stage optimized the training parameters such as the learning rate (0.0001, 0.0003, 0.0005, and 0.0007) and batch size (16, 32, 64, and 128) using the same validation loss criterion.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.13"><label>2.13</label><title>Mass spectrometry (MS) analysis of chemical components in CHPs</title><p id="p0155">Chemical analysis of CHPs was performed using an Acquity H-Class ultra-high performance liquid chromatography (UPLC) system with a Xevo G2-XS quadrupole time-of-flight (QToF) mass spectrometer (Waters, Milford, MA, USA), equipped with an electrospray ionization (ESI) source. Liquid chromatography (LC)-MS grade acetonitrile and formic acid were purchased from Merck (Darmstadt, Germany). Ultrapure water was prepared using a Milli-Q system (Merck Millipore, Burlington, MA, USA). An analytical balance (FA1004B) was obtained from Shanghai H&amp;P International Trade Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). CHP samples were purchased from Jiazhile Grocery (Bozhou, China). One gram of each sample was extracted with 10 mL of acetonitrile by ultrasonic treatment for 30 min, then filtered through a 0.22-μm membrane.</p><p id="p0160">Chromatographic separation was conducted using an HSS T<sub>3</sub> column (100 mm × 2.1 mm, 1.8 μm) at 40 °C, with a flow rate of 0.3 mL/min. Mobile phase A was 0.1% formic acid in water, and mobile phase B was acetonitrile. The gradient was: 0–2 min, 10% B; 2–42 min, 10%–95% B; 42–45 min, 95% B; 45–47 min, 95%–10% B; and 47–50 min, 10% B. Mass detection was carried out in both positive and negative modes (<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> 50–2000), with low and high collision energies of 6 V and 20–40 V, respectively. Capillary voltage was 3 kV (ESI<sup>+</sup>) and 2.5 kV (ESI<sup>−</sup>); cone voltage was 40 V; desolvation temperature was 500 °C; and gas flow was 1000 L/h. Leucine enkephalin (<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> 556.2771 for ESI<sup>+</sup> and 554.2615 for ESI<sup>−</sup>) was used for real-time calibration.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.14"><label>2.14</label><title>Enrichment analysis and software</title><p id="p0165">To explore the potential mechanisms of small-molecule compounds in TCM, functional enrichment analysis was performed based on compound-target associations integrated from the TCM-MKG. To improve coverage, high-confidence associations generated by the neighbor-diffusion strategy (binding affinity threshold p<italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>i</sub> &gt; 5.0) were included. Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway enrichment was used to identify key metabolic and signaling pathways associated with compound targets. Gene Ontology (GO) analysis was conducted across three categories, i.e., biological process (BP), molecular function (MF), and cellular component (CC), to further characterize functional properties of the targets. Enrichment significance was assessed using the hypergeometric test with a threshold of P &lt; 0.05. Results were visualized by adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values and gene ratios to highlight significantly enriched terms. All analyses were performed in R (version 4.3.1). The clusterProfiler package was used for annotation and enrichment, and ggplot2 was applied for visualization. All workflows were independently designed and implemented by the researchers to ensure reproducibility and methodological transparency.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Structuring the TCM-MKG</title><p id="p0170">Data-driven TCM research has long been hindered by challenges in data standardization and interdisciplinary integration. These limitations prevent the effective synthesis of traditional theories with modern biomedical knowledge. To address these issues, we developed the TCM-MKG that integrated seven core modules: TCM terminology, CPM, CHPs, POs, chemical compounds, targets, and diseases (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). Data from 31 authoritative databases were standardized via semantic integration, forming a multilayered framework comprising 24 primary data tables (detailed in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S1</xref> [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>]), enabling systematic interdisciplinary research.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Data structure in the traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) multidimensional knowledge graph (TCM-MKG). (A) Overview of the TCM-MKG database structure, including TCM terminology, Chinese patent medicines (CPMs), Chinese herbal pieces (CHPs), pharmacognostic origin (PO), chemical components, targets, and diseases. (B) Distribution of the number of CHPs per CPM. The inset shows a magnified view of the tail distribution for CPMs containing more than 40 CHPs. (C) Dosage ratio distribution of CHPs in CPMs. The inset displays a magnified view of the dosage ratio distribution for values greater than 0.5. TCMT: TCM terminology; ICD-11: International Classification of Diseases, 11th revision; CUI: Concept Unique Identifier; MeSH: Medical Subject Headings; DOID: Disease Ontology Identifier; SD: standard deviation.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0175">The TCM terminology module included 1,810 standardized terms that are foundational for understanding the etiology, pathogenesis, and therapeutic principles. These terms are linked to the CPM, disease, and target modules, forming the semantic core of the knowledge graph. The CPM module documented 8,977 CHFs, linked to TCM terms (11,185 records), CHPs (74,084 records), and 69,431 ICD-11 codes, facilitating integration with Western medicine classifications. On average, the CHFs comprised eight CHPs (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B), with a mean dose ratio of 0.11 among CHPs (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>C), reflecting the typical multi-herbal compatibility of TCM. The CHP module described 6,207 CHPs with 23,517 medicinal property records and 226,589 associations with chemical compounds, thereby elucidating the pharmacological basis of CHPs. The PO module included 4,810 POs linked to chemical compounds through 426,305 associations.</p><p id="p0180">The chemical compound module integrated 123,647 unique molecules (identified by InChIKey), including structural, source, and biological relevance data. Among them, 2,175,154 compound-target pairs were collected. The target module standardized 20,053 protein identifiers and curated 6,879,008 PPI. All identifiers were mapped across EntrezID, gene symbols, and other biomedical vocabularies for downstream inference and validation. The disease module included 65,758 CUIs, 6,853 MeSH terms, and 4,803 DOIDs. These were linked to molecular targets through large-scale associations: 575,153 for CUIs, 24,097,586 for MeSH, and 6,522,131 for DOIDs.This comprehensive graph structure enables multi-level reasoning across TCM theory, pharmacological substances, biomolecular targets, and modern disease systems. All datasets are publicly available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/records/13763953" id="intref0175">https://zenodo.org/records/13763953</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Discovery of TCM compound-target associations via neighbor-diffusion strategy</title><p id="p0185">The sparsity of compound-target annotations has long limited the performance and generalizability of network pharmacology models in TCM. As shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A, only 7,631 (12.0%) out of 62,830 TCM-derived compounds in TCM-MKG have known target information, indicating a critical gap in data coverage. To evaluate the effectiveness of different molecular feature types in supporting neighbor-based target prediction, we performed UMAP-based dimensionality reduction for five feature sets: physicochemical descriptors, Morgan fingerprints, and graph embeddings generated by GCN, GAT, and GAE. The distribution of three compound categories was visualized in each feature space: i) high-fidelity targets from DrugBank, TTD, and STITCH; ii) TCM compounds with known targets; and iii) TCM compounds without annotated targets (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B). In traditional feature spaces (descriptors and fingerprints), compounds with known targets showed partial clustering, while unannotated TCM compounds were broadly dispersed, limiting the feasibility of neighborhood-based inference. In contrast, GNN-based embeddings showed tighter local continuity, reducing the distribution gap across categories. This improved spatial proximity enabled better neighbor matching for unannotated TCM compounds, supporting more accurate and scalable target diffusion.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Neighbor-diffusion–based inference and validation of compound-target associations in traditional Chinese medicine (TCM). (A) Distribution of known-target compounds across the TCM compound space. (B) Uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) visualization of molecular descriptors, Morgan fingerprints, and graph-based models: graph convolutional network (GCN), graph attention network (GAT), and graph autoencoder (GAE). (C) Binding affinity distribution across three datasets: diffused TCM targets (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7,260,578), high-fidelity targets consisting of 10,000 non-TCM compounds with 283,793 compound-target associations, and recorded TCM targets (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 343,373), sourced from DrugBank, Therapeutic Target Database (TTD), and STITCH (confidence score &gt; 700). (D) Number of EntrezIDs per InChIKey across binding affinity thresholds. (E) InChIKey coverage across binding affinity thresholds. (F) EntrezID coverage across binding affinity thresholds.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0190">To assess the biological plausibility of predicted associations, binding affinities were estimated using the physicochemical GNN model. As shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>C, the predicted TCM diffused targets exhibited a bimodal distribution, resembling the pattern of high-fidelity targets and contrasting with the lower-affinity profile of recorded TCM targets. This suggests that the diffusion approach successfully captures interaction patterns comparable to experimentally validated bioactive compounds. The impact of binding affinity thresholds on coverage was further analyzed. At a threshold of p<italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>i</sub> &gt; 5.0, the number of targets per compound reached a stable and meaningful level (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>D). Under this criterion, compound coverage increased from 7,631 to 62,744 (98.7% of all TCM compounds), as shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>E, and the number of covered targets (EntrezID) rose from 13,761 to 14,370 (99.0% of known human targets, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>F). The total number of compound-target associations expanded from 343,373 to 6,526,940, representing an over 18-fold increase.</p><p id="p0195">Further analysis of the feature representation methods, molecular weight, and target sequence length confirmed the reliability and broad applicability of this approach (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Figs. S1 and S2</xref> and Supplementary text in Supplementary data). These results demonstrate that the neighbor-diffusion strategy, combined with affinity-based filtering, substantially enhances both the breadth and confidence of compound-target associations. This provides a robust foundation for subsequent studies in mechanism discovery, drug repositioning, and indication expansion within the TCM domain.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Feature engineering and embedding of CHPs</title><p id="p0200">The multidimensional characteristics of CHPs introduce complexity into pharmacological research. To comprehensively represent their origin, medicinal properties, efficacy, and combination, we proposed a multimodal feature integration method. By combining feature engineering with vector embedding techniques, unified feature-vector representations were generated. Inspired by multimodal feature integration and multitask learning strategies [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], this approach provides a robust foundation for analyzing the roles of CHPs in complex compatibility mechanisms.</p><p id="p0205"><xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> outlines the encoding process for multisource CHP features and their dimensionality reduction visualizations. For the origin features, we extracted ten principal components using phylogenetic tree genetic distances and principal component analysis (PCA). These were combined with dummy variables for taxonomic kingdoms (plants, animals, fungi, algae, and minerals) to create a 15D origin feature vector. The extraction and phylogenetic structures of these features are detailed in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref>. Relational attributes, medicinal properties, efficacy, and combination features were encoded using the Word2Vec model, producing 15D medicinal property vectors, 30D efficacy vectors, and 30D compatibility vectors. To ensure consistency, all features were standardized before integration (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>A).<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Multi-feature encoding and dimensionality reduction analysis of Chinese herbal pieces (CHPs). (A) Workflow of multi-feature encoding for CHPs. Features include sources (encoded with one-hot and principal component analysis (PCA)), medicinal properties (vectorized using Word2Vec with window size = 5 and vector size = 15), efficacy (vectorized using Word2Vec with window size = 10 and vector size = 30), and combination relationships (vectorized using Word2Vec with window size = 10 and vector size = 30). <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-standardization was applied where necessary. Encoded feature dimensions are labeled as: sources one-hot (5), sources PCA (10), medicinal properties (15), efficacy (30), and combination (30). (B) Uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) projection of source features. (C–E) UMAP projections of features representing medicinal properties (C), combination relationships (D), and efficacy (E), respectively. (F) UMAP projection of combined features: medicinal properties, combination, and efficacy. (G) UMAP projection of all combined features, integrating sources, medicinal properties, efficacy, and combination. (H) <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-SNE) projection of all combined features. PC: principal component.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0075">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0210">UMAP revealed distinct characteristics for each feature type (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3</xref>B–E). The source features (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B) showed clear hierarchical structures that effectively clustered CHPs from different biological sources. Medicinal property features (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C) moderately represented flavor and nature information but exhibited weaker category distinctions. Combination features (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>D) captured synergistic relationships among CHPs but showed less defined boundaries. The efficacy features (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>E) excelled at linking CHPs to therapeutic applications with strong clustering patterns.</p><p id="p0215">To enhance expressiveness, the medicinal properties, efficacy, and combination features were merged into a composite relational feature (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>F), significantly improving category separation. Integrating the original features with this composite relational representation resulted in a 90D comprehensive feature vector (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>G). The UMAP projections of these integrated features displayed a robust structural organization and pronounced category boundaries, validating the multimodal feature fusion strategy for characterizing complex CHP attributes.</p><p id="p0220">To evaluate the dimensionality reduction methods, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-SNE) was used for comparison (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>H). The results aligned with the UMAP projections, showing a consistent category separation and reinforcing the robustness of the multimodal feature integration approach. This unified encoding strategy effectively integrated the origin, medicinal properties, efficacy, and combination attributes into a single feature representation. The resulting feature vectors provided a technical foundation for the data-driven characterization of CHPs, facilitating a deeper exploration of TCM mechanisms and CHF modeling.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Encoding and classification of medicinal properties and diagnostic terminologies in TCM</title><p id="p0225">The medicinal properties of CHPs, including therapeutic nature, flavor, and meridian tropism, form an interconnected system in TCM theory. To capture their internal relationships, we constructed an undirected co-occurrence network based on shared annotations. A heatmap of property interactions (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A) revealed strong co-occurrence among certain attributes. We modeled the network with properties as nodes and co-occurrence frequency as edge weights. The ForceAtlas2 algorithm optimized spatial layout, and Louvain community detection identified three functional clusters (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>B): cold-bitter-multi-meridian cluster, linked to heat-clearing and detoxifying CHPs (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Coptidis Rhizoma</italic>); hot-pungent-stomach cluster, reflecting warming and dispersing herbs (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Zingiberis Rhizoma</italic>); and mild-sweet/sour–liver/spleen/kidney cluster, associated with tonic and harmonizing herbs (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Ginseng Radix</italic>). Finally, a 23 × 23 coordinate encoding system was generated to represent medicinal properties numerically, preserving topological relationships for downstream modeling.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Analysis of medicinal properties and traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) diagnostic terminology. (A) Heatmap showing the association strengths between medicinal properties of Chinese herbal pieces (CHPs), with numeric values representing the logarithmic transformation of association frequencies. (B) Network distribution of medicinal properties, visualized with community detection and optimized layout, highlighting functional modules and interrelationships. (C) Network structure of TCM diagnostic terminologies, encompassing etiological factors, pathogenesis, treatment principles, treatment methods, traditional medicine patterns, and traditional medicine disorders, encoded into 32-dimensional (32D) vectors using Node2Vec. (D) Hierarchical clustering dendrogram of TCM diagnostic terminologies, classified into six major groups. (E) Proportional distribution of diagnostic terminologies across six TCM etiological types.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0080">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0230">To explore the structural relationships among TCM diagnostic terminologies, we constructed a terminology network based on co-occurrence within CPM formulas. Nodes represent terms such as etiology, pathogenesis, treatment principles, and treatment methods, while edges indicate shared presence in the same formula (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>C). This network reflects the semantic organization of clinical knowledge in TCM. Node embeddings were generated using Node2Vec and projected into a 32D feature space. Hierarchical clustering divided the terms into six categories (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>D). Further analysis revealed that each cluster comprised a mixture of etiological factors, pathogenic mechanisms, therapeutic methods, and related diagnostic concepts (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>E), suggesting vertical semantic integration across multiple levels of TCM reasoning. Detailed characteristics of each cluster are provided in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Figs. S4–S9</xref>; and due to its limited size, cluster 6 was excluded from further analysis.</p><p id="p0235">To characterize the diagnostic significance of these clusters, we applied node centrality metrics (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S10</xref> and Supplementary text in Supplementary data) to identify key features across the remaining five groups. These core features were integrated into a unified feature matrix spanning the five major TCM disease types (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Analysis of this matrix reveals that the five etiological clusters reflect a progressive pathological structure aligned with the TCM doctrine of “root deficiency and excess manifestation”. The clusters form a stratified system: metabolic and circulatory imbalances represent internal dysfunction underlying chronic conditions; organ aging and immune deficiency indicate systemic decline and constitutional weakness; lifestyle and environmental influences, along with physical and mental stress, reflect external and emotional triggers; while internal pathological changes and infectious factors represent disease consolidation associated with acute or epidemic causes. This structure outlines a logical progression from internal imbalance to external activation and overt disease, bridging classical TCM concepts with modern biomedical paradigms of metabolism, immunity, inflammation, and infection. The clusters thus not only reflect semantic coherence but also provide a structured framework for modeling the logic of TCM diagnosis and treatment.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Diagnostic characteristics of five major traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) etiological types.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0095">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCM etiological types</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Internal etiological</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">External pathogenic</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pathogenesis</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment principles</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment methods</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Traditional medicine patterns</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Traditional medicine disorders</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metabolic and circulatory imbalances within the body</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Internal cold and internal dampness</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Blood stasis due to Qi stagnation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Regulate and balance Yin and Yang</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Warm and tonify kidney Yang, supplement Qi, and nourish Yin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Qi and Yin deficiency pattern and spleen deficiency with phlegm dampness pattern</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wei-flaccidity, insomnia, chronic cough, and cold semen</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Organ aging and immune deficiency</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dual deficiency of Qi and Yin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reinforce healthy Qi to eliminate pathogenic factors</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tonify Qi and blood, induce urination, resolve oedema, soften hardness, and dissipate masses</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Deficiency of the liver and kidney pattern, Yang deficiency of the spleen, and kidney pattern</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Breast nodules, postpartum oligogalactia, hypersomnia, and wind oedema</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Influences of lifestyle factors and environmental</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stone and dietary irregularities</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pathogenic cold and pathogenic heat</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Qi counterflow and Yin deficiency leading to fire hyperactivity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reinforce healthy Qi to strengthen the body</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Circulate blood and transform stasis, tonify Qi and regulate and harmonize the spleen and stomach</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Qi and blood deficiency pattern and disharmony between the spleen and stomach pattern</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Insomnia, phlegm-fluid retention, acne, impotence, stomach reflux, and wasting of the middle Jiao</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical and mental stress and external stimuli</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Five exhaustions and seven damages</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pathogenic summer heat and pathogenic wind</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Qi impediment and recurrence due to overwork</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clear heat, eliminate dampness, and harmonize meridians</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liver Qi stagnation pattern and damp heat downflow pattern</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hemilateral head wind, dysmenorrhea, haemoptysis, knee impediment, and amenorrhoea</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Internal pathological changes and infectious factors</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Internal wind and static blood</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Seasonal pathogenic factors, epidemic pathogenic factor, pathogenic dampness, and pathogenic warmth</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Qi deficiency and reckless flow of blood due to heat</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transform phlegm, open the orifices, clear heat, remove toxins, and tonify Qi of the spleen and stomach</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Qi stagnation, blood stasis pattern, and phlegm fire blocked the heart spirit pattern</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Common cold, multiple boils, profuse nasal discharge, dampness pestilence, and cough</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>N/A: not applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Graph encoding and attention mechanisms for CHFs</title><p id="p0240">To model compatibility mechanisms in CHFs, we constructed a formula-level graph incorporating virtual nodes and applied three GNN variants, GTN, HGNN, and GAT, for structural encoding (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A). Nodes were categorized into actual nodes (CHPs) and virtual nodes representing therapeutic nature, medicinal flavor, and meridian tropism. Each CHP node was encoded with a 91D feature vector, consisting of source features (15), medicinal property features (15), combination features (30), efficacy features (30), and dosage weight (1). Edges captured the connections between CHPs and medicinal properties, with attributes encoded using a 23 × 23 matrix to quantify similarity across the nature-flavor-tropism dimensions. To capture higher-order compatibility patterns, virtual nodes connected CHPs sharing similar properties, forming hyperedges (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>B). This design allowed for a more expressive representation of property co-regulation and formula structure. Among the GNN models, GTN employed global attention to capture long-range functional interactions (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>C); HGNN aggregated information across hyperedges to model group-level compatibilities (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>D); and GAT applied edge-level attention to emphasize key CHPs and core compatibility units within the formula structure (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>E).<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Graph encoding and message-passing mechanisms for Chinese herbal formulas (CHFs). (A) Graph structure representing the associations between Chinese herbal pieces (CHPs) and virtual nodes corresponding to medicinal properties, including therapeutic nature, medicinal flavor, and meridian tropism. (B) Graph and hypergraph structures organized via virtual nodes. (C) Graph transformer network (GTN): attention mechanisms across all nodes. (D) Hypergraph neural network (HGNN): message passing along hyperedges. (E) Graph attention network (GAT): attention-based message passing along standard edges. (F) Feature-level contributions to model performance measured by area under the curve (AUC). (G) Node-level contributions to model performance measured by AUC.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0085">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0245">We optimized the model performance using a two-stage grid search combined with five-fold cross-validation to tune the structural parameters (hidden_dim, num_heads, and dropout_rate) and training parameters (learning_rate and batch_size). The optimal configurations were GTN (hidden_dim = 64, num_heads = 8, dropout_rate = 0.3, learning_rate = 0.0007, and batch_size = 128), HGNN (hidden_dim = 96, num_heads = 4, dropout_rate = 0.5, learning_rate = 0.0005, and batch_size = 64), and GAT (hidden_dim = 64, num_heads = 4, dropout_rate = 0.5, learning_rate = 0.0001, and batch_size = 32). Details of the optimization process are provided in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S11</xref> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S2</xref>.</p><p id="p0250">Model performance is summarized in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. GAT achieved the most balanced performance. It showed high AUC in metabolic and circulatory imbalances within the body (0.8918), internal pathological changes and infectious factors (0.8366), and influences of lifestyle factors and environmental (0.8013), along with leading values in accuracy (0.7924), F1 score (0.6790), and specificity (0.7783). HGNN achieved the highest AUC (0.8994) in metabolic and circulatory imbalances within the body and performed well in organ aging and immune deficiency (0.7766), but had lower precision in some categories. GTN performed well in selected types but was less stable overall, with a notably low AUC (0.6178) in physical and mental stress and external stimuli. In general, GAT offered the most consistent and reliable classification.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Performance comparison of graph neural network (GNN) models across five major traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) etiological types.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0100">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Model type</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Metrics</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Metabolic and circulatory imbalances within the body<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Organ aging and immune deficiency<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Influences of lifestyle and environmental conditions<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Physical and mental stress and external stimuli<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Internal pathological changes and infectious factors<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cal</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Val</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Test</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cal</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Val</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Test</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cal</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Val</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Test</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cal</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Val</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Test</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cal</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Val</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Test</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">GTN</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Precision</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1660</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1751</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1111</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1313</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1347</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1111</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7082</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6961</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7258</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1606</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1538</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1483</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5665</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5558</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5774</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recall</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8037</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8214</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7692</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8352</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8193</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6750</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.772</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7819</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7989</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5070</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5179</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5167</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7924</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7466</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7806</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F1 score</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2752</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2887</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1942</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2269</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2313</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1908</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7387</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7365</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7606</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2440</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2372</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2305</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6607</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6372</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6638</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUC</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8259</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8445</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8168</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7962</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7852</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7446</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.733</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6971</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7641</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6672</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6713</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6178</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8336</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8187</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8241</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7314</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7218</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7243</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6349</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6301</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6196</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.687</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6768</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7093</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6826</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6948</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6561</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7521</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7447</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7425</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specificity</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7265</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7144</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7222</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6211</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6163</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6157</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5729</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5329</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5866</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7023</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7126</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6716</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7345</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7439</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7241</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">HGNN</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Precision</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3133</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2768</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1947</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2621</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2218</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1655</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7895</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7574</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7578</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2559</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1843</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1961</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6758</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6241</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6301</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recall</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9074</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7381</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8462</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8938</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7349</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5750</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7368</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7210</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7011</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8279</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6518</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6667</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7978</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7057</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7041</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F1 score</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4658</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4026</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3165</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4053</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3408</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2570</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7622</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7388</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7284</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3910</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2874</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3030</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7318</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6624</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6651</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUC</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9558</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8869</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8994</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9386</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8028</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7766</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8209</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7674</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7841</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8627</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7323</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7317</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8909</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8295</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8445</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.868</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8494</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8422</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8318</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8069</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7791</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7366</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7054</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6977</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7394</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7038</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6944</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8219</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7840</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7691</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specificity</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8653</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8576</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8420</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8275</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8121</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7936</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7364</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6841</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6929</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7295</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7090</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6974</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8324</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8175</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">GAT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Precision</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2241</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2207</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1489</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2191</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2150</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1825</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7465</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7289</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7647</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2190</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1802</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2113</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6182</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6104</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6203</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recall</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8407</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7857</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8077</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7656</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7590</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6250</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7618</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7691</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7471</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7140</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6518</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7500</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7809</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7384</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7500</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F1 score</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3539</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3446</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2515</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3407</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3351</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2825</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7541</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7484</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7558</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3352</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2824</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3297</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6901</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6683</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6790</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUC</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9004</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8842</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8918</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8736</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8347</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8106</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7939</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7650</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8013</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7757</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7341</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7589</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8644</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8393</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8366</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8052</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7946</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7924</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8099</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7954</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7890</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7152</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7013</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7209</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7138</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6964</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6960</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7864</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7799</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7691</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specificity</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8028</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7953</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7917</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8130</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7981</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8007</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6527</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6085</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6850</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7138</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7009</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6900</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7889</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7977</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7783</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The dataset comprises 6,080 samples, divided into 4,256 calibration set (Cal), 1,222 validation set (Val), and 602 testing set (Test), following a 7:2:1 split. Positive sample proportions for the five major TCM etiological types are as follows: metabolic and circulatory imbalances within the body: Cal (training set) (6.34%), Val (6.87%), and Test (4.32%); organ aging and immune deficiency: Cal (6.41%), Val (6.79%), and Test (6.64%); influences of lifestyle and environmental conditions: Cal (57.31%), Val (57.77%), and Test (57.81%); physical and mental stress and external stimuli: Cal (10.10%), Val (9.17%), and Test (9.97%); and internal pathological changes and infectious factors: Cal (30.45%), Val (30.03%), and Test (32.56%). GTN: graph transformer network; Precision: positive predictive value; Recall: sensitivity (true positive rate); F1 score: F1 measure (harmonic mean of precision and recall); AUC: area under the curve; Accuracy: classification accuracy; HGNN: hypergraph neural network; Specificity: true negative rate; HGNN: hypergraph neural network; GAT: graph attention network.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0255">To further investigate the internal mechanisms of GAT model, we conducted feature and node masking experiments. AUC change was used to quantify the impact of each input type (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S3</xref> for full results). The compatibility feature was identified as the most influential, indicating its key role in capturing herbal compatibility (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>F). Source and medicinal property features followed, while dosage had minimal effect. Node-level masking showed that CHP nodes had the greatest impact on prediction, with a significant drop in AUC after masking. In contrast, therapeutic nature, medicinal flavor, and meridian tropism nodes contributed less (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>G). Changes in prediction outputs before and after masking (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S12</xref>) further confirmed the dominant role of combination features and CHP nodes.</p><p id="p0260">In conclusion, the graph-encoding method with virtual nodes significantly improves the modeling of multidimensional relationships in the CHF. The GAT model, with its superior classification performance and feature interpretability, has emerged as the most effective model for uncovering complex compatibility mechanisms. The CHP nodes and combination features were identified as the core factors for CHF prediction. All research outcomes, including methods and data, are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ZENGJingqi/GraphAI-for-TCM" id="intref0180">https://github.com/ZENGJingqi/GraphAI-for-TCM</ext-link>, enabling users to analyze the prediction results and attention weights among the CHPs. This provides robust scientific support for further studies on the CHF compatibility mechanisms.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Compatibility mechanisms in CHFs used for COVID-19 management</title><p id="p0265">This study analyzed 215 CHFs used in the prevention and treatment of COVID-19, sourced from official guidelines issued by provincial health commissions, TCM administrations, and local governments across China. Of these, 186 formulas were collected from regional treatment protocols, and 29 were included in the Diagnosis and Treatment Protocol for Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia (Trial Version 8) released by China's National Health Commission. All formulas were designed for adult patients and included 167 therapeutic and 48 preventive prescriptions (details in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S4</xref>). Using the GAT model, most formulas were classified under the category of internal pathological changes and infectious factors, based on their predicted distribution across the five TCM etiological types (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A). This result aligns with TCM theories regarding COVID-19 etiology [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and supports the model's ability to capture disease-specific compatibility patterns. Detailed model outputs and attention weights between nodes are provided in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S5</xref>.<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Analysis of compatibility mechanisms in Chinese herbal formulas (CHFs) for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) management. (A) Heatmap of model-predicted associations between 215 CHFs used in COVID-19 management and five major traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) etiological types, reflecting the distribution of predicted pathological patterns across formulas. (B) Attention weight matrix of Chinese herbal pieces (CHPs) in the Huashi Baidu decoction. Each cell represents the strength of information flow from one CHP (row: source of attention) to another (column: target of attention), highlighting the directional and asymmetric nature of attention. (C) Top 10 highest attention weights among CHPs, selected from those with a frequency greater than 10 across all formulas. (D) Top 10 highest attention weights among herb pairs, selected from pairs with a co-occurrence frequency greater than 10 across all formulas. (E, F) Mass spectrometry (MS)-based chemical profiling of <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic> (E) and <italic toggle="yes">Rhizoma Phragmitis</italic> (F), showing the number and intensity of detected peaks in both positive and negative ion modes, as well as the proportion of identified compounds. (G) CHP-compound-target-pathway network for <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Rhizoma Phragmitis</italic>, illustrating multi-level mechanisms of action. NA: not applicable. <italic toggle="yes">CYGB</italic>: cytoglobin; <italic toggle="yes">GABBR2</italic>: gamma-aminobutyric acid type B receptor subunit 2; <italic toggle="yes">HTR2C</italic>: 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor 2C; <italic toggle="yes">ADRA1B</italic>: alpha-1B adrenergic receptor; <italic toggle="yes">CYSLTR1</italic>: cysteinyl leukotriene receptor 1; <italic toggle="yes">DRD2</italic>: dopamine receptor D2; <italic toggle="yes">ADRB3</italic>: beta-3 adrenergic receptor; <italic toggle="yes">TAAR1</italic>: trace amine-associated receptor 1; <italic toggle="yes">BCHE</italic>: butyrylcholinesterase.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0090">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0270">After efficacy classification, we used the GAT model to analyze internal structure in CHFs based on attention weights between CHPs. Herbs that consistently exert high attention to others are considered dominant (monarch), those receiving strong attention support the main function (minister), and herbs with low, peripheral attention play auxiliary roles (assistant or guide). Using Huashi Baidu decoction as an example, a formula clinically validated for COVID-19 treatment [<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], the attention map (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>B) showed that <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic> exerted the strongest attention across the network, indicating a leading role in the formula. Mid-level herbs such as <italic toggle="yes">Semen Lepidii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Radix Paeoniae Alba</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Semen Armeniacae Amarum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fructus Tsaoko</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Herba Agastaches</italic> showed stable interactions with <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic> and acted as minister herbs. Other CHPs, such as <italic toggle="yes">Gypsum Fibrosum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Poria</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Radix Glycyrrhizae</italic>, had lower attention scores but maintained broad connections across the network. These played supporting roles in harmonizing and guiding the formula.</p><p id="p0275">We further analyzed average attention weights across all CHFs to identify key herbs and herb pairs (detailed results are provided in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S6</xref>). To ensure reliability, only CHPs and herb pairs with a frequency greater than 10 were included, excluding low-frequency items with potentially inflated weights. As shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>C, <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic> consistently ranked highest in attention weights across multiple efficacy categories, confirming its central role. In the herb pair analysis (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>D), the pair <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">Rhizoma Phragmitis</italic> showed the highest attention value, followed by <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">Herba Agastaches</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">Flos Lonicerae Japonicae</italic>. These results highlight the importance of <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic> and its key combinations in COVID-19-related CHFs.</p><p id="p0280">A total of 215 compounds were identified in <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic> and 17 in <italic toggle="yes">Rhizoma Phragmitis</italic> using MS (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figs. 6</xref>E and F; detailed data are provided in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S7</xref> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S8</xref>). Based on compound-target predictions (p<italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>i</sub> &gt; 9.0 for Radix Astragaliand p<italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>i</sub> &gt; 8.0 for <italic toggle="yes">Rhizoma Phragmitis</italic>), a multi-level CHP-compound-target-pathway network was constructed (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>G; full dataset available in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S9</xref>). Representative compounds included corydalin and methylinissolin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside from <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic>, and pingbeinine from <italic toggle="yes">Rhizoma Phragmitis</italic>. These compounds converged on shared targets enriched in three key pathways: neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction, involving neurotransmitter receptors (e.g., 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor 2C (<italic toggle="yes">HTR2C</italic>) and dopamine receptor D2 (<italic toggle="yes">DRD2</italic>)), suggesting synergy in regulating neuroimmune responses and alleviating COVID-19-related neurological symptoms. The targets are involved in the response to xenobiotic stimulus, indicating enhanced defense against external stressors through targets like butyrylcholinesterase (<italic toggle="yes">BCHE</italic>) and cysteinyl leukotriene receptor 1 (<italic toggle="yes">CYSLTR1</italic>). They are also associated with the neuronal cell body, implying direct involvement in neuronal structure and function. Despite differing chemical profiles, the two herbs show strong target-level complementarity and potential synergistic regulation across neural, immune, and detoxification pathways.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0285">This study presents a novel framework for modeling compatibility mechanisms in TCM by integrating multidimensional data with GraphAI. Through the construction of a comprehensive TCM-MKG, and the implementation of interpretable GNN models, we addressed long-standing challenges in TCM research, including the lack of structured knowledge representation, the complexity of formula compatibility, and the limited explainability of computational models. The findings demonstrate that our approach not only enhances the semantic expressiveness and interpretability of TCM theory in a digital context, but also holds practical value in supporting mechanism-driven drug discovery. Below, we discuss three key dimensions of this work: data integration and standardization, mechanism modeling of compatibility theory, and substance-based discovery in real-world applications.</p><p id="p0290">The TCM-MKG developed in this study represents a critical advancement in the standardization and high-dimensional integration of TCM knowledge. By incorporating seven core modules, including TCM terminology, CPM, CHPs, PO, compounds, targets, and diseases, TCM-MKG offers semantic consistency and structural interoperability that surpass existing TCM databases such as TCMID [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], ETCM [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and TCMSP [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The ontology-driven design enables a transition from fragmented knowledge points to a semantically structured network, thereby supporting the full pipeline from concept definition to mechanism inference. In particular, the standardized terminology module allows for the computational representation of abstract TCM concepts such as etiology, syndrome differentiation, and treatment principles. At the compound-target layer, a neighbor-diffusion strategy significantly alleviated structural biases in prior datasets, raising target coverage from 12.0% to 98.7%, and enabling a more balanced foundation for downstream pharmacological modeling. This multidimensional and open-source infrastructure provides a scalable platform for future integration with omics data and electronic medical records, supporting data-driven modernization of TCM.</p><p id="p0295">Building upon the TCM-MKG, we proposed a mechanism-driven paradigm for modeling formula compatibility using GATs and virtual node structures. This approach aligns closely with the holistic perspective and multi-layered reasoning logic of TCM. By embedding diagnostic terminologies, medicinal properties (e.g., therapeutic nature, flavor, and meridian tropism) and efficacy types into a unified graph structure, we established a computational representation of core TCM concepts. One of the key innovations was the reconstruction of the medicinal property network, enabling the modular division of herbal features through unsupervised clustering. Furthermore, a theoretical classification model of five major compatibility categories, ranging from metabolic imbalance to infection, was derived from diagnostic node clusters. This system reflects a progressive disease logic consistent with TCM pattern differentiation, providing a structured foundation for disease modeling and syndrome-specific formula design.</p><p id="p0300">Crucially, the attention-based GAT model enabled interpretable quantification of inter-CHP relationships, mapping the classical “monarch-minister-assistant-guide” framework into a directed, weighted graph. Case studies on representative formulas such as Huashi Baidu decoction demonstrated the model's ability to identify core and auxiliary CHPs, revealing synergistic structures consistent with expert knowledge. Compared to existing models that focus on “formula-disease” or “herb-target” mappings [<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>], our framework emphasizes the internal structure of formula logic, offering a novel perspective on the representation of TCM compatibility.</p><p id="p0305">To assess the real-world applicability of our model, we analyzed 215 CHFs used in COVID-19 management. The GAT model consistently highlighted <italic toggle="yes">Radix Astragali</italic>, often paired with <italic toggle="yes">Rhizoma Phragmitis</italic>, as a key compatibility unit across these formulas. This herb pair exhibited strong model attention and therapeutic relevance, aligning with TCM principles and known clinical practices. Their involvement in immune and neuroactive pathways suggests potential utility in addressing long-COVID conditions [<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>]. These results demonstrate the model's ability to uncover interpretable compatibility patterns with practical clinical implications. Notably, both herbal pieces have high safety profiles and are commonly consumed as dietary ingredients in traditional Chinese food therapy. Given their regulatory potential and accessibility, this herb pair holds promise for diet-based interventions in managing long COVID-19 [<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], especially in subclinical or recovery-phase populations.</p><p id="p0310">While this study provides a comprehensive framework for TCM compatibility modeling and substance discovery, several limitations remain. First, the current approach relies primarily on computational inference, lacking direct experimental validation at the molecular or clinical level. Although we introduced MS analysis to support our computational predictions, we fully acknowledge that targeted <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> validation is essential to further strengthen the biological credibility of our findings. This remains a critical limitation of our study, and future work will incorporate <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> assays, as well as real-world clinical data, to strengthen biological credibility. Second, the modeling framework focuses primarily on herbal-level interactions and does not yet fully integrate multiscale data such as compound metabolism, target expression, or host-pathogen interactions. Expanding the model to capture these biological layers will enhance its precision and applicability. Third, the current framework does not yet support automated formula generation or personalized optimization. Future extensions may include generative graph models to enable new formula design and individualized TCM recommendation.</p><p id="p0315">Moreover, the cross-cultural applicability of this framework presents exciting opportunities. Its adaptable architecture allows for the incorporation of theories and data from other traditional medicine systems, such as Tibetan, Mongolian, or Uyghur medicine. Notably, we have already applied this technical framework to Uyghur medicine by integrating its unique humoral constitution theory to quantify compatibility mechanisms. The results are currently being systematized and will be shared in forthcoming publications. Moving forward, we plan to extend this methodology to other traditional systems worldwide. Additionally, recent international initiatives, such as the WHO-led global technical meeting on AI applications in traditional medicine, underscore the growing momentum to apply AI in traditional knowledge systems [<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Our GraphAI-based approach may serve as a transferable tool in this global movement, supporting comparative studies that explore both shared compatibility principles and culturally distinct medical logics.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0320">By combining a semantically rich knowledge graph with interpretable GraphAI models, this study offers a mechanism-aware and data-driven framework for modeling Chinese herbal compatibility. It bridges traditional theory with modern computational logic, supports active substance identification, and lays the groundwork for precision TCM and new drug discovery. The proposed approach marks a significant step toward the modernization, quantification, and internationalization of TCM.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0325"><bold>Jingqi Zeng:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Writing – original draft, Visualization, Validation, Software, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation. <bold>Xiaobin Jia:</bold> Supervision, Project administration, Funding acquisition, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Declaration of generative AI and AI-assisted technologies in the writing process</title><p id="p0330">During the preparation of this work, the authors used ChatGPT, an AI language model developed by OpenAI, in order to improve the clarity and wording of the written English. After using this tool, the authors reviewed and edited the content as needed and take full responsibility for the content of the publication.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0335">The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systems theory-driven framework for AI integration into the holistic material basis research of traditional Chinese medicine</article-title><source>Engineering</source><volume>40</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanisms and clinical application of Traditional Chinese Medicine Lianhua-Qingwen capsule</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>142</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">111998</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8352581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34385103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness and safety of traditional Chinese medicine in treating COVID-19: Clinical evidence from China</article-title><source>Aging Dis.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1850</fpage><lpage>1856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34881072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14336/AD.2021.0906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8612612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wedding rigorous scientific methodology and ancient herbal wisdom to benefit cancer patients: The development of PHY906</article-title><source>Oncology (Williston Park)</source><volume>32</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>e20</fpage><lpage>e27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29492950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of artificial intelligence on traditional Chinese medicine</article-title><source>Am. J. Chin. Med.</source><volume>49</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>1314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34247564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1142/S0192415X21500622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Advances in the application of traditional Chinese medicine using artificial intelligence: A review</article-title><source>Am. J. Chin. Med.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37417927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1142/S0192415X23500490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative knowledge presentation models of traditional Chinese medicine (TCM): A review</article-title><source>Artif. Intell. Med.</source><volume>103</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101810</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.artmed.2020.101810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32143806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Network medicine framework reveals generic herb-symptom effectiveness of traditional Chinese medicine</article-title><source>Sci. Adv.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">eadh0215</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/sciadv.adh0215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10610911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37889962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and application of traditional Chinese medicine using AI machine learning and deep learning strategies</article-title><source>Am. J. Chin. Med.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38715181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1142/S0192415X24500265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noori</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Graph artificial intelligence in medicine</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biomed. Data Sci.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38749465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-biodatasci-110723-024625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11344018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toward better drug discovery with knowledge graph</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</source><volume>72</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34649044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.sbi.2021.09.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FordNet: Recommending traditional Chinese medicine formula via deep neural network integrating phenotype and molecule</article-title><source>Pharmacol. Res.</source><volume>173</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105752</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phrs.2021.105752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34481072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group><part-title>WHO International Standard Terminologies on Traditional Chinese Medicine, Geneva</part-title><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref14"><source>Pharmacopoeia Commission of the Ministry of Health of The People’s Republic of China, Pharmacopoeia of The People’s Republic of China 2020 Edition</source><edition>English ed.</edition><year>2020</year><publisher-name>China Medical Science and Technology Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NCBI Resource Coordinators</collab></person-group><article-title>Database resources of the national center for biotechnology information</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>43</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>D6</fpage><lpage>D17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25398906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gku1130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4383943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TCMID 2.0: A comprehensive resource for TCM</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>46</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>D1117</fpage><lpage>D1120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29106634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkx1028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5753259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TCMBank: Bridges between the largest herbal medicines, chemical ingredients, target proteins, and associated diseases with intelligence text mining</article-title><source>Chem. Sci.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>10684</fpage><lpage>10701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37829020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/d3sc02139d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10566508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SymMap: An integrative database of traditional Chinese medicine enhanced by symptom mapping</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>D1110</fpage><lpage>D1117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30380087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gky1021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6323958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HIT 2.0: An enhanced platform for Herbal Ingredients’ Targets</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>50</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>D1238</fpage><lpage>D1243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34986599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkab1011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8728248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HERB 2.0: an updated database integrating clinical and experimental evidence for traditional Chinese medicine</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>53</volume><year>2025</year><fpage>D1404</fpage><lpage>D1414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39558177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkae1037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11701625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ETCM v2.0: An update with comprehensive resource and rich annotations for traditional Chinese medicine</article-title><source>Acta Pharm. Sin. B</source><volume>13</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>2559</fpage><lpage>2571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37425046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.apsb.2023.03.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10326295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ru</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TCMSP: A database of systems pharmacology for drug discovery from herbal medicines</article-title><source>J. Cheminform.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24735618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1758-2946-6-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4001360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CMAUP database update 2024: Extended functional and association information of useful plants for biomedical research</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>D1508</fpage><lpage>D1518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37897343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkad921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10767869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leber</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NPClassifier: A deep neural network-based structural classification tool for natural products</article-title><source>J. Nat. Prod.</source><volume>84</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>2795</fpage><lpage>2807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34662515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.jnatprod.1c00399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8631337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feunang</surname><given-names>Y.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DrugBank 5.0: A major update to the DrugBank database for 2018</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>D1074</fpage><lpage>D1082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29126136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkx1037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5753335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TTD: Therapeutic Target Database describing target druggability information</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>D1465</fpage><lpage>D1477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37713619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkad751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10767903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Mering</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STITCH 5: Augmenting protein-chemical interaction networks with tissue and affinity data</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>D380</fpage><lpage>D384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26590256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkv1277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4702904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilson</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baitaluk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BindingDB in 2015: A public database for medicinal chemistry, computational chemistry and systems pharmacology</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>D1045</fpage><lpage>D1053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26481362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkv1072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4702793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amode</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneja</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ensembl 2023</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>D933</fpage><lpage>D941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36318249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkac958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9825606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UniProt Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>UniProt: The universal protein knowledgebase in 2023</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>D523</fpage><lpage>D531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36408920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkac1052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9825514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koutrouli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The STRING database in 2023: Protein-protein association networks and functional enrichment analyses for any sequenced genome of interest</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>D638</fpage><lpage>D646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36370105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkac1000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9825434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo Surdo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iannuccelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Contino</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SIGNOR 3.0, the SIGnaling network open resource 3.0: 2022 update</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>D631</fpage><lpage>D637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36243968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkac883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9825604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Licata</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briganti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MINT, the molecular interaction database: 2012 update</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>D857</fpage><lpage>D861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22096227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkr930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3244991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Toro</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ragueneau</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The IntAct database: Efficient access to fine-grained molecular interaction data</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>50</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>D648</fpage><lpage>D653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34761267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkab1006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8728211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breitkreutz</surname><given-names>B.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reguly</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BioGRID: A general repository for interaction datasets</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>34</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>D535</fpage><lpage>D539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkj109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1347471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodenreider</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Unified Medical Language System (UMLS): Integrating biomedical terminology</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>32</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>D267</fpage><lpage>D270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkh061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC308795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schor</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The DO-KB Knowledgebase: A 20-year journey developing the disease open science ecosystem</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>D1305</fpage><lpage>D1314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37953304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkad1051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10767934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piñero</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saüch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The DisGeNET cytoscape app: Exploring and visualizing disease genomics data</article-title><source>Comput. Struct. Biotechnol. J.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>2960</fpage><lpage>2967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34136095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.csbj.2021.05.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8163863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiegers</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiegers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CTD tetramers: A new online tool that computationally links curated chemicals, genes, phenotypes, and diseases to inform molecular mechanisms for environmental health</article-title><source>Toxicol. Sci.</source><volume>195</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37486259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/toxsci/kfad069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10535784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grissa</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Junge</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oprea</surname><given-names>T.I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diseases 2.0: A weekly updated database of disease-gene associations from text mining and data integration</article-title><source>Database (Oxford)</source><volume>2022</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>baac019</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35348648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/database/baac019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9216524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>A.T.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical graph neural network for learning protein–ligand interaction fingerprints from sequence data</article-title><source>Nat. Mach. Intell.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>687</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multitask joint strategies of self-supervised representation learning on biomedical networks for drug discovery</article-title><source>Nat. Mach. Intell.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>456</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bioactive compounds from Huashi Baidu decoction possess both antiviral and anti-inflammatory effects against COVID-19</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A</source><volume>120</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2301775120</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.2301775120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10160982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37094153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transformer- and generative adversarial network-based inpatient traditional Chinese medicine prescription recommendation: Development study</article-title><source>JMIR Med. Inform.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e35239</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2196/35239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9198826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35639469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PresRecRF: Herbal prescription recommendation via the representation fusion of large TCM semantics and molecular knowledge</article-title><source>Phytomedicine</source><volume>135</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">156116</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phymed.2024.156116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39396402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neural network analysis of Chinese herbal medicine prescriptions for patients with colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Complement. Ther. Med.</source><volume>42</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30670255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ctim.2018.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Application of weighted gene co-expression network and immune infiltration for explorations of key genes in the brain of elderly COVID-19 patients</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><volume>14</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1157179</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1157179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10102454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37063869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adnan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network pharmacology study to elucidate the key targets of underlying antihistamines against COVID-19</article-title><source>Curr. Issues Mol. Biol.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1597</fpage><lpage>1609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35723367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cimb44040109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9164076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole-transcriptome sequencing data reveals a disparate cognitive and immune signature in COVID-19 patients with and without dementia</article-title><source>J. Med. Virol.</source><volume>95</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e28177</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jmv.28177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9538945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36168207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antar</surname><given-names>A.A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translating insights into therapies for long covid</article-title><source>Sci. Transl. Med.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">eado2106</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/scitranslmed.ado2106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12173445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39536116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group><article-title>Kicking off the journey of artificial intelligence in traditional medicine</article-title><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news/item/13-09-2024-kicking-off-the-journey-of-artificial-intelligence-in-traditional-medicine" id="intref0010a">https://www.who.int/news/item/13-09-2024-kicking-off-the-journey-of-artificial-intelligence-in-traditional-medicine</ext-link></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0345">The following are the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 2</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 2</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 3</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc3.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 3</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 4</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc4.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 4</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 5</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc5.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 5</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 6</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc6.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 6</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 7</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc7.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 7</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 8</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc8.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 8</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 9</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc9.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 9</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 10</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc10.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 10</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0340">This research was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (Grant No.: <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">82230117</award-id>). This work benefited from the integration of data from numerous open-access and authoritative databases. We acknowledge the valuable contributions of resources such as DrugBank, BindingDB, BioGRID, DisGeNET, and many others. These datasets provided essential insights into TCM, modern drug chemistry, genetics, diseases, and related fields, forming the foundation for the TCM-MKG used in this study. Furthermore, we utilized the PSICHIC model (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/huankoh/PSICHIC" id="intref0185">https://github.com/huankoh/PSICHIC</ext-link>) to analyze the binding interactions between components and targets. Full citations for these resources are included in the manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="d36e918"><p id="ntpara0010">Peer review under responsibility of Xi'an Jiaotong University.</p></fn><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0350">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpha.2025.101342" id="intref0190">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpha.2025.101342</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>