<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">63</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcph</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12641946</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12641946.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12641946</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12641946</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41286763</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-025-25457-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">25457</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The hidden burden: prevalence and risk factors of long COVID among university students in Chiang Mai, Thailand</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Assavanopakun</surname><given-names initials="P">Pheerasak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wangkawong</surname><given-names initials="S">Suphapich</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiratipaisarl</surname><given-names initials="W">Wuttipat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sirikul</surname><given-names initials="W">Wachiranun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Promkutkao</surname><given-names initials="T">Tharntip</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Promkutkeo</surname><given-names initials="S">Suchat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitro</surname><given-names initials="A">Amornphat</given-names></name><address><email>amornphat.kit@cmu.ac.th</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05m2fqn25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7132.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9039 7662</institution-id><institution>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Chiang Mai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chiang Mai, 50200 Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05m2fqn25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7132.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9039 7662</institution-id><institution>Environmental and Occupational Medicine Excellence Center (EnOMEC), Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Chiang Mai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chiang Mai, 50200 Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05m2fqn25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7132.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9039 7662</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Chiang Mai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chiang Mai, 50200 Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05m2fqn25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7132.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9039 7662</institution-id><institution>Department of Biomedical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Chiang Mai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chiang Mai, 50200 Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05m2fqn25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7132.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9039 7662</institution-id><institution>School of Economics, Faculty of Economics, </institution><institution>Chiang Mai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chiang Mai, 50200 Thailand </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478168</issue-id><elocation-id>4123</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-26 11:25:13.227"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12889_2025_Article_25457.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">As the COVID-19 pandemic transitions to an endemic phase, long COVID symptoms following SARS-CoV-2 infection have emerged as a new global health challenge. However, its impact on university students remains underexplored. This study aimed to assess the prevalence of long COVID symptoms and identify its predictive factors.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A cross-sectional study was conducted from February to August 2023 among Thai university students in Chiang Mai. An online questionnaire collected data on demographics, COVID-19 history, vaccination, and health status. Multivariable binary logistic regression was used to identify factors associated with long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 997 students participated (60.5% female, mean age 20.6 years). Of these, 60.9% had received at least three COVID-19 vaccine doses, and 21.4% had received more than three mRNA vaccine doses. The prevalence of long COVID symptoms was 21.9% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 218). Common symptoms included respiratory issues (54.6%), neurological complaints (50.4%), psychological symptoms (42.7%), and poor sleep quality (34.9%). Significant predictors of long COVID included severe initial infection (aOR = 15.3; 95% CI: 5.3–44.3; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), longer illness duration (aOR = 1.05; 95% CI: 1.0-1.1; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.031), and poor sleep quality (aOR = 2.1; 95% CI: 1.4–3.1). Each additional dose of mRNA vaccine reduced the likelihood of severe outcomes by 14% (aOR = 0.86; 95% CI: 0.8-1.0; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.044).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">A minority of Thai university students reported long COVID symptoms. Vaccination, especially with multiple mRNA doses, was linked to reduced risk. Early detection and targeted support during recovery may help mitigate long-term health consequences in this group.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12889-025-25457-3.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Risk factor</kwd><kwd>University students</kwd><kwd>Thailand</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100010731</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>No.074/2566</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Promkutkao</surname><given-names>Tharntip</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Since the World Health Organization (WHO) declared COVID-19 a global pandemic on March 11, 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] The world has faced profound and lasting health challenges. Although many countries have transitioned from a pandemic to an endemic phase, a significant concern remains: the persistence of symptoms long after the acute infection has resolved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This condition, commonly referred to as “long COVID,” “long-term COVID,” or “post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection (PASC),” has emerged as a growing public health issue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Typically, the viral load becomes undetectable within a few weeks after diagnosis, marking the end of the acute phase and the beginning of the post-acute period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, many individuals continue to experience a range of physical, neurological, and psychological symptoms beyond this point, highlighting the long-term impact of SARS-CoV-2 infection on multiple organ systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Understanding long COVID is essential for effective prevention, management, and support strategies in the ongoing response to the pandemic.</p><p id="Par6">Long COVID can manifest in a variety of ways, including neuropsychiatric, cardiorespiratory, gastrointestinal, dermatologic, and other symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The incidence of symptoms such as fatigue and headache, as well as other factors associated with long COVID among children and adolescents, was reported worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], even though there were a few reports in Thailand. Several studies have found that being female, having more than five early symptoms, having severe acute COVID-19, and having few previous COVID-19 vaccines or boosters are some of the most important higher-risk factors for long COVID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. One previous study found that age, underlying allergy diseases, and residing in polluted locations may be related to long COVID, although it was conducted in young children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Some children and adolescents with COVID-19 had long-term infections and disabilities, while many experienced symptoms despite testing negative for the virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Immunization is another key to large-scale disease prevention. Immunizing a large section of the population can boost community immunity through herd immunity. If vaccine coverage is high enough, it can prevent the disease from spreading [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. There might be an alteration in strong health measurements since COVID-19 has been downgraded from a communicable disease to a communicable disease under surveillance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Evidence on the prevalence of long COVID-19 symptoms among adolescents in Thailand, particularly university students, remains limited. This study aims to assess the prevalence of long COVID among university students in Chiang Mai, Thailand, and to identify factors associated with the development of long COVID symptoms in this population. The study offers a novel contribution by focusing on university students. The findings may inform the development of targeted interventions for early symptom detection and timely management by the public health sector and relevant stakeholders, emphasizing prevention and appropriate care for individuals with prior COVID-19 infection or those at risk of developing Long COVID. Moreover, the results can guide school- and university-based strategies to design health support systems and learning platforms that are responsive to students’ educational needs and well-being in the post-COVID era.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design, study population, and sample size estimation</title><p id="Par8">This cross-sectional study was conducted between February and August 2023 using an online survey targeting undergraduate students from seven universities in Chiang Mai, Thailand—the country’s second-largest province, with a total university student population of 83,877. Data were collected via REDCap (Research Electronic Data Capture), a secure, web-based platform designed for managing research data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Before data collection, the research team contacted university administrators and obtained approval letters from the deans of each institution. During the data collection phase, we collaborated with university COVID-19 prevention teams to explain the study’s objectives, procedures, and data collection methods. Designated university coordinators facilitated the distribution of the online survey to students (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). To ensure confidentiality, coordinators were informed that they would not have access to the survey responses or the identities of participating students. Participation was entirely voluntary and had no impact on students’ academic standing. The definition of Long COVID in this study was followed the UK National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE), which defines “Long COVID” as the presence of persistent symptoms lasting 4 weeks or more after acute infection, in the absence of an alternative etiological diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">The required sample size was estimated using the finite population prevalence estimation method, assuming a 9.1% prevalence of post-infection symptoms at three months, with a 2% absolute error margin (d) and a 0.05 alpha level. This yielded a minimum required sample size of 787 participants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study Flow Diagram</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e374" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_25457_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Questionnaire design</title><p id="Par11">The questionnaire for this study was developed and disseminated by the Ministry of Public Health of Thailand for direct use by medical personnel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The questionnaire was divided into four main sections:</p><p id="Par12">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par13">Project Details and Consent: Information about the study and a consent form for participants.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par14">Personal and Sociodemographic Information: This includes details such as age, gender, year of study, university affiliation, and type of discipline.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par15">COVID-19 History and Health Data: This covers self-reported COVID-19 infections, vaccination history, treatments received, and post-infection symptoms. The post-infection symptoms were classified according to the organ system. The symptom categories included ten organ systems: respiratory, psychiatric, neurological, musculoskeletal, cardiovascular, dermatological, otolaryngological, immunological, gastrointestinal, and reproductive. Furthermore, nonspecific symptoms and sleep quality were distinct categories incorporated in this section.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par16">Activities and Preventive Behaviors: Assesses participants’ behaviors after the “new normal” period, including mask usage when outdoors, use of alcohol-based hand sanitizers, and social distancing practices. Responses were categorized as “never,” “sometimes (occasionally practiced), or “always (practice that behavior regularly every time there is a risk of virus exposure).</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par17">An assessment of the qualitative questionnaire’s content validity was performed following the adaptation of the Ministry of Public Health’s questionnaire, created in conjunction with the Health Promotion Foundation. It underwent a content validity review by three experts, including a specialist in COVID-19 control and prevention from the Chiang Mai Provincial Public Health Office, a public health expert from Chiang Mai University, and a research instrument specialist from Chiang Mai University. The Cronbach’s alpha coefficient values for all sections of the questionnaire were above 0.7, ranging from 0.713 for the respiratory system to 0.942 for behavioral practices. Details for each subdomain are provided in the Supplementary Material (Table S1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par18">All statistical analyses were performed using the statistical software STATA (Stata Corp. 2019, Stata Statistical Software: Release 16, Stata Corp LLC, College Station, TX, USA). For the categorical data, the personal information, details of outside activities, preventive or risky behaviors, willingness for vaccination, and COVID-19 information resources were described by a frequency and a percentage (n (%)). The continuous variables were described using a mean with a standard deviation (SD) for parametric data or a median with an interquartile range (IQR) for non-parametric data. A comprehensive exploratory analysis using a multivariable binary logistic regression was conducted to identify factors associated with long COVID-19 at one month; robust variance correction was used to address potential outliers and influential observations. Covariates for inclusion in the regression models were selected based on a well-established theoretical framework aligned with the research objectives and hypotheses. Variance inflation factor (VIF) was explored to examine the collinearity of determinants included in the statistical model. The threshold VIF of more than 10 indicated the risk of collinearity. The study findings were reported by the STROBE (Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology) reporting guideline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. All statistical analyses were performed on a two-tailed basis, and a p-value of less than 0.05 was regarded as statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Ethical considerations</title><p id="Par19">This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Thailand (Study Code: COM-2565–09280). Informed consent was obtained from all subjects involved in the study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Result</title><p id="Par20">A total of 1,087 participants were recruited and consented to participate in the study, of whom 997 were included in the analysis. Ninety participants were excluded due to incomplete questionnaire. Among the 997 participants, the majority were female (60.5%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 603) with a mean age of 20.6 years (SD = 2.1). Most were affiliated with government universities (80.6%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 804), and nearly half (46.3%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 462) studied health and life sciences.</p><p id="Par21">Regarding COVID-19 infection, 21.9% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 218) reported experiencing Long COVID symptoms, while 56.1% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 559) had symptoms lasting less than one month. The severity of infection varied: most participants reported minimal symptoms (34.9%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 348), followed by moderate symptoms (28.4%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 283), asymptomatic cases (12.3%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 123), and a small proportion reported severe symptoms (2.3%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 23). The median duration of treatment for previously infected participants was 8 days (IQR: 7–10), with those experiencing Long COVID having a longer median treatment duration of 10 days (IQR: 7–14).</p><p id="Par22">COVID-19 vaccination uptake was high overall: 98.7% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 984) had received at least one dose, with 60.9% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 599) having received three or more doses. However, only 21.4% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 208) had received three or more doses of an mRNA vaccine. Among participants who had never been infected with COVID-19, vaccine coverage was slightly lower at 95.0% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 209), with 63.2% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 132) receiving at least three doses and 82.0% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 168) receiving fewer than three doses of an mRNA vaccine.</p><p id="Par23">Preventive practices varied among participants. Overall, 56.3% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 561) reported always wearing a face mask outdoors, 51.6% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 514) sometimes used alcohol gel, and 53.8% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 536) sometimes practiced social distancing. Notably, participants who had never been infected with COVID-19 demonstrated higher adherence to preventive measures: 85.9% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 189) always wore a mask, 65.5% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 144) always used alcohol gel, and 55.0% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 121) always practiced social distancing. (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>)</p><p id="Par24">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sociodemographic characteristics of university students reporting long COVID Symptoms, Non-long COVID Symptoms, and those never infected with COVID-19</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2">Parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Long COVID</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Long COVID</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value¤</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never got infected</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value†</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 997</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 218</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 559</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 220</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">394 (39.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (40.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">233 (41.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (33.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">603 (60.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (59.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">326 (58.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147 (66.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean age (years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.6 (2.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.9 (2.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.6 (1.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.030*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.3 (2.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Academic year</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year 1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">181 (18.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (9.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (18.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58 (26.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">304 (30.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78 (35.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">159 (28.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (30.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232 (23.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (29.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132 (23.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (15.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year 4 and above</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">280 (28.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (25.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">165 (29.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (27.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Type of discipline</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Science and technology</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">212 (21.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (17.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115 (20.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58 (26.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.094</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Health and life sciences</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">462 (46.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110 (50.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">256 (45.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (43.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Humanities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">323 (32.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (31.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">188 (33.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (30.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ever have a COVID-19 vaccination</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Received COVID-19 vaccine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">984 (98.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">216 (99.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">559 (100.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.078</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">209 (95.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.021*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not received COVID-19 vaccine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (1.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (5.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">The total number of vaccines received</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 3 doses</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">385 (39.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (35.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232 (41.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (36.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥ 3 doses</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">599 (60.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140 (64.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">327 (58.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132 (63.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">The number of mRNA vaccines received</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 3 doses</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">763 (78.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">169 (80.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">426 (76.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">168 (82.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥ 3 doses</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">208 (21.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (19.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (23.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (18.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Infection severity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asymptomatic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">123 (12.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (6.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109 (19.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Minimal symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">348 (34.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (33.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274 (49.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">283 (28.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115 (52.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">168 (30.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Severe symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (2.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (6.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (1.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of Treatment in days, median (Q1, Q3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (7, 10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (7, 14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (5, 10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Wearing mask when going outdoors</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Always</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">561 (56.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 (45.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">272 (48.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.021*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189 (85.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sometimes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">392 (39.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">113 (51.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">250 (44.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (13.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not done</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (4.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (2.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (6.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Alcohol gel usage</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Always</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">429 (43.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85 (39.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200 (35.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">144 (65.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sometimes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">514 (51.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129 (59.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">317 (56.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68 (30.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not done</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (5.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (1.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (7.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Social distancing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Always</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">336 (33.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (28.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154 (27.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121 (55.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sometimes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">536 (53.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (59.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">324 (58.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (37.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not done</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">125 (12.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (12.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (14.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (7.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.001</p><p>¤Comparing between long-COVID and non-long COVID group</p><p>†Comparing between long COVID and never get infected group</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par25">Among participants with long COVID symptoms, 19.7% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 43) experienced non-specific symptoms, while 54.6% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 119) reported respiratory symptoms such as shortness of breath and cough. Psychiatric symptoms were present in 42.7% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 93), and 50.4% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 108) had neurological symptoms. Additionally, 34.9% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 76) reported bad sleep quality and 23.9% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 52) experienced musculoskeletal symptoms, 21.6% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 47) had cardiovascular symptoms, and 20.2% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 44) reported dermatological symptoms. Among female participants, 42.3% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 58) experienced reproductive-related symptoms (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par26">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Prevalence of long COVID-19 symptoms among university students by affected organ systems (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 218)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Long COVID symptoms are characterized by organ system</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptom presented</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-specific</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (19.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Respiratory</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119 (54.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neurological</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108 (50.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychiatric</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (42.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poor Sleep quality</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (34.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Musculoskeletal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (23.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiovascular</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (21.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dermatological</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (20.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Otolaryngological</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (18.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Immunology</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (14.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gastrointestinal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (13.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reproductive (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 137, female)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58 (42.3%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par27">As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, three factors were significantly associated with a higher likelihood of long COVID-19 symptoms among university students, including infection severity, duration of treatment, and sleep quality. The severity of infection played a significant role, students with severe symptoms were 15.3 times more likely to experience long COVID (95% CI: 5.29–44.38, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), those with moderate symptoms had a 6.2 times higher likelihood (95% CI: 3.12–12.38, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and those with minimal symptoms had a 2.2 times higher likelihood (95% CI: 1.13–4.33, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.021) compared to asymptomatic individuals. Students who underwent a longer treatment duration had a higher likelihood of experiencing long COVID symptoms (aOR = 1.05, 95% CI: 1.00–1.09.00.09, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.031). Poor sleep quality was also a significant factor, with those experiencing poor sleep having a 2.1 times higher likelihood of long COVID symptoms (95% CI: 1.41–3.09, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) compared to those with normal sleep quality. Conversely, receiving an mRNA vaccine was associated with a lower risk of long COVID symptoms (aOR = 0.86, 95% CI: 0.75–1.00.75.00, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.044). No collinearity was detected based on mean VIF of 1.11 with determinant-specific values ranging from 1.04 for age to 1.14 for days under treatment.</p><p id="Par28">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Factors associated with long COVID-19 among university students</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Adjusted Odds Ratio</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">VIF***</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lower bound</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper bound</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male (ref: female)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.251</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Age (per 1 year increase)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.255</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Infection severity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Asymptomatic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Minimal symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.021*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Moderate symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Severe symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Days under treatment (per 1-day increase)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.031*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sleep Quality</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Poor (ref: no symptom)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> mRNA (per 1 dose increase)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.044*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.11</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.001, *** Mean VIF = 1.11</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par29">To the best of our knowledge, this study found that the prevalence of long COVID among university students was 21.9%. The most reported symptoms were respiratory (54.6%), followed by neurological (50.4%), psychological (42.7%), and poor sleep quality (34.9%). Factors associated with a higher risk of long COVID included a history of moderate to severe symptoms, longer treatment duration, and poor sleep quality. In contrast, receiving an mRNA COVID-19 vaccine was associated with a lower risk of long COVID symptoms.</p><p id="Par30">Our study found the prevalence of long COVID at 21.9%, which was slightly lower than the pooled prevalence of 23.4% among children and adolescents under 18 years of age reported in a 2023 meta-analysis, in which approximately one-fourth of the included studies were conducted among Asian populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Our finding was also substantially lower than the global adult prevalence of 43% and the 51% among Asian adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Additionally, it was lower than a study conducted in a U.S. university setting, which reported a prevalence of 36% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] Prior research in Thailand during 2021–2022 reported long COVID prevalence rates of 32.9%−60% among adolescents and adults in Bangkok [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Several factors may explain why our study reported a lower prevalence of long covid compared with previous studies. Younger and healthier individuals may have a lower risk, consistent with reports showing a lower incidence among children (4%) than adults (10.2–25.9%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In addition, differences in the circulating SARS-CoV-2 variants during the post-pandemic period may also have contributed to the reduced risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Although the risk of long COVID was lower, it was not negligible. Therefore, university students should be advised to monitor their health for at least one month following COVID-19 diagnosis, especially those with a history of moderate to severe symptoms at diagnosis could increase the risk by 15 times, as well as a longer duration of treatment, and seek appropriate medical care if any symptoms develop.</p><p id="Par31">The top three organ systems most affected in our study were the respiratory system (54.6%), the neurological system (50.4%), and the psychiatric system (42.7%). Our findings are consistent with those from a study conducted in a U.S. university setting, which reported respiratory symptoms such as cough and shortness of breath in 43.2–64.5% of participants, and a slightly higher rate of neurological symptoms, including headache and fatigue, ranged from 48.9 to 52.3% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Moreover, a meta-analysis among adolescents reported a lower prevalence of long COVID symptoms, with respiratory symptoms at 14.8%, neurological symptoms at 13.5%, and psychiatric symptoms at 12.3%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. A 2022 review similarly found a lower rate of neurological post-COVID symptoms, including fatigue (37%), brain fog (32%), and headache (10%), with some symptoms persisting for over 24 weeks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The mechanisms by which symptoms develop throughout multiple systems of the body tend to involve tissue damage attributable to immune-mediated responses and inflammation. Furthermore, neurological and psychological manifestations may result from impaired neurological signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Although post COVID manifestations vary widely, respiratory and neuropsychiatric symptoms should receive particular attention due to their potential to cause long-term sequelae. Raising awareness among university students about the possible burden and impacts on daily life is essential for early recognition and appropriate management. Moreover, healthcare providers should schedule follow-up evaluations for high-risk individuals to facilitate early detection.</p><p id="Par32">Our study found that 34.9% of participants reported poor sleep quality. This prevalence is comparable to that reported in a meta-analysis, which found sleep disturbance in 30.7% (95% CI 19.3–42.1%), with symptoms persisting for more than six months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. A study conducted in Poland similarly reported that 68.3% of individuals experienced new-onset sleep disturbances after recovery, with 83.6% reporting symptoms that last for more than a month without spontaneous resolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Although total sleep duration was preserved, many individuals reported irregular sleep patterns like frequent awakenings, difficulty maintaining sleep, moderate to severe insomnia, and increased reliance on sleep aids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The mechanisms underlying poor sleep following COVID-19 infection are likely multifactorial, involving physiological, psychological, and neurological interactions. The acute SARS-CoV-2 infection can trigger inflammatory responses that interfere with neurotransmitter systems responsible for sleep regulation. Additionally, the virus may directly affect the central nervous system (CNS) through hematogenous spread or retrograde neuronal pathways, leading to disruptions in brain regions involved in sleep–wake control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Given these findings, sleep disturbance may serve as an early warning sign of potential long-term consequences following COVID-19 infection. Moreover, sleep disturbances are associated with adverse mental health outcomes, including depression, anxiety, and poor quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The use of self-reported Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) and the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI) could be beneficial for early identification of sleep problems among university students, facilitating timely intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par33">Our study found that the number of mRNA COVID-19 vaccine doses received was associated with a 14% reduction in the risk of severe outcomes per additional dose of mRNA (aOR 0.86, 95% CI 0.75–1.00.75.00) among university students. This finding is consistent with a U.S. study, which reported that university students who were either not fully vaccinated or fully vaccinated without a booster had a 2.2–3.0 times higher risk of developing symptoms consistent with long COVID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. A systematic review further demonstrated the protective effect of COVID-19 vaccination, particularly with mRNA vaccines, in reducing the incidence of long COVID. The review reported a 15% reduction in odds after one dose (OR 0.85, 95% CI 0.73–0.98, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.024), a 24% reduction after two doses (OR 0.76, 95% CI 0.65–0.89), and a 69% reduction after three doses (OR 0.31, 95% CI 0.05–1.84, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.198) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. While booster vaccinations have shown clear benefits in reducing infection, hospitalization, and death, particularly among older adults and individuals at high risk for severe COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Notably, mRNA booster vaccines have been associated with an increased risk of myocarditis, particularly among males aged 18–39 years, with a reported 7.5-fold increased risk within the first week after booster administration. However, most individuals with vaccine-associated myocarditis recovered within 3–8 months after diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Given these findings, healthcare providers should discuss both the risks and benefits of COVID-19 vaccination with university students, allowing them to make informed decisions about staying up to date with booster doses. The annual booster dose with an mRNA COVID-19 vaccine could be recommended for university students aged 18 years and older, particularly for those at higher risk of severe outcomes from COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Individuals who choose not to receive a booster dose should continue to adhere to appropriate health measures to prevent infection.</p><p id="Par34">This study had several limitations. The cross-sectional design precludes the ability to establish causal relationships between potential determinants and severe health outcomes. Recall bias may have occurred, as participants self-reported symptoms that may have changed or improved over time, potentially affecting the accuracy of their responses. Furthermore, the study’s findings may have limited applicability to Thai university students or other undergraduate students with similar ethnic or cultural backgrounds to those in Thailand. Future research should include broader sampling through multicenter designs to capture a more diverse population. Moreover, the use of more robust diagnostic tools to objectively assess Long COVID symptoms would enhance the validity of the findings. Despite these limitations, this study offers valuable insights into the burden of long COVID among university students. The findings could inform stakeholders in developing supportive strategies for early detection, timely treatment, and preventive measures, as well as guiding the creation of university or school policies to address long COVID more effectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par35">A minority of Thai university students reported experiencing long COVID symptoms, most commonly involving the respiratory, neuropsychiatric, and sleep-related symptoms. Receiving additional doses of mRNA COVID-19 vaccines was associated with a reduced likelihood of developing long COVID symptoms, highlighting the potential benefit of booster vaccinations in this population. Early detection and timely intervention, particularly within the first month after COVID-19 diagnosis, are crucial in mitigating serious health outcomes among university students. These findings underscore the need for stakeholders to develop supportive strategies focused on the prevention, early identification, and management of long COVID symptoms. Furthermore, universities and schools should consider implementing guidelines and policies that promote COVID-19 prevention measures, support vaccination uptake, and ensure accessible health services to address the long-term impacts of COVID-19 among young adults.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12889_2025_25457_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1. Table S1.The Cronbach’s alpha coefficient for each section and subdomain of the questionnaire used in the study.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We wish to offer our sincere thanks to all the participants for their willingness to take part in this study. We are deeply grateful to the entire research team for their valuable contributions and support throughout the project.</p><sec id="FPar2"><title>Informed Consent Statement</title><p id="Par36">Informed consent was obtained from all subjects involved in the study.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>Conceptualization, P.A., W.S., T.P., W.K., S.P., S.W., and A.K.; methodology, P.A., S.W., T.P., and A.K.; software, W.K., and W.S.; validation, T.P., S.P., A.K., and P.A.; formal analysis, W.K., W.S., P.A., and A.K.; investigation, P.A., A.K., S.W., S.P., and T.P.; resources, T.P. and S.P.; data curation, S.W., W.S., A.K. and P.A.; writing—original draft preparation, P.A., A.K., W.K., T.P., and S.W.; writing—review and editing, S.W., W.K., W.S., P.A., and A.K.; visualization, W.K.; supervision, P.A., A.K., and T.P.; project administration, P.A., A.K., and T.P.; funding acquisition, P.A., S.P., and T.P. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by the Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Grant No.074/2566.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data presented in this study are available on request from the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title> Declarations</title><notes id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par37">This study was conducted following the Declaration of Helsinki, and the protocol was approved by the Research Ethics Committee, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Thailand (Study code: COM-2565-09280).</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par38">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar5" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par39">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucinotta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic</article-title><source>Acta Biomed</source><year>2020</year><volume>91</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7569573</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Cucinotta D, Vanelli M. WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic. Acta Biomed. 2020;91(1):157–60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191675</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7569573</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>COVID is here</collab></person-group><article-title>To stay: countries must decide how to adapt</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>601</volume><issue>7892</issue><fpage>165</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-022-00057-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35013606</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">COVID is here. To stay: countries must decide how to adapt. Nature. 2022;601(7892):165.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35013606</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/d41586-022-00057-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zayachkivska</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is really ‘Long COVID’?</article-title><source>Inflammopharmacology</source><year>2023</year><volume>31</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10787-023-01194-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36964860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10039447</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Szabo S, Zayachkivska O, Hussain A, Muller V. What is really ‘Long COVID’? Inflammopharmacology. 2023;31(2):551–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36964860</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10787-023-01194-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10039447</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munipalli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seim</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabrh</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC): a meta-narrative review of pathophysiology, prevalence, and management</article-title><source>SN Compr Clin Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>90</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42399-022-01167-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8977184</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Munipalli B, Seim L, Dawson NL, Knight D, Dabrh AMA. Post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC): a meta-narrative review of pathophysiology, prevalence, and management. SN Compr Clin Med. 2022;4(1):90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402784</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s42399-022-01167-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8977184</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koc</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID and its management</article-title><source>Int J Biol Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>4768</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7150/ijbs.75056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35874958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9305273</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Koc HC, Xiao J, Liu W, Li Y, Chen G. Long COVID and its management. Int J Biol Sci. 2022;18(12):4768–80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35874958</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7150/ijbs.75056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9305273</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Leon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wegman-Ostrosky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayuzo Del Valle</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perelman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sepulveda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebolledo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuapio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villapol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-COVID in children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9950</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-13495-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35739136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9226045</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Lopez-Leon S, Wegman-Ostrosky T, Ayuzo Del Valle NC, Perelman C, Sepulveda R, Rebolledo PA, et al. Long-COVID in children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analyses. Sci Rep. 2022;12(1):9950.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35739136</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-13495-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9226045</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondratiuk</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factor for long COVID in children and adolescents: a meta-analysis and systematic review</article-title><source>J Infect Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2023.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36931142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9990879</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Zheng YB, Zeng N, Yuan K, Tian SS, Yang YB, Gao N, et al. Prevalence and risk factor for long COVID in children and adolescents: a meta-analysis and systematic review. J Infect Public Health. 2023;16(5):660–72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36931142</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jiph.2023.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9990879</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagaraj</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sardon</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonnell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agneshwar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 in university setting</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>29</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2903.221522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36703253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9973677</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Landry M, Bornstein S, Nagaraj N, Sardon GA Jr., Castel A, Vyas A, et al. Postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 in university setting. Emerg Infect Dis. 2023;29(3):519–27.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36703253</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3201/eid2903.221522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9973677</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID or post-COVID-19 syndrome: putative pathophysiology, risk factors, and treatments</article-title><source>Infect Dis (Lond)</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23744235.2021.1924397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34024217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8146298</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Yong SJ. Long COVID or post-COVID-19 syndrome: putative pathophysiology, risk factors, and treatments. Infect Dis (Lond). 2021;53(10):737–54.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34024217</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/23744235.2021.1924397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8146298</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wongwathanavikrom</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tovichien</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Udomittipong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palamit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiamduangtawan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahoran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charoensittisup</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and risk factors for long COVID in children with COVID-19 pneumonia</article-title><source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>2024</year><volume>59</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1330</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.26910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38353350</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Wongwathanavikrom NB, Tovichien P, Udomittipong K, Palamit A, Tiamduangtawan P, Mahoran K, et al. Incidence and risk factors for long COVID in children with COVID-19 pneumonia. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2024;59(5):1330–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38353350</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ppul.26910</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gupta M, Gupta N, Esang M. Long COVID in children and adolescents. Prim Care Companion CNS Disord. 2022;24(2):21r03218. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4088/PCC.21r03218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35486940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lek-Uthai U. COVID-19 vaccines help with herd immunity. Thai J Public Health. 2021;51:183–7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suryawanshi</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herd immunity to fight against COVID-19: a narrative review</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e33575</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36779140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.33575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9909126</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Suryawanshi YN, Biswas DA. Herd immunity to fight against COVID-19: a narrative review. Cureus. 2023;15(1):e33575.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36779140</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.33575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9909126</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tuangratananon T, Rajatanavin N, Khuntha S, Rittimanomai S, Asgari-Jirhandeh N, Tangcharoensathien V. Governance, policy, and health systems responses to the COVID-19 pandemic in thailand: a qualitative study. Front Public Health. 2024;12:1250192. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2024.1250192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10996397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38584930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minor</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Neal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delacqua</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delacqua</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The REDCap consortium: Building an international community of software platform partners</article-title><source>J Biomed Inform</source><year>2019</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>103208</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31078660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7254481</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Harris PA, Taylor R, Minor BL, Elliott V, Fernandez M, O’Neal L, McLeod L, Delacqua G, Delacqua F, Kirby J, et al. The REDCap consortium: Building an international community of software platform partners. J Biomed Inform. 2019;95:103208.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31078660</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7254481</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thielke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conde</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Research electronic data capture (REDCap)—a metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support</article-title><source>J Biomed Inform</source><year>2009</year><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2008.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18929686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2700030</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Harris PA, Taylor R, Thielke R, Payne J, Gonzalez N, Conde JG. Research electronic data capture (REDCap)—a metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support. J Biomed Inform. 2009;42(2):377–81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18929686</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jbi.2008.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2700030</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Institute for Health and Care Excellence. COVID-19 rapid guideline: managing the long-term effects of COVID-19. 2020.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33555768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bunrod K. Prevalence of post COVID-19 condition in SARS-Cov-2 infection patients at 3 months follow up in Chaiya Hospital, Surat thani. Region 11 Med J. 2024;38(1):1–15.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordin</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul Rahman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naing</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sample size calculation for prevalence studies using scalex and scalar calculators</article-title><source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>209</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12874-022-01694-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35907796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9338613</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Naing L, Nordin RB, Abdul Rahman H, Naing YT. Sample size calculation for prevalence studies using scalex and scalar calculators. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2022;22(1):209.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35907796</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12874-022-01694-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9338613</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Operational Manual for Educational Institutions in Preventing the Spread of COVID-19. In. Edited by Sarawut Boonsuk M. Nonthaburi province. 2020:78.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Department of Medical Service MoPH, Thailand. COVID-19 infection and Post-Infection symptoms questionnaire for the general public. In.; 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gøtzsche</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2007</year><volume>335</volume><issue>7624</issue><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.39335.541782.AD</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2034723</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, Pocock SJ, Gøtzsche PC, Vandenbroucke JP. Strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. BMJ. 2007;335(7624):806–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947786</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.39335.541782.AD</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2034723</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haupert</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global prevalence of post-Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) condition or long COVID: a meta-analysis and systematic review</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>226</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiac136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35429399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047189</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Chen C, Haupert SR, Zimmermann L, Shi X, Fritsche LG, Mukherjee B. Global prevalence of post-Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) condition or long COVID: a meta-analysis and systematic review. J Infect Dis. 2022;226(9):1593–607.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35429399</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/infdis/jiac136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047189</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krongthaeo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Partiprajak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piaseu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ckumdee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taaon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kongsuwan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and exploratory factor analysis of long COVID-19 symptoms among experienced infected population in Bangkok, Thailand</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2863</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-20275-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39420307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11488197</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Krongthaeo S, Partiprajak S, Piaseu N, Ckumdee S, Taaon C, Kongsuwan A. Prevalence and exploratory factor analysis of long COVID-19 symptoms among experienced infected population in Bangkok, Thailand. BMC Public Health. 2024;24(1):2863.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39420307</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-024-20275-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11488197</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jarupan M, Jantarabenjakul W, Jaruampornpan P, Subchartanan J, Phasomsap C, Sritammasiri T, Cartledge S, Suchartlikitwong P, Anugulruengkitt S, Kawichai S et al. Long COVID and hybrid immunity among children and adolescents Post-Delta variant infection in Thailand. Vaccines (Basel). 2023;11(5):884.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vaccines11050884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10223729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37242988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mandel H, Yoo YJ, Allen AJ, Abedian S, Verzani Z, Karlson EW, Kleinman LC, Mudumbi PC, Oliveira CR, Muszynski JA et al. Long-COVID incidence proportion in adults and children between 2020 and 2024. Clin Infect Dis. 2025;80(6):1247–61.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cid/ciaf046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12272849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39907495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection in the pre-Delta, Delta, and Omicron eras</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>391</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2403211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39018527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687648</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Xie Y, Choi T, Al-Aly Z. Postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection in the pre-Delta, Delta, and Omicron eras. N Engl J Med. 2024;391(6):515–25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39018527</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa2403211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687648</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zawilska</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuczyńska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychiatric and neurological complications of long COVID</article-title><source>J Psychiatr Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2022.10.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36326545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582925</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Zawilska JB, Kuczyńska K. Psychiatric and neurological complications of long COVID. J Psychiatr Res. 2022;156:349–60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36326545</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2022.10.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582925</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Premraj</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kannapadi</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Battaglini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fanning</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robba</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mid and long-term neurological and neuropsychiatric manifestations of post-COVID-19 syndrome: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>434</volume><fpage>120162</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2022.120162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35121209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8798975</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Premraj L, Kannapadi NV, Briggs J, Seal SM, Battaglini D, Fanning J, et al. Mid and long-term neurological and neuropsychiatric manifestations of post-COVID-19 syndrome: a meta-analysis. J Neurol Sci. 2022;434:120162.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35121209</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jns.2022.120162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8798975</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Topol EJ. Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023;21(3):133–46.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tański W, Tomasiewicz A, Jankowska-Polańska B. Sleep disturbances as a consequence of long COVID-19: insights from actigraphy and clinimetric Examinations-An uncontrolled prospective observational pilot study. J Clin Med. 2024;13(3):839.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm13030839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10856322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38337533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batool-Anwar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fashanu</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term effects of COVID-19 on sleep patterns</article-title><source>Thorac Res Pract</source><year>2025</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39663632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5152/ThoracResPract.2024.24013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11784924</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Batool-Anwar S, Fashanu OS, Quan SF. Long-term effects of COVID-19 on sleep patterns. Thorac Res Pract. 2025;26(1):9–16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39663632</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5152/ThoracResPract.2024.24013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11784924</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yi GD, Ching LW, Zhong LLD. Effect of interventions for the management of sleep disturbances in patients with long COVID: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. J Clin Sleep Med. 2025;21(11):1993–2005. 10.5664/jcsm.11782.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5664/jcsm.11782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12582205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40590080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edison</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long covid—mechanisms, risk factors, and management</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2021</year><volume>374</volume><fpage>n1648</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n1648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34312178</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Crook H, Raza S, Nowell J, Young M, Edison P. Long covid—mechanisms, risk factors, and management. BMJ. 2021;374:n1648.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34312178</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.n1648</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szentkirályi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madarász</surname><given-names>CZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novák</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep disorders: impact on daytime functioning and quality of life</article-title><source>Expert Rev Pharmacoecon Outcomes Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14737167.9.1.49</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19371179</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Szentkirályi A, Madarász CZ, Novák M. Sleep disorders: impact on daytime functioning and quality of life. Expert Rev Pharmacoecon Outcomes Res. 2009;9(1):49–64.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19371179</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1586/14737167.9.1.49</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chow NKN, Tsang CYW, Chan YH, Telaga SA, Ng LYA, Chung CM, Yip YM, Cheung PP-H. The effect of pre-COVID and post-COVID vaccination on long COVID: A systematic review and meta-analysis. J Infect. 2024;89(6):106358.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2024.106358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39580033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CDC US. Oct, Staying Up to Date with COVID-19 Vaccines, assessed on <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/covid/vaccines/stay-up-to-date.html">https://www.cdc.gov/covid/vaccines/stay-up-to-date.html</ext-link>. Assessed date: 5 2025.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shimabukuro T. Update on myocarditis following mRNA COVID-19 vaccination updated 7 June 2022. Assessed date: 2 May 2025.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>