<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open Sport Exerc Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open Sport Exerc Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3055</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjopensem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjsem</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open Sport &amp; Exercise Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2055-7647</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12927326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12927326.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12927326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12927326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41736939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjsem-2025-003157</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjsem-2025-003157</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Understanding the factors influencing participant engagement and adherence in exercise referral in the City of Manchester</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-4811-9800</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names initials="M">Matthew</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names initials="C">Craig</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names initials="ZA">Zoë A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Birkett</surname><given-names initials="S">Stefan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3766-9835</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Cable</surname><given-names initials="NT">Nigel Timothy</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5745-2564</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names initials="AE">Amy E</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Sport and Exercise Sciences</institution>, <institution>Manchester Metropolitan University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Manchester</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Physical Activity Referral</institution>, <institution>MCRactive</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Manchester</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><p>Additional supplemental material is published online only. To view, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjsem-2025-003157" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjsem-2025-003157</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>None declared.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Matthew Sharp; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="matthew.sharp@stu.mmu.ac.uk">matthew.sharp@stu.mmu.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503987</issue-id><elocation-id>e003157</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-25 15:25:13.233"><day>25</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2026. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjsem-12-1.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjsem-12-1.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>To identify demographic, clinical, socioeconomic and referral-pathway determinants of engagement, early dropout and non-participation in a large metropolitan exercise referral scheme (ERS), and to assess whether machine learning (ML) methods provide additional explanatory value beyond conventional regression.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This retrospective cohort study analysed data from 11 909 adults (≥18 years) referred for ERS in Manchester, UK, between 27 January 2022 and 28 February 2025. Outcomes were programme adherence (completion of ≥12 exercise sessions), early dropout and non-participation. Multinomial logistic regression was used to examine predictors of outcomes. ML methods, including Random Forest models and k-means clustering, were applied to assess predictive performance, rank feature importance and identify participant subgroups.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Of 11 909 referrals, 34.6% completed the programme, 34.2% declined to participate and 8.0% left early. Younger age, higher neighbourhood deprivation and psychosocial referral reasons (eg, loneliness, long covid) were associated with lower completion. Participants referred through outreach/social prescribing pathways were substantially more likely to remain in an ‘intends to participate’ state rather than complete, compared with those referred through clinical pathways. Random Forest models demonstrated good predictive accuracy, with early engagement indicators and deprivation emerging as the strongest predictors. Clustering identified a high-risk subgroup characterised by younger age, higher deprivation and low early attendance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Engagement and adherence in ERS were strongly shaped by early engagement, deprivation, age and referral pathways. ML methods identified high-risk subgroups and reinforced the importance of early attendance. Targeted early support and ML-informed risk indicators may improve retention, particularly among younger and more deprived participants.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Physical activity</kwd><kwd>Exercise</kwd><kwd>Public health</kwd><kwd>Health promotion</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Manchester Metropolitan University and MCRactive</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>N/A</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec><title>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Exercise referral schemes (ERS) are widely used across the UK as a public health approach to increasing physical activity among people with, or at risk of, chronic conditions. However, despite reach, engagement and adherence remain inconsistent, and many schemes report substantial levels of drop-out. Existing research has explored socio-demographic and health-related factors that may influence participation, but findings have been mixed and often depend heavily on local context.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>This study provides the first large-scale metropolitan analysis of ERS engagement using machine learning (ML) alongside traditional regression. It identifies deprivation, sex, health conditions and early engagement as key predictors of adherence and highlights the pivotal role of referral pathways. Outreach routes appear to broaden access but also reveal an intention–behaviour gap. At the same time, some deprived wards show strong completion once participants engage, challenging assumptions about uniformly poorer outcomes in disadvantaged areas. The combination of ML and regression offers new insight into dropout risk and patterns of participation.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, PRACTICE OR POLICY</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>The findings support the need for targeted interventions for younger males and individuals referred for psychosocial reasons, who appear most vulnerable to dropout. Strengthening triage processes, improving the quality of referrals and embedding warm handovers where referrers personally introduce participants to ERS staff to maintain engagement or structured follow-up mechanisms may help to convert initial intent into active participation. The analysis also suggests value in co-designing community outreach approaches with local partners to improve retention in deprived communities. Finally, the use of ML-based risk flags offers a practical tool for identifying participants who may require additional support, contributing to more personalised and equitable ERS delivery.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> Physical inactivity is a major global health risk, associated with a 20–30% increase in disease-related mortality.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Public health strategies increasingly prioritise interventions linking healthcare with structured physical activity. Exercise referral schemes (ERS) were introduced in the UK in the early 1990s to provide supervised activity programmes for individuals with medical conditions or risk factors.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 3</sup></xref> Despite widespread use, engagement and long-term adherence remain inconsistent, with dropout rates commonly exceeding 40%.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p>Demographic, health-related and socioeconomic factors influence ERS participation, yet findings are mixed and often context-specific.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5 6</sup></xref> Many evaluations use relatively small samples, often involving only a few hundred participants, limiting generalisability and highlighting the need for larger, whole-system analyses.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 4</sup></xref> National evaluations indicate that younger adults and residents of deprived communities are less likely to complete programmes.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3 7</sup></xref> However, local schemes vary widely in delivery models, referral pathways and settings, making localised analyses essential. Traditional regression approaches capture some determinants of engagement but may struggle with the complexity of demographic, clinical and behavioural interactions.</p><p>Manchester represents an important case for investigation. The city has a diverse population of over 550 000, a young median age of 34 compared with the national average of 40.7 years<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> and high levels of deprivation, with around a quarter of residents living in the most deprived neighbourhoods. These factors contribute to significant health inequalities, including elevated rates of chronic illness and mental health concerns.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> In response, the Physical Activity Referral Service (PARS) was launched in 2018 by MCRactive, in partnership with healthcare providers, community organisations and the local authority. Referral routes include general practitioners (GPs), physiotherapists, social prescribers and other health professionals, with programmes delivered across leisure centres and community venues. Despite investment, challenges around uptake and sustained engagement persist, and the drivers of these outcomes within this metropolitan context remain unclear.</p><p>Machine learning (ML) offers an opportunity to complement traditional statistical approaches by modelling non-linear relationships, identifying complex interactions, ranking predictor importance and detecting subgroups at heightened risk of dropout.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Although applications in physical activity and health services research are limited, early evidence suggests its potential to inform targeted interventions and improve programme adherence.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></p><p>Therefore, this study aimed to examine factors influencing engagement and adherence within Manchester’s ERS by integrating traditional statistical analyses with ML to identify predictors of adherence, explore early dropout and assess the influence of referral pathways on participant outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study design and participants</title><p>This retrospective cohort study analysed Manchester Active ERS data collected between 27 January 2022 and 28 February 2025. Data were extracted from the ReferAll system, which records referrals, engagement and outcomes. Adults ≥18 years were included. Duplicate records (n=3025) and referrals to third-party providers without chronic conditions (n=5536) were removed, yielding 11 909 participants.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Outcome measures and predictor variables</title><p>Primary outcomes were adherence, dropout and non-participation. Adherence was defined as completing ≥12 exercise sessions (up to 24), consistent with Manchester Active’s operational criteria and broadly aligned with the traditional 12-week ERS model.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 12</sup></xref> Dropout was defined as leaving before completing the prescribed sessions, and non-participation was defined as declining engagement following referral. Referral status was originally coded into five categories; analyses focused on the three most frequent: Completed, Left Early and Not Participating.</p><p>Predictor variables included age (Office for National Statistics age bands), sex, neighbourhood deprivation (Index of Multiple Deprivation, 2019, quintiles), referral source and referral reason (eg, musculoskeletal, diabetes, mental health). Ethnicity was excluded due to &gt;40% missing data.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Descriptive statistics summarised participant characteristics and outcomes. Group differences were assessed using χ<sup>2</sup> tests for categorical variables and t-tests/analysis of variance for continuous variables. Multinomial logistic regression examined predictors of outcomes, with ORs and 95% CIs reported (p&lt;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Machine learning analysis</title><p>Supervised and unsupervised ML methods were used to complement regression analyses. Random Forest and Decision Tree models were used to predict outcomes, with performance assessed using accuracy, precision, recall and F1 scores. Random Forests were prioritised due to stronger performance and the ability to rank feature importance. K-means clustering identified participant subgroups based on demographic and engagement variables.</p><p>All analyses were conducted using routinely collected, anonymised service-level data provided by Manchester Active under a data-sharing and confidentiality agreement. Data handling complied with General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR, 2018) and institutional governance requirements.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Patient and public involvement statement</title><p>Patients or members of the public were not involved in the design, conduct, reporting or dissemination of this study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Programme uptake, dropout (Left Early) and completion</title><p>Between 27th January 2022 and 28th February 2025, 11 909 participants were referred to Manchester’s ERS (after exclusions; see <xref rid="SP3" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure S1</xref>). Uptake, defined as accepting participation following referral, was high, with 57.8% of referred individuals engaging with the programme. Of these, 34.6% completed the programme, while 8% left early (classified as dropouts in this study). A further 34.2% declined to participate and were therefore categorised as non-participants, with a smaller proportion still engaged or awaiting consultation. Referrals were most frequently received from hospitals (38.7%), GP surgeries (25.2%), medical centres (20.7%) and outreach services (15.2%). Most participants (62.9%) lived in the most deprived quintile of neighbourhoods in England (Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD), 2019), an area-level measure of relative deprivation, with fewer than 1% residing in the least deprived quintile.</p><p>Participants presented with a diverse clinical profile typical of an urban ERS population. Musculoskeletal (MSK) conditions, referring to disorders affecting bones, joints and soft tissues such as arthritis, back and/or knee pain and other movement-related problems, were the most common referral reason (39.2%), followed by metabolic conditions, including type 2 diabetes (6.6%) and weight management referrals (7.6%), and respiratory conditions such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) (7.3%) and asthma (2.8%) were also well represented. Cardiovascular conditions accounted for a smaller proportion of the cohort, including stroke/transient ischaemic attack (TIA) (3.1%) and previous myocardial infarction (1.3%). Psychosocial and mental-health-related referrals formed another notable subgroup, with primary mental health concerns (3.7%), loneliness (2.1%) and long covid (0.2%) contributing to the overall case mix. Collectively, this clinical profile reflects the multimorbidity and psychosocial complexity characteristic of densely populated and highly deprived urban settings.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Predictors of adherence and dropout</title><p>Multinomial logistic regression identified several demographic and clinical predictors of programme outcomes. Participants with MSK conditions, alongside those with type 2 diabetes, cardiovascular disease, asthma, stroke/TIA, COPD and a history of falls, were more likely to intend to participate but not complete, compared with completers (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). Younger participants and those referred for psychosocial reasons, such as long covid or loneliness, were less likely to complete (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">tables2 </xref><xref rid="T3" ref-type="table"> 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Odds of intending to participate by health condition</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health condition</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Musculoskeletal conditions</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.14 to 5.29)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type 2 diabetes</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.59 to 3.57)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.27 to 9.05)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asthma</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.48 to 4.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroke or TIA</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.19 to 4.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPD</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.08 to 2.73)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Falls</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.14 to 2.49)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long covid</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.04 to 0.34)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arthritis</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.31 to 0.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No weight management referral</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.21 to 0.35)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported loneliness</td><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.19 to 0.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>Multinomial logistic regression results showing the likelihood of intending to participate relative to completing the programme, with completion as the reference category.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; TIA, transient ischaemic attack.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Odds of leaving the programme early by health and demographic characteristics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPD</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.36 to 0.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type 2 diabetes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.56 to 0.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fibromyalgia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.40 to 0.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate cancer</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.04 to 0.78)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (vs male)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.71 to 0.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group 1 (youngest vs oldest)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.04 to 1.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group 4 (vs oldest)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.61 to 0.98)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>Multinomial logistic regression results comparing participants who left early with those who completed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Odds of not participating by health and demographic characteristics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Musculoskeletal conditions</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.27 to 0.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Falls</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.36 to 0.58)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CABG</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.10 to 0.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angioplasty or stent</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.07 to 0.72)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroke or TIA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.40 to 0.81)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (vs female)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.71 to 0.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No weight management referral</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.43 to 0.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reporting loneliness</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.38 to 0.89)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>Multinomial logistic regression results comparing participants who declined to engage after referral with those who completed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>CABG, coronary artery bypass grafting; TIA, transient ischaemic attack.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Referral sources and outcomes</title><p>Within the PARS/MCRactive coding framework, social prescribing referrals (eg, via Be Well) are categorised as ‘outreach’ at the point of referral. Participants referred through outreach were over six times more likely to remain in the ‘Intends to Participate’ category rather than complete the programme (OR=6.08, p&lt;0.001). In contrast, referrals from clinical sources such as GPs, nurses and physiotherapists were associated with significantly higher odds of completion; these referrer types showed reduced likelihood of early dropout relative to completion (all p&lt;0.05) and indicate that clinical referrals carry greater predictive value for engagement than outreach (<xref rid="SP4" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table S3</xref>)</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Geographical patterns</title><p><xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Online supplemental table S2</xref> shows ward-level variation in participation outcomes (see <xref rid="SP2" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental file 2</xref>). Several highly deprived wards, such as Harpurhey (OR=0.25, p=0.005 for Intends to Participate vs Completed), Charlestown (p=0.020–0.047 across comparisons) and Moston (p&lt;0.001–0.021) demonstrated significantly lower odds of non-completion relative to completion across multiple outcome categories. In contrast, wards that are generally less deprived, including Deansgate (OR=2.16, p=0.038), Piccadilly (OR=4.20, p=0.006) and Stretford and Humphrey Park (OR=6.69, p=0.020), showed higher odds of non-completion or reduced engagement.</p></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>Subgroups identified through ML</title><p>Random Forest models accurately predicted who would complete the programme and who would leave early (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">table 4</xref>). Early engagement and deprivation emerged as the strongest predictors (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">table 5</xref>). K-means clustering identified three participant subgroups: ‘Committed Completers’, ‘At-Risk Starters’ and a smaller ‘Administrative’ group (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table S1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Random Forest model performance</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Precision</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completed vs Left Early</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completed vs Others</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Early vs Others</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T4_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>Classification accuracy, precision, recall and F1 scores for three binary outcome comparisons.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Top five predictors from Random Forest models</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fourth</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fifth</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completed vs Left Early</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total attended</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMD score</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ward referral count</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current age</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at referral</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completed vs Others</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total attended</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total booked</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total absent</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMD score</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Session cancelled</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Early vs Others</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total attended</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total absent</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMD score</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ward referral count</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Session cancelled</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T5_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>Most important variables identified for each outcome comparison, ranked by feature importance.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>IMD (Index of Multiple Deprivation, 2019), Area-level measure of relative deprivation in England.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study examined factors influencing engagement and adherence within Manchester’s ERS using both regression and ML approaches. Completion rates were lower than national benchmarks; however, high referral volumes from deprived areas indicated strong outreach, reflecting patterns reported in recent evaluations of UK ERS delivery.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Age, deprivation and psychosocial referral reasons consistently predicted dropout or non-participation, aligning with evidence showing that socio-demographic and psychosocial need remain central determinants of ERS engagement.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Outreach strongly shaped outcomes, emphasising the importance of programme design and flexible, person-centred delivery in supporting sustained engagement. Finally, exploratory ML analyses identified at-risk subgroups based on early engagement, echoing emerging work proposing that personalised interventions support individuals with complex barriers to participate in ERS.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref></p><sec id="s4-1"><title>Uptake, dropout and completion</title><p>Manchester’s completion rate of 34.6% was lower than the national averages of 43–50%.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 4</sup></xref> However, it is important to note that many national reviews are based on considerably smaller samples, often involving hundreds rather than thousands of participants, with most studies reporting sample sizes between 68 and 347 and only a minority exceeding 1000.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 15</sup></xref> In contrast, this study draws on a whole-system dataset of 11 909 referrals, including 62.9% of participants from the most deprived IMD quintile. This more comprehensive dataset reduces selection bias and provides a more realistic estimate of adherence in a densely populated, highly deprived metropolitan setting. Several contextual factors help explain the lower completion rate observed. Manchester serves a younger, more diverse and substantially more deprived population than many comparator regions. Deprivation is consistently associated with reduced engagement with health services and a barrier to sustained participation in structured programmes.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3 7</sup></xref> Individuals living in deprived urban areas often face competing financial, social and occupational demands, alongside poorer baseline health and higher psychosocial stress, all of which limit adherence even when initial intent is strong.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5 16</sup></xref> In addition, inner-city populations frequently present with more complex multimorbidity, mental health concerns and fluctuating symptoms, which may disrupt routine attendance.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> These structural and psychosocial pressures partly explain the lower completion rate observed.</p><p>Furthermore, Manchester’s unusually high referral volumes from deprived communities suggest that the service is successfully widening access to groups who are typically underrepresented in ERS participation nationally.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> While this is a strength, it also introduces a greater proportion of individuals facing significant barriers to sustained engagement. This combination of broad access and higher underlying vulnerability may therefore depress completion rates relative to schemes in less deprived or less complex populations. For these reasons, direct comparisons with wider regions should be made cautiously, as uptake and adherence are known to vary substantially between dense urban centres and areas with mixed or rural deprivation profiles.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15 17</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Predictors of adherence and dropout</title><p>Regression analyses showed that younger participants, particularly those aged 16–24 years, and those referred for psychosocial reasons, such as long covid, loneliness, anxiety or low mood, were less likely to complete the scheme. This aligns with previous work demonstrating that psychosocial complexity can reduce motivation, confidence and emotional capacity to engage consistently in structured activity.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5 6</sup></xref> Psychosocial referrals often involve fluctuating symptoms, low mood, social isolation and reduced self-efficacy, all of which are known barriers to sustained behaviour change and adherence.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18 19</sup></xref> In contrast, participants referred for musculoskeletal or metabolic conditions (eg, diabetes, obesity, weight management) frequently recognise a clearer clinical rationale for participation and therefore engage initially, but may still struggle to maintain attendance in the absence of ongoing support, particularly when symptoms worsen or pain limits activity.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 17</sup></xref></p><p>Age and sex differences also reflected broader national evidence. Younger adults consistently show lower adherence to ERS and health programmes,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3 15</sup></xref> and younger men in deprived communities appear particularly vulnerable to early dropout due to competing life pressures, lower health service engagement and stigma around help-seeking.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4 7</sup></xref> Together, these factors help explain why these groups differ in their likelihood of completing the programme and highlight the importance of tailored support for individuals whose circumstances make adherence more challenging.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Referral pathways</title><p>Referral type was strongly associated with outcomes. In this study, outreach referrals specifically referred to social prescribing pathways, including those made through the Be Well service. These routes were effective at generating intent to participate, but this intent often failed to translate into completion, reflecting the well-documented intention–behaviour gap.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> One explanation relates to the perceived authority and legitimacy of the referrer. Referrals made by GPs, nurses, and physiotherapists were associated with higher completion rates, likely reflecting greater perceived trust and professional credibility attributed to clinical referrers, which may increase the likelihood of acting on their recommendations.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In contrast, outreach referrals via social prescribing may carry less perceived clinical authority, requiring additional support to sustain engagement.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Consequently, outreach referrals may require additional early support, such as structured follow-up, warm handovers and personalised contact, to help convert intention into engagement. These findings suggest that while social prescribing expands reach, enhancing referral quality and early contact processes is essential to improve completion.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Geographical variation</title><p>Ward-level analyses demonstrated meaningful variation across Manchester, with some highly deprived wards (eg, Harpurhey, Moston, Charlestown) showing comparatively strong completion among those who engaged. This pattern aligns with the principle of proportionate universalism, which argues that interventions should be available to everyone but delivered with an intensity proportionate to the level of need,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> such as offering more frequent contact or additional support in communities facing greater disadvantage. In practice, this means that communities facing greater structural disadvantage may experience greater benefit once they are successfully engaged, because the intervention addresses an unmet need that is more pronounced in these areas. The findings, therefore, challenge the assumption that deprivation uniformly predicts poorer outcomes. Instead, they suggest that when access barriers are overcome, and individuals in deprived wards begin the programme, the ERS can be particularly impactful<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> despite previous research consistently reporting lower uptake and adherence among individuals living in more deprived areas.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25 26</sup></xref> This underlines the importance of locally responsive service design, with tailored engagement strategies that recognise both the higher need and the strong potential for benefit in deprived communities.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Machine learning insights</title><p>ML added value by modelling complex, non-linear interactions that are not easily captured by regression. Whereas regression assumes linear, additive relationships, the Random Forest models detected combinations of factors, such as age, deprivation and early engagement patterns, distinguishing those likely to complete from those at higher risk of dropping out. Early engagement measures (sessions attended, booked and missed) consistently predicted adherence, reinforcing the evidence that the first few weeks are critical for adherence.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Clustering analysis also highlighted a distinct high-risk subgroup of younger, deprived males with low early attendance, a pattern consistent with recent ML work identifying similar dropout-risk profiles in community exercise programmes.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Together, these findings indicate that younger males living in deprived areas, particularly those who do not engage early, require the greatest support at the point of entry into the programme.</p><p>These insights offer a practical foundation for targeted intervention. ML-derived ‘risk flags’ could be incorporated into referral management systems to trigger proactive follow-up, helping staff direct additional support to individuals most likely to disengage. Embedding predictive outputs as simple risk indicators, updated at referral and again after early attendance, would provide a structured way to prioritise contact, allocate resources and support, rather than replace practitioner judgement.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Clinical and policy implications</title><p>This study highlights several priorities for strengthening exercise referral schemes. Early engagement appears crucial, with rapid follow-up and triage-style contact helping convert referrals into active participation. Improving referral quality through clearer guidance and better integration with clinical pathways may reduce inappropriate or low-commitment referrals. The findings also highlight an ‘intent to engagement gap’ among participants referred through social prescribing: while outreach generates interest, it is less successful in converting intent into sustained attendance. Incorporating brief assessments of readiness to change, clearer communication about programme expectations and more structured ‘warm handover’ processes may help ensure outreach referrals reflect genuine preparedness to participate.</p><p>Targeted support is particularly important for younger males and individuals referred for psychosocial reasons, who were consistently more vulnerable to dropout. Closer community integration, such as co-designing outreach approaches with local partners, may further enhance retention in deprived wards. The findings also support integrating simple predictive tools within routine workflows. ML-derived risk indicators, updated at referral and after early attendance, could help staff proactively identify individuals at heightened risk of disengagement and prioritise follow-up, complementing practitioner judgement.</p><p>Finally, these implications should be interpreted within the context of Manchester; comparisons with other regions must account for differences in deprivation levels, service models and population profiles.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Limitations</title><p>This study has several limitations. Its retrospective and cross-sectional design restricts the ability to draw firm causal conclusions, as associations observed in such datasets may simply reflect underlying patterns rather than directional effects. The use of broad age bands limits the precision with which demographic differences can be understood, and the exclusion of ethnicity, due to high levels of missing data, constrains the extent to which equity-related patterns can be explored, a recognised challenge when working with incomplete public health datasets.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> The machine-learning analyses are exploratory and remain unvalidated outside this sample; it is well established that predictive models in health settings require external testing before informing practice.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Ward-level comparisons should be interpreted cautiously, given local contextual variation and the reliance on administrative records, rather than participant-reported experience, means that important psychosocial or behavioural factors may not have been fully captured.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Completion rates in exercise referral schemes remain below national benchmarks, but Manchester’s model demonstrates a strong reach into deprived communities. Age, deprivation, psychosocial referral reasons and referral pathways all shaped outcomes, while ML highlighted the added value of early engagement and risk profiling. Strengthening referral quality, supporting at-risk subgroups and embedding predictive tools may improve retention and ensure ERS delivers equitable benefits. These findings should be interpreted in the context of a single metropolitan setting; comparisons with wider regions must consider differences between dense urban centres and areas with more mixed or rural deprivation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjsem-2025-003157</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjsem-12-1-s001.docx" id="d67e835" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SP2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjsem-2025-003157</object-id><label>online supplemental file 2</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjsem-12-1-s002.pdf" id="d67e840" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SP3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjsem-2025-003157</object-id><label>online supplemental file 3</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjsem-12-1-s003.png" id="d67e845" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SP4" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjsem-2025-003157</object-id><label>online supplemental file 4</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjsem-12-1-s004.pdf" id="d67e850" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors wish to thank Maxine Taylor at MCRactive for support in navigating the ReferAll system and assisting with data access. They are also grateful to MCRactive for providing access to anonymised referral data. Finally, we thank the community partners across Manchester who continue to support the delivery of exercise referral programmes.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study forms part of a larger PhD project jointly funded by Manchester Metropolitan University and MCRactive. The funders had no role in the study design, data analysis, interpretation or the decision to submit this manuscript for publication.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> This study was approved under a formal data sharing agreement between Manchester Metropolitan University and MCRactive, with oversight by the Manchester Metropolitan University Research Ethics Committee. As the study involved secondary analysis of routinely collected service data, a separate ethics reference number was not issued. Participants gave informed consent to participate in the study before taking part.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> The data analysed in this study were provided by MCRactive under a data-sharing agreement. Due to governance and confidentiality restrictions surrounding public health data, the dataset cannot be shared openly. Access may be granted to bona fide researchers upon reasonable request to MCRactive, subject to approval under their data-sharing policies.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organisation</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Physical activity</article-title><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pavey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anokye</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The clinical effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of exercise referral schemes: a systematic review and economic evaluation</article-title><source>Health Technol Assess</source><year>2011</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3310/hta15440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4781450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22182828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>An evaluation of the effectiveness and cost effectiveness of the National Exercise Referral Scheme in Wales, UK: a randomised controlled trial of a public health policy initiative</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">J Epidemiol Community Health</italic>
</source><year>2012</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech-2011-200689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22577180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3402741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The effects of exercise referral schemes in the United Kingdom in those with cardiovascular, mental health and musculoskeletal disorders: a systematic review</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>949</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-018-5868-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30068338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6090762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crone</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Factors associated with physical activity referral uptake and participation</article-title><source>J Sports Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>26 (2)</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640410701468863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Battersby</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weightman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Adherence to exercise referral schemes by participants - what do providers and commissioners need to know? A systematic review of barriers and facilitators</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>227</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-016-2882-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26944952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4779205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>National Institute for Health and Care Research (NIHR)</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Exercise referral schemes: supporting people in the most deprived areas is crucial</article-title><publisher-name>NIHR Evidence</publisher-name><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Office for National Statistics (ONS)</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Population estimates for the UK, England and Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland: mid-2020</article-title><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Manchester City Council</collab>
</person-group><article-title>State of the city report: health and well-being</article-title><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pedregosa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Varoquaux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gramfort</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Scikit-learn: machine learning in Python</article-title><source>J Mach Learn Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2825</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Obermeyer</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vogeli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Dissecting racial bias in an algorithm used to manage the health of populations</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2019</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aax2342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31649194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Department of Health</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Exercise referral systems: a national quality assurance framework</article-title><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Department of Health</publisher-name><year>2001</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Newby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Howlett</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Moving an exercise referral scheme to remote delivery during the Covid-19 pandemic: an observational study examining the impact on uptake, adherence, and costs</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>2324</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-19392-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39192229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11348648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mino</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Are physical activity referral scheme components associated with increased physical activity, scheme uptake, and adherence rate? A meta-analysis and meta-regression</article-title><source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source><year>2024</year><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>82</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12966-024-01623-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39095805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11295389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Influencing factors and implementation pathways of adherence behaviour to intelligent personalised exercise prescription: a qualitative study</article-title><source>JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1180</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/59610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11659695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39636668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pavey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hillsdon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Levels and predictors of exercise referral scheme uptake and adherence: a systematic review</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>2012</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech-2011-200354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22493474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goldblatt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Fair society, healthy lives: strategic review of health inequalities in England post–2010</article-title><publisher-name>The Marmot Review Institute of Health Equity</publisher-name><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gidlow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crone</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Attendance of exercise referral schemes in the UK: A systematic review</article-title><source>Health Educ J</source><year>2005</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/001789690506400208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Bruijn</surname><given-names>G-J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>How big is the physical activity intention-behaviour gap? A meta-analysis using the action control framework</article-title><source>Br J Health Psychol</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjhp.12032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sheeran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Intention–Behavior Gap</article-title><source>Social &amp; Personality Psych</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/spc3.12265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Trust in physicians and medical institutions: what is it, can it be measured, and does it matter?</article-title><source>Milbank Q</source><year>2001</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1468-0009.00223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11789119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2751209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Impact of Health Information on the Internet on the Physician-Patient Relationship</article-title><source>Patient Perceptions Arch Intern Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>163 (14)</volume><fpage>1727</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.163.14.1727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12885689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ajzen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The theory of planned behavior</article-title><source>Organ Behav Hum Decis Process</source><year>1991</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0749-5978(91)90020-T</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Husk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elston</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gradinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Social prescribing: where is the evidence?</article-title><source>Br J Gen Pract</source><year>2019</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3399/bjgp19X700325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30591594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6301369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kearns</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Katikireddi</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Proportionate universalism in practice? A quasi-experimental study (GoWell) of a UK neighbourhood renewal programme’s impact on health inequalities</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2016.01.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26829008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Patterning in Patient Referral to and Uptake of a National Exercise Referral Scheme (NERS) in Wales From 2008 to 2017: A Data Linkage Study</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>3942</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17113942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32498367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7313463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Portman</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Exercise referral scheme participant characteristics, referral mode and completion status</article-title><source>Health Educ J</source><year>2023</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00178969231156108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Early behavioural patterns predict long-term physical activity adherence: a machine learning analysis of exercise programme attendance</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>9</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Torbica</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Systematic literature review: limitations of cross-sectional studies in assessing causal relationships in population health research</article-title><source>The Lancet Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e475</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Memon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mohebati</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Perceived barriers to accessing mental health services among BAME communities: A Qualitative Study</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2016</year><volume>16;6 (11)</volume><elocation-id>6132</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5128839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27852712</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data are available upon reasonable request.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>