<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12799803</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12799803.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12799803</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12799803</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41541965</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.99231</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious Disease</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Psychological Burden of Long COVID and Associated Factors Among Nurses Two Years Post-infection: A Cross-Sectional Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="L">Lin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="L">Liang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="J">Junyi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names initials="S">Suhua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhenjiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="Y">Youde</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Department of Infectious Diseases, The Affiliated Suqian First People’s Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Suqian, CHN </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Department of Infectious Diseases, Xuzhou Medical University, Suqian Clinical College, Suqian, CHN </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Youde Yan <email>19825190088@163.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">501569</issue-id><elocation-id>e99231</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-16 09:25:14.620"><day>16</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025, Zhang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000099231.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cureus.com/articles/441291-psychological-burden-of-long-covid-and-associated-factors-among-nurses-two-years-post-infection-a-cross-sectional-study">This article is available from https://cureus.com/articles/441291-psychological-burden-of-long-covid-and-associated-factors-among-nurses-two-years-post-infection-a-cross-sectional-study</self-uri><abstract><p>Background: The COVID-19 pandemic has generated sustained physical and psychological impacts on healthcare workers. Growing evidence suggests that some individuals develop persistent multisystem manifestations long after the acute phase, collectively referred to as long COVID. Nurses, who have borne heavy workloads and ongoing psychological stress since the pandemic, may be particularly vulnerable; however, limited research has examined their mental health status two years after infection.</p><p>Aims: This study aimed to evaluate anxiety and depression levels among nurses two years after COVID-19 infection, compare psychological characteristics across clinical departments, and identify factors associated with long COVID.</p><p>Methods: A cross-sectional online survey was conducted among nurses at a tertiary hospital, yielding 735 valid responses. Data were collected using a general information questionnaire, the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7), and the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9). Participants were categorized into long COVID (n = 263) and non-long COVID (n = 472) groups. Between-group differences were examined using appropriate parametric or non-parametric tests, and variables with P &lt; 0.10 were entered into multivariable logistic regression to identify independent predictors.</p><p>Results: Nurses with long COVID were significantly older and exhibited higher GAD-7 and PHQ-9 scores than those without long COVID (all P &lt; 0.001). Multivariate analysis showed that higher PHQ-9 scores (odds ratio (OR) = 1.147, 95% confidence interval (CI): 1.108-1.188) and older age (OR = 1.040, 95% CI: 1.011-1.070) were independently associated risk factors for long COVID. Although the prevalence of long COVID did not differ significantly across departments (P = 0.378), anxiety and depression levels varied, with nurses in high-risk exposure departments reporting higher GAD-7 and PHQ-9 scores than those in outpatient and medical-technical departments.</p><p>Conclusion: Two years after infection, nurses with long COVID continue to experience substantial psychological burden, particularly among older individuals and those with more severe depressive symptoms. Although long COVID was evenly distributed across clinical departments, significant interdepartmental differences in anxiety and depression underscore the influence of work characteristics and environment. Targeted psychological support and ongoing mental health monitoring are warranted to promote recovery and enhance occupational resilience in the post-pandemic era.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>anxiety</kwd><kwd>depression</kwd><kwd>long covid</kwd><kwd>nurses</kwd><kwd>occupational mental health</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the Suqian Science and Technology Program (Grant No. SY202215). The funding body had no role in the design of the study, data collection, analysis, interpretation, or writing of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The outbreak of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) at the end of 2019 has had a profound impact on global public health systems, socioeconomic stability, and population health [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Although most individuals recover after the acute phase, substantial evidence indicates that some patients develop long-term, multisystem dysfunction, manifested as persistent fatigue, respiratory symptoms, cognitive impairment, and other chronic complaints, lasting months to years after infection. This condition is collectively referred to as long COVID [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Nurses, as frontline healthcare professionals, have borne heavy workloads, infection risks, and sustained psychological stress throughout the pandemic and subsequent control phases [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Previous studies have demonstrated that healthcare workers, particularly nurses, face a significantly higher risk of anxiety, depression, insomnia, and other mental health problems compared with the general population. During the post-infection recovery phase, ongoing physical discomfort, occupational stress, and insufficient social support may further exacerbate emotional distress, contributing to chronic psychological burden [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Notably, while some studies have examined the psychological status of healthcare workers after COVID-19 infection, systematic investigations focusing on long COVID among nurses two years post-infection remain limited. This population not only continues to suffer from physical sequelae but also faces sustained occupational demands in high-intensity, fast-paced clinical settings, resulting in dual physical and psychological strain [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Differences in departmental characteristics, such as job nature, patient exposure risk, night-shift frequency, and workload intensity, may further contribute to heterogeneity in mental health outcomes [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, this study aimed to evaluate anxiety and depression levels among nurses two years after COVID-19 infection, compare psychological differences across departments, and identify factors associated with long COVID. The findings are expected to provide empirical evidence for long-term mental health surveillance, risk stratification, and targeted psychological interventions for nurses, supporting the establishment of a sustainable occupational mental health support system in the post-pandemic era.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Study design</p><p>This study adopted a cross-sectional design and conducted an online survey in June 2024 to assess anxiety and depression levels among nurses two years after confirmed COVID-19 infection. Participants were recruited using convenience sampling through internal communication platforms in participating hospitals. A structured online questionnaire incorporating validated psychological scales was used for data collection.</p><p>Participants</p><p>Inclusion Criteria</p><p>Participants were eligible if they were aged ≥18 years, had a confirmed history of COVID-19 infection at least two years prior, and provided voluntary informed consent.</p><p>Long COVID was determined using a predefined yes/no checklist of persistent physical symptoms lasting three months or longer after acute infection, based on commonly used World Health Organization (WHO) and National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) criteria. Participants without such symptoms were classified as the non-long COVID group, and all individuals in both groups had a confirmed COVID-19 history. To avoid overlap with psychological outcomes, mood-, sleep-, and cognition-related symptoms assessed by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) and the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7) were excluded from the long COVID definition.</p><p>Exclusion Criteria</p><p>Participants were excluded if they had no confirmed history of COVID-19 infection; had severe pre-existing psychiatric disorders, cognitive impairment, or major comorbidities likely to affect psychological assessment; or declined to participate. Individuals with incomplete or invalid questionnaire responses were also excluded to ensure data quality.</p><p>Department Classification</p><p>To examine potential differences in psychological outcomes across clinical settings, nurses were classified into five departmental categories based on workplace characteristics and occupational exposure. Department 1 included high-risk exposure units such as the Emergency Department, Intensive Care Unit (ICU), Infectious Diseases, Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Fever Clinic, and Isolation Ward, where nurses face heavy workload intensity and direct contact with high-risk patients. Department 2 consisted of surgical and perioperative units, including General Surgery, Orthopedics, Urology, Thoracic Surgery, Neurosurgery, the Operating Room, and Burn &amp; Plastic Surgery, characterized by fast-paced work and frequent night shifts. Department 3 encompassed internal medicine departments such as Cardiology, Nephrology, Gastroenterology, Hematology, Oncology, and Endocrinology, which typically involve prolonged management of chronic or critically ill patients. Department 4 included obstetrics, pediatrics, and other specialty units such as Obstetrics and Gynecology, the Delivery Room, Pediatrics, Neonatology, Rehabilitation, and Traditional Chinese Medicine, where high emotional demands are common. Department 5 comprised outpatient and medical-technical units, including outpatient clinics, Hemodialysis, Endoscopy, Interventional Radiology, Imaging, Laboratory, Pharmacy, and Intravenous Admixture Center, which usually operate with more regular work rhythms and comparatively lower psychological stress.</p><p>Sample size calculation</p><p>The required sample size was estimated using the simple random sampling formula with a 95% confidence level (Z = 1.96), an expected prevalence of 0.5, and a permissible error of 0.05 [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The minimum calculated sample size was 384, and considering a potential 10% invalid response rate, the final target sample size was set at no fewer than 420 participants.</p><p>Research instruments</p><p>General Information Questionnaire</p><p>The general information questionnaire was developed based on a comprehensive literature review and consultation with clinical and methodological experts. It captured key demographic and occupational variables, including sex, age, height, weight, marital status, educational level, annual income, working years, professional category, past medical history, and post-infection symptoms. These items were selected to ensure adequate characterization of participants and to allow exploration of potential associations with psychological outcomes.</p><p>Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</p><p>The PHQ-9 was used to assess the severity of depressive symptoms. The scale contains nine items, each scored from 0 to 3, with total scores ranging from 0 to 27. The PHQ-9 total score is classified into five levels: 0-4 (no depression), 5-9 (mild), 10-14 (moderate), 15-19 (moderately severe), and 20-27 (severe). Higher scores indicate more severe depression [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7)</p><p>The GAD-7 scale was used to evaluate the severity of anxiety symptoms. It comprises seven items, each scored from 0 to 3, with total scores ranging from 0 to 21. The GAD-7 total score is classified into four levels: 0-4 (no anxiety), 5-9 (mild), 10-14 (moderate), and 15-21 (severe). Higher scores indicate greater anxiety severity [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Data collection</p><p>Data were collected via an online questionnaire distributed through the hospital’s internal network and email system. Participation was voluntary, and all responses were submitted anonymously. The questionnaire included the general information form and the PHQ-9 and GAD-7 scales. Logical consistency checks were embedded in the survey system to automatically identify and exclude invalid responses.</p><p>Statistical analysis</p><p>Data were double-checked, entered into Excel (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, WA, USA), and analyzed using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 26 (Released 2018; IBM Corp., Armonk, New York, United States) and GraphPad Prism (Dotmatics, Boston, MA, USA). Continuous variables were presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD) or median (IQR), and categorical variables as frequencies and percentages. Group differences were analyzed using the t-test, Kruskal-Wallis test, or χ<sup>2</sup> test, as appropriate. Variables with statistical significance in univariate analysis (P &lt; 0.05) were included in multivariate logistic regression to identify independent factors associated with depression or anxiety, with results expressed as odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs).</p><p>Quality control</p><p>Quality control was implemented throughout all stages of the study, including questionnaire design, distribution, data collection, and statistical analysis. The questionnaire was reviewed by domain experts and pre-tested before formal administration. Data entry was conducted by two independent researchers to ensure accuracy, and statistical analyses were independently performed by two analysts to verify the consistency and reliability of the results.</p><p>Ethical considerations</p><p>This study was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Ethics Committee of the participating hospital (Ethics Approval Number: 2024-SL-0046). All participants provided informed consent before enrollment and were free to withdraw from the study at any time without any impact on their work or rights. Data were used exclusively for research purposes and stored anonymously on a secure, access-controlled server. Participants who exhibited signs of psychological distress were offered counseling and referral services by the research team.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Baseline characteristics of participants</p><p>After excluding invalid and incomplete questionnaires, a total of 735 valid responses were included in the final analysis. The participants had a mean age of 30.12 ± 5.70 years, and the majority were female and married. Regarding departmental distribution, 95 (12.9%) worked in high-risk exposure departments, 175 (23.8%) in surgical and perioperative departments, 167 (22.7%) in internal medicine departments, 70 (9.5%) in obstetrics, pediatrics, and specialty departments, and 228 (31.0%) in outpatient and medical-technical departments. A total of 263 nurses reported persistent long COVID symptoms two years after infection (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of the Study Participants (n = 735)</title><p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD) or n (%).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n (%)/Mean ± SD</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1 ± 5.7</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">699 (95.1)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Body mass index (BMI) (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.21 ± 3.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Education level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associate degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (12.5)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor’s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">633 (86.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master’s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (1.4)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Working years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245 (33.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-10 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">306 (41.6)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-20 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (20.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;21 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (4.6)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">724 (98.5)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Drinking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (4.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">705 (95.9)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Marriage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">265 (36.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">465 (63.3)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Department (category)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (12.9)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (23.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167 (22.7)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (9.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228 (31.0)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">COVID status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-long COVID</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">472 (64.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long COVID</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">263 (35.8)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.97 ± 4.80</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28 ± 4.90</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Demographic and occupational differences between nurses with and without long COVID</p><p>Among the 735 participants, 263 nurses (35.8%) were identified as having long COVID, while 472 (64.2%) reported no persistent symptoms. Initial comparisons revealed notable differences between the two groups, prompting further analysis to explore the demographic and psychological characteristics associated with long COVID (Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Nurses in the long COVID group were older and had significantly higher GAD-7 and PHQ-9 scores than those in the non-long COVID group, indicating higher levels of anxiety and depression. Regarding occupational characteristics, the distribution of working years differed significantly between groups: the long COVID group included fewer nurses with 0-5 years of experience but more with 6-10 years or 11-20 years of experience.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Comparison of Demographic and Occupational Characteristics Between Nurses With and Without Long COVID (n = 735)</title><p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD), median (interquartile range (IQR)), or n (%). Statistical comparisons were conducted using the chi-square test, t-test, or Mann-Whitney U test, depending on data distribution. A p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p><p>GAD-7: Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7; PHQ-9: Patient Health Questionnaire-9</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long COVID (n = 263)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-long COVID (n = 472)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.08 ± 5.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.59 ± 5.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (6.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.068</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245 (93.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">454 (96.2)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.50 ± 3.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.04 ± 3.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0675</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Education level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associate degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (10.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (13.8)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.187</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor’s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">234 (89.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">399 (84.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master’s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1.7)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Working years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (28.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (36.2)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-10 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (39.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 (42.8)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-20 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (25.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 (17.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;21 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (3.6)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.322</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">257 (97.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">467 (98.9)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Drinking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.143</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248 (94.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">457 (96.8)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Marriage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (33.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178 (37.7)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.326</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (66.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">290 (61.4)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Department (category)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (13.1)</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">0.378</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (22.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (24.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (25.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (21.0)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (11.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (8.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (28.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">154 (32.6)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">GAD-7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.71 ± 5.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00 ± 4.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">PHQ-9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.34 ± 5.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12 ± 4.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Multivariate logistic regression analysis of factors associated with long COVID</p><p>In the univariate analysis, several variables, including GAD-7, PHQ-9, age, sex, BMI, and working years, were found to be associated with long COVID. These factors were subsequently entered into a multivariate logistic regression model to determine which variables remained significant after adjustment. After stepwise selection, the PHQ-9 score and age remained in the final model (Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The results showed that higher PHQ-9 scores (OR = 1.147, 95% CI = 1.108-1.188, P &lt; 0.001) and older age (OR = 1.040, 95% CI = 1.011-1.070, P = 0.007) were independent risk factors for long COVID among nurses. The model demonstrated good overall fit (Nagelkerke R<sup>2</sup> = 0.142; Hosmer-Lemeshow P &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Multivariate Logistic Regression Analysis of Factors Associated With Long COVID</title><p>Values are presented as odds ratios (ORs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Logistic regression was performed using variables with p &lt; 0.10 in univariate analysis. A p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. “-” indicates not applicable.</p><p>PHQ-9: Patient Health Questionnaire-9; SE: standard error</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wald</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI for OR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHQ-9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.716</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.147</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.108-1.188</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.351</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.011-1.070</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.518</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Comparison of demographic and psychological characteristics among departments</p><p>Across the five departmental categories, the incidence of long COVID did not differ significantly, indicating that the distribution of long COVID cases was relatively uniform across clinical settings. However, psychological indicators such as GAD-7 and PHQ-9 scores showed significant variation across departments, suggesting that work environments may influence emotional well-being even when infection risk is comparable (Table <xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Post hoc analysis using Tamhane’s T2 test showed that nurses in Department 1 had significantly higher GAD-7 and PHQ-9 scores than those in Department 5 (both P &lt; 0.05), whereas no other pairwise departmental comparisons showed significant differences (P &gt; 0.05). Overall, nurses in high-risk exposure departments tended to exhibit higher anxiety and depression levels compared with those in outpatient and technical departments.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Comparison of Demographic, Psychological, and Outcome Variables Among Nurses by Department (n = 735)</title><p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD). Statistical analysis was performed using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), followed by Tamhane’s T2 post-hoc test due to unequal variances. A p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p><p>GAD-7: Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7; PHQ-9: Patient Health Questionnaire-9</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAD-7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.13 ± 5.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.94 ± 4.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.38 ± 4.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63 ± 4.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.32 ± 4.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHQ-9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.18 ± 4.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.48 ± 5.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76 ± 5.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.19 ± 4.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42 ± 4.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.73 ± 5.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.87 ± 5.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.75 ± 5.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.89 ± 5.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.07 ± 6.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.562</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.52 ± 3.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.06 ± 3.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.27 ± 3.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.68 ± 3.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.30 ± 3.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.592</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 ± 0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 ± 0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04 ± 0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 ± 0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 ± 0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.671</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long COVID, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (34.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (33.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (40.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (41.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (32.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.378</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The present study found that nurses with long COVID were significantly older and exhibited higher GAD-7 and PHQ-9 scores compared with those without long COVID. Although statistically significant, these differences were clinically mild, as the mean scores in the long COVID group fell within the mild anxiety and mild depression ranges. These findings indicate that long COVID is associated with a substantial psychological burden among nursing staff, and they underscore the importance of identifying high-risk individuals within this population. Multivariate analysis further identified higher PHQ-9 scores and older age as factors independently associated with long COVID, suggesting that psychological distress and age-related physiological changes may be related to the presence and persistence of long COVID symptoms. Additionally, interdepartmental comparisons showed no significant difference in the incidence of long COVID across departments, implying a relatively even distribution among different clinical work settings. However, significant departmental differences were observed in GAD-7 and PHQ-9 scores, suggesting that variations in psychological stress among nurses may be influenced by job characteristics and working environments.</p><p>Comparison with previous studies</p><p>Previous studies have consistently indicated that healthcare workers are at high risk for long COVID, with more pronounced clinical and psychological sequelae than the general population [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Multiple systematic reviews have shown that within six months after infection, approximately one-third of healthcare professionals continue to report symptoms such as fatigue, insomnia, anxiety, or depression [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The findings of this study are generally consistent with those reports, further supporting the crucial role of psychological factors in the development and persistence of long COVID sequelae.</p><p>However, this study did not identify significant differences in the incidence of long COVID among nurses from different departments, which differs from some reports suggesting a higher risk among those working in intensive care, emergency, or infectious disease departments [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Possible explanations include (1) improved infection control systems and rotation mechanisms across departments in the later stages of the pandemic, leading to more balanced occupational exposure risks; (2) the development of similar psychological defense and coping mechanisms among nurses through prolonged pandemic response experience; and (3) relatively balanced sample sizes but limited within-group variability, which may have reduced the statistical power to detect intergroup differences.</p><p>Notably, this study revealed significant differences in anxiety and depression scores among nurses from different departments, with those in high-risk exposure departments showing markedly greater psychological burden compared with nurses in outpatient and medical-technical departments. This suggests that even when the infection risk is relatively uniform, the level of psychological stress may still vary depending on job characteristics and environmental intensity.</p><p>Nurses working in high-risk exposure departments, such as emergency, intensive care, infectious diseases, respiratory and critical care, fever clinics, and isolation wards, are often subjected to high-intensity shifts, emergency treatments, infection control pressure, and critically ill patients, all of which may trigger persistent anxiety and hypervigilance. In contrast, nurses in outpatient and medical-technical units, such as general outpatient services, dialysis centers, endoscopy and interventional suites, radiology, laboratories, and pharmacy or infusion centers, generally experience more controllable workloads and lower patient exposure risks, resulting in lighter psychological strain [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. These findings suggest that nurses’ psychological responses are more strongly influenced by occupational exposure and job characteristics rather than by infection experience alone. Future interventions should therefore be tailored to specific departmental contexts, with targeted psychological support and stress management for high-exposure nurses to promote emotional recovery, professional resilience, and the sustainable well-being of the nursing workforce [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>Possible mechanisms linking depression and age to long COVID</p><p>Depression and age were the two principal factors significantly associated with long COVID in this study. Their mechanisms of influence may involve dysregulation of immune-inflammatory responses, neuroendocrine imbalance, and chronic psychological stress.</p><p>Depression is not merely a psychological state but a systemic condition characterized by chronic immune activation and neuroinflammatory processes. Multiple studies have demonstrated that individuals with depression exhibit elevated proinflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin-6 (IL-6), tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), and C-reactive protein (CRP), and decreased anti-inflammatory mediators. This inflammatory imbalance may delay post-viral tissue repair and sustain immune activation, thereby contributing to the persistence of long COVID symptoms [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Furthermore, depression affects the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and autonomic nervous system function, leading to elevated cortisol levels, circadian rhythm disruption, and metabolic dysregulation, all of which impair stress adaptation and resilience [<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Behaviorally, depressive symptoms such as reduced physical activity, poor sleep quality, and diminished perceived social support may hinder recovery. The frequently observed pattern of “chronic fatigue-depression-immune activation” among long COVID patients supports this hypothesis [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>With increasing age, the human immune system undergoes profound changes characterized by immunosenescence and inflammaging, including weakened adaptive immunity and heightened baseline inflammatory activity [<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This immune state predisposes older adults to persistent inflammatory responses and delayed tissue repair following SARS-CoV-2 infection. In addition, endothelial dysfunction, mitochondrial energy impairment, and reduced neural plasticity have been implicated in the pathophysiology of sustained symptoms such as fatigue and cognitive dysfunction in long COVID [<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>-<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>Within the nursing workforce, older nurses frequently face heavier workloads, greater managerial responsibilities, chronic sleep deprivation, and circadian rhythm disruption-chronic stressors that may further impair immune regulation and diminish psychological recovery capacity. The interaction between physiological vulnerability and occupational stress exposure may therefore create a “dual susceptibility” of both mind and body, increasing the likelihood of persistent long COVID manifestations [<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>Importantly, an interactive amplification effect may exist between aging and depression. Age-related neuroinflammation and heightened HPA-axis reactivity increase biological susceptibility to depressive symptoms, while prolonged depression may, in turn, accelerate immune aging, metabolic dysfunction, and systemic inflammation - forming a vicious feedback loop of inflammatory, endocrine, and psychological dysregulation. This bidirectional interplay provides a plausible explanation for why older and more depressed nurses in this study were more likely to experience persistent long COVID symptoms [<xref rid="REF31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="REF32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>Recommendations for clinical nurses in the context of the pandemic</p><p>The findings of this study show that although the incidence of long COVID did not differ significantly across departments, anxiety and depression levels varied markedly, and older age, together with higher depression scores, appeared to be factors independently associated with long COVID. These results highlight that in a prolonged pandemic context, equal attention should be given to both the physical and psychological recovery of nurses, alongside infection prevention and control.</p><p>A priority is to establish a risk-based psychological support system that incorporates mental health screening into routine occupational health management and records screening outcomes in health files. For high-risk individuals, such as those of older age, with elevated depression scores, or with a history of severe infection, priority follow-up should be arranged, including mental-health nursing interviews, anonymous counselling platforms, and accessible online self-assessment tools [<xref rid="REF33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p>Improving work scheduling and rehabilitation mechanisms is also essential. Nurses who contract COVID-19 or develop long COVID may benefit from phased return-to-work plans that gradually reduce night shifts and high-intensity tasks. Regular monitoring of physical strength, sleep quality, and emotional well-being through a structured “rehabilitation assessment form,” as well as providing temporary rest or duty rotation for those with recurrent symptoms, can support recovery. Existing intervention studies have demonstrated that tailored psychological and wellness programmes effectively improve nurse well-being during the pandemic [<xref rid="REF34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p><p>Strengthening professional resilience and fostering a supportive team culture further contribute to long-term psychological health. Continuing education on emotional regulation, peer-support activities, mentorship systems that pair experienced nurses with junior staff, and mindfulness-based practices may enhance team cohesion, reduce anxiety and burnout, and build sustained resilience [<xref rid="REF35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="REF36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p><p>Finally, developing a sustainable occupational health and rehabilitation framework is necessary to embed nurses’ physical and psychological well-being into routine quality and safety indicators. Leveraging hospital information systems to deliver periodic health questionnaires and constructing databases for dynamic monitoring and risk prediction can help shift nursing organizations from a focus solely on infection prevention toward holistic recovery and resilience.</p><p>Limitations</p><p>This study has several limitations that should be acknowledged. First, the use of a voluntary online survey introduces the possibility of selection and response bias. Because the response rate was not recorded, nurses experiencing persistent symptoms may have been more likely to participate, which could inflate both the estimated prevalence of long COVID and the strength of the observed associations. Second, the single-center, cross-sectional design limits the generalizability of the findings and prevents the determination of temporal sequence, raising the possibility of reverse causality. Third, long COVID was identified through self-reported symptoms without clinical confirmation, which may lead to misclassification or underestimation of mild or transient cases. In addition, psychological outcomes were assessed using self-reported instruments (GAD-7 and PHQ-9), which are subject to recall or reporting bias. Fourth, the sample consisted predominantly of female nurses, which may limit the applicability of the findings to more gender-balanced populations. Moreover, important confounding variables, such as social support, occupational stress, and sleep quality, were not included in the analysis and may have influenced psychological outcomes.</p><p>Despite these limitations, the study has several strengths. It focuses on nurses two years after COVID-19 infection, providing timely evidence on long-term psychological health in a high-risk occupational group. The use of validated mental health scales and a clearly defined long COVID classification enhances the robustness of the findings. Future studies should incorporate longitudinal follow-up, multi-center recruitment, documented response rates, and a broader range of psychosocial variables to improve generalizability and causal inference.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study revealed that nurses with long COVID were generally older and had significantly higher levels of anxiety and depression compared with those without long COVID. Multivariate analysis identified depressive severity (PHQ-9 score) and older age as independent risk factors. Although the prevalence of long COVID did not differ significantly across departments, variations in GAD-7 and PHQ-9 scores suggest that psychological burden is influenced by work-related factors. These findings highlight the need for continuous psychological monitoring and targeted interventions, particularly for older and high-risk nurses, to promote recovery and enhance occupational resilience in the post-pandemic era.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Dr. Lin Zhang, Dr. Liang Li, and Dr. Junyi Chen contributed equally to this work.</p></ack><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Informed consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. The Affiliated Suqian First People’s Hospital of Nanjing Medical University issued approval 2024-SL-0046.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> This study was supported by the Suqian Science and Technology Program (Grant No. SY202215). The funding body had no role in the design of the study, data collection, analysis, interpretation, or writing of the manuscript.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>  Lin Zhang, Suhua Pang, Zhenjiang Zhang, Youde Yan</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>  Lin Zhang, Liang Li, Junyi Chen, Suhua Pang</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>  Lin Zhang, Liang Li, Junyi Chen, Youde Yan</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>  Lin Zhang, Suhua Pang, Zhenjiang Zhang</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Posttraumatic stress symptoms and attitude toward crisis mental health services among clinically stable patients with COVID-19 in China</article-title><source>Psychol Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bo</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1052</fpage><lpage>1053</lpage><volume>51</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32216863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0033291720000999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7200846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Timely mental health care for the 2019 novel coronavirus outbreak is urgently needed</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatry</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><volume>7</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32032543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30046-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7128153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mental health of frontline healthcare workers exposed to COVID-19 in Egypt: a call for action</article-title><source>Int J Soc Psychiatry</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elkholy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tawfik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><volume>67</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32972298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0020764020960192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Characterizing long COVID in an international cohort: 7 months of symptoms and their impact</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>101019</fpage><volume>38</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34308300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mental health of the nursing and midwifery workforce in Wales during the COVID-19 pandemic: a cross-sectional analysis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kyle</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Challenger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>400 Suppl 1</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)02253-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9691053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36929988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Physical and psychological health of medical students involved in the coronavirus disease 2019 response in Switzerland</article-title><source>Swiss Med Wkly</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aebischer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weilenmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gachoud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Méan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spiller</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>150</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4414/smw.2020.20418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33306812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Depression and anxiety among nurses during the COVID-19 pandemic: longitudinal results over 2 years from the multicentre VOICE-EgePan study</article-title><source>J Clin Nurs</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grasmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>871</lpage><volume>34</volume><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38519850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jocn.17079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11808471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mental health disorders in nurses during the COVID-19 pandemic: implications and coping strategies</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riedel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horen</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidian Jahromi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>707358</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34765579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2021.707358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8575697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Identifying the most important workplace factors in predicting nurse mental health using machine learning techniques</article-title><source>BMC Nurs</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Havaei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>XR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>MacPhee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Straight</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>216</fpage><volume>20</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34724942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12912-021-00742-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8559368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>How to calculate sample size for different study designs in medical research?</article-title><source>Indian J Psychol Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Charan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><volume>35</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24049221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/0253-7176.116232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3775042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Gender distribution of depression among undergraduate medical students by using PHQ-9 scale</article-title><source>J Bahria Univ Med Dent Coll</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Munawar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shakoor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Psychometric properties of the generalized anxiety disorder scale-7 item (GAD-7) in a large sample of Chinese adolescents</article-title><source>Healthcare (Basel)</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1709</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34946435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/healthcare9121709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8701121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence of depression, anxiety, and insomnia among healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Brain Behav Immun</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pappa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ntella</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Giannakas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Giannakoulis</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Papoutsi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Katsaounou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>907</lpage><volume>88</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32437915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.05.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7206431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mental health in healthcare workers post-COVID-19: a Latin American Review and insights into personalized management strategies</article-title><source>J Pers Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Muñoz-Ortega</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santamaría-Guayaquil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pluas-Borja</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>680</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39063934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jpm14070680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11278025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Psychological factors associated with Long COVID: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Engelmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reinke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Salzmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Löwe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Toussaint</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shedden-Mora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>102756</fpage><volume>74</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39764180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2024.102756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11701445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on ICU healthcare professionals: a mixed methods study</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno-Mulet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sansó</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carrero-Planells</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>9243</fpage><volume>18</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34501832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph18179243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8431632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Global prevalence of long COVID and its most common symptoms among healthcare workers: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMJ Public Health</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Oraibi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Naidu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>3</volume><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjph-2023-000269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12010341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40260126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mental health changes in healthcare workers during COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review of longitudinal studies</article-title><source>Eval Health Prof</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Umbetkulova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kanderzhanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stolyarova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cobb-Zygadlo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><volume>47</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37143216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/01632787231165076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10160822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Long COVID among healthcare workers: a narrative review of definitions, prevalence, symptoms, risk factors and impacts</article-title><source>Br Med Bull</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Madan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stevelink</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><volume>151</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39183058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bmb/ldae008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11436955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Inflammation as the potential basis in depression</article-title><source>Int Neurourol J</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maeng</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><volume>23</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5213/inj.1938226.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6905209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31795605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Chronic stress, neuroinflammation, and depression: an overview of pathophysiological mechanisms and emerging anti-inflammatories</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hassamal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1130989</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37252156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1130989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10213648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Inflammatory mediators in major depression and bipolar disorder</article-title><source>Transl Psychiatry</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poletti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>247</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38851764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41398-024-02921-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11162479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Inflammation and severity of depressive symptoms in physically active individuals after COVID-19 - an exploratory immunopsychological study investigating the effect of inflammation on depressive symptom severity</article-title><source>Brain Behav Immun Health</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matits</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Munk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bizjak</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>100614</fpage><volume>30</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37033771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbih.2023.100614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10035808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Depressive symptoms, insomnia and dyspnea in COVID-19 survivors: a tunisian study</article-title><source>Eur Psychiatry</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nadia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mariem</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Houda</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>67</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Inflammaging: a new immune-metabolic viewpoint for age-related diseases</article-title><source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garagnani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Giuliani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><volume>14</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30046148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41574-018-0059-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Immunosenescence: molecular mechanisms and diseases</article-title><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>200</fpage><volume>8</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37179335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41392-023-01451-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10182360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Endothelial dysfunction and altered endothelial biomarkers in patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome and chronic fatigue syndrome (ME/CFS)</article-title><source>J Transl Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haffke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Freitag</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rudolf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>138</fpage><volume>20</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35317812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12967-022-03346-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8938726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinical implications of COVID-19-related endothelial dysfunction</article-title><source>JACC Adv</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aljadah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blanker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Widlansky</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>101070</fpage><volume>3</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39055276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jacadv.2024.101070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11269277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Monocytic mitochondrial dysfunction and impaired monocytic bioenergetic profile in patients with heart failure symptoms in post-COVID syndrome</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Semo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shomanova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sindermann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>666</fpage><lpage>3701</lpage><volume>45</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mitochondrial metabolic rescue in post-COVID-19 syndrome: MR spectroscopy insights and precision nutritional therapeutics</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1597370</fpage><volume>16</volume><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40486513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1597370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12141278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Cognitive impairment in long-COVID and its association with persistent dysregulation in inflammatory markers</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Damiano</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rocca</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Serafim</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1174020</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37287969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1174020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10242059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Blood-brain barrier disruption and sustained systemic inflammation in individuals with long COVID-associated cognitive impairment</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><volume>27</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38388736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41593-024-01576-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10917679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mental health and COVID-19: the psychological implications of a pandemic for nurses</article-title><source>Clin J Oncol Nurs</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roggenkamp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brassil</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><volume>25</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33480882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1188/21.CJON.69-75</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Interventional studies on nurses’ mental health in the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review</article-title><source>Psych</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Köse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MMM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><volume>4</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Predictors of nurses' work-related mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: a paired follow-up study</article-title><source>Front Health Serv</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1583357</fpage><volume>5</volume><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40353254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/frhs.2025.1583357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12062014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Post-acute care rehabilitation services and outcomes in skilled nursing facilities before and during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>JAMA Health Forum</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kosar</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gouskova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>4</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2023.0019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9984966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36867421</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>