<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12887480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12887480.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12887480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12887480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41651528</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2025-112376</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2025-112376</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Respiratory Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1731</subject><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Recurrent COVID-19 infection and the risk of exacerbation, mortality and long covid in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a nationwide retrospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4379-0260</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="HW">Hyun Woo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names initials="KY">Kwang Yong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5060-7255</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="JK">Jung-Kyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names initials="WS">Won Seo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="Y">Youlim</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names initials="KH">Kwang-Ha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3502-5211</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names initials="YI">Yong Il</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Seoul National University College of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Hallym University Sacred Heart Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Anyang-si</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Gyeonggi-do</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Seoul National University Seoul Metropolitan Government Boramae Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Division of Pulmonary, Allergy and Critical Care Medicine</institution>, <institution>Konkuk University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Gwangjin-gu</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine</institution>, <institution>Hallym University Chuncheon Sacred Heart Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Chuncheon</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution content-type="department">Internal Medicine</institution>, <institution>Konkuk University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Gwangjin-gu</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution content-type="department">Pulmonary, Allergy and Critical Care Medicine</institution>, <institution>Hallym University Sacred Heart Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Anyang-si</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>None declared.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Yong Il Hwang; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hyicyk@gmail.com">hyicyk@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">507106</issue-id><elocation-id>e112376</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-11 00:25:14.143"><day>11</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2026. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-16-2.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-16-2.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title> Abstract</title></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>To evaluate how recurrent COVID-19 infections influence the clinical course of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), focusing on moderate-to-severe symptom flare-ups, all-cause mortality and long covid.</p></sec><sec><title>Design</title><p>Nationwide retrospective cohort study.</p></sec><sec><title>Setting</title><p>Korean Health Insurance Review and Assessment database covering the entire Korean population between January 2020 and December 2023.</p></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p>A total of 313 760 patients aged ≥40 years who met an established operational definition of COPD based on diagnostic codes and inhaled therapy prescriptions. Patients were stratified by the number of COVID-19 events: none, one, two or three or more.</p></sec><sec><title>Primary and secondary outcome measures</title><p>The primary outcomes were moderate-to-severe COPD exacerbations and all-cause mortality. The secondary outcome was long covid, defined by WHO criteria using International Classification of Diseases (ICD)-10 codes persisting ≥2 months within 3 months after infection.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Among 313 760 patients, 154 095 (49.1 %) experienced at least one COVID-19 event. COVID-19 infection was associated with increased risk of exacerbations (adjusted HR (aHR) 1.64, 95% CI 1.62 to 1.66) and mortality (aHR 2.25, 95 % CI 2.19 to 2.31). Risk rose progressively with repeated infections, reaching an aHR of 2.41 for exacerbations and 2.93 for mortality after three or more events. Long covid was more frequent in patients with multiple infections, but most cases occurred after the first event, with diminishing occurrence after subsequent infections.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Recurrent COVID-19 infections in patients with COPD were linked to progressively higher risk of exacerbations and mortality, whereas the burden of long covid was greatest after the first infection. Preventing the initial infection and reducing reinfection risk remain critical components of COPD care in the post-COVID-19 era.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Mortality</kwd><kwd>Pulmonary Disease</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003653</institution-id><institution>Korea National Institute of Health</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2016ER670101</award-id><award-id>2016ER670102</award-id><award-id>2018ER67100</award-id><award-id>2018ER67101</award-id><award-id>2018ER67102</award-id><award-id>2021ER120500</award-id><award-id>2021ER120501</award-id><award-id>2021ER120502</award-id><award-id>2023ER120500</award-id><award-id>2023ER120501</award-id><award-id>2024ER120100</award-id><award-id>2024ER120101</award-id><award-id>CODE 2016ER670100</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY</title></caption><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Nationwide, population-based cohort including all patients diagnosed with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) in Korea.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Use of time-dependent Cox models to account for infection timing and recurrent-event exposure.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Large-scale analysis to distinguish cumulative versus sequence-specific effects of repeated COVID-19 events in COPD.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Reliance on administrative International Classification of Diseases (ICD)-10 codes may have led to misclassification of diagnoses and underestimation of long covid.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Lack of detailed clinical data such as lung-function indices, smoking history and vaccination status limits mechanistic interpretation.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a leading cause of morbidity and mortality worldwide and represents a major public health challenge.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Chronic respiratory diseases are the third leading cause of death worldwide and account for 7% of all deaths, which corresponded to 3.9 million deaths, and COPD was the largest contributor among chronic respiratory diseases.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> In addition, COPD accounted for 63.9 million disability-adjusted life years, which represented 2.6% of the total global burden of disease.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Despite advances in management strategies, the global prevalence and disease burden of COPD remain high, particularly in ageing populations.</p><p>The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has further magnified the vulnerability of patients with COPD. Even mild COVID-19 can lead to pneumonia in approximately 27 percent of cases, and timely administration of dexamethasone has been shown to reduce progression to severe disease or death among patients with COVID-19 pneumonia.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> COPD has been consistently identified as a risk factor for severe COVID-19 outcomes, including hospitalisation, intensive care admission and death.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Beyond the acute phase, the long-term consequences of COVID-19, including impaired lung function, increased exacerbation frequency and excess mortality, are of particular concern in patients with COPD. Previous studies have reported elevated long-term risks of exacerbation and mortality in patients with COPD following COVID-19 recovery, especially among those who experienced severe infection, reinforcing concerns about long-term prognostic implications.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11 12</sup></xref> However, these studies have largely focused on outcomes following a single episode of infection, with limited evaluation of how repeated severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infections influence the subsequent exacerbations and all-cause mortality in patients with COPD.</p><p>The phenomenon of long covid, defined as new or persistent health problems lasting for at least 2 months and beginning within 3 months after the initial infection, has emerged as a major public health issue.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Despite accumulating evidence on post-COVID outcomes in COPD, large-scale population-based studies examining the cumulative and sequence-specific effects of recurrent COVID-19 infections on long covid remain lacking. Whether the clinical consequences differ according to infection sequence also remains unclear.</p><p>This study aimed to investigate the association between the number of COVID-19 events and the disease course of COPD, focusing on moderate-to-severe exacerbations, all-cause mortality and long covid.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Reporting guideline adherence</title><p>This study adhered to the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology statement to ensure completeness and transparency in reporting observational research.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Study design and population</title><p>This study was designed as a retrospective cohort analysis using nationwide claims data from the Korean Health Insurance Review and Assessment (HIRA) database. The HIRA database provides comprehensive medical claims information for the entire Korean population, including demographics, diagnoses, procedures, prescriptions and mortality. Patients were initially screened for COPD between 1 January 2017 and 31 December 2019, and were subsequently followed from 1 January 2020 through 31 December 2023.</p><p>Eligible patients were those aged 40 years or older who met the operational definition of COPD during a predefined baseline ascertainment period between 1 January 2017 and 31 December 2019. COPD was defined as (1) the presence of an ICD-10 diagnosis code for COPD (J43–J44, except J43.0) recorded as either a primary or secondary diagnosis, and (2) the prescription of COPD-related medications at least twice within a year, including short-acting beta-agonist (SABA), short-acting muscarinic antagonist (SAMA), long-acting beta-agonist (LABA), long-acting muscarinic antagonist (LAMA), inhaled corticosteroid (ICS), ICS/LABA, LABA/LAMA, ICS/LABA/LAMA, systemic bronchodilators, theophylline or phosphodiesterase-4 inhibitors. This operational definition of COPD has been widely applied in previous population-based studies using the HIRA database.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Patients were excluded if they had no claims data available after 1 January 2020 or if they did not satisfy the operational definition of COPD.</p><p>Eligible patients with COPD were classified into two groups according to whether they experienced any COVID-19 event: the any COVID-19 event group and the no COVID-19 event group. COVID-19 events were identified using ICD-10 diagnosis codes U07.1 and U07.2 recorded in the HIRA claims database during the follow-up period between 1 January 2020 and 31 December 2023. For patients who experienced at least one COVID-19 event during follow-up, the index date was defined as the date of the first recorded COVID-19 diagnosis. For patients without any COVID-19 event, index dates were assigned using an incidence density sampling approach to align the distribution of index dates with that of patients with COVID-19 events. Among patients with COVID-19 events, further stratification was conducted according to the number of events, categorised as one, two, or three or more.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcomes were moderate-to-severe COPD exacerbations and all-cause mortality. The definitions of moderate and severe COPD exacerbations were based on previously established criteria.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20 21</sup></xref> Moderate exacerbations were defined as outpatient visits for COPD, identified by ICD-10 codes J43–J44 except J43.0 (pulmonary emphysema without chronic bronchitis), accompanied by prescriptions for systemic corticosteroids or antibiotics. Severe exacerbations were defined as events requiring emergency department visits or hospitalisation with a diagnosis of COPD (ICD-10 codes J43–J44 except J43.0), together with prescriptions for systemic corticosteroids or antibiotics. Admissions primarily attributed to pneumonia (J12–J17), pulmonary embolism (I26, I26.0 and I26.9), acute dyspnoea without specified cause (R06.0), or acute respiratory distress syndrome (J80) were excluded to improve specificity for COPD related exacerbations. For hospitalisations, readmissions were considered separate events, whereas outpatient visits within 14 days after discharge were considered part of the same event. For emergency department visits, re-visits were regarded as separate events, whereas outpatient visits within 14 days after discharge were considered part of the same event. Multiple claims within the same hospitalisation or emergency department visit were regarded as a single event. Moderate-to-severe exacerbations included either moderate or severe episodes, and both the incidence and the annual rate of exacerbations were evaluated. These operational definitions have been widely applied in previous epidemiological and claims-based studies to identify different severity of COPD exacerbations.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">1719 22</xref> All-cause mortality was ascertained from official death records provided by Statistics Korea linked with the HIRA claims database for research purposes.</p><p>The secondary outcome was long covid. In accordance with the definition recommended by the WHO, long covid was defined as new ICD-10 diagnostic codes that appeared within 3 months after the initial COVID-19 event and persisted for at least 2 months.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> This outcome was assessed only among patients identified by ICD-10 codes for COVID-19.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Variables</title><p>Baseline demographic variables included age, sex and socioeconomic status, which was classified as medical aid recipients or health insurance beneficiaries. Clinical comorbidities were identified using ICD-10 codes recorded in the HIRA database within 3 years prior to cohort entry, including myocardial infarction, heart failure, diabetes mellitus, chronic kidney disease, hypertension, osteoporosis, gastro-oesophageal reflux disease, dyslipidaemia, thyroid disease, inflammatory bowel disease, malignancy, asthma, chronic bronchitis, bronchiectasis and lung destruction due to tuberculosis.</p><p>Previous exacerbation history was assessed during the 1 year prior to the index date and categorised as moderate or severe according to the operational definitions described above. COPD-related treatments were identified from prescription records and classified as LABA, LAMA, LABA/LAMA, ICS/LABA or triple therapy (ICS/LABA/LAMA). Regular healthcare use was assessed by the number of outpatient visits per year, with three or more visits annually considered regular outpatient visits.</p><p>No missing data were observed for the variables included in the analyses because this study used a nationwide administrative claims database in which diagnostic, prescription and registration records are mandatorily recorded.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>To describe and compare baseline characteristics of the study population according to COVID-19 infection status, continuous variables were compared between groups using the Student’s t-test or analysis of variance (ANOVA), and categorical variables were compared using the χ<sup>2</sup> test. Standardised mean differences (SMDs) were additionally calculated to assess covariate balance.</p><p>To evaluate whether the burden of COVID-19 infection was associated with differences in the incidence and annual rates of moderate-to-severe exacerbations and all-cause mortality, these outcomes were compared across categories defined by the number of COVID-19 events, and linear trend tests were applied to assess dose-response relationships across groups. Specifically, the Cochran–Armitage test for trend was used for binary outcomes, the Cochran–Mantel–Haenszel test for ordered categorical variables and ANOVA with trend analysis for continuous variables.</p><p>To assess the association between COVID-19 infection and time-to-event outcomes, including moderate-to-severe exacerbations and all-cause mortality, cumulative incidence was illustrated using Simon-Makuch plots, and group differences were assessed with the Mantel-Byar test. These methods were chosen to appropriately account for COVID-19 infection as a time-varying exposure occurring at different time points during follow-up. Time-dependent Cox proportional hazards regression models with time-varying covariates were used to estimate HRs and 95% CIs for moderate-to-severe exacerbations and all-cause mortality. The proportional hazards assumption was assessed for time-fixed covariates and the baseline hazard using Schoenfeld residuals and graphical inspection of log minus log survival plots. No substantial violations of the proportional hazards assumption were detected. Two models were constructed: model 1 evaluated the presence of any COVID-19 event, and model 2 stratified patients by the number of events (one, two, or three or more) with no COVID-19 event as the reference. For multivariable Cox models, adjustment variables were selected a priori based on established clinical relevance and prior literature, including age, sex, socioeconomic status, comorbidities, previous exacerbation history, COPD treatment status and healthcare use, all of which are known or plausible determinants of exacerbation risk and mortality in COPD. These variables were included to minimise confounding rather than selected through data-driven procedures.</p><p>For long covid, two complementary logistic regression models were constructed to address distinct analytical objectives. First, to evaluate the cumulative association between repeated COVID-19 events and the risk of long covid, the patients were categorised according to the total number of COVID-19 events experienced during the entire follow-up period (no event, one, two, or three or more events). In this model, ORs represent the relative odds of long covid among patients with increasing numbers of COVID-19 events compared with those without any COVID-19 event. Second, to examine whether the likelihood of long covid differed according to infection sequence, a separate episode-based model was constructed. In this model, each COVID-19 episode was treated as a distinct exposure, and the reference category consisted of patients without any documented COVID-19 event. ORs from this model reflect the relative odds of developing long covid following the first, second or third COVID-19 event compared with no COVID-19 event. Both models were adjusted for age, sex, socioeconomic status, comorbidities, previous exacerbation history, COPD treatment status and regular outpatient visits.</p><p>All statistical analyses were conducted using SAS Enterprise V.7.1 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) and R V.4.5.0 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria). A two-sided p value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>Patients or members of the public were not involved in the design, conduct, reporting or dissemination plans of this research.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 995 591 individuals aged 40 years or older with at least one ICD-10 diagnosis code for COPD were initially screened in the Korean HIRA database between January 2017 and December 2019. We excluded 134 499 individuals without claims data available after 2020 and 547 332 individuals who did not meet the operational definition of COPD. Finally, 313 760 patients met the operational definition of COPD, which additionally required evidence of active treatment, and were included.</p><p>During the COVID-19 pandemic period, 159 665 patients (50.9%) did not experience any COVID-19 events, whereas 154 095 patients (49.1%) experienced at least one event. Among 154 095 patients with COVID-19 events, 133 913 (86.8%) were identified with U07.1 (laboratory-confirmed COVID-19), and 20,431 (13.2%) were identified with U07.2 (clinically diagnosed or suspected COVID-19). Among those with COVID-19 events, 124 793 (39.8%) had a single event, 27 506 (8.8%) had two events and 1796 (0.6%) experienced three or more events (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). The temporal distribution of COVID-19 events is illustrated in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>. The proportion of patients with COPD who experienced events was low in 2020 (0.4%) and 2021 (1.3%) but increased markedly in 2022 (39.3%) following major epidemic waves, and 15.8% experienced events in 2023.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Flow diagram of patient inclusion. COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; HIRA, Health Insurance Review and Assessment.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-16-2-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Longitudinal dynamics of COVID-19 infection status.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-16-2-g002.jpg"/></fig><sec id="s3-1"><title>Baseline characteristics</title><p>Compared with patients without COVID-19 events, those with COVID-19 events were younger, had a lower proportion of men and were less likely to receive medical aid (SMD&gt;0.1; <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental information 1</xref>). Gastro-oesophageal reflux disease and bronchiectasis were more prevalent in the COVID-19 group.</p><p>Baseline characteristics stratified by the number of COVID-19 events are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. Patients with increasing numbers of events were progressively younger, with a stepwise decrease in mean age and a higher proportion of younger age groups. The proportions of men and medical aid recipients declined with repeated events. The prevalence of gastro-oesophageal reflux disease, bronchiectasis, asthma, osteoporosis and dyslipidaemia increased progressively with the number of events. Malignancy was less common among patients with recurrent COVID-19 events. Moderate exacerbation history showed a slight increase, while severe exacerbation history was less frequent with higher numbers of events. Inhaler use also varied, with more frequent ICS/LABA prescriptions and less frequent LABA/LAMA or ICS/LABA/LAMA as the number of events increased.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Baseline characteristics according to the number of COVID-19 events</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No COVID-19 event<break/>(n=159 174, 50.81%)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single COVID-19 event<break/>(n=124 793, 39.84%)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two COVID-19 events<break/>(n=27 506, 8.78%)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three or more COVID-19 events (n=1796, 0.57%)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value for linear trend</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years, mean (SD)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.1±10.63</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.09±10.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.22±10.23</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.46±10.14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, category</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;50 years old, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3520 (2.21)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3413 (2.73)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">889 (3.23)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (3.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 50–65 years old, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 438 (22.23)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 634 (22.91)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6763 (24.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">475 (26.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 66–80 years old, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 472 (48.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 791 (52.64)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 796 (53.68)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">984 (54.61)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;80 years old, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 986 (26.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 142 (21.72)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5114 (18.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">279 (15.48)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, male, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 308 (72.33)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 434 (67.56)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 461 (63.35)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1127 (62.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic status</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Medical aid, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 619 (13.56)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 492 (10.80)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2962 (10.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184 (10.21)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical comorbidities</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MI, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 438 (22.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 134 (23.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6647 (24.12)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">449 (24.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CHF, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,980 (15.67)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,588 (14.07)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3669 (13.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">276 (15.32)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DM, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 815 (37.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 609 (38.09)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 575 (38.37)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">730 (40.51)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0003</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CKD, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8165 (5.12)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5686 (4.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1263 (4.58)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (5.05)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 926 (62.06)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 459 (61.98)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 828 (61.06)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1135 (62.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0119</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0339</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Osteoporosis, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 831 (17.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 657 (19.73)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6182 (22.43)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">418 (23.20)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GERD, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 868 (62.02)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 405 (66.73)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 583 (71.05)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1321 (73.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Dyslipidaemia, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 213 (39.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 003 (42.41)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 108 (43.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">864 (47.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Thyroid disease, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 172 (8.89)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 732 (9.39)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2773 (10.06)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182 (10.10)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IBD, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">399 (0.25)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">385 (0.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (0.39)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0.39)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Malignancy, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 646 (9.19)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9509 (7.61)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1920 (6.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (7.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulmonary comorbidities</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asthma, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 429 (19.09)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 710 (19.77)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5985 (21.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">438 (24.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chronic bronchitis, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 971 (32.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 810 (33.45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9479 (34.39)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">623 (34.57)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bronchiectasis, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 933 (9.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 433 (11.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3659 (13.28)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265 (14.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TDL, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6282 (3.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4669 (3.74)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1022 (3.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (3.72)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0242</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0047</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous exacerbation history within 1 year</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 466 (25.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 794 (25.44)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7297 (26.47)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">488 (27.08)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0014</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 939 (15.64)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 062 (12.85)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3472 (12.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228 (12.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regular inhaled treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LABA, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7326 (4.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5430 (4.34)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1223 (4.44)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (4.11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0116</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0068</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LAMA, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 386 (7.14)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9237 (7.39)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2051 (7.44)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (6.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0467</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0155</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LABA/LAMA, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 089 (23.27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 075 (22.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5825 (21.13)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">387 (21.48)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ICS/LABA, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 293 (13.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 679 (14.15)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4129 (14.98)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">288 (15.98)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ICS/LABA/LAMA, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 228 (12.69)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 741 (11.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3296 (11.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211 (11.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regular outpatient visits</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥3 visits/year, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 035 (53.34)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 107 (51.29)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 847 (50.24)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">908 (50.39)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1" fn-type="abbr"><p>CHF, congestive heart failure; CKD, chronic kidney disease; DM, diabetes mellitus; GERD, gastro-oesophageal reflux disease; IBD, inflammatory bowel disease; ICS, inhaled corticosteroid; LABA, long-acting beta-agonist; LAMA, long-acting muscarinic antagonist; MI, myocardial infarction; TDL, tuberculosis-destroyed lung.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Moderate-to-severe exacerbations</title><p>The incidence and annual rate of moderate-to-severe exacerbations increased progressively with the number of COVID-19 events (p for trend&lt;0.0001; <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental information 2</xref>).</p><p>The Simon-Makuch plots showed that the cumulative probability of moderate-to-severe exacerbations was significantly higher in patients with COVID-19 events compared with those without events, with index dates aligned by matching the first infection date of patients with COVID-19 to corresponding dates in the non-COVID group (Mantel-Byar test p&lt;0.0001, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref>). In the time-dependent Cox regression analysis, any COVID-19 event was significantly associated with an increased risk of moderate-to-severe exacerbations, with an adjusted HR (aHR) of 1.64 (95% CI 1.62 to 1.66, p&lt;0.0001; <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). When analysed according to the number of events, the risk increased progressively with repeated events: aHRs were 1.49 (95% CI 1.47 to 1.51) for a single event, 1.84 (95% CI 1.79 to 1.90) for two events and 2.41 (95% CI 2.16 to 2.68) for three or more events (all p&lt;0.0001).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Cumulative incidence of moderate-to-severe exacerbation and all-cause mortality according to COVID-19 event Simon-Makuch plots showing the cumulative incidence of first exacerbation and mortality according to COVID-19 infection status. The landmark was set at 2 months after the index date to reduce potential length-time bias.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-16-2-g003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Time-dependent Cox regression model for moderate-to-severe exacerbation and all-cause mortality</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Univariable model</th><th colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Multivariable model 1<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Multivariable model 2<xref rid="T2_FN3" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></th></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unadjusted HR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted HR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted HR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Moderate-to-severe exacerbation</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any COVID-19 event</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.563 (1.542 to 1.584)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.638 (1.616 to 1.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">The number of COVID-19 events (reference: no COVID-19 event)</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single COVID-19 event</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.420 (1.401 to 1.440)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.493 (1.473 to 1.514)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Two COVID-19 events</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.734 (1.686 to 1.783)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.844 (1.793 to 1.896)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Three or more COVID-19 events</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.276 (2.042 to 2.537)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.407 (2.159 to 2.683)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All-cause mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any COVID-19 event</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.168 (2.112 to 2.225)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.248 (2.190 to 2.307)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">The number of COVID-19 events (reference: no COVID-19 event)</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single COVID-19 event</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.134 (2.078 to 2.192)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.206 (2.149 to 2.265)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Two COVID-19 events</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.605 (2.458 to 2.760)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.802 (2.645 to 2.968)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Three or more COVID-19 events</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.695 (2.056 to 3.533)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.933 (2.237 to 3.847)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>For the moderate-to-severe exacerbation and all-cause mortality analyses, 313 760 patients with COPD defined by the operational criteria were included in all analyses presented in this table</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN2" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>Multivariable model 1 was adjusted for age, sex, socioeconomic status, myocardial infarction, heart failure, diabetes mellitus, chronic kidney disease, hypertension, osteoporosis, gastro-oesophageal reflux disease, dyslipidaemia, thyroid disease, inflammatory bowel disease, malignancy, asthma, chronic bronchitis, bronchiectasis, tuberculosis-destroyed lung, previous exacerbation history (moderate and severe), treatment status (no treatment, LABA, LAMA, LABA/LAMA, ICS/LABA and ICS/LABA/LAMA) and regular outpatient visits (≥3 visits/year)</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN3" fn-type="other"><label>†</label><p>Multivariable model 2 was adjusted for the same covariates with model 1 but evaluated the number of COVID-19 events (1, 2 or ≥3) with no COVID-19 event as the reference</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; ICS, inhaled corticosteroid; LABA, long-acting beta-agonist; LAMA, long-acting muscarinic antagonist.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>All-cause mortality</title><p>The incidence of all-cause mortality decreased with increasing numbers of COVID-19 events (p for trend&lt;0.0001, (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental information 3</xref>), with deaths in the COVID-19 groups observed only after the index event date, indicating the presence of immortal time bias.</p><p>The Simon-Makuch plots showed that the cumulative probability of all-cause mortality was significantly higher in patients with COVID-19 events compared with those without events, with index dates aligned by matching the first infection date of patients with COVID-19 to corresponding dates in the non-COVID group (Mantel-Byar test p&lt;0.0001, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref>). In the time-dependent Cox regression analysis, any COVID-19 event was associated with a more than twofold increase in the risk of all-cause mortality, with an aHR of 2.25 (95% CI 2.19 to 2.31, p&lt;0.0001; <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). When analysed according to the number of events, the risk of mortality was higher in patients with two events (aHR 2.80, 95% CI 2.65 to 2.97) and in those with three or more events (aHR 2.93, 95% CI 2.24 to 3.85) compared with patients with a single event (aHR 2.21, 95% CI 2.15 to 2.27; all p&lt;0.0001).</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Long covid</title><p>Analysis of ICD-10-defined diagnoses revealed a heterogeneous spectrum of long covid manifestations, with the most frequent conditions including neuromuscular dysfunction of the bladder, hypertension, peripheral vascular disease, heart failure and depressive episodes (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental information 4</xref>). When categorised by organ systems, musculoskeletal (8.6%), cardiovascular (7.0%) and respiratory (6.3%) disorders were most common, followed by metabolic, neurocognitive and gastrointestinal involvement (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental information 5</xref>).</p><p>Among patients with COVID-19 events, the cumulative prevalence of long covid increased with repeated events (p&lt;0.0001), whereas the majority of cases occurred after the first event, with markedly lower occurrence after subsequent events (p&lt;0.0001; <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref>). In the multivariable analysis, the risk of long covid increased with repeated events, with adjusted ORs (aORs) of 2.22 (95% CI 2.16 to 2.28) for two events and 4.12 (95% CI 3.73 to 4.54) for three or more events compared with a single event. In contrast, when stratified by event sequence, the likelihood of long covid was highest after the first event and decreased substantially thereafter, with aORs of 0.41 (95% CI 0.40 to 0.42) for the second event and 0.10 (95% CI 0.08 to 0.13) for the third event (all p&lt;0.0001; <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Long covid according to the number and sequence of COVID-19 events.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-16-2-g004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Risk of long covid after the first and subsequent episodes of COVID-19 events</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Univariable model</th><th colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Multivariable model<xref rid="T3_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unadjusted OR (95% CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted OR (95% CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">The number of COVID-19 events (reference: single COVID-19 event)</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two COVID-19 events</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.215 (2.157 to 2.274)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.215 (2.157 to 2.275)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three or more COVID-19 events</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.118 (3.735 to 4.540)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.117 (3.733 to 4.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">COVID-19 episode number (reference: first COVID-19 event)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second COVID-19 event</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411 (0.397 to 0.425)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408 (0.395 to 0.423)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr style="background:#EDEDED"><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third COVID-19 event</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101 (0.081 to 0.127)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100 (0.080 to 0.125)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>For the long covid analyses, 1,54,344 patients with at least one documented COVID-19 event were included</p></fn><fn id="T3_FN2" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>Multivariable model was adjusted for age, sex, socioeconomic status, myocardial infarction, heart failure, diabetes mellitus, chronic kidney disease, hypertension, osteoporosis, gastro-oesophageal reflux disease, dyslipidaemia, thyroid disease, inflammatory bowel disease, malignancy, asthma, chronic bronchitis, bronchiectasis, tuberculosis-destroyed lung, previous exacerbation history (moderate and severe), treatment status (no treatment, LABA, LAMA, LABA/LAMA, ICS/LABA and ICS/LABA/LAMA) and regular outpatient visits (≥3 visits/year).</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>ICS, inhaled corticosteroid; LABA, long-acting beta-agonist; LAMA, long-acting muscarinic antagonist.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This nationwide cohort study was performed to clarify how COVID-19 infection, particularly repeated events, influences the clinical course of patients with COPD. We found that COVID-19 infection was consistently associated with adverse outcomes, including a higher risk of moderate-to-severe exacerbations and increased all-cause mortality. Importantly, the risks of exacerbations and mortality increased progressively with the number of COVID-19 events, highlighting the cumulative burden of repeated infections. In addition, among patients with COVID-19, the risk of long covid increased with repeated events, although the occurrence was most pronounced after the first infection, suggesting that the initial event exerts the greatest impact on post-infectious sequelae. Taken together, these findings underscore the profound and enduring effects of COVID-19 on patients with COPD and emphasise the need to consider both the frequency and sequence of infections when evaluating long-term outcomes.</p><p>Previous studies have consistently shown that COPD is an established risk factor for severe COVID-19 outcomes, including hospitalisation and mortality. <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24 25</sup></xref>In addition, observational studies reported that COVID-19 can trigger COPD exacerbations and worsen clinical outcomes, although most investigations were limited to the first infection episode.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22 26</sup></xref> Large population-based analyses in the general population further demonstrated that repeated SARS-CoV-2 infections confer cumulative risks of death, hospitalisation and multi-organ sequelae.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Emerging data also suggest that patients with chronic lung disease, including COPD, have a higher susceptibility to long covid compared with those without pre-existing respiratory disease.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28 29</sup></xref> However, few studies have examined the cumulative burden of repeated infections or distinguished outcomes according to infection sequence in COPD. Our study addresses this gap by evaluating both the number and sequence of COVID-19 events in a nationwide COPD cohort.</p><p>In this nationwide COPD cohort, COVID-19 infection was associated with increased risks of both moderate to severe exacerbations and all-cause mortality, with progressively higher risks observed in patients who experienced repeated infections. These findings are consistent with prior evidence showing that COPD confers particular vulnerability to severe and fatal outcomes of COVID-19,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> as well as with population-based and hospital-based studies reporting higher exacerbation rates following infection, particularly after severe episodes.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16 22</sup></xref> Large-scale analyses in the general population have similarly demonstrated that SARS-CoV-2 reinfections are linked to incremental increases in death and hospitalisation during both the acute and post-acute phases.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24 27</sup></xref> Mechanistic studies provide biological plausibility by showing that SARS-CoV-2 disrupts epithelial barrier integrity, induces persistent airway inflammation and impairs mucociliary clearance, thereby predisposing the airways in COPD to recurrent instability.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31 32</sup></xref> The observed stepwise increase in exacerbation and mortality risk accords with these mechanistic insights, suggesting that cumulative viral injury and impaired host defence translate into greater clinical vulnerability. Additional contributing factors may include diminished pulmonary reserve, heightened systemic inflammation and the burden of comorbidities, which together exacerbate the fragile condition of patients with COPD.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> A meta-analysis reported that the use of renin–angiotensin system blockers was associated with improved COVID-19 outcomes, supporting the notion that effective control of systemic inflammation and comorbid conditions contributes to better clinical outcomes during acute viral infection.<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref></p><p>From a clinical perspective, repeated infections contribute to a higher exacerbation and mortality burden in COPD and underscore the relevance of reinfection prevention and vigilant follow-up as essential considerations in post-COVID management strategies for this population.</p><p>Notably, the majority of long covid cases in our study occurred after the first infection, indicating that the initial viral insult carries the greatest risk for long-term sequelae in patients with COPD. While subsequent infections were also associated with long covid, their contribution was comparatively modest, suggesting a diminishing impact beyond the first episode. This sequence-specific pattern provides novel evidence that the burden of long covid in COPD is driven primarily by the initial infection rather than by cumulative exposures. Prior studies have reported that COPD and other chronic lung diseases increase susceptibility to long covid, yet few have examined outcomes according to infection sequence.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28 29</sup></xref> These findings indicate that preventing the first COVID-19 infection is likely the most effective strategy to reduce the burden of long covid in COPD, complemented by close monitoring and early management following infection.</p><p>From a policy perspective, our findings suggest that repeated COVID-19 events represent an important risk stratifier among patients with COPD. The observed associations with exacerbation burden, mortality and long covid indicate that patients with a history of multiple COVID-19 events may benefit from targeted preventive strategies, including prioritisation for vaccination, closer post-infection monitoring and timely access to pulmonary care. In addition, these results support the incorporation of COVID-19 event history into risk assessment frameworks used in population-level COPD management and healthcare resource allocation.</p><sec id="s4-1"><title>Strength</title><p>This nationwide cohort study included all patients diagnosed with COPD in Korea and used time-dependent Cox models to account for the timing and recurrence of COVID-19 infections, allowing a comprehensive assessment of cumulative infection burden and its clinical implications.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Limitations</title><p>This study has several limitations. First, as an observational study, our analysis is subject to residual confounding from unmeasured factors such as environmental exposures, health behaviours and healthcare access, despite extensive adjustment for available covariates. Second, the study period spanned different phases of the pandemic with evolving viral variants and vaccine coverage, which could not be fully incorporated into the analysis and may have influenced outcomes. Third, reliance on administrative claims data introduces the possibility of misclassification of diagnoses and outcomes, and important clinical variables such as lung function, smoking history and detailed treatment patterns were unavailable. Fourth, long covid was defined using diagnostic codes, which may not fully capture the heterogeneity of this condition. In particular, patients with mild or subclinical symptoms who did not seek medical evaluation may not have been recorded, leading to potential underestimation of its true prevalence. Finally, as the data were derived from the Korean healthcare system, caution is warranted when generalising these findings to other populations.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Recurrent COVID-19 infections in patients with COPD were associated with progressively increased risks of exacerbations and mortality, whereas the burden of long covid was most evident after the first infection. These findings underscore the importance of preventing the initial infection and minimising the risk of reinfection, while also supporting the need for vigilant monitoring and timely intervention once infection occurs. These insights can inform COPD management in the post-COVID era, with a focus on prioritisation of preventive measures, reinforcement of vaccination programmes and structured follow-up for long-term outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2025-112376</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-16-2-s001.docx" id="d67e1294" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work was supported by the Research Program funded by the Korea National Institute of Health (Fund CODE 2016ER670100, 2016ER670101, 2016ER670102, 2018ER67100, 2018ER67101, 2018ER67102, 2021ER120500, 2021ER120501, 2021ER120502, 2023ER120500, 2023ER120501, 2024ER120100 and 2024ER120101).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Prepublication history and additional supplemental material for this paper are available online. To view these files, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2025-112376" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2025-112376</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> The data that support the findings of this study are available from the KOrea COpd Subgroup Study (KOCOSS) team but restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under licence for the current study, and so are not publicly available. However, data are available from the authors upon reasonable request and with permission of the KOCOSS team.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> The study protocol received approval from the Institutional Review Board (IRB) at each hospital (Seoul Metropolitan Government-Seoul National University Boramae Medical Center IRB No. 07-2025-2). Due to the retrospective design and the use of an anonymised database, the requirement for written informed consent for participation and publication was waived. This waiver was justified as obtaining consent was impracticable, there was no reasonable basis to assume participants would object and the exemption posed minimal risk to participants.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abbafati</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories, 1990–2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><year>2020</year><volume>396</volume><fpage>1204</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30925-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7567026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33069326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paulson</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence and attributable health burden of chronic respiratory diseases, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30105-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32526187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7284317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abajobir</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Global, regional, and national deaths, prevalence, disability-adjusted life years, and years lived with disability for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and asthma, 1990–2015: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2015</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(17)30293-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28822787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5573769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Emberson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Dexamethasone in Hospitalized Patients with Covid-19</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>384</volume><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2021436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32678530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7383595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J-K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Effect of the Timing of Dexamethasone Administration in Patients with COVID-19 Pneumonia</article-title><source>Tuberc Respir Dis (Seoul)</source><year>2021</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4046/trd.2021.0009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34078038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8273022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J-K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical implication and risk factor of pneumonia development in mild coronavirus disease 2019 patients</article-title><source>Korean J Intern Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3904/kjim.2020.329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32972121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7820649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alqahtani</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oyelade</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aldhahir</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence, Severity and Mortality associated with COPD and Smoking in patients with COVID-19: A Rapid Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e0233147</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0233147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32392262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7213702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The impact of COPD and smoking history on the severity of COVID-19: A systemic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>2020</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>1915</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.25889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32293753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7262275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Niikura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CWT</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and COPD</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2020</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>2002108</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.02108-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32817205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7424116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ronksley</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Impact of COVID-19 Pandemic on Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease Healthcare Use, Exacerbations, and Mortality: A Population Study</article-title><source>Ann Am Thorac Soc</source><year>2024</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1281</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202312-1078OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38820253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11376357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and risk of long-term mortality in COPD: a nationwide population-based cohort study</article-title><source>BMJ Open Respir Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e002694</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2024-002694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11836811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39961706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Long-Term Effects of COVID-19 on Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2025</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2539</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/COPD.S523149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40698121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12282603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) Statement: Guidelines for Reporting Observational Studies</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e296</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0040296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17941714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2020495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease and Inhaled Treatment Effects on Mortality in Patients with Lung Cancer</article-title><source>Ann Am Thorac Soc</source><year>2025</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1764</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202409-990OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40569182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12548749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Change in exacerbation rate of COPD patients before and after COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>2427</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-86426-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39827278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11743209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J-K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Impact of inhaled corticosteroids on metabolic dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease risk in COPD patients</article-title><source>Respir Med Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>101171</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmer.2025.101171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40334452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular Events According to Inhaler Therapy and Comorbidities in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/COPD.S433583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38269030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10806337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Differential response to roflumilast in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: real-world evidence</article-title><source>J Thorac Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1338</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-23-1129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38505074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10944795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD)</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Global strategy for prevention, diagnosis and management of copd: 2025 report</article-title><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://goldcopd.org/2025-gold-report" ext-link-type="uri">http://goldcopd.org/2025-gold-report</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>15-Jun-2025</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pharmacologic Therapies for Preventing Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease Exacerbations: A Comprehensive Review</article-title><source>Tuberc Respir Dis (Seoul)</source><year>2025</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4046/trd.2024.0170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39904363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12010717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Risk of acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease after COVID-19 recovery: a nationwide population-based cohort study</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>26</volume><elocation-id>116</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-025-03123-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40148876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11951598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Post COVID-19 condition</article-title><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/post-covid-19-condition-(long-covid)" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/post-covid-19-condition-(long-covid)</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>3-Sep-2025</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Finnerty</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>ABMA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ponnuswamy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Asthma and COPD as co-morbidities in patients hospitalised with Covid-19 disease: a global systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>462</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-023-02761-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37993829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10664669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Underlying conditions and the higher risk for severe COVID-19</article-title><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/covid/hcp/clinical-care/underlying-conditions.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/covid/hcp/clinical-care/underlying-conditions.html</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>2-Sep-2025</date-in-citation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34009770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>TCC</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Outcomes among patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease after recovery from COVID-19 infection of different severity</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>13881</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-64670-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38880813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11180653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Acute and postacute sequelae associated with SARS-CoV-2 reinfection</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2398</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02051-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9671810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anzalone</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Chronic Lung Disease as a Risk Factor for Long COVID in Patients Diagnosed With Coronavirus Disease 2019: A Retrospective Cohort Study</article-title><source>Open Forum Infect Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>ofae424</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofae424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39183811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11342242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Heidel</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Risk of long covid in patients with pre-existing chronic respiratory diseases: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMJ Open Respir Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e002528</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2024-002528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11784193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39884720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gerayeli</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>COPD and the risk of poor outcomes in COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><elocation-id>100789</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33758801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7971471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>LLY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The establishment of COPD organoids to study host-pathogen interaction reveals enhanced viral fitness of SARS-CoV-2 in bronchi</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>7635</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-35253-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36496442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9735280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W-J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 envelope protein impairs airway epithelial barrier function and exacerbates airway inflammation via increased intracellular Cl<sup>-</sup> concentration</article-title><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther</source><year>2024</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>74</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-024-01753-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38528022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10963779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mathioudakis</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and COVID-19: interrelationships</article-title><source>Curr Opin Pulm Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCP.0000000000000834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34690257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8815646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Renin-angiotensin system blocker and outcomes of COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2021</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-215322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33504565</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data are available upon reasonable request.</p></sec></back><sub-article id="sub-article1" article-type="aggregated-review-documents"><front-stub><title-group><article-title>Review Process File</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></pub-date></front-stub><body><fig id="d67e2183" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2025-112376.reviewer_comments.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig></body></sub-article></article></pmc-articleset>