<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">36</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcid</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12512682</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12512682.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12512682</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12512682</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41073932</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-025-11677-w</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">11677</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact of vaccination on SARS-CoV-2 infections and long COVID symptoms: a cross-sectional study in China</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaolong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="X">Xin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="L">Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianhua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qi</given-names></name><address><email>wangqi_tj@hust.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names initials="S">Sheng</given-names></name><address><email>ws2008cn@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00p991c53</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.33199.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0368 7223</institution-id><institution>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, School of Public Health, </institution><institution>Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>13 Hangkong Road, Wuhan, 430030 Hubei China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02yr91f43</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.508372.b</institution-id><institution>Center for Disease Control and Prevention, </institution></institution-wrap>Yichang, Hubei China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/049tv2d57</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.263817.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 1790</institution-id><institution>School of Public Health and Emergency Management, </institution><institution>Southern University of Science and Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Shenzhen, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478176</issue-id><elocation-id>1266</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-15 12:25:28.290"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12879_2025_Article_11677.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="structured"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Following the adjustment of the dynamic zero-COVID-19 strategy, China has witnessed a rapid increase in COVID-19 cases. However, the relationship between diverse vaccination statuses and the spectrum of symptom presentation, disease severity, and long-term post-COVID conditions remains to be fully understood. This study aimed to assess the impact of vaccination on the incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infections, the manifestation of acute symptoms, and the occurrence of long-term symptoms post-infection within the context of China's revised pandemic prevention and control measures.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This study investigated 6,572 participants from the Yichang COVID-19 Antibody Longitudinal Survey (YC-CALS) in March 2023, focusing on demographic and health-related information, including vaccination history, infection status, and symptomatology. Univariate and multivariate analysis methods were used to determine the correlations between vaccination status and COVID-19 outcomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Among the surveyed participants, 85.91% reported positive for SARS-CoV-2. Of those who were positive, 96.79% experienced at least one common symptom, with fever (79.34%), cough (62.56%), and fatigue (60.59%) being the most reported symptoms. Despite the high incidence of symptoms, only 2.05% of those who tested positive needed hospitalization. Importantly, symptoms such as palpitations, chest pain, and shortness of breath persisted beyond 90 days in certain individuals. Booster shots significantly reduced the risk of specific symptoms including dyspnea, eye soreness and fatigue, and gastrointestinal discomfort (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Vaccination beyond 12 months significantly increased symptoms such as decreased sense of smell, palpitations, and chest distress (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Additionally, the study found a positive correlation between the timing of vaccination and the development of long COVID symptoms, with individuals vaccinated more than 12 months prior exhibiting a higher likelihood of enduring symptoms such as fatigue (OR = 1.218, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.023) and headache dizziness (OR = 1.244, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.038) for over one month.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The findings highlight the critical importance of vaccination in controlling the spread of COVID-19 and reducing symptoms and disease prognosis, providing important insights for future vaccine policy.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12879-025-11677-w.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Vaccination</kwd><kwd>Symptoms</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>72061137006</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100012166</institution-id><institution>National Key Research and Development Program of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2022YFC2305103</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par11">With the ongoing evolution of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) Pandemic, the world is facing the challenge of coexisting with the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). As of January 2024, over 700 million infections and more than 6.8 million deaths have been reported globally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The virus's continuous mutations complicate vaccination strategies and public health responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Despite global vaccination efforts, the risks of infections and long COVID remain. In China, the relaxation of the zero-COVID policy in late 2022 triggered a large-scale infection surge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. This highlights regional disparities in pandemic control and vaccine efficacy, underscoring the need for research on post-vaccination infection symptoms and long-term effects.</p><p id="Par12">With the widespread administration of COVID-19 vaccines, research on vaccine efficacy and long-term sequelae (Long COVID) has become vital. Current research shows that vaccines effectively prevent severe illness and death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], but viral variants have contributed to rising infection rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. These infections can cause varying degrees of symptoms and, in some individuals, lead to Long COVID, characterized by persistent fatigue, cognitive disturbances, and other health issues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Evidence suggests that vaccine timing, dosage, and type influence protection against variants and post-infection symptom severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However, further studies are needed to explore these factors' impacts on specific populations, particularly in China.</p><p id="Par13">Shortly after the adjustment of China's dynamic zero-COVID strategy, a large-scale survey of SARS-CoV-2 infection was conducted in the Yichang area of Hubei Province, China. This study aimed to analyze the impact of different vaccination statuses on SARS-CoV-2 infection rates, disease severity, acute symptom presentation, and long-term symptoms post-infection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par14">This study depended on the Yichang COVID-19 Antibody Longitudinal Survey (YC-CALS). Briefly, the project selected all 14 districts and counties in Yichang, Hubei Province, China, as designated survey locations (S1A figure). Firstly, a cross-sectional survey was conducted to retrospectively assess the prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 infections following the relaxation of strict COVID-19 control measures in China in December 2022. Secondly, a prospective cohort study was employed to follow up on the population's SARS-CoV-2 antibody levels. Inclusion criteria for study subjects: (i) age over 1 year, (ii) no contraindication to venipuncture, (iii) acceptance of informed consent.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study participants</title><p id="Par15">The cross-sectional survey was conducted from March 20 to 30, 2023. The target population included community-based populations, special groups (including medical workers, epidemic prevention and control management populations, and nursing home workers), as well as early clustered infected populations (a university in Yichang in September 2022), with a total of 6,875 individuals surveyed.</p><p id="Par16">A stratified cluster sampling method was employed to survey community residents in Yichang. Initially, 1–2 communities were selected from each of the 14 districts using convenience sampling. Then, households within these communities were surveyed, with participants stratified by age groups (&lt; 20 years, 20–39 years, 40–59 years, and ≥ 60 years), resulting in a total of 4,804 community residents surveyed. The survey of special groups was conducted with the assistance of relevant institutions, where questionnaires were distributed and collected directly within these institutions. A total of 1,768 individuals from special groups participated in the survey. Additionally, a retrospective survey was carried out for the early cluster outbreak population, with 303 individuals surveyed.</p><p id="Par17">This study focused on SARS-CoV-2 infections after December 2022, following the relaxation of strict COVID-19 control measures. Consequently, the 303 individuals from the early cluster outbreak were excluded from the analysis. In total, 6,572 participants were included in the analysis (S1B figure). Statistical analysis showed that the age and sex distribution of the 6,572 participants did not significantly differ from the general population distribution in Yichang (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) (S2 figure).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Questionnaire survey</title><p id="Par18">The survey questionnaire collected information on general demographic characteristics (age, sex, height, weight, smoking status, etc.), SARS-CoV-2 infection characteristics after December 2022 (nucleic acid test results, antigen test results, onset time of symptoms, symptom types, symptom duration, medication use, medical visits, treatment details, etc.), COVID-19 vaccination history (vaccine doses, types of vaccines, vaccination dates, etc.), and underlying comorbidities (metabolic diseases, lung diseases, cardiovascular diseases, cancer, immunodeficiency diseases, etc.). Demographic and SARS-CoV-2 infection characteristics were primarily obtained through self-report from the participants. Information on medical behavior after SARS-CoV-2 infection was collected through self-report combined with the medical records provided by the participants. COVID-19 vaccination information was obtained through Yichang’s medical data platform, linked with participants' ID card information. Medical history was gathered through self-reports and diagnostic certificates or records provided by medical institutions. Detailed information on the survey questionnaire was provided in S1 Table.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par19">The count data were described using frequency (n) and percentage (%). The Chi-square test was used to compare the basic characteristics between the SARS-CoV-2 positive and negative groups. The Chi-square test was also used to analyze the effects of different vaccination statuses (including vaccine dosage, vaccine type, and vaccination timing) on disease outcomes related to SARS-CoV-2 infection. Multivariate logistic regression analyses were conducted to assess the relationship between vaccine doses, vaccine type, and vaccination timing with the occurrence and duration of symptoms. To control for potential confounders, all models adjusted for age, sex, risk group, smoking status, body mass index (BMI), comorbidities, previous infections, vaccine dose, and vaccination timing. The results were presented as odds ratios (OR) with corresponding 95% confidence intervals (95% CI). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values less than 0.05 were considered significant. Statistical analyses were performed using R (version 4.3.3).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Characteristics of participants</title><p id="Par20">Baseline characteristics of the 6,572 participants were shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3 figure. A total of 5,646 (85.91%) reported SARS-CoV-2 positivity (positive antigen and/or nucleic acid tests and/or self-reported symptoms) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3A figure). The age of participants was distributed in the 30–45, 45–59, and ≥ 60 age groups and the difference in age between SARS-CoV-2 positive and negative groups was statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3B figure). The proportion of female participants was significantly higher than males (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3C figure), and the proportion of smokers in the SARS-CoV-2 positive group was slightly lower than the negative group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3D figure). Sixty-two participants (0.94%) received one dose of the vaccine, 1,177 (17.91%) received two doses, 4,876 (74.19%) received three doses, and 394 (6.00%) received four doses (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3E figure). Most participants received three doses of inactivated vaccine, with 4659 individuals (70.89%). A total of 352 individuals (5.36%) received protein vaccines, and 17 individuals (2.59%) received adenoviral vector vaccines (S3J figure). The proportion of the population at high risk of exposure to SARS-CoV-2 in the SARS-CoV-2 positive group (healthcare workers, epidemic prevention and control management populations, and nursing home workers) was higher than the negative group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3F figure). There was no difference in BMI between the two groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.704) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3G figure). The proportion of participants with comorbidities was approximately 12% higher in the SARS-CoV-2 positive group than in the negative group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S3H figure). Among the participants, 215 (3.27%) had a history of SARS-CoV-2 infection before December 2022, when China lifted the dynamic clearance policy (S3I figure). The proportion of past infections was significantly lower in the SARS-CoV-2 positive group than in the negative group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of survey participants, March 2023, Yichang, Hubei Province, China</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics Category</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SARS-CoV-2 Positive(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5646)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SARS-CoV-2 Negative(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 926)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age group, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 12 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161(2.85)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56(6.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 12–18 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">701(12.42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129(13.93)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 18–29 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">790(13.99)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92(9.94)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 30–45 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,893(33.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161(17.39)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 45–59 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,296(22.95)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">196(21.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 60 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">805(14.26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">292(31.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,580(45.70)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">573(61.88)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,066(54.30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">353(38.12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Non-smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,556(80.69)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">664(71.71)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Quite<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">226(4.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45(4.86)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 10 per day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">220(3.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46(4.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 10—20 per day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">601(10.64)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151(16.31)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 20 per day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43(0.76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20(2.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risk population<sup>b</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Low risk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,616(28.62)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">380(41.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Medium risk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,844(50.37)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">456(49.24)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> High risk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,186(21.01)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90(9.72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.704</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Normal [18.5–24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,567(63.18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">574(61.99)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Overweight [25–29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,589(28.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">273(29.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Obese [&gt; 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">490(8.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79(8.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of comorbidities<sup>c</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> None</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,715(83.51)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">886(95.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">658(11.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23(2.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">206(3.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16(1.73)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67(1.19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1(0.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of past infections<sup>d</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Uninfected</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,545(98.21)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">812(87.69)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1 infection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95(1.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109(11.77)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 2 infection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6(0.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5(0.54)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of vaccination, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unvaccinated</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48(0.85)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15(1.62)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> One dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39(0.69)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23(2.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Two dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">977(17.30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200(21.61)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Three dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,385(77.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">491(53.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Four dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">197(3.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">197(21.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>a Quite: Individuals in the smoking cessation group are those who had previously smoked but ceased the habit at least one year ago</p><p>b Low risk: occupations include homeworker, unemployed, retired, freelance, farmers, construction workers, etc. Medium risk: occupations include transportation and basic industrial workers, employees of institutions and enterprises, students, teachers, etc. High risk: occupations include healthcare workers, epidemic prevention and control management populations, and nursing home workers</p><p>c Comorbidities refer to self-reported conditions by participants based on their medical records. These primarily include metabolic diseases, pulmonary diseases, cardiovascular diseases, cerebrovascular diseases, chronic kidney disease, cancer, chronic liver disease, immunodeficiency disorders, mental health conditions, and other chronic illnesses</p><p>d Past infection was defined as a previous infection before December 2022</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Symptoms of SARS-CoV-2 infection</title><p id="Par21">Of the 5,646 SARS-CoV-2 positive participants, 5,465 (96.79%) self-reported symptoms and only 181 (3.21%) were asymptomatic (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Of the symptomatic infected participants, 4,514 (82.60%) were using over-the-counter (OTC) medications for self-treatment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B), 820 (15.00%) were outpatients, and 112 (2.05%) were hospitalized (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C). Further analysis of the hospitalized participants showed that 80 (71.43%) were hospitalized for less than 10 days and only 1 was hospitalized for more than 30 days (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D). The most common symptoms in COVID-19 patients were fever (79.34%), cough (62.56%), fatigue (60.59%), pharyngeal discomfort (48.49%), full body soreness (45.54%), fear of cold shivering (37.13%), headache dizziness (35.72%), nasal congestion (28.67%), runny nose (26.15%) and decrease in taste (24.85%) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>E). In addition, other symptoms reported were mainly urticaria, night sweats, tinnitus and earache (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>F).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of symptoms among SARS-CoV-2 positive participants, March 2023, Yichang, Hubei Province, China. <bold>A</bold> Distribution of whether positive participants had symptoms. <bold>B</bold> Distribution of self-medication among symptomatic participants. <bold>C</bold> Distribution of type of medical visits among symptomatic participants. <bold>D</bold> Distribution of length of hospital stay among hospitalized participants. <bold>E</bold> Frequency of symptoms among symptomatic participants. <bold>F</bold> Distribution of other symptoms. <bold>G</bold> Duration of symptoms among symptomatic participants</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12879_2025_11677_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">Persistent symptoms (medium- and long-term symptoms) were evaluated by analyzing the duration of symptoms in symptomatic infected individuals (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>G). The results showed that although most symptoms improved in the short term (&lt; 7 or &lt; 14 days), a certain percentage of symptoms lasted longer than 30 or 60 days, especially cough, shortness of breath, palpitations, decreased smell, decreased taste, and fatigue. In terms of long-term symptoms, those that lasted longer than 90 days were most prevalent in palpitations, chest pain, and shortness of breath.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Effect of vaccination doses on SARS-CoV-2 infection</title><p id="Par23">The effects of vaccination doses on SARS-CoV-2 positivity rate, symptomatic or not, self-medication, medical visit, and hospital length of stay were shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A-E. The results showed that the number of vaccination doses significantly affected the SARS-CoV-2 positivity rate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). In particular, the positive rate gradually increased in participants who received 1–3 doses of vaccine, while the lowest positive rate was observed in participants who received 4 doses of vaccine. The proportion of symptomatic participants was similar across vaccine doses, and asymptomatic infections were not observed in unvaccinated individuals (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.772) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). The proportion of self-medication was similar in vaccinated and slightly lower in unvaccinated participants, but the difference was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.062) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). There was a difference in the proportion of outpatient visits and hospitalizations among participants with different vaccine doses (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D), and interestingly, the proportion of hospitalizations was lowest among participants who received 1 and 4 doses. No association was observed between vaccination and length of hospital stay (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.871) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>E). The effects of vaccine combinations (doses and type) on SARS-CoV-2 positivity, presence of symptoms, self-medication, presence of clinic visits, and length of hospitalization are shown in S4 figure. The results showed that participants who received 3 doses of inactivated and 1 dose of protein vaccine had the lowest percentage of SARS-CoV-2 positivity, followed by participants who received 4 doses of inactivated vaccine (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (S4A figure). Vaccine combinations were associated with the proportion of self-medication (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.034) (S4C figure) and clinic visits (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.031) (S4D figure).<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The effect of vaccination dose on SARS-CoV-2 infected participants, March 2023, Yichang, Hubei Province, China. <bold>A</bold> Effect of different vaccination doses on SARS-CoV-2 positive. <bold>B</bold> Effect of different vaccination doses on the presence of symptoms among positive participants. <bold>C</bold> Effect of different vaccination doses on self-medication among symptomatic participants. <bold>D</bold> Effect of different vaccination doses on the type of medical visits among symptomatic participants. <bold>E</bold> Effect of different vaccination doses on length of hospital stay among hospitalized participants. <bold>F</bold> Effect of different vaccination doses on the frequency of symptoms among symptomatic participants. Participants who received ≤ 2 vaccine doses were used as control group. Age, sex, risk population, smoking, BMI, comorbidities, past infections and vaccination timing were used as adjusted variables. OR &gt; 1 indicates an increased risk of symptoms, and OR &lt; 1 indicates a decreased risk of symptoms</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12879_2025_11677_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par24">Multivariate logistic regression was also utilized to assess the relationship between vaccination doses and symptoms of infection. After adjusting for age, sex, and other factors, the results showed that different vaccination doses were negatively associated with different symptoms (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>F). Specifically, vaccination with 3 and 4 doses significantly reduced dyspnea (OR = 0.526, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.009 and OR = 0.275, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002), eye soreness and fatigue (OR = 0.553, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.026 and OR = 0.263, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003), and gastrointestinal discomfort (OR = 0.57, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.03 and OR = 0.237, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001). Furthermore, vaccination with 3 or 4 doses significantly reduced the occurrence of shortness of breath, decrease in smell, chest distress, headache dizziness, and fever (OR &lt; 1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The results of the multivariate analysis showed that different vaccination combinations (doses and type) were significantly negatively associated with different symptoms (S4F figure). Specifically, compared with participants who received 2 doses of inactivated vaccine, receiving 3 doses of protein vaccine significantly reduced shortness of breath (OR = 0.370, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.03), runny nose (OR = 0.293, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001), nasal congestion (OR = 0.296, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and eye pain and fatigue (OR = 0.184, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.01). In addition, vaccination with 3 doses of inactivated vaccine combined with 1 dose of protein vaccine significantly reduced the decrease in smell (OR = 0.241, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.007), decrease in taste (OR = 0.4, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.032), and gastrointestinal discomfort (OR = 0.075, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Effect of vaccination timing on SARS-CoV-2 infection</title><p id="Par25">The effect of recent vaccination date on SARS-CoV-2 positivity, symptomatic or not, self-medication, clinic visits, and length of hospitalization were shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A-E. SARS-CoV-2 positivity was lower among participants vaccinated within 6 months (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). Vaccination timing was not associated with symptom status (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.087) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B) and was associated with self-medication (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C). A higher proportion of hospitalizations and longer hospital stays were observed among participants vaccinated for more than 6 months, but the differences were not significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.074 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.574) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D and E).<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The effect of vaccination timing on SARS-CoV-2 infected participants, March 2023, Yichang, Hubei Province, China. <bold>A</bold> Effect of different vaccination timing groups on SARS-CoV-2 positive. <bold>B</bold> Effect of different vaccination timing groups on the presence of symptoms among positive participants. <bold>C</bold> Effect of different vaccination timing groups on self-medication among symptomatic participants. <bold>D</bold> Effect of different vaccination timing groups on the type of medical visits among symptomatic participants. <bold>E</bold> Effect of different vaccination timing groups on length of hospital stay among hospitalized participants. <bold>F</bold> Effect of different vaccination timing groups on the frequency of symptoms among symptomatic participants. Participants who received vaccinations within 3 months were used as control group. Age, sex, risk population, smoking, BMI, comorbidities, past infections and vaccination dose were used as adjusted variables. OR &gt; 1 indicates an increased risk of symptoms, and OR &lt; 1 indicates a decreased risk of symptoms</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12879_2025_11677_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par26">Additionally, the results of the multivariate analysis showed that the different vaccination times were positively associated with different symptoms (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>F). Compared to participants vaccinated within 3 months, vaccination beyond 12 months significantly increased decrease in smell (OR = 1.912, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002), palpitations (OR = 2.252, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.039), chest distress (OR = 1.649, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.025), decrease in taste (OR = 1.665, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0. 003), fatigue (OR = 1.454, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006), eye pain and fatigue (OR = 2.031, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.033), full body soreness (OR = 1.456, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006), gastrointestinal discomfort (OR = 2.476, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006), headache dizziness (OR = 1.372, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.035), and fever (OR = 1.458, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.019).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Effect of different vaccination statues on duration of COVID-19 symptoms</title><p id="Par27">There was a correlation between the different vaccination statuses (doses, type, and timing) and the duration of symptoms (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The results showed that vaccination with 3 or 4 doses significantly reduced cough (OR = 0.707, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.049), decrease in smell (OR = 0.268, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.009), and eye soreness and fatigue (OR = 0.21, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022) more than 1 week. Vaccination with 3 doses of protein vaccine significantly reduced cough more than 1 week (OR = 0.459, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.019). Compared with the vaccination within 12 months, more than 12 months significantly increased the decrease in smell (OR = 1.854, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), palpitations (OR = 2.607, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004), decrease in taste (OR = 1.348, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024) and headache dizziness (OR = 1.57, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.013). Vaccination with 3 or 4 doses significantly reduced the decrease in smell (OR = 0.237, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.018) and joint pain (OR = 0.253, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.019) for more than 2 weeks. Vaccination more than 12 months prior significantly increased the likelihood of decreased smell (OR = 1.833, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002), decreased taste (OR = 1.462, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.032) and full body soreness (OR = 1.589, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.038) lasting more than 2 weeks. Additionally, it significantly increased fatigue (OR = 1.218, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.023) and headache/dizziness (OR = 1.244, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.038) for more than one month. The above results suggest that the interval between the latest vaccination and the infection could contribute to the persistence of individual symptoms (long COVID).<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlation between vaccination doses, vaccine type and vaccination timing with duration of symptoms among survey participants, March 2023, Yichang, Hubei Province, China</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR(95%CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptom (duration of time)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Vaccination dose<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Third dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.707(0.503 ~ 0.999)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.049</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cough (over 7 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Fourth dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.268(0.092 ~ 0.686)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decrease in smell (over 7 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Third dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21(0.063 ~ 0.989)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Eye soreness and eye fatigue (over 7 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Vaccination status<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3 protein vaccine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.459(0.273 ~ 0.888)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cough (over 7 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Vaccination timing<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.854(1.367 ~ 2.561)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decrease in smell (over 7 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.607(1.403 ~ 5.262)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Palpitations (over 7 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.348(1.044 ~ 1.759)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.024</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decrease in taste (over 7 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.57(1.366 ~ 1.895)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache dizziness (over 7 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Vaccination dose<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Fourth dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.237(0.063 ~ 0.734)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decrease in smell (over 14 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Third dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.253(0.089 ~ 0.928)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Joint pain (over 14 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Vaccine type<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3 inactivated vaccine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.193(0.062 ~ 0.848)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.011</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Joint pain (over 14 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Vaccination timing<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.883(1.285 ~ 2.838)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decrease in smell (over 14 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.462(1.043 ~ 2.09)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.032</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decrease in taste (over 14 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.589(1.359 ~ 1.978)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.038</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Full body soreness (over 14 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Vaccination timing<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.218(1.023 ~ 1.841)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.023</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue (over 30 days)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.244(1.059 ~ 1.922)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.038</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache dizziness (over 30 days)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>a Participants who received ≤ 2 vaccine doses were used as control group</p><p>b Participants who received 2 inactivated vaccine doses were used as control group</p><p>c Participants who received vaccinations within 12 months were used as control group</p><p>Age, sex, risk population, smoking, BMI, comorbidities, past infections, vaccination dose and timing were used as adjusted variables. Table 2 presents only symptoms at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; the full analysis was shown in S5 figure—S7 figure. OR &gt; 1 indicates an increased risk of symptoms, and OR &lt; 1 indicates a decreased risk of symptoms</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par28">This study analyzed vaccine administration and SARS-CoV-2 infection in 6,572 participants in the context of China's relaxation of strict COVID-19 control measures in December 2022. Over 98% of participants had received at least two vaccine doses, with 85.91% reporting SARS-CoV-2 positivity. Among the positive cases, 96.79% reported at least one common symptom, with fever (79.34%), cough (62.56%), and fatigue (60.59%) being the most prevalent. The study also revealed that symptoms such as palpitations, chest pain, and shortness of breath persisted for more than 90 days in some individuals. Notably, receiving three and four doses of the vaccine significantly reduced the incidence of symptoms like dyspnea, eye soreness and fatigue, and gastrointestinal discomfort. Vaccination beyond 12 months significantly increased symptoms such as decreased sense of smell, palpitations, and chest distress. Moreover, the interval between vaccination and infection was positively correlated with the occurrence of long COVID symptoms, with individuals vaccinated over 12 months prior more likely to exhibit persistent symptoms, especially fatigue and headache dizziness, lasting more than one month. These findings offer crucial insights into the epidemiological characteristics of breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 infections, the long-term efficacy of vaccination, and its impact on the persistence of long COVID symptoms.</p><p id="Par29">Despite the relatively lower severity of SARS-CoV-2 infections, the prevalence of persistent symptoms among many patients highlights the necessity for an in-depth understanding and strategy to address the long-term impacts of this disease. Among participants reporting positive for SARS-CoV-2, 85.91% manifested at least one symptom, yet only 2.05% required hospitalization. This proportion was significantly lower compared to the hospitalization rates observed in the early severe cases of COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], reflecting the mitigating effects of widespread vaccination and viral strain evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Recent studies have shown that during the Omicron variant pandemic, vaccination, particularly booster doses, as well as previous infections, still play a role in controlling new infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In the context of the global Omicron outbreak, many individuals who have been vaccinated or previously infected with COVID-19 still experience breakthrough infections. These breakthrough infections are primarily characterized by mild symptoms such as fever, cough, fatigue, and sore throat. This is mainly due to the reduced virulence of the Omicron Strain, as well as the presence of a certain level of immune response and immune memory within the population. Notably, while most symptoms resolved within two weeks, a considerable proportion of participants reported persistent medium to long-term symptoms, including cough, shortness of breath, palpitations, diminished taste and smell, and fatigue, with some individuals experiencing these symptoms for over 90 days. The observed persistence of these symptoms aligns generally with the high frequency of prolonged COVID-19 symptoms attributed to the BA.5 and BF.7 variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. These observations suggest that the recovery period post-SARS-CoV-2 infection, even in the context of extensive vaccination, may be longer than that of typical viral colds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. These findings highlight the need for further research into recovery mechanisms and symptom resolution after SARS-CoV-2 infection, as well as the importance of focusing on patients' quality of life and long-term rehabilitation strategies for managing COVID-19.</p><p id="Par30">This study further corroborates the significant role of multiple vaccine doses and the intervals between vaccinations in mitigating the severity of COVID-19. The findings indicate that individuals vaccinated with four doses exhibited lower rates of SARS-CoV-2 positivity and hospitalization, aligning with prior research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In addition, individuals vaccinated within the previous six months had significantly lower rates of positivity and hospitalization. Further analysis showed that participants who were hospitalized more than six months after vaccination had longer hospital stays. This observation is consistent with the notion that vaccine efficacy wanes over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Multiple studies have shown that booster immunity provides stable protection against severe COVID-19 for up to one year, but the protection against symptomatic infection significantly declines over time after the last dose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. This highlighted the critical role of booster vaccinations in reducing the burden of COVID-19 on healthcare resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Importantly, the study also found that different vaccine doses and types significantly improved several COVID-19 symptoms, such as dyspnea, eye pain, and fatigue, which is consistent with previous findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Apart from vaccine dosage and type, the results suggest that the interval between vaccination and infection also plays a role in alleviating COVID-19 symptoms. A possible reason is that timely vaccination can more effectively enhance the immune system's defense against the virus, thereby reducing the occurrence of symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. As time passes, however, the immune protection gradually decreases, especially against symptomatic infections, making timely booster doses an important strategy for mitigating COVID-19 symptoms.</p><p id="Par31">Timely vaccination, especially booster doses, helps reduce the duration of COVID-19 symptoms and alleviates long-term effects. The study findings indicate that receiving three or four doses of the vaccine significantly reduced symptoms such as cough, loss of smell, eye pain, and fatigue lasting more than 1–2 weeks or even longer. This aligns with previous research on the impact of booster doses on the long-term symptoms of breakthrough infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Individuals who received three doses of a protein-based vaccine experienced a notable reduction in the duration of cough, suggesting that different vaccine types may have varying effects on the alleviation of specific symptoms. Heterologous booster vaccination generally induces a stronger immune response compared to homologous boosters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Given that inactivated vaccines were primarily used in early vaccinations in China, other vaccines, such as adenovirus-vectored vaccines or recombinant subunit vaccines, could be considered for future boosters. Furthermore, individuals vaccinated more than 12 months ago exhibited significantly longer durations of symptoms such as loss of smell, palpitations, loss of taste, fatigue, and headache dizziness. This suggests that delayed vaccination may have an adverse impact on the experience of long COVID symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. These findings were of significant value for public health strategies, particularly in optimizing vaccination schedules to mitigate the long-term impacts of COVID-19.</p><p id="Par32">This study has several limitations. Firstly, it is unable to establish a causal relationship between vaccination and the alleviation of the severity and duration of COVID-19 symptoms due to the cross-sectional nature of the study. Although logistic regression analysis was employed to adjust for potential confounders, unmeasured variables could still affect the observed associations. Secondly, reliance on participant-reported symptoms and duration may introduce recall bias, potentially affecting the accuracy of study findings. Additionally, the focus on the Yichang area of Hubei Province, China, might limit the generalizability of our results. Local public health policies and vaccination campaigns may not fully represent the global diversity of SARS-CoV-2 transmission and vaccine distribution scenarios. Finally, due to the rapid evolution of SARS-CoV-2 and the frequent emergence of new variants, there is a lack of sufficient analysis of the clinical characteristics of populations infected with new variants in the post-pandemic period. The findings of this study reflect the situation only up until March 2023, and therefore, the conclusions are time-sensitive. Future research will provide important insights into the timely updates on changes in vaccine efficacy, especially concerning the waning effects over time. Nevertheless, this study provided valuable evidence for the ongoing discussion on COVID-19 vaccination strategies and their role in mitigating the impact of the pandemic.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par33">Following the relaxation of strict COVID-19 control policies in December 2022, SARS-CoV-2 breakthrough infections in the study population were generally mild. However, persistent long COVID symptoms suggest lasting health impacts. Booster doses and different vaccine types may help alleviate some symptoms, and regular vaccination can prevent certain long COVID outcomes. Public health authorities should monitor viral evolution and adjust vaccination strategies to effectively address variants and reduce COVID-19’s public health impact.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12879_2025_11677_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>SARS-CoV-2</term><def><p id="Par5">Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par6">Coronavirus disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YC-CALS</term><def><p id="Par7">Yichang COVID-19 Antibody Longitudinal Survey</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p id="Par8">Body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p id="Par9">Odds ratios</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par10">Confidence intervals</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Xiaolong Yan and Xin Zhao contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors express sincere gratitude to all study participants. Furthermore, the staff at the Disease Control Center in Yichang City, Hubei Province, China are acknowledged for their invaluable assistance throughout the entire project.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>XL led the study conceptualization and the development of the research question, supported by SW and JH. YD and XZ were responsible for data collection. XL, HW, LL and QW developed the statistical analysis plan and performed the analyses. XL and XZ wrote the first draft of the paper. All authors contributed to the interpretation and discussion of the results, critically revised the manuscript, and approved the final version and the submission of the manuscript. The corresponding author had final responsibility for the decision to submit for publication.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Key Research and Development Program of China (grant no. 2022YFC2305103) and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant no. 72061137006).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data supporting the findings and conclusions are available upon request from the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par34">This study performed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. The study protocol was approved by the Clinical Research Review Board of Huazhong University of Science and Technology Tongji Medical College (registration number: 2021-IEC-A209). All participants signed an informed consent form.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par35">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par36">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. WHO coronavirus (COVID-19) dashboard. 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int/">https://covid19.who.int/</ext-link>. Accessed 06 May 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies for the development and approval of COVID-19 vaccines and therapeutics in the post-pandemic period</article-title><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>466</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-023-01724-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38129394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10739883</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Ao D, He X, Liu J, Xu L. Strategies for the development and approval of COVID-19 vaccines and therapeutics in the post-pandemic period. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2023;8(1):466. 10.1038/s41392-023-01724-w.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38129394</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41392-023-01724-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10739883</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Challenges and developments in universal vaccine design against SARS-CoV-2 variants</article-title><source>NPJ Vaccines</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>167</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41541-022-00597-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36535982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9761649</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Zhao F, Zai X, Zhang Z, Xu J, Chen W. Challenges and developments in universal vaccine design against SARS-CoV-2 variants. NPJ Vaccines. 2022;7(1):167. 10.1038/s41541-022-00597-4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36535982</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41541-022-00597-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9761649</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farlow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torreele</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruxrungtham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The future of epidemic and pandemic vaccines to serve global public health needs</article-title><source>Vaccines</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>690</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines11030690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36992275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10052681</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Farlow A, Torreele E, Gray G, Ruxrungtham K, Rees H, Prasad S, et al. The future of epidemic and pandemic vaccines to serve global public health needs. Vaccines. 2023;11(3):690. 10.3390/vaccines11030690.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36992275</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vaccines11030690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10052681</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of SARS-CoV-2 variants in Beijing during 2022: an epidemiological and phylogenetic analysis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2023</year><volume>401</volume><issue>10377</issue><fpage>664</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00129-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36773619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9949854</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Pan Y, Wang L, Feng Z, Xu H, Li F, Shen Y, et al. Characterisation of SARS-CoV-2 variants in Beijing during 2022: an epidemiological and phylogenetic analysis. Lancet. 2023;401(10377):664–72. 10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00129-0.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36773619</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00129-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9949854</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of mild patients with breakthrough infection of Omicron variant in China after relaxing the dynamic zero COVID-19 policy</article-title><source>Vaccines</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>968</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines11050968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37243072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10224174</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">He Y, Zhang F, Liu Y, Xiong Z, Zheng S, Liu W, et al. Clinical characteristics of mild patients with breakthrough infection of Omicron variant in China after relaxing the dynamic zero COVID-19 policy. Vaccines. 2023;11(5):968. 10.3390/vaccines11050968.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37243072</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vaccines11050968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10224174</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dynamic COVID-Zero strategy in China</article-title><source>China CDC Wkly</source><year>2022</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46234/ccdcw2022.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35186372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8837441</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Liu J, Liu M, Liang W. The dynamic COVID-Zero strategy in China. China CDC Wkly. 2022;4(4):74–5. 10.46234/ccdcw2022.015.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35186372</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.46234/ccdcw2022.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8837441</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez Bernal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gower</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stowe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tessier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of the Pfizer-BioNTech and Oxford-AstraZeneca vaccines on covid-19 related symptoms, hospital admissions, and mortality in older adults in England: test negative case-control study</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2021</year><volume>373</volume><fpage>n1088</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n1088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33985964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8116636</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Lopez Bernal J, Andrews N, Gower C, Robertson C, Stowe J, Tessier E, et al. Effectiveness of the Pfizer-BioNTech and Oxford-AstraZeneca vaccines on covid-19 related symptoms, hospital admissions, and mortality in older adults in England: test negative case-control study. BMJ. 2021;373:n1088. 10.1136/bmj.n1088.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33985964</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.n1088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8116636</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cromer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynaldi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlub</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting vaccine effectiveness against severe COVID-19 over time and against variants: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1633</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-37176-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36964146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10036966</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Cromer D, Steain M, Reynaldi A, Schlub TE, Khan SR, Sasson SC, et al. Predicting vaccine effectiveness against severe COVID-19 over time and against variants: a meta-analysis. Nat Commun. 2023;14(1):1633. 10.1038/s41467-023-37176-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36964146</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-023-37176-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10036966</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines and the dose-response relationship with three major antibodies: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</article-title><source>Lancet Microbe</source><year>2023</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e236</fpage><lpage>e246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2666-5247(22)00390-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36868258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9974155</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Yang ZR, Jiang YW, Li FX, Liu D, Lin TF, Zhao ZY, et al. Efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines and the dose-response relationship with three major antibodies: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Lancet Microbe. 2023;4(4):e236–46. 10.1016/s2666-5247(22)00390-1.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36868258</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2666-5247(22)00390-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9974155</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madewell</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Longini</surname><given-names>IM</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halloran</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Household secondary attack rates of SARS-CoV-2 by variant and vaccination status: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e229317</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.9317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35482308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9051991</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Madewell ZJ, Yang Y, Longini IM Jr., Halloran ME, Dean NE. Household secondary attack rates of SARS-CoV-2 by variant and vaccination status: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5(4):e229317. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.9317.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35482308</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.9317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9051991</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 vaccine breakthrough infection in the older adults: a meta-analysis and systematic review</article-title><source>Bmc Infect Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>577</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-023-08553-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37667195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10478381</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Jing X, Han M, Wang X, Zhou L. SARS-CoV-2 vaccine breakthrough infection in the older adults: a meta-analysis and systematic review. Bmc Infect Dis. 2023;23(1):577. 10.1186/s12879-023-08553-w.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37667195</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-023-08553-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10478381</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Topol EJ. Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023;21(3):133–46. 10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A one-year follow-up study of systematic impact of long COVID symptoms among patients post SARS-CoV-2 omicron variants infection in Shanghai, China</article-title><source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>2220578</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2023.2220578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37272336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10281439</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Cai J, Lin K, Zhang H, Xue Q, Zhu K, Yuan G, et al. A one-year follow-up study of systematic impact of long COVID symptoms among patients post SARS-CoV-2 omicron variants infection in Shanghai, China. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2023;12(2):2220578. 10.1080/22221751.2023.2220578.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37272336</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/22221751.2023.2220578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10281439</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of vaccinations and breakthrough infections after adjustment of the dynamic zero-COVID-19 strategy in China: an online survey</article-title><source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>2258232</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2023.2258232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37691586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10512888</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Qin S, Li Y, Wang L, Zhao X, Ma X, Gao GF. Assessment of vaccinations and breakthrough infections after adjustment of the dynamic zero-COVID-19 strategy in China: an online survey. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2023;12(2):2258232. 10.1080/22221751.2023.2258232.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37691586</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/22221751.2023.2258232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10512888</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a descriptive study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><volume>395</volume><issue>10223</issue><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30211-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32007143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7135076</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Chen N, Zhou M, Dong X, Qu J, Gong F, Han Y, et al. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a descriptive study. Lancet. 2020;395(10223):507–13. 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30211-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32007143</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30211-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7135076</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>3044 cases reveal important prognosis signatures of COVID-19 patients</article-title><source>Comput Struct Biotechnol J</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1163</fpage><lpage>1175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2021.01.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33584997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7870437</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Qin S, Li W, Shi X, Wu Y, Wang C, Shen J, et al. 3044 cases reveal important prognosis signatures of COVID-19 patients. Comput Struct Biotechnol J. 2021;19:1163–75. 10.1016/j.csbj.2021.01.042.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33584997</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.csbj.2021.01.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7870437</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedston</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCowan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Severe COVID-19 outcomes after full vaccination of primary schedule and initial boosters: pooled analysis of national prospective cohort studies of 30 million individuals in England, Northern Ireland, Scotland, and Wales</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2022</year><volume>400</volume><issue>10360</issue><fpage>1305</fpage><lpage>1320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01656-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36244382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9560746</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Agrawal U, Bedston S, McCowan C, Oke J, Patterson L, Robertson C, et al. Severe COVID-19 outcomes after full vaccination of primary schedule and initial boosters: pooled analysis of national prospective cohort studies of 30 million individuals in England, Northern Ireland, Scotland, and Wales. Lancet. 2022;400(10360):1305–20. 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01656-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36244382</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01656-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9560746</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaxman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of the risks of hospitalisation and death associated with SARS-CoV-2 omicron (B.1.1.529) and delta (B.1.617.2) variants in England: a cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2022</year><volume>399</volume><issue>10332</issue><fpage>1303</fpage><lpage>1312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00462-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35305296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8926413</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Nyberg T, Ferguson NM, Nash SG, Webster HH, Flaxman S, Andrews N, et al. Comparative analysis of the risks of hospitalisation and death associated with SARS-CoV-2 omicron (B.1.1.529) and delta (B.1.617.2) variants in England: a cohort study. Lancet. 2022;399(10332):1303–12. 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00462-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35305296</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00462-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8926413</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Accorsi</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming-Dutra</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between 3 doses of mRNA COVID-19 vaccine and symptomatic infection caused by the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron and Delta variants</article-title><source>Jama-J Am Med Assoc</source><year>2022</year><volume>327</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.0470</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Accorsi EK, Britton A, Fleming-Dutra KE, Smith ZR, Shang N, Derado G, et al. Association between 3 doses of mRNA COVID-19 vaccine and symptomatic infection caused by the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron and Delta variants. Jama-J Am Med Assoc. 2022;327(7):639–51. 10.1001/jama.2022.0470.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming-Dutra</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Link-Gelles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Accorsi</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of prior BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccination with symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection in children and adolescents during Omicron predominance</article-title><source>Jama-J Am Med Assoc</source><year>2022</year><volume>327</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>2210</fpage><lpage>2219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.7493</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Fleming-Dutra KE, Britton A, Shang N, Derado G, Link-Gelles R, Accorsi EK, et al. Association of prior BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccination with symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection in children and adolescents during Omicron predominance. Jama-J Am Med Assoc. 2022;327(22):2210–9. 10.1001/jama.2022.7493.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlsson Valik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Werff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanushi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Requena Mendez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Granath</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical phenotypes and outcomes of SARS-CoV-2, influenza, RSV and seven other respiratory viruses: a retrospective study using complete hospital data</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2022</year><volume>77</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2021-216949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34226206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8260304</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Hedberg P, Karlsson Valik J, van der Werff S, Tanushi H, Requena Mendez A, Granath F, et al. Clinical phenotypes and outcomes of SARS-CoV-2, influenza, RSV and seven other respiratory viruses: a retrospective study using complete hospital data. Thorax. 2022;77(2):154–63. 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2021-216949.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34226206</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2021-216949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8260304</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Danza P, Koo TH, Haddix M, Fisher R, Traub E, K OY, et al. SARS-CoV-2 infection and hospitalization among adults aged &gt;/=18 years, by vaccination status, before and during SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.529 (Omicron) variant predominance - Los Angeles county, California, November 7, 2021-January 8, 2022. MMWR Morbidity and mortality weekly report 2022;71(5):177–181. 10.15585/mmwr.mm7105e1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferdinands</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeSilva</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Waning 2-dose and 3-dose effectiveness of mRNA vaccines against COVID-19-associated emergency department and urgent care encounters and hospitalizations among adults during periods of Delta and Omicron variant predominance - VISION network, 10 states, August 2021-January 2022</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>71</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7107e2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35176007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8853475</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Ferdinands JM, Rao S, Dixon BE, Mitchell PK, DeSilva MB, Irving SA, et al. Waning 2-dose and 3-dose effectiveness of mRNA vaccines against COVID-19-associated emergency department and urgent care encounters and hospitalizations among adults during periods of Delta and Omicron variant predominance - VISION network, 10 states, August 2021-January 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71(7):255–63. 10.15585/mmwr.mm7107e2.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35176007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm7107e2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8853475</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marimuthu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thevasagayam</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of COVID-19 incidence and severity among adults vaccinated with 2-dose mRNA COVID-19 or inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccines with and without boosters in Singapore</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e2228900</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.28900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36018588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9419014</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Ng OT, Marimuthu K, Lim N, Lim ZQ, Thevasagayam NM, Koh V, et al. Analysis of COVID-19 incidence and severity among adults vaccinated with 2-dose mRNA COVID-19 or inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccines with and without boosters in Singapore. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5(8):e2228900. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.28900.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36018588</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.28900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9419014</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pribylova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Majek</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarkovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protection by vaccines and previous infection against the Omicron variant of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>226</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1385</fpage><lpage>1390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiac161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35482442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9129207</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Smid M, Berec L, Pribylova L, Majek O, Pavlik T, Jarkovsky J, et al. Protection by vaccines and previous infection against the Omicron variant of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2. J Infect Dis. 2022;226(8):1385–90. 10.1093/infdis/jiac161.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35482442</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/infdis/jiac161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9129207</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulper-Schiek</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piechotta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pilic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreveton</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geurts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Facing the Omicron variant-how well do vaccines protect against mild and severe COVID-19? Third interim analysis of a living systematic review</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>940562</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.940562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36091023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9449804</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Kulper-Schiek W, Piechotta V, Pilic A, Batke M, Dreveton LS, Geurts B, et al. Facing the Omicron variant-how well do vaccines protect against mild and severe COVID-19? Third interim analysis of a living systematic review. Front Immunol. 2022;13:940562. 10.3389/fimmu.2022.940562.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36091023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2022.940562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9449804</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheelock</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of booster vaccination in decreasing COVID-19 age-adjusted case fatality rate: evidence from 32 countries</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1150095</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1150095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37143970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10151823</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Zhou C, Wheelock AM, Zhang C, Ma J, Dong K, Pan J, et al. The role of booster vaccination in decreasing COVID-19 age-adjusted case fatality rate: evidence from 32 countries. Front Public Health. 2023;11:1150095. 10.3389/fpubh.2023.1150095.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37143970</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1150095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10151823</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Kaabi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Qahtani</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdulrazzaq</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of 2 inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccines on symptomatic COVID-19 infection in adults: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2021</year><volume>326</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.8565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34037666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8156175</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Al Kaabi N, Zhang Y, Xia S, Yang Y, Al Qahtani MM, Abdulrazzaq N, et al. Effect of 2 inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccines on symptomatic COVID-19 infection in adults: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2021;326(1):35–45. 10.1001/jama.2021.8565.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34037666</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2021.8565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8156175</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slama</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumesges</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Baut</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hakim</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patients with Long COVID continue to experience significant symptoms at 12 months and factors associated with improvement: A prospective cohort study in France (PERSICOR)</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>3</volume><issue>140</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2023.11.038</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Salmon D, Slama D, Linard F, Dumesges N, Le Baut V, Hakim F, et al. Patients with Long COVID continue to experience significant symptoms at 12 months and factors associated with improvement: A prospective cohort study in France (PERSICOR). Int J Infect Dis. 2024;3(140):9–16. 10.1016/j.ijid.2023.11.038.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapuente</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tenbusch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>B-cell and antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2: infection, vaccination, and hybrid immunity</article-title><source>Cell Mol Immunol</source><year>2024</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41423-023-01095-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37945737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10805925</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Lapuente D, Winkler TH, Tenbusch M. B-cell and antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2: infection, vaccination, and hybrid immunity. Cell Mol Immunol. 2024;21(2):144–58. 10.1038/s41423-023-01095-w.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37945737</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41423-023-01095-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10805925</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Domenico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of long COVID decreases for increasing COVID-19 vaccine uptake</article-title><source>PLOS Glob Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e0001917</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0001917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37342998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10284420</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">De Domenico M. Prevalence of long COVID decreases for increasing COVID-19 vaccine uptake. PLOS Glob Public Health. 2023;3(6):e0001917. 10.1371/journal.pgph.0001917.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37342998</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pgph.0001917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10284420</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Togt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hishmeh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of COVID vaccination on symptoms of long COVID: an international survey of people with lived experience of long COVID</article-title><source>Vaccines</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>652</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines10050652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35632408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9146071</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Strain WD, Sherwood O, Banerjee A, Van der Togt V, Hishmeh L, Rossman J. The impact of COVID vaccination on symptoms of long COVID: an international survey of people with lived experience of long COVID. Vaccines. 2022;10(5):652. 10.3390/vaccines10050652.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35632408</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vaccines10050652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9146071</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>