<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Neurol Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Neurol Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4001</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjno</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjno</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Neurology Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2632-6140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12863312</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12863312.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12863312</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12863312</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41635577</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjno-2025-001399</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjno-2025-001399</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Short Report</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Non-invasive electrodiagnostic testing for small fibre neuropathy in long COVID-19</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3493-5202</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names initials="A">Anthony</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8465-4364</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Manuel</surname><given-names initials="K">Kisani</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names initials="T">Tracy</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2996-5135</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Crotty</surname><given-names initials="M">Maria</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">College of Medicine and Public Health</institution>, <institution>Flinders University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Adelaide</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">South Australia</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Neurology</institution>, <institution>Southern Adelaide Local Health Network</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Bedford Park</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">South Australia</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Flinders Health and Medical Research Institute</institution>, <institution>Flinders University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Bedford Park</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">South Australia</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Rehabilitation and Aged Care</institution>, <institution>Southern Adelaide Local Health Network</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Bedford Park</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">South Australia</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><p>Additional supplemental material is published online only. To view, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjno-2025-001399" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjno-2025-001399</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn4"><p>No, there are no competing interests.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Dr Anthony Khoo; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="anthony.khoo@flinders.edu.au">anthony.khoo@flinders.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">504459</issue-id><elocation-id>e001399</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-04 09:25:12.630"><day>04</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2026. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjno-8-1.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjno-8-1.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>Long COVID-19 is associated with a diverse range of debilitating neuropathic and autonomic symptoms that may indicate small fibre neuropathy (SFN). We aimed to assess the utility of multimodal non-invasive electrodiagnostic techniques in evaluating symptomatic individuals.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>People with confirmed long COVID-19 who scored &gt;10 points on the Small Fibre Neuropathy Screening List (SFNSL) questionnaire underwent routine neurophysiological testing and a non-invasive SFN protocol of (a) sympathetic skin responses, (b) cutaneous silent period, (c) quantitative thermal thresholds and (d) electrochemical skin conductance. Clinical and demographic information was collected on all individuals who underwent comprehensive physical and psychometric evaluation, including a 6-min walk test, National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Lean Test, Composite Autonomic Symptom Score-31 (COMPASS-31), European Quality of Life 5-Dimension 5-Level Questionnaire (ED-5D-5L), Modified Fatigue Impact Scale (MFIS) score and Patient Health (depression) Questionnaire (PHQ-9).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We assessed nine individuals, of whom three (33%) had neurophysiological evidence of SFN. Median age was 47.8 (range 26.3–67.6) years, duration from COVID-19 infection 23.0 (range 8.5–35.7) months and median SFNSL 34/84. All individuals scored highly in disability measures.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Long COVID-19 is associated with functional disability and reduced quality of life. SFN should be considered in all individuals with a suggestive clinical phenotype of neuropathic and autonomic symptoms.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>NEUROPHYSIOLOGY</kwd><kwd>AUTONOMIC</kwd><kwd>NEUROPATHY</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> Long COVID-19 is a complex, multisystem disorder that affects over 400 million people worldwide.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> It is associated with a diverse range of debilitating symptoms, with a variety of therapies being trialled for symptomatic individuals with varying success.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 3</sup></xref> The mechanisms that underpin symptoms in long COVID-19 are poorly understood, although associations with immune dysregulation and nervous system dysfunction have been proposed.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> For individuals with concomitant neuropathic and autonomic symptoms, the presence of a small fibre neuropathy (SFN) affecting thinly myelinated or unmyelinated sensory and autonomic fibres is a likely unifying diagnosis.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5 6</sup></xref> Up to half of long COVID-19 sufferers with co-existing pain and autonomic symptoms have evidence of SFN on skin biopsy.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7 8</sup></xref></p><p>In clinical practice, SFN can often be diagnosed on clinical and targeted electrodiagnostic testing without proceeding to a skin biopsy.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9 10</sup></xref> Identification of SFN is important as it allows for more tailored management strategies and provides critical validation of symptoms for long COVID-19 sufferers. Multimodal electrodiagnostic testing in diabetic patients with SFN has demonstrated high sensitivity (&gt;70%–80%) and specificity (96%–100%) when compared against gold standard intraepidermal nerve fibre density in distal punch skin biopsy.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></p><p>We aimed to explore the use of multimodal non-invasive small fibre electrodiagnostic testing in people diagnosed with long COVID-19 experiencing neuropathic and autonomic symptoms.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>We prospectively evaluated a multimodal electrodiagnostic protocol on consecutive patients referred from a multidisciplinary long COVID-19 clinic at Flinders Medical Centre in South Australia between May 2024 and January 2025.</p><p>We included individuals with confirmed long COVID-19 and the presence of neurological and/or autonomic symptoms as evidenced by history, physical examination and a score of &gt;10 points on the Small Fibre Neuropathy Screening List (SFNSL) questionnaire. This questionnaire has been used to screen for SFN in other medical conditions such as sarcoidosis, where a score &gt;10 has high (&gt;90%) sensitivity for SFN.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12 13</sup></xref> Individuals were directly referred by treating clinicians and contacted by the study team for consent if eligible for inclusion. Individuals with a history of peripheral neuropathy or the presence of any neuropathic symptoms predating the onset of COVID-19 were excluded. All patients also had blood tests looking for common causes of large fibre neuropathy and excluded from the study if there was another identifiable cause of neuropathy (eg, diabetes mellitus, B12/folate deficiency, hypothyroidism, haematological malignancy).</p><p>Individuals underwent a single neurophysiology testing session, including assessment of (1) sympathetic skin responses, (2) cutaneous silent period, (3) quantitative thermal thresholds and (4) electrochemical skin conductance (Sudoscan), with additional details in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental tables 1 and 4</xref>. In line with our clinical practice, individuals had to demonstrate abnormalities in at least two of four small fibre tests to have electrophysiological evidence of SFN. All individuals also underwent routine nerve conduction studies (NCS).</p><p>We collected detailed clinical, demographic, functional and psychometric data on individuals to assess for differences between disability measures in those with or without neurophysiological evidence of SFN. This included a 6-min walk test, National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Lean Test, Composite Autonomic Symptom Score-31 (COMPASS-31), European Quality of Life 5-Dimension 5-Level Questionnaire (ED-5D-5L), Modified Fatigue Impact Scale (MFIS) score and Patient Health (depression) Questionnaire (PHQ-9).</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>We assessed nine (6 female, 3 male) individuals recruited from the Flinders Medical Centre long COVID-19 clinic between April 2024 and January 2025. Median age was 47.8 (range 26.3–67.6) years and median duration from COVID-19 infection was 23.0 (range 8.5–35.7) months. The median SFNSL score was 34 (range 17–62) and median Composite Autonomic Symptom Score-31 was 45.4 (range 26.3–57.0) reflecting a high cumulative burden of neuropathic and autonomic symptoms. Clinical and demographic information of tested individuals, and results of SFN testing are summarised in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2 and 3</xref>.</p><p>All patients reported significant fatigue, with other frequent complaints of ‘brain-fog’ (89%), limb paraesthesias (66%), dizziness/light-headedness (56%) and postural light-headedness (33%). A variety of medications had been trialled for these symptoms including naltrexone, pyridostigmine, ivabradine, pregabalin and tricyclic antidepressants.</p><p>Routine nerve conduction studies in all individuals were normal. We detected neurophysiological evidence of SFN in three (33%) individuals. This included two individuals with bilaterally absent lower limb sympathetic skin responses (SSRs), two individuals with prolonged cutaneous silent period (CSP) onset latency with normal duration in both upper and lower limbs, and two individuals with reduced electrochemical skin conductance (ESC) on Sudoscan. In the two individuals with abnormal quantitative sensory testing, one individual had abnormal cold and warm detection thresholds in the lower limbs, with the other individual having abnormal cold but preserved warm detection thresholds in the lower limbs (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2</xref>). An example of abnormal multimodal SFN testing is shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Neurophysiological tests for small fibre neuropathy (SFN). A1: Normal example of quantitative thermal thresholds with detection limits of three cold and hot stimuli assessed in an upper and lower limb (only lower limb shown). A2: Example of abnormal cold and hot detection thresholds in SFN (Supplementary Information: Patient 1). B1: Normal example of sympathetic skin responses recorded in the lower limbs. B2: Absent sympathetic skin response in SFN. (Patient 1) C: Markedly prolonged cutaneous silent period onset (147 ms) in SFN. (Patient 3) D: Abnormal electrochemical skin conductance in a length-dependent distribution in SFN. (Patient 2)</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjno-8-1-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Five patients had a positive NASA Lean Test indicating orthostatic intolerance, although none had a significant (&gt;20 mm Hg) postural blood pressure drop. There was no significant difference across symptom scores between people with and without SFN, with both groups scoring highly in disability measures (median EQ-5D-5L 40/100; MFIS 69/84; PHQ-9 18/27).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Small fibre neuropathy is frequently seen in patients with long COVID-19 and is associated with symptoms including pain, paraesthesia, dysautonomia and fatigue which cause considerable disability.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></p><p>We evaluated a multimodal electrodiagnostic testing protocol in people with confirmed long COVID-19 to determine if evidence of SFN can be detected non-invasively. Notably, we demonstrated different combinations of abnormality among the four small fibre neuropathy tests illustrating the benefit of multimodal SFN testing protocols which interrogate different small nerve fibres.</p><p>The average time from COVID-19 infection was almost 2 years, consistent with current experiences worldwide that long COVID-19 symptoms persist in the majority of individuals between 12 and 36 months.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14 15</sup></xref> Despite the length of time since initial infection, individuals scored highly across a range of different symptom scores, which highlights both the considerable disability experienced by many people with long COVID-19, and also the value in performing electrodiagnostic testing, as symptom scores alone were unable to distinguish the presence of SFN between the two groups. Although an SFNSL &gt;10 has demonstrated high sensitivity for detecting SFN, it lacks specificity. Among our tested individuals, median SFNSL was considerably higher than this cut-off, even among those without SFN. Further research assessing rates of SFN in long COVID-19 is required to evaluate the utility of this as a screening tool. Nonetheless, in our experience, it provides a simple questionnaire that can be easily self-completed to provide a basis for further assessment by a trained clinician. Given our small sample size, we were unable to comment on the sensitivity of our multimodal electrodiagnostic SFN protocol; however, the rate of detected abnormalities (33%) compares favourably to other cohorts using skin biopsy, where approximately 50% of symptomatic individuals with long COVID-19 were diagnosed with SFN.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7 8</sup></xref></p><p>Patients reported a wide variety of neurological, cardio-respiratory and psychological symptoms, in keeping with reports from other long COVID-19 cohorts. While we were unable to determine the overall prevalence of neuropathic symptoms from all patients seen in our long COVID-19 clinics, neuropathic symptoms have previously been reported in half of individuals with the condition. Where skin biopsy has been performed, up to 50% of these have evidence of SFN.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7 8</sup></xref> Consistent with previous reports, all our individuals reported symptoms occurring within 2 months of SARS-CoV-2 infection (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2</xref>).<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref></p><p>A key finding of our study was demonstrating that objective abnormalities on small fibre electrodiagnostic testing can be identified in people with long COVID-19 and neuropathic symptoms. The combination of four SFN tests was quick, well-tolerated and able to be performed with minimal specialist training. There are, nonetheless, limitations to electrodiagnostic testing for SFN, emphasising the need for multimodal techniques and appropriate candidate selection to maximise sensitivity and specificity. Sympathetic skin responses and cutaneous silent period results may both be impacted by large fibre dysfunction; CSPs are also abnormal in a variety of other central and peripheral nervous system disorders as they rely on polysynaptic circuits which are influenced by supraspinal pathways. Thermal threshold testing is heavily reliant on patient cooperation and therefore prone to subjective bias. Electrochemical skin conductance testing requires specialist equipment that may not be available in routine neurophysiology testing laboratories.</p><p>Another limitation to electrodiagnostic SFN testing—even for SSR and CSP assessments that do not require specialist equipment—is a lack of international consensus regarding how these tests should be performed and scored, with various reference ranges for different stimuli settings, limb temperature, and degrees of muscle contraction or relaxation. Nonetheless, testing of the CSP, which has been described in a variety of settings including SFN for decades, is a likely underutilised method of assessing small A delta fibres. Ideally, local normative values are established with standardised protocols prior to utilisation of these tests in the clinical setting.</p><p>Routine large fibre studies were normal in all subjects, while small fibre studies were normal in two thirds despite high neuropathic and autonomic symptom scores. Future research is therefore required to better elucidate the cause of this discrepancy. It is possible there are other non-neuropathic drivers of symptoms such as central sensitisation. Even with gold standard skin biopsy, up to 40%–50% of people with long COVID-19 and neuropathic symptoms do not have histological evidence of an SFN on intraepidermal nerve fibre density testing. Previous studies have not demonstrated any relationship between the prevalence of a long COVID-19-related SFN and either demographic or COVID-19 clinical variables.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref></p><p>Despite widespread limitations in testing for SFN, we have nonetheless provided proof of concept that there is utility to a multimodal neurophysiological testing protocol assessing SFN in long COVID-19. Although numbers are small, our results indicate that demonstrable abnormalities can be detected in a proportion of those complaining of both neuropathic and autonomic symptoms. This result is particularly notable given many of these individuals undergo extensive and often unremarkable investigations. Small fibre neuropathy should be considered in all individuals with long COVID-19 and a suggestive clinical phenotype of painful neuropathic and autonomic symptoms.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjno-2025-001399</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjno-8-1-s001.docx" id="d67e292" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>AK was supported by the CMPH David and Margaret Wattchow Research Fund to present this work at the Australian &amp; New Zealand Association of Neurologists Annual Scientific Meeting 2025.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors have not declared a specific grant for this research from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> This study involves human participants and was approved by Southern Adelaide Local Health Network Research Ethics Committee (Reference Number 009.24). All participants provided informed consent prior to taking part in the study.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> Data is available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID science, research and policy</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2148</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-024-03173-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39122965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bramante</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Buse</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liebovitz</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Outpatient treatment of COVID-19 and incidence of post-COVID-19 condition over 10 months (COVID-OUT): a multicentre, randomised, quadruple-blind, parallel-group, phase 3 trial</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37302406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(23)00299-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11259948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Treadwell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reston</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Treatments for Long COVID autonomic dysfunction: a scoping review</article-title><source>Clin Auton Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10286-024-01081-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39658729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Neuroimmune pathophysiology of long COVID</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source><year>2025</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.13855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40536011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12247276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bandinelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Colantuono</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 Small Fiber Neuropathy as a New Emerging Quality of Life-Threatening Disease: A Systematic Review</article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><year>2025</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>328</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40005694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/microorganisms13020328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11858652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dalakas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Post-COVID Small Fiber Neuropathy, Implications of Innate Immunity, and Challenges on IVIG Therapy</article-title><source>Neurol Neuroimmunol Neuroinflamm</source><year>2024</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e200248</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/NXI.0000000000200248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38630951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11087046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Falco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Litewczuk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Di Stefano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Small fibre neuropathy frequently underlies the painful long-COVID syndrome</article-title><source>Pain</source><year>2024</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>2002</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000003259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38723183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>RMC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Navis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Small fiber neuropathy associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Muscle Nerve</source><year>2022</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mus.27458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34766365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8661991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Devigili</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rinaldo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Diagnostic criteria for small fibre neuropathy in clinical practice and research</article-title><source>Brain (Bacau)</source><year>2019</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>3728</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awz333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6906595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31665231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Verdugo</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matamala</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Inui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Review of techniques useful for the assessment of sensory small fiber neuropathies: Report from an IFCN expert group</article-title><source>Clin Neurophysiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2022.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35131635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alkotami</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elkholy</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elshamy</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Diabetic small fiber neuropathy: clinical and electrophysiological study</article-title><source>Egypt J Neurol Psychiatry Neurosurg</source><year>2024</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>148</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41983-024-00923-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hoitsma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Vries</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Drent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The small fiber neuropathy screening list: Construction and cross-validation in sarcoidosis</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2010.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>SFN-SIQ, SFNSL and skin biopsy of 55 cases with small fibre involvement</article-title><source>Int J Neurosci</source><year>2018</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00207454.2017.1398152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29077516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ranucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baryshnikova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anguissola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Very Long COVID: Persistence of Symptoms after 12-18 Months from the Onset of Infection and Hospitalization</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>1915</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12051915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36902702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10003916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Differences in Long COVID severity by duration of illness, symptom evolution, and vaccination: a longitudinal cohort study from the INSPIRE group</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">The Lancet Regional Health - Americas</italic>
</source><year>2025</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>101026</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2025.101026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40040820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11875141</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>All data relevant to the study are included in the article or uploaded as supplementary information.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>