<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">AIMS Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">AIMS Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3313</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">aimsph</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PublicHealth</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>AIMS Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2327-8994</issn><publisher><publisher-name>AIMS Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12795776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12795776.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12795776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12795776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41536833</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3934/publichealth.2025051</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">publichealth-12-04-051</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparison of physical fitness in youth with post-COVID-19: A study of individuals with and without symptoms</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amput</surname><given-names initials="P">Patchareeya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wongphon</surname><given-names initials="S">Sirima</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Physical Therapy, School of Allied Health Sciences, University of Phayao, Phayao 56000, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Unit of Excellence of Human Performance and Rehabilitations, University of Phayao, Phayao, Thailand, Phayao 56000, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine, School of Public Health, University of Phayao, Phayao 56000, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>* Correspondence:</bold> Email: <email>patchareeya.am@up.ac.th</email>; Tel: <phone>+6654466697</phone>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">501594</issue-id><fpage>1026</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-15 09:25:13.700"><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 the Author(s), licensee AIMS Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>the Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="publichealth-12-04-051.pdf"/><abstract><p>This study aims to examine differences in physical fitness among young adults in three distinct groups: individuals with long COVID, those who had recovered from COVID-19 without lingering symptoms, and healthy individuals with no history of infection. A total of 105 participants were equally divided into the three groups (n = 35 each). Evaluations included handgrip strength for upper body strength, handheld dynamometry for quadricep strength, and a six-minute walk test (6MWT) to assess the cardiorespiratory performance. Participants with long COVID demonstrated significantly lower handgrip strengths compared to the control group. Additionally, both post-COVID groups showed reduced 6MWT distances and elevated post-exercise physiological responses, including heart rate, systolic blood pressure, perceived exertion, and leg fatigue, regardless of symptom persistence. These findings indicate that individuals recovering from COVID-19, especially those with persistent symptoms, exhibit measurable declines in muscular and cardiorespiratory fitness, along with heightened physiological stress during physical activity.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>post-COVID-19</kwd><kwd>youth</kwd><kwd>muscle strength</kwd><kwd>respiratory system</kwd><kwd>physical fitness</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Post-coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) involves the persistence of symptoms long after the initial infection caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) virus, typically occurring three months after the onset of COVID-19. These individuals experience symptoms that persist for at least two months and cannot be explained by any alternative diagnosis <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Post-COVID-19 is characterized by lingering symptoms such as fatigue, dyspnea, muscle weakness, and a reduced exercise tolerance, all of which can significantly impair daily functioning and the overall quality of life <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, thus leading to limitations in social and physical activities <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>,<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Additionally, several studies have reported that post-COVID-19 patients experience worsening symptoms with physical exertion, thus resulting in exercise intolerance <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>,<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. These conditions are associated with impaired oxygen uptake, autonomic function, and inflammation <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>–<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>Physical fitness plays a crucial role in the overall health and functional independence, making it essential to evaluate whether post-COVID-19 patients experience long-term impairments in their physical performance. Several studies have reported declines in cardiorespiratory fitness, muscle strength, and endurance in individuals recovering from COVID-19, particularly those with long COVID <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>–<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. These impairments may result from various physiological mechanisms, including persistent inflammation, autonomic dysfunction, mitochondrial abnormalities, and deconditioning due to prolonged illness or reduced physical activity during recovery <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Additionally, respiratory complications, such as a decreased lung diffusion capacity and impaired oxygen uptake, may further contribute to exercise intolerance in post-COVID-19 individuals. The combination of these factors can lead to fatigue, a reduced functional capacity, and limitations in performing physical activities, ultimately impacting long-term recovery and quality of life <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. However, there is limited research that directly compares physical fitness between post-COVID-19 patients with and without persistent symptoms. Understanding these differences is crucial to design targeted rehabilitation strategies to enhance the recovery outcomes. To bridge these gaps in knowledge, this study aims to compare the physical fitness of post-COVID-19 patients with long COVID, those without persistent symptoms, and individuals who have never had a COVID-19 infection. The assessment includes measures of muscle strength and cardiorespiratory fitness. The findings of this study will provide valuable insights into the long-term effects of COVID-19 on physical health and inform rehabilitation approaches to enhance recovery and the quality of life of affected individuals.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2.1"><label>2.1.</label><title>Study design</title><p>This cross-sectional investigation evaluated physical fitness across three young adult groups. Tests included handgrip dynamometry for upper body strength, handheld dynamometry for quadricep strength, and a six-minute walk test (6MWT) to assess the cardiorespiratory capacity.</p></sec><sec id="s2.2"><label>2.2.</label><title>Participants</title><p>The study included post-COVID-19 patients with long COVID, those without persistent symptoms, and individuals who have never had a COVID-19 infection. A total of 105 participants were recruited and evenly assigned to three groups (n = 35/group). The sample size was determined through a power analysis, with a statistical power of 0.95, an alpha level of 0.05, and an effect size d of 0.40 <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Three groups of age- and sex-matched adults were recruited: the control group (CG) included individuals who had never had a COVID-19 infection; the persistent symptom group (PSG) included individuals who experienced persistent symptoms for more than 12 weeks; and the recovered COVID group (RCG) consisted of individuals who had previously developed COVID-19 but recovered without persistent symptoms. The inclusion criterion required participants to be 18 years or older. Those in the long COVID and recovered groups had confirmed COVID-19 diagnoses via either PCR or antigen testing at least 12 weeks prior to the study. The long COVID group included participants with symptoms that lasted over 12 weeks, whereas the recovered group had resolved symptoms within four weeks post-infection. The control group members had no history of COVID-19. Individuals were excluded if they had a body mass index (BMI) over 30 kg/m², an oxygen saturation below 95%, or pre-existing conditions that affect the cardiopulmonary or musculoskeletal systems. All participants provided written informed consent after being fully informed about the study's protocol. Ethical clearance was granted by the University of Phayao Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC–UP–HSST 1.2/110/67).</p></sec><sec id="s2.3"><label>2.3.</label><title>Procedure</title><p>The participants completed interviews to collect demographic and medical data, including anthropometric measurements and vital signs. The physical assessments are described below.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Handgrip strength test: Measured using a T.K.K 5001 Grip-A dynamometer</italic>
<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p><p>Each participant gripped the device with their dominant hand for three seconds while standing with the arm extended and slightly abducted. The test was performed three times, with one-minute rest intervals between trials, and the highest score (in kilograms) was recorded <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Quadriceps muscle strength: Evaluated using a</italic> hand-held dynamometer (Model-01165, Lafayette Instrument Company, Lafayette IN, USA) <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p><p>The participants were seated with their hips and knees flexed at 90 degrees and performed maximal isometric knee extensions using their dominant lower limb. The test was conducted at least three times, and the highest recorded value (in kilograms) was used for the analysis <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">6-minute walk test</italic>.</p><p>Before the test, the participants rested in a seated position for at least 10 minutes to ensure they were adequately prepared. Then, baseline cardiorespiratory parameters, including heart rate (HR), systolic blood pressure (SBP), diastolic blood pressure (DBP), oxygen saturation (SpO<sub>2</sub>), rate of perceived exertion (RPE), and leg fatigue, were measured. The test was conducted along a 30-meter corridor, where the participants were instructed to walk as far as possible within a 6-minute period. Running was not permitted, but the participants were encouraged to walk at a comfortable pace, with the option to slow down or take a brief rest if needed. The total distance covered during the 6MWT was recorded to assess the participant's cardiorespiratory fitness <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. After the test, the cardiorespiratory parameters were measured again.</p></sec><sec id="s2.4"><label>2.4.</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Descriptive statistics were calculated for all variables. A one-way ANOVA was used to identify group differences in muscular strength and physiological responses before and after the 6MWT. The statistical significance was set at p &lt; 0.05. Analyses were carried out using the SPSS software, version 22.0.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><p>The characteristics of the participants are shown in <xref rid="publichealth-12-04-051-t01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. There were no statistically significant differences in age, weight, height, or BMI among the groups. The average time since the first COVID-19 infection was 7.51 months for the PSG and 7.31 months for the RCG. The average number of vaccine doses received was 2.80 for the CG, 2.89 for the PSC, and 2.71 for the RCG.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="publichealth-12-04-051-t01" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Characteristics of the participants. Values are presented as means ± SD.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col width="130*" span="1"/><col width="89*" span="1"/><col width="89*" span="1"/><col width="89*" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CG</bold>
<break/><bold>(n = 35; F = 20, M = 15)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>
<break/><bold>(n = 35; F = 20, M = 15)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RCG</bold>
<break/><bold>(n = 35; F = 20, M = 15)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.14 ± 0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.23 ± 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.20 ± 0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.80 ± 1.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.86 ± 1.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.20 ± 1.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (m)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.79 ± 0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67 ± 0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.07 ± 0.34</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time since first COVID-19 infection, month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccination status, numbers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.71</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: CG = control group; PSG = persistent symptom group; RCG = recovered COVID group; F = female; M = male; BMI = body mass index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The handgrip strength test showed a significant decrease for the PSG compared to the CG (p &lt; 0.05). There were no statistically significant differences in quadricep strength among the groups. The 6MWT distance was significantly decreased for the PSG and RCG compared to the CG (<xref rid="publichealth-12-04-051-t02" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="publichealth-12-04-051-t02" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Comparison of upper and lower limb muscle strength and 6MWT distance among groups.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCG</td></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Handgrip strength test (kg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.35 ± 5.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.50 ± 6.09<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.03 ± 6.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadricep strength (kg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.53 ± 2.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.56 ± 3.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.74 ± 4.98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distance of the 6MWT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">601.29 ± 30.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">588.71 ± 16.85<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590.14 ± 18.09<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: CG = control group; PSG = persistent symptom group; RCG = recovered COVID group; 6MWT = 6-minute walk test; <sup>a</sup>p &lt; 0.05 vs. CG and <sup>b</sup>p &lt; 0.05 vs. PSG.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The baseline cardiorespiratory parameters showed no statistically significant differences among the groups. The post-HR, post-SBP, post-RPE, and post-leg fatigue were significantly increased for the PSG and RCG compared to the CG (p &lt; 0.05) after performing the 6WMT (<xref rid="publichealth-12-04-051-t03" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="publichealth-12-04-051-t03" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Comparison of cardiorespiratory parameters from the 6MWT among groups.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col width="112*" span="1"/><col width="95*" span="1"/><col width="95*" span="1"/><col width="95*" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CG</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PSG</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>RCG</bold>
</td></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-HR (bpm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.40 ± 9.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.00 ± 7.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.80 ± 8.86</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-HR (bpm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.77 ± 9.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.69 ± 7.10<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.74 ± 7.74<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-SBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.49 ± 11.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.23 ± 9.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.23 ± 11.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-SBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.43 ± 9.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142.17 ± 6.02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.11 ± 9.25<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-DBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.71 ± 7.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.00 ± 6.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.29 ± 7.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-DBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.94 ± 6.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.31 ± 6.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.43 ± 6.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-O<sub>2</sub> sat (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.14 ± 0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.43 ± 0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.31 ± 0.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-O<sub>2</sub> sat (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.40 ± 0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.31 ± 0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.40 ± 0.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-RPE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.26 ± 1.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.09 ± 1.40<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.74 ± 1.24<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-leg fatigue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 ± 0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49 ± 0.78<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43 ± 0.81<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: CG = control group; PSG = persistent symptom group; RCG = recovered COVID group; HR = heart rate; SBP = systolic blood pressure; DBP = diastolic blood pressure; O<sub>2</sub> sat = pulse oxygen saturation; RPE = rate of perceived exertion; <sup>a</sup>p &lt; 0.05 vs. CG and <sup>b</sup>p &lt; 0.05 vs. PSG.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion</title><p>This study indicates that individuals who experienced persistent symptoms for more than 12 weeks had decreased upper limb muscle strengths compared to healthy individuals. Additionally, both individuals with persistent symptoms for more than 12 weeks and those who had recovered from COVID-19 without persistent symptoms showed decreased 6MWT distances and increased post-HR, post-SBP, post-RPE, and post-leg fatigue when compared to healthy individuals. The findings reveal significant impairments in muscle strength and cardiorespiratory fitness, particularly among individuals who experienced long COVID.</p><p>Our results indicate that the upper limb muscle strength, assessed through the hand-grip strength test, was significantly reduced for the PSG compared to the CG. This decline in strength is consistent with previous studies that reported muscle weakness in individuals with long COVID, which may be attributed to persistent inflammation, mitochondrial dysfunction, and physical inactivity during the recovery phase <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>,<xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>–<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. These findings are consistent with prior studies and highlight the importance of monitoring muscle strength in post-COVID-19 rehabilitation. Persistent inflammation has been widely recognized as a key factor that contributes to muscle weakness in long COVID patients. Studies suggest that elevated levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin-6 (IL-6) and tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α), may promote muscle catabolism, reduce protein synthesis, and impair muscle regeneration <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. This chronic inflammatory state may explain the observed reduction in upper limb muscle strength, particularly in individuals who experienced prolonged post-COVID symptoms. Additionally, mitochondrial dysfunction has been implicated in post-viral fatigue and muscle weakness. Research has shown that SARS-CoV-2 can disrupt mitochondrial function, thus leading to impaired energy production, increased oxidative stress, and muscle fatigue <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>,<xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. These mitochondrial abnormalities may contribute to the decline in handgrip strength for+ the PSG, as muscle contraction and endurance heavily depend on mitochondrial ATP production. In contrast, quadricep strength did not significantly differ among the groups. While some post-COVID-19 patients have exhibited lower limb muscle weakness, the absence of a statistically significant difference in this study suggests that the extent of lower limb impairment may depend on factors such as disease severity, activity level, or recovery duration <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>,<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. One possible explanation for this finding is that daily activities naturally involve lower limb movement, such as walking, standing, and stair climbing, which could help maintain muscle strength. In contrast, the upper limb muscles are less frequently engaged in routine activities, thus potentially leading to a more noticeable decline in strength <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Although some results, such as quadricep strength (PSG mean 23.56 kg vs. CG 24.53 kg), did not reach statistical significance, we acknowledge that exploring trends in these measures and conducting subgroup analyses (e.g., by sex) could provide additional insights. The upper limb muscle weakness observed for the PSG aligns with previous studies that reported post-COVID-19 muscle impairment <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>,<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>–<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, whereas the absence of significant lower limb differences may reflect variations in the study populations, disease severity, physical activity, or recovery duration. Additionally, we note that our participants were primarily young to middle-aged adults, and findings may not fully generalize to older populations <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>–<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p><p>The 6MWT distance was significantly reduced for both the PSG and RCG compared to the CG, thus indicating a diminished functional capacity, even in individuals who had recovered without persistent symptoms. However, limitations include a lack of gas exchange measurements, autonomic function tests, and pre-morbid physical activity data. This finding is consistent with prior studies that demonstrated a reduced exercise tolerance among post-COVID-19 patients, which may be attributed to the lingering effects on pulmonary function, cardiovascular health, or muscle metabolism <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The more pronounced reductions in walking distance observed for the PSG suggests that long COVID further exacerbates the physical limitations, potentially due to sustained inflammation, autonomic dysfunction, or prolonged deconditioning <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Furthermore, the cardiorespiratory responses during the 6MWT revealed increased post-exercise HR, SBP, RPE, and leg fatigue for both the PSG and RCG compared to the CG. These findings indicate that post-COVID-19 individuals experience greater physiological strain during physical activity, which may stem from autonomic dysregulation, impaired oxygen uptake, or cardiovascular deconditioning <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The heightened exertion and fatigue responses for the PSG further reinforce the notion that persistent symptoms contribute to prolonged impairments in physical fitness and exercise tolerance.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><label>5.</label><title>Strength and limitations of this study</title><p>This study has several limitations that should be acknowledged. The present study demonstrated no significant differences among groups in age, weight, height, BMI, vaccination status, or the average time since the first COVID-19 infection, thus indicating that participants were generally well matched. However, the severity of prior COVID-19 infection (e.g., hospitalization, oxygen supplementation) was not assessed. This limitation may have influenced the recovery trajectories and should be considered when interpreting the findings. In addition, the physical activity levels before and after COVID-19 infection were not measured, which could potentially explain some degree of deconditioning. Finally, the interpretation of our findings relies on between-group comparisons without individual pre-morbid fitness data. Overall, these findings highlight the importance of monitoring muscle strength and functional capacity in post-COVID-19 rehabilitation, as well as provide valuable insights for designing targeted interventions to improve long-term recovery and the quality of life.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><label>6.</label><title>Conclusions</title><p>Persistent symptoms following COVID-19, particularly in individuals with long COVID, lead to significant reductions in the upper limb muscle strength and functional exercise capacity, even for those who have recovered from acute infection. The study highlights the physiological strain experienced during physical activity and underscores the importance of monitoring and implementing targeted rehabilitation interventions. Our findings provide critical evidence to inform strategies aimed at improving long-term recovery and the quality of life of post-COVID-19 patients.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Use of AI tools declaration</title><p>The authors declare they have not used Artificial Intelligence (AI) tools in the creation of this article.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank all the volunteers who participated in this study. This research was supported by University of Phayao and Thailand Science Research and Innovation Fund (Fundamental Fund 2026, Grant No. 2264).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Authors' contributions:</bold> Conception and design: P Amput; Administrative support: P Amput; Provision of study materials or patients: P Amput, S Wongphon; Collection and assembly of data: P Amput, S Wongphon; Data analysis and interpretation: P Amput; Manuscript writing: All authors; Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>e102</fpage><lpage>e107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nasserie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hittle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Assessment of the Frequency and Variety of Persistent Symptoms Among Patients With COVID-19: A Systematic Review</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e2111417</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.11417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34037731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8155823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Havervall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillipson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Symptoms and Functional Impairment Assessed 8 Months After Mild COVID-19 Among Health Care Workers</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2021</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>2015</fpage><lpage>2016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.5612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33825846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8027932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Halpin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McIvor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Whyatt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Postdischarge symptoms and rehabilitation needs in survivors of COVID-19 infection: A cross-sectional evaluation</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>2021</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1013</fpage><lpage>1022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.26368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32729939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aparisi</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ladrón</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ybarra-Falcón</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Exercise Intolerance in Post-Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 and the Value of Cardiopulmonary Exercise Testing- a Mini-Review</article-title><source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>924819</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.924819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35935782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9352932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Befus</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Damant</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Exertional intolerance and dyspnea with preserved lung function: an emerging long COVID phenotype?</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>222</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-021-01814-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34362372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8343348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mustonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kanerva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luukkonen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Cardiopulmonary exercise testing in long covid shows the presence of dysautonomia or chronotropic incompetence independent of subjective exercise intolerance and fatigue</article-title><source>BMC Cardiovasc Disord</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>413</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12872-024-04081-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39117999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11308233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Lázaro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santamaría</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez-Serrano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Efficacy of Therapeutic Exercise in Reversing Decreased Strength, Impaired Respiratory Function, Decreased Physical Fitness, and Decreased Quality of Life Caused by the Post-COVID-19 Syndrome</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2797</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v14122797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36560801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9784943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Lázaro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santamaría</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez-Serrano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID a New Derivative in the Chaos of SARS-CoV-2 Infection: The Emergent Pandemic?</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>5799</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10245799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34945095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8708091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Amput</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tapanya</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sangkarit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Balance Ability and Quality of Life in Older Adult with Recovery from Mild COVID-19</article-title><source>Ann Geriatr Med Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4235/agmr.23.0084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37592748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10556712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Amput</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wongphon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Follow-Up of Cardiopulmonary Responses Using Submaximal Exercise Test in Older Adults with Post-COVID-19</article-title><source>Ann Geriatr Med Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4235/agmr.24.0093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38986675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11695753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Amput</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wongphon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Assessment of Muscle Strength and Cardiorespiratory Parameters Using Simple Tests in Older Adults With Recovery From Mild COVID-19</article-title><source>Ann Rehabil Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5535/arm.240033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39654436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11703608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al Saikhan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alghamdi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Mechanisms underlying exercise intolerance in long COVID: An accumulation of multisystem dysfunction</article-title><source>Physiol Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e15940</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14814/phy2.15940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38346773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10861355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Salmam</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perreault</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Best</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Physical impairments in individuals with Long COVID</article-title><source>Front Sports Act Living</source><year>2025</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1511942</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fspor.2025.1511942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39949717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11821922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Validity and reliability of the takei hand dynamometer</article-title><source>Int J Exerc Sci: Conf Proc</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>130</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Savas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kilavuz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kayhan Koçak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Comparison of Grip Strength Measurements by Widely Used Three Dy-namometers in Outpatients Aged 60 Years and Over</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>4260</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12134260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37445293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10342845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mentiplay</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perraton</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Assessment of Lower Limb Muscle Strength and Power Using Hand-Held and Fixed Dynamometry: A Reliability and Validity Study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0140822</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26509265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4624940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>ASEP procedures recommendation I: accurate assessment of muscular strength and power</article-title><source>J Exerc Physiol Online</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>ATS Committee on Proficiency Standards for Clinical Pulmonary Function Laboratories</collab><article-title>ATS statement: guidelines for the six-minute walk test</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.166.1.at1102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12091180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Disser</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Micheli</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schonk</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Musculoskeletal Consequences of COVID-19</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2020</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>1204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/jbjs.20.00847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32675661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7508274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Montes-Ibarra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>CLP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Orsso</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>The Impact of Long COVID-19 on Muscle Health</article-title><source>Clin Geriatr Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cger.2022.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35868672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8934728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Belli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Balbi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Low physical functioning and impaired performance of activities of daily life in COVID-19 patients who survived hospitalisation</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2020</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>2002096</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.02096-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32764112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7411272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zampogna</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paneroni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Belli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Pulmonary Rehabilitation in Patients Recovering from COVID-19</article-title><source>Respiration</source><year>2021</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000514387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33784696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8089404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Del Valle</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim-Schulze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>An inflammatory cytokine signa-ture predicts COVID-19 severity and survival</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1636</fpage><lpage>1643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-1051-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32839624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7869028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Molnar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lehoczki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial dysfunction in long COVID: mechanisms, consequences, and potential therapeutic approaches</article-title><source>Geroscience</source><year>2024</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>5267</fpage><lpage>5286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11357-024-01165-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38668888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11336094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Causes Mitochondrial Dysfunction and Mitophagy Impairment</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>780768</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.780768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35069483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8770829</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>