<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12517539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12517539.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12517539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12517539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41089587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.94386</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Other</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neurology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Otolaryngology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Platelet-Rich Plasma for COVID-19-Related Olfactory Dysfunction: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albazee</surname><given-names initials="E">Ebraheem</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alajmi</surname><given-names initials="SA">Saad A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkandari</surname><given-names initials="AM">Ali M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aladwani</surname><given-names initials="AN">Abdullah N</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alenezi</surname><given-names initials="YY">Yaqoub Y</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaeed</surname><given-names initials="MA">Munawer A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uqlah</surname><given-names initials="B">Bader</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abu-Zaid</surname><given-names initials="A">Ahmed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Otorhinolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Kuwait Institute for Medical Specializations (KIMS), Kuwait City, KWT </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Al-Jahra Hospital, Al-Jahra, KWT </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Medicine and Surgery, Kuwait Institute for Medical Specializations (KIMS), Kuwait City, KWT </aff><aff id="aff-4">
<label>4</label>
Medicine and Surgery, College of Medicine, Arabian Gulf University, Manama, BHR </aff><aff id="aff-5">
<label>5</label>
Biochemistry and Molecular Medicine, College of Medicine, Alfaisal University, Riyadh, SAU </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Ebraheem Albazee <email>ebraheemalbazee@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>10</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">498077</issue-id><elocation-id>e94386</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-15 09:25:42.707"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025, Albazee et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Albazee et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000094386.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cureus.com/articles/418746-platelet-rich-plasma-for-covid-19-related-olfactory-dysfunction-a-systematic-review-and-meta-analysis-of-randomized-controlled-trials">This article is available from https://cureus.com/articles/418746-platelet-rich-plasma-for-covid-19-related-olfactory-dysfunction-a-systematic-review-and-meta-analysis-of-randomized-controlled-trials</self-uri><abstract><p>A notable rise in olfactory dysfunction (OD) prevalence has been observed since the COVID-19 pandemic. COVID-19-related OD is associated with several consequences, especially deteriorated quality of life. Hence, several treatment options have been investigated, with platelet-rich plasma (PRP) showing promising results. A systematic review and meta-analysis summarizing randomized controlled trial (RCT) evidence were retrieved from PubMed, Google Scholar, Scopus, and Web of Science up to June 2025. The risk of bias was assessed using the Cochrane Risk of Bias 2 assessment tool. Data were analyzed using Stata MP version 18 (StataCorp LLC, College Station, TX), pooling dichotomous outcomes as relative risks (RRs) and continuous outcomes as standardized mean differences (SMDs), each with 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Four RCTs, including 198 participants, were included in our meta-analysis. PRP significantly improved objective olfactory scores (SMD = 1.86, 95% CI (0.14, 3.57), p = 0.03) and subjective olfactory scores (SMD = 0.92, 95% CI (0.32, 1.51), p &lt; 0.001). Additionally, PRP significantly increased the response rate (RR = 1.79, 95% CI (1.14, 2.81), p = 0.01). PRP was generally well-tolerated across the included trials, with no major adverse events reported. Two RCTs showed an overall low risk of bias, one trial showed some concerns, and another showed a high risk of bias. With uncertain evidence, PRP may improve both objective and subjective smell function and clinical outcomes in people with long COVID-related OD. PRP treatment was reported to be safe, with minor, temporary side effects primarily related to the procedure. Although initial results are promising, the small number of RCTs requires a cautious approach to interpretation.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>anosmia</kwd><kwd>olfaction</kwd><kwd>otolaryngology</kwd><kwd>platelet-rich plasma</kwd><kwd>prp</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction and background</title><p>Since the COVID-19 pandemic, there has been a considerable increase in the prevalence of olfactory dysfunction (OD) [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. OD encompasses a range of disorders, including anosmia (complete loss of smell), hyposmia (reduced ability to smell), and parosmia (distorted perception of smells). Studies show that 26.5% to 46% of people experience COVID-related OD one year after infection, dropping to 8.3% after two years [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Recent research shows partial smell recovery in up to 54.3% and complete recovery in 38.2% of patients within two years of infection [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Yet, subjective reports of smell function in anosmic patients do not strongly correlate with psychophysical measures [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. While approximately 79% of participants in a recent study reported subjective recovery 36 weeks post-COVID-19 infection, a significantly smaller percentage (51.5%) achieved normal Brief Smell Identification Test (BSIT) scores [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Objective psychophysical testing can reveal dysfunction even in patients who do not report smell difficulties [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Patients with OD experience various negative consequences, such as altered taste, weight fluctuations, social withdrawal, poor hygiene, reduced quality of life, and a higher mortality rate [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Smell training has shown limited but consistent success across various causes of OD and is commonly prescribed [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Nonetheless, additional treatment options remain warranted for optimal management.</p><p>Platelet-rich plasma (PRP), an autologous concentrate of platelets rich in growth factors, presents a promising approach for managing OD [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Platelet activation triggers the release of a complex mixture of bioactive molecules, such as platelet-derived growth factor, transforming growth factor beta, vascular endothelial growth factor, and nerve growth factor, collectively promoting tissue repair, angiogenesis, cellular proliferation, and neurogenesis [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>-<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Due to the inherent regenerative capacity of the olfactory neuroepithelium, it is posited that PRP enhances this natural process by supporting the survival of olfactory sensory neurons, promoting neurite outgrowth, and modulating local inflammation [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], with its autologous nature ensuring a favorable safety profile. Given its multimodal approach to inflammation, degeneration, and impaired regeneration and its proven success in other regenerative medicine areas, PRP presents a compelling rationale for its application in olfactory system regeneration [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Emerging clinical evidence from randomized controlled trials (RCTs) suggests that PRP may be beneficial for COVID-19-related OD [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Given the significant burden of persistent post-COVID-19 OD, the limitations of current treatment options, and the promising yet heterogeneous emerging evidence for PRP, a comprehensive systematic review and meta-analysis are warranted. Therefore, we performed this systematic review and meta-analysis to investigate the efficacy and safety of PRP for the management of COVID-related OD.</p></sec><sec sec-type="review"><title>Review</title><p>Methodology</p><p>This systematic review and meta-analysis were conducted in accordance with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) statement [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and the Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>Data Sources and Search Strategy</p><p>On June 05, 2025, an electronic search was conducted on the following databases: Web of Science (WOS), PubMed, Scopus, and Google Scholar. The search strategy included the following search entries: “(COVID-19 OR SARS-CoV-2 OR "Coronavirus disease 2019" OR "Post-COVID-19 Syndrome" OR "Long COVID" OR "Post COVID" OR "Persistent COVID") AND ("Platelet-Rich Plasma" OR PRP) AND ("Olfactory Dysfunction" OR "Smell Disorder" OR "Smell Dysfunction" OR Anosmia OR Hyposmia OR Parosmia OR Phantosmia OR Olfaction OR "Smell Loss" OR "Olfactory Loss")”. Our search strategy employed unrestricted access to most databases; however, Scopus searches were limited to the title. Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref> provides detailed information on the specific search terms and results for each database. To maximize the completeness of our search, we conducted a manual screening of the reference lists of all included studies and examined key clinical trial registries such as <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ClinicalTrials.gov" ext-link-type="uri">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> and the WHO International Clinical Trials Registry Platform (ICTRP). Furthermore, supplementary sources, including ResearchGate, were reviewed to capture any relevant unpublished or ongoing studies. No restrictions were applied on the basis of language, country of origin, or publication status.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Search strategy</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Database</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search terms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search results</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PubMed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(COVID-19 OR SARS-CoV-2 OR "Coronavirus disease 2019" OR "Post-COVID-19 Syndrome" OR "Long COVID" OR "Post COVID" OR "Persistent COVID") AND ("Platelet-Rich Plasma" OR PRP) AND ("Olfactory Dysfunction" OR "Smell Disorder" OR "Smell Dysfunction" OR Anosmia OR Hyposmia OR Parosmia OR Phantosmia OR Olfaction OR "Smell Loss" OR "Olfactory Loss")</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All fields</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Web of Science</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(COVID-19 OR SARS-CoV-2 OR "Coronavirus disease 2019" OR "Post-COVID-19 Syndrome" OR "Long COVID" OR "Post COVID" OR "Persistent COVID") AND ("Platelet-Rich Plasma" OR PRP) AND ("Olfactory Dysfunction" OR "Smell Disorder" OR "Smell Dysfunction" OR Anosmia OR Hyposmia OR Parosmia OR Phantosmia OR Olfaction OR "Smell Loss" OR "Olfactory Loss")</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All fields</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCOPUS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TITLE-ABS-KEY ( ( covid-19 OR sars-cov-2 OR "Coronavirus disease 2019" OR "Post-COVID-19 Syndrome" OR "Long COVID" OR "Post COVID" OR "Persistent COVID" ) AND ( "Platelet-Rich Plasma" OR prp ) AND ( "Olfactory Dysfunction" OR "Smell Disorder" OR "Smell Dysfunction" OR anosmia OR hyposmia OR parosmia OR phantosmia OR olfaction OR "Smell Loss" OR "Olfactory Loss" ) )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Title, abstract, and keywords</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Google Scholar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(COVID-19 OR SARS-CoV-2 OR "Coronavirus disease 2019" OR "Post-COVID-19 Syndrome" OR "Long COVID" OR "Post COVID" OR "Persistent COVID") AND ("Platelet-Rich Plasma" OR PRP) AND ("Olfactory Dysfunction" OR "Smell Disorder" OR "Smell Dysfunction" OR Anosmia OR Hyposmia OR Parosmia OR Phantosmia OR Olfaction OR "Smell Loss" OR "Olfactory Loss")</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All fields</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Eligibility Criteria</p><p>RCTs conducted using the following PICO criteria were included: population (P), patients with post-COVID-19 OD; intervention (I), application of PRP; control (C), standard care or saline placebo; and outcomes (O): the primary outcome was the change in objective olfactory scores, including the Sniffin’ Sticks test (threshold, discrimination, and identification (TDI) score), Connecticut Chemosensory Clinical Research Center (CCCRC) olfaction test, and BSIT (for all of these instruments, a higher score indicates a better sense of smell). Secondary outcomes included the change in subjective olfactory scores, including visual analog scale (VAS) and SCENTinel intensity rating; response rate, defined as a significant improvement in symptoms; and adverse events. Furthermore, our analysis excluded quasi-experimental trials, conference presentations and proceedings, observational studies, in vitro research, and review articles.</p><p>The Process of Study Selection</p><p>Screening was performed in Covidence by two independent reviewers (EA and AA). After duplicate removal, titles and abstracts were initially screened, and then the full texts of potentially eligible studies were reviewed. Disagreements were addressed through discussion until consensus was achieved.</p><p>Data Extraction</p><p>A preliminary extraction of eligible publications was performed to develop an Excel (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, WA) extraction form. The form was structured into three sections: (1) summary characteristics of the included trials (study ID, country, study design, sample size, treatment protocols, main inclusion criteria, used scores, response definition, primary outcome, and follow-up duration); (2) baseline characteristics of the included participants (age, gender, symptoms duration, and baseline olfactory scores); and (3) the outcomes sheet (change in objective olfactory score, change in subjective olfactory score, response rate, and adverse events).</p><p>Two reviewers (EA and AA) independently extracted the data, resolving disagreements through discussion with a senior author. Dichotomous data were documented as event rates, whereas continuous data were summarized using means and standard deviations. Mean and standard deviation were calculated from the median and interquartile range (or range) reported in some included studies using the conversion formulas presented by Wan et al. [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>Risk of Bias and Certainty of Evidence</p><p>The risk of bias of the included studies was assessed using the revised Cochrane Collaboration tool for RCTs (ROB 2) [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Two independent reviewers (EA and AA) evaluated each study across key domains, including selection, performance, reporting, and attrition biases, as well as other potential sources of bias. Any disagreements were resolved through consensus.
In addition, the certainty of the evidence was appraised using the Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) framework [<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. This assessment considered risk of bias, inconsistency, imprecision, indirectness, and potential publication bias. Each judgment was carefully documented and justified, and any differences between reviewers were settled by discussion.</p><p>Meta-Analysis</p><p>Data were analyzed using Stata MP version 18 (StataCorp LLC, College Station, TX). Dichotomous outcomes were pooled as risk ratios (RRs), and continuous outcomes as mean differences, each with 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Because olfactory scores varied across the included trials, the standardized mean difference (SMD) was applied for pain-related outcomes. A fixed-effect model was the primary analytical approach; a random-effect model was used when significant heterogeneity was detected. Heterogeneity was evaluated using the chi-squared test and the I² statistic, with p &lt; 0.1 for the chi-square test or I² ≥ 50% indicating substantial heterogeneity. Publication bias was not assessed because all evaluated outcomes included fewer than 10 RCTs [<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>Results</p><p>Search Results and Study Selection</p><p>A total of 165 records were identified through the database search. Covidence automatically removed 59 duplicate records, leaving 89 for screening. After title and abstract screening, 83 studies did not meet the inclusion criteria and were excluded. Six full-text articles were assessed for eligibility, of which two were excluded. Ultimately, four RCTs [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] were left to be included in qualitative and quantitative analyses (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) flow chart of the screening process</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000094386-i01.jpg"/></fig><p>Characteristics of Included Studies</p><p>Four trials and 198 participants were included in our analysis [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Two trials were conducted in the US [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], one in Egypt [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and another in Turkey [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The follow-up duration ranged from one to 12 months. Intervention details and the assessed scores are clarified in Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Further baseline data of the included patients are in Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Summary characteristics of the included randomized controlled trials</title><p>BSIT, Brief smell identification test; CCCRC, Connecticut Chemosensory Clinical Research Center; NA, Not available; PRP, Platelet-rich plasma; RCT, Randomized controlled trial; TDI, Threshold, discrimination, identification; VAS, Visual analog scale</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Study ID</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Study design</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Country</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PRP</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Control</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Main inclusion criteria</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Objective olfactory score</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Subjective olfactory score</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Response definition</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Primary outcome</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Follow-up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abo El Naga et al. 2022 [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egypt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three PRP injections in the olfactory cleft at three-week intervals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Olfactory training, topical corticosteroids, omega-3, vitamin B12, and zinc for six weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age &gt;18 years with post-COVID parosmia, unresponsive to 3 months of conservative treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAS for parosmia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 month</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duffy et al. 2024 [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 monthly treatments of PRP-coated Surgifoam in bilateral olfactory clefts</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monthly treatments of saline-coated Surgifoam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age ≥18 years, post-COVID olfactory dysfunction ≥6 months, BSIT score ≤8/12, or SCENTinel intensity ≤40/100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BSIT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCENTinel intensity rating</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change in BSIT ≥ 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change in BSIT score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 months</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evman and Cetin 2023 [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A single 1 mL PRP injection into the olfactory cleft</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age &gt;18 years, post-COVID olfactory dysfunction &gt;1 year, unresponsive to 1 month of conventional treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCCRC olfaction test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCCRC test scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 month</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yan et al. 2022 [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three submucosal PRP injections (1 mL) in bilateral olfactory clefts at two-week intervals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three submucosal sterile saline injections</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age &gt;18 years, post-COVID smell loss for 6-12 months, UPSIT score ≤33, failed olfactory training and budesonide irrigations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sniffin' Sticks (TDI) score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥5.5 points on the Sniffin' Sticks total score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change in Sniffin' Sticks (TDI) score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Baseline characteristics of the participants</title><p>BSIT, Brief smell identification test; NA, Not available; OD, Olfactory dysfunction; PRP, Platelet-rich plasma; SD, Standard deviation; SIC, Smell intensity category; STC, Smell threshold category; TDI, Threshold, discrimination, identification; VAS, Visual analog scale</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Study ID</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Number of patients in each group</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age (years), mean (SD)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Gender (female), %</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mean duration of OD (months), mean (SD)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline olfactory test, mean (SD)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PRP</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Control</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PRP</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Control</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PRP</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Control</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PRP</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Control</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PRP</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Control</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abo El Naga et al. 2022 [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9 (6.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.07 (5.74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAS: 9.13 (0.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAS: 9.27 (0.78)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duffy et al. 2024 [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BSIT: 5.32 (2.35), SCENTinel: 36 (27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BSIT: 6.10 (2.25), SCENTinel: 39 (29)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evman and Cetin 2023 [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8 (6.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.5 (11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STC: 5.63 (0.68), SIC: 11.42 (1.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STC: 5.69 (0.66), SIC: 11.20 (1.12)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yan et al. 2022 [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6 (12.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4 (16.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sniffin' Sticks (TDI): 24.3 (6.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sniffin' Sticks (TDI): 26.0 (4.4)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Risk of Bias and Certainty of Evidence</p><p>Two RCTs showed an overall low risk of bias [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Abo El Naga et al. raised some concerns regarding open lapel interventions and open lapel assessment of subjective outcomes [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Evman and Cetin showed a high risk of bias due to the lack of data on the randomization process, open-label interventions, and open-label assessment of subjective outcomes (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Summary and graphical presentation of risk of bias assessments for all included randomized controlled trials</title><p>[<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000094386-i02.jpg"/></fig><p>Certainty of evidence assessment is demonstrated in Table <xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>GRADE evidence profile</title><p>CI, Confidence interval; GRADE, Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation; RCT, Randomized controlled trial; RR, Risk ratio; SD, Standard deviation; SMD, Standardized mean difference</p><p>a. Evman and Cetin showed a high risk of bias, with &gt;30% of the pooled analysis weight.</p><p>b. I2 &gt; 75%.</p><p>c. A wide confidence interval, with a low number of patients.</p><p>d. A wide confidence interval, with a low number of events.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Certainty assessment</td><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Summary of findings</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Risk of bias</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Inconsistency</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Indirectness</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Imprecision</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Publication bias</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Overall certainty of evidence</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="2">Study event rates (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative effect</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="2">Anticipated absolute effects</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(studies)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(95% CI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">With control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">With PRP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk with control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk difference with PRP</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="12" rowspan="1">Objective olfactory score</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Serious<sup>a</sup>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Very serious<sup>b</sup>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Not serious</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Very serious<sup>c,d</sup>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">⨁◯◯◯</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMD 1.86 SD higher</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3 RCTs)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low<sup>a,b,c,d</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 higher to 3.57 higher</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" rowspan="1">Subjective olfactory score</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Not serious</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Not serious</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Not serious</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Very serious<sup>c</sup>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">⨁⨁◯◯</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMD 0.92 SD higher</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2 RCTs)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low<sup>c</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 higher to 1.51 higher</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="12" rowspan="1">Response rate (symptoms improvement)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Not serious</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Not serious</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Not serious</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Very serious<sup>d</sup>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">⨁⨁◯◯</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">39/84 (46.4%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">69/85 (81.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.79</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">39/84 (46.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367 more per 1,000</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3 RCTs)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low<sup>d</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 to 2.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">From 65 more to 840 more</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Change in Objective Olfactory Score</p><p>PRP significantly improved objective olfactory scores (SMD = 1.86, 95% CI (0.14, 3.57), p = 0.03) (Figure <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). Pooled studies were heterogeneous (I<sup>2</sup> = 93.63%).</p><p>Change in Subjective Olfactory Score</p><p>PRP significantly improved subjective olfactory scores (SMD = 0.92, 95% CI (0.32, 1.51), p &lt; 0.001) (Figure <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>). Pooled studies were heterogeneous (I<sup>2</sup> = 49.74%).</p><p>Response Rate</p><p>PRP significantly increased the response rate (RR = 1.79, 95% CI (1.14, 2.81), p = 0.01) (Figure <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref>). Pooled studies were heterogeneous (I<sup>2</sup> = 52.53%).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Forest plots of the assessed outcomes: [A] objective olfactory score, [B] subjective olfactory score, and [C] response (symptom improvement)</title><p>[<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</p><p>CI, Confidence interval; PRP, Platelet-rich plasma; SD, Standard deviation; SMD, Standardized mean difference</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000094386-i03.jpg"/></fig><p>Change in Objective Olfactory Score (Sensitivity Analysis)</p><p>Leave-one-out sensitivity analysis showed consistent results, except after the exclusion of Evman and Cetin, which revealed no difference between the two groups (p = 0.115) (Figure <xref rid="FIG4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Leave-one-out sensitivity analysis of the change in objective olfactory score</title><p>[<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</p><p>CI, Confidence interval; SMD, Standardized mean difference</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000094386-i04.jpg"/></fig><p>Adverse Events and Tolerability</p><p>PRP was generally well-tolerated across the included trials [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Abo El Naga and Evman and Cetin reported no adverse events [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Yan et al. noted minor, short-term side effects, including nasal congestion and pressure, in both the PRP and placebo arms, with one placebo participant experiencing transient photophobia [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similarly, Duffy et al. reported transient sequelae, including pressure, congestion, or headache, following the procedure [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Regarding tolerability, two patients in the placebo group withdrew due to anxiety and frustration with the testing methods [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Discussion</p><p>Summary of the Review and Main Findings</p><p>The COVID-19 pandemic has underscored the high incidence of OD, with a substantial number of patients presenting with anosmia as a primary symptom, frequently accompanied by gustatory dysfunction [<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The significant predictive value of anosmia for COVID-19, particularly in asymptomatic individuals, underscores the urgent need for enhanced therapeutic approaches [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Despite the high prevalence and substantial effects of OD, long-term therapeutic approaches remain inadequate [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This is primarily due to a lack of robust empirical evidence resulting from underfunded research, insufficient sample sizes, and methodological heterogeneity, which limit the generalizability of the findings [<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. However, the global impact of the COVID-19 pandemic has prompted this field, leading to a notable increase in publications and registered clinical trials focused on treating post-viral OD, including the recent studies on PRP [<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>The pooled analysis of four RCTs involving 198 participants demonstrated that PRP led to statistically significant improvements across all assessed efficacy outcomes compared with control. PRP was associated with a significant enhancement in both objective and subjective olfactory scores, as well as an increased rate of symptom improvement. The consistent results across clinician assessments, device measurements, and patient reports suggest that PRP may be a useful treatment for COVID-related OD. However, these results must be interpreted cautiously, as the GRADE assessment indicates very low to low certainty of evidence.</p><p>The observed benefits of PRP are biologically plausible. The pathophysiology of COVID-associated OD is hypothesized to involve inflammation and damage to the olfactory neuroepithelium, predominantly affecting sustentacular cells, rather than direct neuronal infection in many instances [<xref rid="REF31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. PRP is rich in several growth factors, including platelet-derived growth factor, transforming growth factor-beta, vascular endothelial growth factor, and nerve growth factor [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], which are reported to promote tissue repair, angiogenesis, cellular proliferation, and neurogenesis [<xref rid="REF32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The regenerative potential of the olfactory neuroepithelium, facilitated by globose and horizontal basal stem cells [<xref rid="REF33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], may be augmented by PRP, thereby improving olfactory sensory neuron survival, neurite outgrowth, and the modulation of local inflammation [<xref rid="REF32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Therefore, the results of this meta-analysis are consistent with an accumulating body of evidence suggesting that PRP has beneficial effects for OD of varied etiologies [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Additionally, although the precise mechanisms remain unclear, studies indicate that PRP promotes neurogenesis and regeneration of olfactory neurons and supporting cells, concurrently restoring the integrity of the nasal mucosa [<xref rid="REF34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p><p>Across the included RCTs, PRP was generally well-tolerated. Abo El Naga et al. and Evman and Cetin reported no adverse events [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Yan et al. noted minor, short-term side effects, such as nasal congestion and pressure, in both PRP and placebo groups, with one placebo participant experiencing transient photophobia [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similarly, Duffy et al. reported transient sequelae, including pressure, congestion, or headache, following the procedure in both arms [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. None of the trials reported any serious adverse events attributable to PRP [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. This favorable safety profile aligns with the established use of PRP in various medical and otolaryngological applications, including androgenetic alopecia [<xref rid="REF35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], tympanic membrane perforation repair [<xref rid="REF36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and vocal fold regeneration [<xref rid="REF37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], where its autologous nature ensures minimal risk of immunogenicity or disease transmission. The favorable safety profile represents a considerable advantage, especially if efficacy can be conclusively demonstrated for a condition causing significant patient distress.</p><p>AlRajhi et al. [<xref rid="REF38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] conducted a systematic review of four studies (two RCTs and two observational studies) involving 233 patients, predominantly female, experiencing anosmia, hyposmia, or parosmia related to COVID-19. The review aimed to assess the efficacy and safety of PRP injections for COVID-19-related OD. While PRP showed potential subjective improvement, particularly in TDI scores and other olfactory assessments, the evidence was insufficient to draw definitive, statistically significant conclusions due to study heterogeneity and limited sample sizes. In contrast, Albazee et al. [<xref rid="REF39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] performed a systematic review and meta-analysis of six RCTs to evaluate PRP use following endoscopic sinus surgery in patients with chronic rhinosinusitis. PRP was associated with improved wound healing, reduced inflammation, and enhanced overall surgical outcomes. However, no statistically significant differences were observed between the PRP and control groups regarding anosmia duration or olfactory function scores, despite a trend toward higher scores in the PRP group.
Our findings align with a recent meta-analysis by Bae et al. [<xref rid="REF40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], which also investigated PRP for persistent post-COVID-19 OD. Their analysis of five studies, including observational studies and 254 participants, found that PRP led to a significant improvement in olfactory scores when compared to control groups (SMD: 1.44; 95% CI (0.59, 2.28)) and substantially increased the odds of recovery (odds ratio: 8.66; 95% CI (2.98, 25.23)) [<xref rid="REF40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. These results are consistent with our findings, which also demonstrated a significant benefit with PRP. Notably, both our meta-analysis and the one by Bae et al. [<xref rid="REF40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] identified a high degree of heterogeneity, underscoring that variations in PRP protocols, patient populations, and outcome assessments remain a significant challenge in the current body of evidence.</p><p>Strengths and Limitations</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, as of June 2025, this is the first RCT-based meta-analysis to synthesize evidence on the efficacy of PRP for COVID-19-related OD. Additionally, we have strictly adhered to the Cochrane guidelines during the conduct of this meta-analysis and the PRISMA guidelines during its reporting. Still, our analysis is limited by the following: first, the small number of eligible RCTs (four studies) and the limited number of participants (198 patients), which inherently limits the statistical power of the meta-analysis and the precision of the pooled effect estimates. Second, the lack of blinding in some studies, where interventions or outcome assessments are not concealed, is problematic due to the potential for placebo effects in procedural interventions. Third, some key differences in the PRP protocols, including preparation, route of administration, and number of sessions, can lead to the noted heterogeneity. Fourth, different psychophysical tests (BSIT, CCCRC, and Sniffin' Sticks) and subjective scales (VAS and SCENTinel) were used, each with varying properties and sensitivities. Still, we used SMD, as advised, to pool data from these scores. Fifth, the follow-up periods ranged from one to 12 months, which may lead to some heterogeneity in the pooled analysis. Sixth, we did not prospectively register our review protocol, while this is the best practice for systematic reviews, the PRISMA guidelines consider it an optional step in the systematic review process.</p><p>Finally, a critical consideration in interpreting these results is the natural history of post-COVID-19 OD, which can include spontaneous recovery, even after several months [<xref rid="REF41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The included trials mitigated the influence of spontaneous recovery by enrolling only patients with long-standing OD. Specifically, the baseline requirement was symptoms persisting for six months or longer (Duffy et al. [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and Yan et al. [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]) or for over one year (Evman and Cetin [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]). Notably, certain studies demonstrated improvements even in control groups, thus underscoring the necessity of rigorous study designs. Also, the procedural aspects of PRP administration (injections or topical application) are likely to generate a substantial placebo effect [<xref rid="REF42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. This highlights the critical need for rigorous blinding and suitable control groups in subsequent trials; this shortcoming contributed to the "some concerns" or "high" risk of bias assessments in studies with open-label elements.</p><p>Implications for Future Research</p><p>Future research should focus on several key areas to overcome current limitations and provide stronger evidence of PRP's utility for COVID-19-related OD. First, there is a critical need for large-scale, multicenter, high-quality RCTs to draw more definitive conclusions. Second, standardizing PRP protocols is crucial for making future trials more comparable and interpretable. Standardized techniques are necessary for PRP administration, including the distinction between injection and topical application, precise anatomical targeting, accurate volume measurement, and appropriate frequency. Third, the adoption of core outcome sets (COS) for clinical trials in post-viral OD is urgently needed [<xref rid="REF43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Using COS ensures consistent measurement and reporting of key outcomes across studies, making future meta-analyses more feasible. Fourth, future trials should incorporate extended follow-up periods, ideally at least 12 to 24 months, to assess the durability of any observed treatment effects and monitor for potential late-onset adverse events. Fifth, head-to-head comparisons are needed to optimize treatment strategies by evaluating different PRP formulations (e.g., leukocyte-rich versus leukocyte-poor), concentrations, and administration methods. Finally, since olfactory training is a recommended treatment for post-viral OD, future trials should investigate PRP as an adjunctive therapy. These studies could compare combined therapy (PRP plus olfactory training) against appropriate comparators, such as olfactory training alone or olfactory training with a sham PRP procedure.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>PRP may offer therapeutic benefits for improving objective and subjective olfactory function, as well as clinical response rates, in individuals with persistent COVID-related OD. PRP has been reported to be safe, with minor and transient adverse events primarily related to the procedure itself. While the preliminary findings are encouraging, the limited number of RCTs included warrants cautious interpretation of the results.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>  Ebraheem Albazee, Abdullah N. Aladwani, Yaqoub Y. Alenezi, Munawer A. Alsaeed, Bader Uqlah , Ahmed Abu-Zaid</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>  Ebraheem Albazee, Saad A. Alajmi, Ali M. Alkandari, Munawer A. Alsaeed, Bader Uqlah , Ahmed Abu-Zaid</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>  Ebraheem Albazee, Saad A. Alajmi, Ali M. Alkandari, Munawer A. Alsaeed, Bader Uqlah , Ahmed Abu-Zaid</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>  Ebraheem Albazee, Saad A. Alajmi, Abdullah N. Aladwani, Yaqoub Y. Alenezi, Bader Uqlah , Ahmed Abu-Zaid</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>  Ebraheem Albazee, Bader Uqlah , Ahmed Abu-Zaid</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinical Olfactory Working Group consensus statement on the treatment of postinfectious olfactory dysfunction</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Addison</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1704</fpage><lpage>1719</lpage><volume>147</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33453291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaci.2020.12.641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The prevalence of olfactory and gustatory dysfunction in COVID-19 patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fastenberg</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><volume>163</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32369429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0194599820926473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Post-viral olfactory loss and parosmia</article-title><source>BMJ Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vaira</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boscolo-Rizzo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>2</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjmed-2022-000382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10568123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37841969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>International consensus statement on allergy and rhinology: olfaction</article-title><source>Int Forum Allergy Rhinol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><volume>12</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35373533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/alr.22929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12261282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Recovery from Covid-19 smell loss: two-years of follow up</article-title><source>Am J Otolaryngol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McWilliams</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Costanzo</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>103607</fpage><volume>43</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35987099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjoto.2022.103607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9375644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Topical platelet-rich plasma as a possible treatment for olfactory dysfunction-a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Int Forum Allergy Rhinol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Naimi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garvey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>1464</lpage><volume>14</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38722276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/alr.23363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Long-term recovery from COVID-19 olfactory and gustatory dysfunction: a longitudinal study</article-title><source>Singapore Med J</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/singaporemedj.SMJ-2022-174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38189414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 effects on psychophysical olfactory scores: prospective study with evaluation before and 60-days after infection</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vaira</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lechien</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Salzano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maglitto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boscolo-Rizzo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Riu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1249</fpage><lpage>1252</lpage><volume>168</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36821798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ohn.166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anosmia and hyposmia</article-title><source>Allergy Asthma Proc</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gaines</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><volume>31</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20615320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2500/aap.2010.31.3357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The evidence for olfactory training in treating patients with olfactory loss</article-title><source>Curr Opin Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><volume>25</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27841770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MOO.0000000000000328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Use of platelet-rich plasma for COVID-19-related olfactory loss: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Int Forum Allergy Rhinol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khanwalkar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>997</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36507615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/alr.23116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9877663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Platelet-rich plasma for the management of intrauterine adhesions: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>J Gynecol Obstet Hum Reprod</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Albazee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Rshoud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Almahmoud</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al Omari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alnifise</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baradwan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abu-Zaid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>102276</fpage><volume>51</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34856385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jogoh.2021.102276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The analgesic and anti-haemorrhagic efficacy of platelet-rich plasma in tonsillectomy: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</article-title><source>Clin Otolaryngol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Albazee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Diab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aboeldahab</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdella</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abu-Zaid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><volume>48</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36029195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/coa.13977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Platelet-rich plasma for patients with olfactory dysfunction: myth or reality? A systematic review</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moffa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nardelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><volume>13</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm13030782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10856510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38337476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effectiveness and safety of PRP on persistent olfactory dysfunction related to COVID-19</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steffens</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bon</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lechien</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prunier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saussez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horoi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>5951</fpage><lpage>5953</lpage><volume>279</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35904632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00405-022-07560-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9336533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effectiveness of platelet-rich plasma on post-COVID chronic olfactory dysfunction</article-title><source>Rev Assoc Med Bras (1992)</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Evman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>ZE</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>69</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1806-9282.20230666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10610757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37909619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The potential therapeutic effect of platelet-rich plasma in the treatment of post-COVID-19 parosmia</article-title><source>Egypt J Otolaryngol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abo El Naga</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>El Zaiat</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamdan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>130</fpage><volume>38</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title><source>Syst Rev</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>89</fpage><volume>10</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33781348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13643-021-01626-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8008539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions</article-title><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Estimating the sample mean and standard deviation from the sample size, median, range and/or interquartile range</article-title><source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>135</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25524443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2288-14-135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4383202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>RoB 2: a revised tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials</article-title><source>BMJ</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sterne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Savović</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>366</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.l4898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31462531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>What is "quality of evidence" and why is it important to clinicians?</article-title><source>BMJ</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vist</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Falck-Ytter</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schünemann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>995</fpage><lpage>998</lpage><volume>336</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18456631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.39490.551019.BE</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2364804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>GRADE: an emerging consensus on rating quality of evidence and strength of recommendations</article-title><source>BMJ</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vist</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Falck-Ytter</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Coello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schünemann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><volume>336</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18436948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.39489.470347.AD</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2335261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Quantifying publication bias in meta-analysis</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><volume>74</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29141096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/biom.12817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5953768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Smell and taste dysfunction in patients with COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Agyeman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Landersdorfer</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ofori-Asenso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1621</fpage><lpage>1631</lpage><volume>95</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32753137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mayocp.2020.05.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7275152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Quantitative assessment of olfactory dysfunction accurately detects asymptomatic COVID-19 carriers</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sangle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>100575</fpage><volume>28</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33083773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7562772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Is loss of sense of smell a diagnostic marker in COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Clin Otolaryngol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rocke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>914</fpage><lpage>922</lpage><volume>45</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32741085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/coa.13620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7436734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Olfactory disorders: the patients' view</article-title><source>Rhinology</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stow</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hugentobler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hummel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>454</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><volume>47</volume><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4193/Rhin08.174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Platelet-rich plasma (PRP) in the treatment of long COVID olfactory disorders: a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maniaci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lavalle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Masiello</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><volume>12</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines12040808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11048638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38672163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Exploring the research landscape of COVID-19-induced olfactory dysfunction: a bibliometric study</article-title><source>Front Neurosci</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1164901</fpage><volume>17</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37034158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnins.2023.1164901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10079987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pathogenesis of olfactory disorders in COVID-19</article-title><source>Brain Sci</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ziuzia-Januszewska</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Januszewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><volume>12</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/brainsci12040449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9029941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35447981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The potential of platelet-rich plasma in promoting axonal regeneration: a narrative review</article-title><source>Proceedings of Malikussaleh International Conference on Health and Disaster Medicine (MICOHEDMED)</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maulina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yuziani</surname><given-names>Yuziani</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sofia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><volume>2</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The neuroregenerative capacity of olfactory stem cells is not limitless: implications for aging</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Child</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Herrick</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwob</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>6806</fpage><lpage>6824</lpage><volume>38</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29934351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3261-17.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6070664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The cellular prion protein promotes olfactory sensory neuron survival and axon targeting during adult neurogenesis</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parrie</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crowell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Telling</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bessen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><volume>438</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29577883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ydbio.2018.03.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5916339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The role of platelet plasma growth factors in male pattern baldness surgery</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Uebel</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cantarelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1458</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><volume>118</volume><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17051119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.prs.0000239560.29172.33</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The efficacy of platelet-rich plasma in the repair of tympanic membrane perforation</article-title><source>Int Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prashanth</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Manjunatha</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><volume>29</volume><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-0044-1791646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11772071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39871953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prospective outcomes after serial platelet-rich plasma (PRP) injection in vocal fold scar and sulcus</article-title><source>Laryngoscope</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santa Maria</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Van Der Woerd</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>5021</fpage><lpage>5027</lpage><volume>134</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39115162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/lary.31683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11563877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Platelet-rich plasma for the treatment of COVID-19 related olfactory dysfunction: a systematic review</article-title><source>Rhinology</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>AlRajhi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alrodiman</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alhuzali</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alrashed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alrodiman</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><volume>61</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37772881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4193/Rhin23.168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Platelet-rich plasma following endoscopic sinus surgery in patients with chronic sinusitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</article-title><source>Clin Otolaryngol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Albazee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alsubaie</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alkanderi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Althaidy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alsafar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaleh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdulrahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><volume>49</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38816910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/coa.14186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Efficacy of platelet-rich plasma in the treatment of persistent olfactory impairment after COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Rhinol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><volume>31</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39664044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18787/jr.2024.00006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11566534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Spontaneous recovery of anosmia after 2.5 years in a young COVID-19 patient</article-title><source>Eur Clin Respir J</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ghadirzadeh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davoodi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khazaei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2178598</fpage><volume>10</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36815941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/20018525.2023.2178598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9930803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Justice for placebo: placebo effect in clinical trials and everyday practice</article-title><source>Medicines (Basel)</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Knezevic</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Worobey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Knezevic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>5</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40137049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/medicines12010005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11944128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The development and validation of the Smell-Qx questionnaire, based on a systematic review of the literature and the COMET initiative on the development of core outcome sets for clinical trials in olfactory disorders</article-title><source>Int Forum Allergy Rhinol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fjaeldstad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>974</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><volume>15</volume><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40344493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/alr.23604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12401079</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>