<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">216</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcmedicine</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1741-7015</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12001646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12001646.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12001646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12001646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40234933</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-025-04027-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4027</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Relationship between multimorbidity, SARS-COV-2 infection and long COVID: a cross-sectional population-based French survey</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3334-4809</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Makovski</surname><given-names initials="TT">Tatjana T.</given-names></name><address><email>tatjana.makovski@santepubliquefrance.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steichen</surname><given-names initials="O">Olivier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rushyizekera</surname><given-names initials="M">Melissa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Akker</surname><given-names initials="M">Marjan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coste</surname><given-names initials="J">Joël</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00dfw9p58</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.493975.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 5948 8741</institution-id><institution>Department of Non-Communicable Diseases and Injuries, </institution><institution>French Public Health Agency (Sante Publique France), </institution></institution-wrap>12 Rue du Val d’Osne, Saint-Maurice Cedex, 94415 France </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02vjkv261</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7429.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000121866389</institution-id><institution>UMR-S 1136, </institution><institution>Sorbonne Universite, INSERM, Institut Pierre Louis d’Epidemiologie Et de Sante Publique, IPLESP, </institution></institution-wrap>Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05h5v3c50</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413483.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2259 4338</institution-id><institution>Service de Medecine Interne, </institution><institution>AP-HP, Hopital Tenon, </institution></institution-wrap>Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04cvxnb49</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7839.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9721</institution-id><institution>Institute of General Practice, </institution><institution>Goethe-University, </institution></institution-wrap>Frankfurt, Frankfurt Am Main, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02jz4aj89</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5012.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0481 6099</institution-id><institution>Department of Family Medicine, </institution><institution>Care and Public Health Research Institute, Maastricht University, </institution></institution-wrap>Maastricht, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05f950310</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5596.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0668 7884</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Health and Primary Care, </institution><institution>Academic Centre of General Practice, KU Leuven, </institution></institution-wrap>Louvain, Belgium </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478654</issue-id><elocation-id>222</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-17 10:26:06.673"><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12916_2025_Article_4027.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Understanding the risks of COVID-19-related consequences for vulnerable groups such as people with multimorbidity is crucial to better tailor health care and public health measures. The main objective of this study was to explore the association between multimorbidity and WHO-defined post-COVID condition (PCC), while also considering the association with SARS-COV-2 infection given that the infection is a prerequisite of PCC.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This population-representative cross-sectional study was conducted in the general adult population in mainland France between 29 August and 31 December 2022 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1813). The analyses of the association between multimorbidity (defined as disease count and most prevalent dyads/triads) and PCC or SAR-COV-2 infection were adjusted for age, sex, socioeconomic variables and number of infections (for PCC only) using adjusted Poisson regression with robust variance.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The study population had a mean age (SD) of 53 (± 18.5) years, while 53.6% were women. The likelihood of SARS-COV-2 infection increased with disease count but was only significant for ≥ 4 diseases. Five dyads and one triad presented a higher risk; almost all included anxiety. The likelihood of PCC increased with disease count, prevalence ratios (PRs) (95% CI) for 1, 2–3 and ≥ 4 diseases versus 0 were 1.90 (1.16–3.13), 3.32 (2.07–5.35) and 5.65 (3.41–9.38), respectively, and for 19 of 26 most prevalent dyads and the triad. The association was strongest for cardiac rhythm disorder and either low back pain (PR (95%CI) 4.17 (2.03–8.53)) or anxiety (PR (95%CI) 3.73 (1.98–7.01)).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Multimorbidity, most frequently in combination with anxiety or low back pain, presented a significant association with PCC beyond that of SARS-CoV-2 infection underscoring the importance of implementing strategies to prevent and manage persistent symptoms in vulnerable groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12916-025-04027-9.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Multimorbidity</kwd><kwd>Multiple conditions</kwd><kwd>SARS-COV-2</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Post COVID-19 condition</kwd><kwd>France</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par18">Understanding high-risk groups during the COVID-19 pandemic has driven major public health decisions such as isolating during outbreaks or prioritising vaccination. Clinical decisions like hospital admission or mechanical ventilation for COVID-19 patients were also guided by preexisting health issues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Although the role of individual diseases such as diabetes, cardiovascular or respiratory illnesses in COVID-19-related risks and consequences was explored in the earlier pandemic years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], the risks for individuals with multiple diseases or multimorbidity were seldom assessed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Recently, more studies have explored this issue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], although they remain focused on short-term outcomes such as mortality, hospitalisation or intensive care unit (ICU) admission, while evidence on the long-term effects of SARS-COV-2 infection among patients with multimorbidity is absent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Given that multimorbidity has become ‘the rule rather than the exception’ in clinical practice due to increased life expectancy and disease accumulation with age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], data regarding the risks for this vulnerable population group in the context of changing epidemiological situations are extremely relevant.
</p><p id="Par19">Individuals with more diseases or a higher comorbidity index score such as Elixhauser or Charlson comorbidity indices have consistently shown a higher likelihood of hospitalisation, ICU admission or mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The relationship with SARS-COV-2 infection is less often investigated and with less conclusive findings: some evidence indicates a higher infection probability for a greater morbidity burden, while the opposite effect is also observed, potentially due to the better compliance with protective measures during the pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">Long COVID refers to prolonged symptoms after SARS-CoV-2 infection. Depending on the duration of symptoms, the time of their appearance and other criteria, this pathology has received several designations. The National Institute for Care and Excellence (NICE) describes ongoing symptomatic COVID-19 in which the signs and symptoms of COVID-19 last from 4 to 12 weeks and post-COVID-19 syndrome in which the signs and symptoms consistent with COVID-19 appear during or after infection and last for over 12 weeks with no alternative diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In addition, the World Health Organisation (WHO) refers to post-COVID-19 condition (PCC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] (with the four criteria detailed later in the manuscript), while Thaweethai et al. describe post-acute COVID-19 sequelae (PASC) involving ongoing, relapsing, or new symptoms or conditions lasting for at least 30 days after infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. All the definitions acknowledge a diversity of symptoms such as chronic fatigue, cognitive dysfunction, altered smell and taste, dyspnea and anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Many potential causes of long COVID have been suggested, including (but not limited to) immune dysregulation, persisting deposits of SARS-COV-2 virus and dysfunctional signalling in the nervous system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Risk factors include socioeconomic characteristics such as larger household size and low financial security, number of SARS-COV-2 infections, vaccination status, work-related factors such as negative effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on occupation (loss or change of profession) and work conditions, overall perception of COVID-19 severity and long COVID awareness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. A recent meta-analysis highlighted the higher risk of long COVID for individuals with existing chronic conditions such as mental health issues, ischemic heart diseases, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and immunosuppression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Only a few studies accounted for the number of diseases or Charlson comorbidity index when analysing the risks of prolonged symptoms after SARS-COV-2 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] or treated multimorbidity as a binary variable, which limits our understanding of the association between more granular multimorbidity groups and long COVID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. A clearer and more focused approach to the risks of long COVID is thus required for individuals with multimorbidity.</p><p id="Par21">This study investigates the association between multimorbidity, operationalised as disease count and disease combinations, and WHO PCC in a representative sample of adults in mainland France. As SARS-COV-2 infection is a prerequisite for PCC, we also analysed the relationship between multimorbidity and SARS-COV-2 infection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par22">This cross-sectional study was conducted among the adult population (≥ 18 years) in mainland France. Participants were randomly selected using landline (two-stage sampling design; one person per household was selected following the Kish model) and mobile phone numbers (the owner of the number was selected) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Data were collected by a specialised market research provider IPSOS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] between 29 August and 31 December 2022 in two phases: computer-assisted telephone interview (CATI) and computer-assisted web interview (CAWI). The first part inquired about the number and date of SARS-COV-2 infection(s) (year/month/day), acute infection symptoms and the confirmed or probable status of infection. Data also included COVID-19-related hospitalisations and ICU admissions, workplace contaminations, every PCC symptom appearance (year/month/day), their link with SARS-COV-2 infection (confirmed by a physician) and impact on daily functioning (participant’s rating as no, low, moderate, strong and very strong impact for each PCC symptom). This part also collected socioeconomic data as well as brief information about health care usage and general and mental health. All participants whose symptoms complied with WHO PCC criteria (PCC participants) were directed to an online platform to complete CAWI, as were sub-samples of non-infected participants (sampling ratio 1/5.7) and infected participants without PCC (sampling ratio 1/2.0). The mentioned sampling ratios were chosen to ensure the minimum sample size for each sample group (&gt; 150 participants) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. CAWI collected detailed information about health care use in the past 12 months (specialist consultations, medical exams), COVID-19-related work absence, vaccination, chronic conditions, health behaviour, mental health, quality of life, social support, impact of COVID-19 crisis on income as well as professional and social life. The full interview (CATI and CAWI) lasted for around 45 min.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Ascertainment of SARS-CoV-2 infections and post-COVID-19 condition</title><p id="Par23">SARS-CoV-2 infections were regarded as confirmed cases when the infection was confirmed by a test or physician and probable cases when participants declared that infection was most likely due to COVID-19 even if no testing was performed or when the test was negative. Multiple infections were separately recorded when occurring more than 2 months apart. For each infection (up to five infections), the same procedure was repeated, including specifying the date of infection (day/month/year) and inquiring whether the infection was confirmed or probable.</p><p id="Par24">We used the WHO PCC definition to select PCC patients: confirmed or probable infected subjects with at least one symptom appearing within 3 months of infection and lasting for at least 2 months, which could not be explained by an alternative diagnosis and had an impact on daily functioning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The date of infection and appearance of symptoms allowed us to estimate the duration of symptoms and exclude those predating SARS-CoV-2 infection. The list of PCC symptoms is available in Supplementary Table 1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Definition and operationalisation of multimorbidity</title><p id="Par25">Multimorbidity was defined as the coexistence of ≥ 2 chronic conditions in an individual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and operationalised through disease groups (0, 1, 2–3, 4 + diseases) and disease combinations (most frequent dyads and triads). Participants selected chronic conditions from a list of 21 + conditions if they were present in the past 12 months and had been diagnosed by a physician (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). All diseases were combined into dyads and triads, which were then tested for prevalence in the total population. Dyads and triads with &gt; 30 subjects were considered the most prevalent.
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Study characteristics of the total study sample, infected participants and participants with post-COVID-19 condition</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total study sample (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1813)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Infected participants (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1448)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Infected participants with post-COVID-19 condition (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 178) </th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%<sup>a</sup> </th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> </th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">779</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">624</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1034</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">824</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18-29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">219</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">198</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30-39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">257</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">225</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40-49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">356</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">299</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50-59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">373</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">323</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60-69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">330</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">238</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">278</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Living alone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">428</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">302</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1385</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1146</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Education</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Less than secondary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">506</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">373</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Secondary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">616</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">503</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tertiary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">691</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">572</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Employment status </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paid employment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1062</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">920</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unemployed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retired</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">508</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">326</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">174</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Household income</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">First tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">320</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">236</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Second tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">659</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">515</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Third tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">759</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">637</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not reported</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Household financially at ease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1194</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">938</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">619</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">510</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking every day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">271</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">213</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1542</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1235</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Moderate physical activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Almost never or never</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">107</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max 3 times a month</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">602</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">495</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Several times a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">880</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No consumption in the last 12 months to 3 times a month</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">938</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">747</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">107</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 to 6 days a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">741</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">604</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Every day or almost every day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">COVID-19 vaccination status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 or 1 doses</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">174</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">378</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 or 4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1261</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">943</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Number of infections</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">365</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1159</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1159</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">289</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">289</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Hospitalisation due to COVID-19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1793</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1428</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">174</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">ICU admission due to COVID-19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1808</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1443</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Multimorbidity (number of diseases)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">637</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">513</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">491</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">384</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 or 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">470</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">380</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">215</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">171</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Individual diseases</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">215</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Angina pectoris or myocardial infarction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stroke or cerebrovascular accident (with or without sequelae)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Lower limb arteritis (arterial disease)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Cardiac rhythm disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Organ or blood cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Chronic bronchitis, emphysema, COPD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Asthma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hearing impairment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Uncorrected eyesight problems</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Liver cirrhosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Thyroid disorders (goiter, hyper- or hypothyroidism)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Depression</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">127</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">316</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">278</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Low back pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">373</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">297</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Peripheral osteoarthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">229</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">166</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Osteoporosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Renal insufficienc</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Physical disability due to accident or illness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Obesity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">311</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">249</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">194</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">COPD</italic> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</p><p><sup>a</sup>weighted percentages</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="Par26">The likelihood of SARS-COV-2 infection was estimated among all study participants who answered CAWI. The likelihood of developing PCC was estimated among infected CAWI subjects.</p><p id="Par27">Study characteristics were presented as crude numbers and weighted percentages using sex, age, region of residence, urbanisation unit, household size and education level for standardisation based on data from the French National Institute for Statistics and Economic Studies (Insee).</p><p id="Par28">All covariates were tested for association with multimorbidity, SARS-COV-2 infection and PCC using age- and sex-adjusted Poisson regression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Associated variables and those identified in the literature as relevant were included in the final models as adjustment factors.</p><p id="Par29">Final models were hence adjusted for age, sex, socioeconomic variables and number of infections (for the risk of PCC) using adjusted Poisson regression with robust variance to estimate prevalence ratios (PRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) for the association between multimorbidity (as a disease count [four categories] or disease combinations [dyads and triads]) and SARS-CoV-2 infection and PCC, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Reference categories were 0 diseases (for the analyses with disease count) and the population without the dyad/triad in question (including individuals with other disease combinations and 0 or 1 disease) (for the analysis with disease combinations).</p><p id="Par30">Multicollinearity was tested among the adjustment factors such as socioeconomic variables and number of infections using the Spearman correlation coefficient.</p><p id="Par31">To conduct a more detailed analysis of the associations, we tested for age- and sex-based interactions with multimorbidity in relation to SARS-COV-2 infection and PCC.</p><p id="Par32">To estimate a possible departure from a multiplicative effect of diseases on the likelihood of PCC and infection, we tested the interactions between diseases constituting the dyads in the fully adjusted models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par33">All analyses were performed in SAS, version 9.2 software (SAS Institute, Cary, NC).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Funding source and ethics approval</title><p id="Par34">This study did not receive any specific funding from public or private agencies or from non-profit entities. The study was approved by the local Ethics and Deontology Committee on 19 August 2022.</p><p id="Par35">Data and codes can be made available upon reasonable request and approval from the ethics committee.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Study population characteristics</title><p id="Par36">The CAWI response rate was 43% with 1813 participants completing the interview; this was similar across all groups. The mean age (SD) was 53 (± 18.5) and 53.6% were women.</p><p id="Par37">Over one-third (35.8%) of the population had two or more chronic conditions (multimorbidity). The most frequent conditions were low back pain, obesity, peripheral osteoarthritis and anxiety (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par38">Twenty-six dyads were identified. The most frequent were low back pain and peripheral osteoarthritis (5.6%), anxiety and low back pain (5.4%), and hypertension and obesity (4.6%). Only one triad was observed in over 30 subjects, combining anxiety, depression and low back pain (1.2%) (Supplementary Table 2). Descriptive statistics showed that individuals with multimorbidity were more frequently older, women and lived alone; they more often had less than secondary education, were less financially at ease, more frequently vaccinated for COVID-19 with three or four doses and, despite being less infected overall, were slightly more infected two or more times, as opposed to people without multimorbidity (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, the age- and sex-adjusted Poisson regression model showed no association between multimorbidity and vaccination, suggesting that vaccination status was associated with age; the association between multimorbidity and vaccination status (0 or 1 vaccine) was PR (95%CI) 0.92 (0.69–1.23) <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.583, while it was 0.89 (0.72–1.14) <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.320 with vaccination status (two vaccinations) compared with three or four vaccinations.
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Sample characteristics of total CAWI study sample with and without multimorbidity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">With multimorbidity (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=685)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Without multimorbidity (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1128)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">236</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">543</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">449</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">585</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18-29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">166</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30-39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40-49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">248</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50-59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">218</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60-69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Living alone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">192</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">236</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">493</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">892</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Education</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Less than secondary </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">234</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">272</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Secondary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">219</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">397</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tertiary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">459</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Employment status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paid employment </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">323</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">739</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unemployed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retired</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">262</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">246</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Household income</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">First tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">192</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Second tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">269</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">390</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Third tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">503</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not reported</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Household financially at ease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">405</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">789</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">280</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">339</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking every day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">581</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">961</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Moderate physical activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Almost never or never</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max 3 times a month</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">237</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">365</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Several times a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">404</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No consumption in the last 12 months to 3 times a month</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">385</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">553</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 to 6 days a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">246</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">495</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Every day or almost every day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">COVID-19 vaccination status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 or 1 doses</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">264</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 or 4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">506</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">755</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Number of infections</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">231</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">427</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">732</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Hospitalisation due to COVID-19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">670</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1123</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">ICU admission due to COVID-19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">681</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1127</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Multimorbidity (number of diseases)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">637</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">491</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 or 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">470</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">215</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Individual diseases</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">178</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Angina pectoris or myocardial infarction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stroke or cerebrovascular accident (with or without sequelae)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Lower limb arteritis (arterial disease)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Cardiac rhythm disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Organ or blood cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Chronic bronchitis, emphysema, COPD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Asthma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hearing impairment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Uncorrected eyesight problems</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Liver cirrhosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Thyroid disorders (goiter, hyper- or hypothyroidism)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Depression</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">260</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Low back pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">298</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Peripheral osteoarthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">197</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Osteoporosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Renal insufficiency</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Physical disability due to accident or illness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Obesity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">209</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">CAWI</italic> Computer-assisted web interview, <italic toggle="yes">COPD</italic> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</p><p><sup>a</sup>weighted precentages</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par39">Overall, 1448 individuals were infected (or 54.8%, weighted percentage), with a mean age (± SD) of 49 (± 14.4) and 53.4% women. Among infected participants, 87.7% had a positive test. Similar to the total sample, 35.2% of infected participants had ≥ 2 chronic conditions and 10.6% had ≥ 4. The most frequent diseases were similar as in the overall CAWI sample (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Anxiety and low back pain (5.6%), anxiety and depression (4.9%), low back pain and peripheral osteoarthritis (4.6%), low back pain and obesity (3.5%), and anxiety and obesity (3.5%) were the most frequent dyads, whereas the anxiety, depression and low back pain triad had a prevalence of 1.9% (Supplementary Table 3). Characteristics of the sample with multimorbidity were similar to those described above (Supplementary Table 4).</p><p id="Par40">Among infected individuals, 178 had PCC (or 7.0%, weighted percentage); PCC was more frequent among women and the 40–49 age group (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). PCC was more frequent among infected individuals with multimorbidity, being 12.5% versus. 4.1% for the non-multimorbidity group (Supplementary Table 4).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Associations with multimorbidity</title><p id="Par41">The model adjusted for age, sex, education and income presented an increasing risk of SARS-COV-2 with an increasing number of diseases, although the association was only significant for the last multimorbidity group (≥ 4 diseases), PR (95%CI): 1.22 (1.01–1.48), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.037 (Supplementary Table 5). There was no between-sex difference. Individuals aged ≥ 60 years and those with the lowest household income had the lowest risk of infection (Supplementary Table 6).</p><p id="Par42">Five dyads and the triad were associated with an increased risk of infection and almost all included anxiety (Supplementary Table 5). Certain individual diseases were significantly associated with SARS-COV-2 infection in the adjusted models such as angina pectoris or myocardial infarction, cardiac rhythm disorder, anxiety and depression (Supplementary Table 7).</p><p id="Par43">The model adjusted for age, sex, household financial ease and number of infections presented an increased likelihood of PCC for an increasing number of diseases. PRs (95%CIs) and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values for 1, 2–3 and ≥ 4 diseases versus 0 were 1.90 (1.16–3.13), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.011; 3.32 (2.07–5.35), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt; 0.000 and 5.65 (3.41–9.38), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.000, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The likelihood of PCC was higher for women and those infected at least twice, while the risk was lower for the oldest age group (≥ 70 years) and financially better-off households (Supplementary Table 8).
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Association between disease groups and disease combinations with post-COVID-19 condition (PCC) among infected individuals adjusted for age, sex, household financially at ease and number of infections</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of chronic conditions (ref. 0)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PR<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% </th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CI<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2-3 diseases</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥4 diseases</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Disease combinations (dyads and triad)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any ≥2 diseases</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension + low back pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension + peripheral osteoarthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.322</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension + obesity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.113</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety + depression </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety + low back pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety + obesity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low back pain + peripheral osteoarthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low back pain + obesity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.786</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension + cardiac rhythm disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension + hearing impairment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension + anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.073</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension + diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.046</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiac rhythm disorder + anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiac rhythm disorder + low back pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiac rhythm disorder + peripheral osteoarthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hearing impairment + anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hearing impairment + low back pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hearing impairment + peripheral osteoarthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Uncorrected eyesight problems + anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Uncorrected eyesight problems + low back pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Uncorrected eyesight problems + peripheral osteoarthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thyroid disorders (goiter, hyper- or hypothyroidism) + low back pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.204</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Depression + low back pain </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.72</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety + peripheral osteoarthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peripheral osteoarthritis + obesity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.981</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes + obesity </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.365</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxity + depression + low back pain </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">PR</italic> Prevalence ratio, <italic toggle="yes">95% CI</italic> 95% Confidence interval</p><p><sup>a</sup>PR and 95% CI estimated with Poisson regression with robust variance</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par44">Using the Spearman correlation coefficient, no collinearity was found between independent variables. Sex- and age-based interactions with multimorbidity in relation to PCC did not present significant results, nor did the sex and multimorbidity interaction with SARS-COV-2 infection. Age (10-year intervals) and multimorbidity interaction in relation to SARS-COV-2 infection was significant for the multimorbidity groups with 2–3 and ≥ 4 conditions, PRs (95%CIs) 0.92 (0.85–1.00) <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.046 and 0.89 (0.81–0.98) <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.018, respectively. This indicates the weakening strength of the association between multimorbidity and infection with age; for example, for the multimorbidity group with two to three conditions, the strength of the association between multimorbidity and infection decreased by 8% with every 10 years of age compared with 11% for the group with ≥ 4 conditions.</p><p id="Par45">The triad and 19 dyads were associated with PCC. PRs (95%CI) were the highest for cardiac rhythm disorder and low back pain 4.17 (2.03–8.53), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.000 and for cardiac rhythm disorder and anxiety 3.73 (1.98–7.01), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.000 compared with individuals without those dyads (including individuals with 0 and 1 disease). For the triad, the PR was 2.73 (1.54–4.84), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001 (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Angina pectoris or myocardial infarction, cardiac rhythm disorder, hearing impairment, uncorrected eyesight problems, depression, anxiety, low back pain and peripheral osteoarthritis were individually associated with PCC in the adjusted models (Supplementary Table 9).</p><p id="Par46">The interaction between the dyad diseases showed no significant results, suggesting that the hypothesis of multiplicative effects of disease combinations on the likelihood of PCC and SARS-COV-2 infection should not be rejected, except for the dyads of anxiety and depression and of low back pain and obesity, which presented significant sub-multiplicative effects for the likelihood of PCC (Supplementary Tables 10 and 11).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par47">This representative population-based study conducted in autumn 2022 in France assessed the likelihood of SARS-COV-2 infection and PCC for individuals with multimorbidity. Only the group with ≥ 4 diseases presented a significantly higher likelihood of SARS-COV-2 infection; the likelihood of infection was also higher for several disease combinations, almost all of which included anxiety. Earlier findings about SARS-COV-2 risks for people with multimorbidity have been inconsistent, indicating either elevated risks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] or lower likelihood of infection or no association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. These discrepancies may be methodological (e.g. different multimorbidity measurements) or depend on the study sample characteristics or country-specific contexts (e.g., different protective measures, SARS-COV-2 testing policies, availability of tests in the early months after their release) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Our study may not be fully comparable, as it was conducted during the Omicron strain, which was more contagious but less harmful compared with previous ones, also reflected in the high infection rate in our population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Furthermore, the vast majority of our sample was vaccinated, which can increase the number of asymptomatic cases. The recent concepts of ‘immunosenescence’ and ‘inflammaging’ acknowledge age-related changes in the immune system, leading to deteriorated immune response and lasting silent inflammation due to the overstimulated but inefficient immune system. Older people may therefore have higher susceptibility to infections and more severe outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Although our regression analysis showed a lower infection risk in older people, this may result from better adherence to non-pharmaceutical (such as masks use and social distancing) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] and pharmaceutical (such as vaccination) interventions. In addition, the healthy survivor effect, which is a type of selection bias that may diminish the strength of the association due to the survival of healthier individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], cannot be excluded, especially since over one-third of our population had multiple conditions, which is associated with higher mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. However, given the low hospitalisation rate and even lower ICU admission rate of our study sample, we do not believe that this effect had a significant impact on our findings. In our study, given the lack of association between multimorbidity and vaccination status, our models were not adjusted for vaccination. This is not surprising considering the very high vaccination rate in France during the COVID-19 pandemic, particularly during the advanced stages of the Omicron wave [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Interactions between biological changes associated with advanced age and elevated morbidity burden may have resulted in significant results in the group with the highest disease count. The interaction between multimorbidity and age presented a decreasing strength of association between multimorbidity and SARS-COV-2 infection with age in our study. This phenomenon is not exceptional, as the strength of the association for other outcomes, e.g. quality of life, has been observed to weaken with age among people with multimorbidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par48">Huang et al. observed almost a doubled risk of infection for individuals with cardiovascular and complex comorbidities (hypertension, arthritis, retinopathy/eye diseases and hyperlipidaemia) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Our method focused on the most prevalent dyads and triads, which may have generated different combinations compared with the cluster analysis of Huang et al. Both studies nevertheless included a long list of chronic conditions and adjusted for several potential confounders, although our study had vaccinated population. None of our combinations associated with a higher infection risk included cardiovascular disease, while eyesight problems formed part of two patterns with significant associations.</p><p id="Par49">One of our strongest findings was that four out of five dyads and the triad involved anxiety. Mental health issues, included in a heterogeneous cluster in Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], also showed a stronger association with infection. This may be because anxious people report more symptoms or engage in more frequent testing or more frequent visits to general practitioners because SARS-COV-2 infection causes mental stress and anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] or because chronic psychological stress makes people more susceptible to infection by triggering unregulated immune responses, as previously suggested for several upper respiratory infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Specifying the date of symptom occurrence (including anxiety) in our study aimed to exclude symptoms predating the SARS-COV-2 infection. However, it is possible that anxiety, like other symptoms, that occurred after the infection may not have had a direct link with PCC.</p><p id="Par50">The likelihood of PCC was higher for people with more diseases and for dyads combining cardiac rhythm disorder and low back pain or anxiety and for dyads combining peripheral osteoarthritis with eyesight problems or anxiety. Only one identified triad, combining anxiety, depression and low back pain, was associated with an elevated risk of PCC and, to a much lower extent, SARS-COV-2 infection.</p><p id="Par51">Our results confirm previous findings about the higher likelihood of long COVID in people with greater disease burden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Several studies did not observe a higher risk of long COVID but rather more long COVID symptoms in individuals with multimorbidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Higher risk of PCC was linked to a wide range of individual chronic conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], as was the case in our study. We nevertheless could not identify studies exploring the effect of disease combinations on long COVID. In our sample, 19 of the 26 most prevalent dyads were significantly associated with PCC. In addition, our results suggest a probable multiplication effect of certain disease combinations. However, the combinations of anxiety and depression, and low back pain and obesity presented sub-multiplicative effects on PCC, probably due to the frequent overlapping of these conditions. Similar studies using comparable lists of diseases and analytical methods would elucidate this disease coupling and their joint effects on PCC.</p><sec id="Sec12"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="Par52">This large representative population-based study was conducted on a random sample of the general population residing in France. The questionnaire was based on the WHO PCC criteria (Coste J. Under revision: Prevalence of long COVID in the general adult population according to different definitions and sociodemographic and infection characteristics. A nationwide random sampling survey in France after the Omicron waves in autumn 2022.) and included a large list of chronic conditions to explore multimorbidity. Operationalising multimorbidity as the number and pattern of diseases allowed a more detailed examination of the associations. Nevertheless, the cross-sectional study design did not allow for the causal interpretation of findings, and longitudinal observations are required to understand temporal trajectories of this condition. This is particularly relevant for chronic conditions, which may show the same symptoms as PCC. However, in the study questionnaire, the date of symptom onset allowed us to identify their occurrence before or after infection. It cannot be excluded that some new symptoms were linked to pre-existing chronic conditions, triggered or not by the infection, and not linked to PCC, as also mentioned above. The study was self-reported, which may have led to recall and social desirability biases, even though for certain information such as SARS-COV-2 infection, PCC symptoms and chronic conditions, other means of validation were sought such as infection confirmed by a test or physician (for confirmed infections), exclusion of other diagnoses (for PCC symptoms) and medical diagnoses for chronic diseases. This study did not collect biomedical data, which would provide additional information about the physiological vulnerability of different multimorbidity groups. It was not possible to distinguish cases with different virus variants, which would be informative when investigating the risks associated with different variants. Certain PCC cases may have been omitted due to recovery over time. Using a comprehensive database, the analyses were adjusted for different variables, although some factors like hospitalisation or ICU admission, which are potential risk factors for PCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], were not considered due to their small prevalence.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Research and policy recommendations</title><p id="Par53">Despite recent advances that consider multimorbidity alongside individual diseases, evidence is still lacking regarding its impact on COVID-19 outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Although it may be expected that more diseases combined with advanced age are associated with poorer COVID-19 outcomes, our results provide precise estimates of the risk associated with different multimorbidity groups. Certain disease combinations significantly affect outcomes like functionality, quality of life, health care management and costs due to their additive or multiplicative interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Similar considerations emerge in the context of COVID-19 where certain disease clusters present stronger associations with COVID-19 outcomes. Efforts should focus on identifying the most common and most impactful disease combinations to improve overall care for patients with multimorbidity. Potential mechanisms of disease pairing were described over a decade ago through pathways of direct causation between diseases, associated risk factors, and interacting risk factors where each can cause either disease, independent mechanisms or chance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. A better understanding of these mechanisms would help explain the logic of disease clustering and predict the impact on various health outcomes. This goes beyond understanding mere physiological processes and includes interactions with socioeconomic circumstances, health behaviours and environmental factors. Considering a particular vulnerability of the population with multimorbidity to a number of health outcomes, including COVID-19 and perhaps other potential health threats should they emerge, further understanding and surveying multimorbidity remains one of the major health and population health priorities.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par54">Multimorbidity, most frequently in combination with anxiety or low back pain, presented a significant association with PCC beyond that of SARS-CoV-2 infection underscoring the importance of implementing strategies to prevent and manage persistent symptoms in vulnerable groups. COVID-19 and especially long COVID are yet to be understood, but evidence points to their long-lasting consequences requiring comprehensive and multisectoral management. This is already the case for people with multimorbidity who often navigate through single-disease-oriented health care systems to manage their multiple needs. Integrated care, which is often recommended for people with multimorbidity, might therefore be valuable for individuals with long COVID. This may be another incentive to move toward a more integrated and multidisciplinary approach to health care.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12916_2025_4027_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par5">COronaVIrus Disease of 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p id="Par6">World Health Organisation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCC</term><def><p id="Par7">Post-COVID-19 condition</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SARS-COV-2</term><def><p id="Par8">Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PR</term><def><p id="Par9">Prevalence ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par10">Confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICU</term><def><p id="Par11">Intensive care unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NICE</term><def><p id="Par12">The National Institute for Care and Excellence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PASC</term><def><p id="Par13">Post-acute COVID-19 sequelae</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CATI</term><def><p id="Par14">Computer-assisted telephone interview</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAWI</term><def><p id="Par15">Computer-assisted web interview</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>INSEE</term><def><p id="Par16">French National Institute for Statistics and Economic Studies</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par17">Standard deviation</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements
</title><p>The authors would like to thank a Santé publique France colleague Jean-Baptiste RICHARD on his help in calculating the appropriate statistical weights and preparing the data.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions
</title><p>TM and JC designed the study. TM conducted the analyses. OS, MvdA, MR, JC and TM participated in the data interpretation. TM wrote the first draft of the article. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was funded by Santé Publique France, the French Public Health Agency. The funder had no role in the design of the data or the collection, analysis and interpretation of data, neither in the writing of this article nor the decision to submit it for publication.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data are available upon reasonable request and approval from the ethics committee.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par55">The planning, conduct and reporting of the survey was in line with the Declaration of Helsinki and French laws. The study was approved by the local Ethics and Deontology Committee on 19 August 2022. This study relies only on the analysis of anonymously collected data. In accordance with the guidelines of the French Data Protection Authority (Commission Nationale de l’Informatique et des Libertées); all subjects included in this study were informed and gave oral consent to participate before the telephone interview.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par56">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests
</title><p id="Par57">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References
</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lone</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidities, multimorbidity and COVID-19</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02156-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36797482</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Russell CD, Lone NI, Baillie JK. Comorbidities, multimorbidity and COVID-19. Nat Med. 2023;29(2):334–43.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36797482</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-022-02156-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikoloski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alqunaibet</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfawaz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almudarra</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Saharty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Covid-19 and non-communicable diseases: evidence from a systematic literature review</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1068</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-021-11116-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34090396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8178653</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Nikoloski Z, Alqunaibet AM, Alfawaz RA, Almudarra SS, Herbst CH, El-Saharty S, et al. Covid-19 and non-communicable diseases: evidence from a systematic literature review. BMC Public Health. 2021;21(1):1068.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34090396</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-021-11116-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8178653</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makovski</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghattas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monnier-Besnard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavillot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrožová</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vašinová</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multimorbidity and frailty are associated with poorer SARS-CoV-2-related outcomes: systematic review of population-based studies</article-title><source>Aging Clin Exp Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>36</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40520-023-02685-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38353841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10866755</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Makovski TT, Ghattas J, Monnier-Besnard S, Cavillot L, Ambrožová M, Vašinová B, et al. Multimorbidity and frailty are associated with poorer SARS-CoV-2-related outcomes: systematic review of population-based studies. Aging Clin Exp Res. 2024;36(1):40.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38353841</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40520-023-02685-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10866755</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azcoaga-Lorenzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fagbamigbe</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasileiou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between multimorbidity and mortality in a cohort of patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19 in Scotland</article-title><source>J R Soc Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>115</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01410768211051715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34672832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8811325</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Agrawal U, Azcoaga-Lorenzo A, Fagbamigbe AF, Vasileiou E, Henery P, Simpson CR, et al. Association between multimorbidity and mortality in a cohort of patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19 in Scotland. J R Soc Med. 2022;115(1):22–30.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34672832</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/01410768211051715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8811325</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calazans</surname><given-names>MIP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>ELO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aristizábal</surname><given-names>LYG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between multimorbidity, intensive care unit admission, and death in patients with COVID-19 in Brazil: a cross-section study, 2020</article-title><source>Sao Paulo Med J</source><year>2022</year><volume>141</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e2022226</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1516-3180.2022.0226.r1.21072022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36197353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10065096</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Cardoso JP, Calazans MIP, Carneiro A, Costa CM, Monteiro ELO, Aristizábal LYG, et al. Association between multimorbidity, intensive care unit admission, and death in patients with COVID-19 in Brazil: a cross-section study, 2020. Sao Paulo Med J. 2022;141(3):e2022226.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36197353</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1516-3180.2022.0226.R1.21072022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10065096</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dansero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilcrease</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macciotta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saugo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manfredi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multimorbidity and SARS-CoV-2-related outcomes: analysis of a cohort of Italian patients</article-title><source>JMIR Public Health Surveill</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e41404</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/41404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36626821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9951075</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Catalano A, Dansero L, Gilcrease W, Macciotta A, Saugo C, Manfredi L, et al. Multimorbidity and SARS-CoV-2-related outcomes: analysis of a cohort of Italian patients. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2023;9:e41404.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36626821</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2196/41404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9951075</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duclos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godillon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dequin</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrinier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Case fatality inequalities of critically ill COVID-19 patients according to patient-, hospital- and region-related factors: a French nationwide study</article-title><source>Ann Intensive Care</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>127</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13613-021-00915-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34410543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8375279</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Guillon A, Laurent E, Duclos A, Godillon L, Dequin PF, Agrinier N, et al. Case fatality inequalities of critically ill COVID-19 patients according to patient-, hospital- and region-related factors: a French nationwide study. Ann Intensive Care. 2021;11(1):127.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34410543</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13613-021-00915-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8375279</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanasse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapointe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of multimorbidity among adults seen in family practice</article-title><source>Ann Fam Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15928225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1466875</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Fortin M, Bravo G, Hudon C, Vanasse A, Lapointe L. Prevalence of multimorbidity among adults seen in family practice. Ann Fam Med. 2005;3(3):223–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15928225</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1370/afm.272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1466875</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norbury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wyke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of multimorbidity and implications for health care, research, and medical education: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2012</year><volume>380</volume><issue>9836</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60240-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579043</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Barnett K, Mercer SW, Norbury M, Watt G, Wyke S, Guthrie B. Epidemiology of multimorbidity and implications for health care, research, and medical education: a cross-sectional study. Lancet. 2012;380(9836):37–43.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579043</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60240-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmona-Pírez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gimeno-Miguel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bliek-Bueno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poblador-Plou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Díez-Manglano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioakeim-Skoufa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying multimorbidity profiles associated with COVID-19 severity in chronic patients using network analysis in the PRECOVID Study</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2831</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-06838-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35181720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8857317</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Carmona-Pírez J, Gimeno-Miguel A, Bliek-Bueno K, Poblador-Plou B, Díez-Manglano J, Ioakeim-Skoufa I, et al. Identifying multimorbidity profiles associated with COVID-19 severity in chronic patients using network analysis in the PRECOVID Study. Sci Rep. 2022;12(1):2831.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35181720</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-06838-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8857317</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>JKL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuja-Halkola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hägg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jylhävä</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frailty and comorbidity in predicting community COVID-19 mortality in the U.K. Biobank: the effect of sampling</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc.</source><year>2021</year><volume>69</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1128</fpage><lpage>1139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.17089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33619733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8013405</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Mak JKL, Kuja-Halkola R, Wang Y, Hägg S, Jylhävä J. Frailty and comorbidity in predicting community COVID-19 mortality in the U.K. Biobank: the effect of sampling. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2021;69(5):1128–39.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33619733</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jgs.17089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8013405</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Institute for Health and Care Excellence: Clinical Guidelines. COVID-19 rapid guideline: managing the long-term effects of COVID-19. London: National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE). Copyright
© NICE 2020.; 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organisation (WHO). A clinical case definition of post COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus. 2021. Report No.: WHO/2019-nCoV/Post_COVID-19_condition/Clinical_case_definition/2021.1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thaweethai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levitan</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McComsey</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of a definition of postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2023</year><volume>329</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>1934</fpage><lpage>1946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2023.8823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37278994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10214179</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Thaweethai T, Jolley SE, Karlson EW, Levitan EB, Levy B, McComsey GA, et al. Development of a definition of postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection. JAMA. 2023;329(22):1934–46.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37278994</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2023.8823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10214179</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carcaillon-Bentata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makovski</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alleaume</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beltzer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-Covid-19 condition: a comprehensive analysis of the World Health Organisation definition</article-title><source>J Infect.</source><year>2023</year><volume>87</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e83</fpage><lpage>e87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2023.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37604211</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Carcaillon-Bentata L, Makovski TT, Alleaume C, Decio V, Beltzer N, Gallay A, et al. Post-Covid-19 condition: a comprehensive analysis of the World Health Organisation definition. J Infect. 2023;87(5):e83–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37604211</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2023.08.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tebeka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carcaillon-Bentata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alleaume</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beltzer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complex association between post-COVID-19 condition and anxiety and depression symptoms</article-title><source>Eur Psychiatry</source><year>2023</year><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2023.2473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38088068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10964277</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Tebeka S, Carcaillon-Bentata L, Decio V, Alleaume C, Beltzer N, Gallay A, et al. Complex association between post-COVID-19 condition and anxiety and depression symptoms. Eur Psychiatry. 2023;67(1):e1.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38088068</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2023.2473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10964277</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Topol EJ. Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023;21(3):133–46.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Coste J, Delpierre C, Robineau O, Rushyizekera M, Richard J, Alleaume C, et al. Risk factors for long COVID. A comprehensive nationwide population-based study in France in autumn 2022. Commun Med (in press). 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsampasian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elghazaly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Debski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naing</surname><given-names>TKP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with post−COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>183</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10037203</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Tsampasian V, Elghazaly H, Chattopadhyay R, Debski M, Naing TKP, Garg P, et al. Risk factors associated with post−COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Intern Med. 2023;183(6):566–80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951832</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10037203</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emecen</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keskin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turunc</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suner</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siyve</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basoglu Sensoy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The presence of symptoms within 6 months after COVID-19: a single-center longitudinal study</article-title><source>Ir J Med Sci (1971).</source><year>2023</year><volume>192</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11845-022-03072-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9205653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35715663</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Emecen AN, Keskin S, Turunc O, Suner AF, Siyve N, Basoglu Sensoy E, et al. The presence of symptoms within 6 months after COVID-19: a single-center longitudinal study. Ir J Med Sci (1971). 2023;192(2):741–50.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11845-022-03072-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9205653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35715663</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shikotra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singapuri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sereno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physical, cognitive, and mental health impacts of COVID-19 after hospitalisation (PHOSP-COVID): a UK multicentre, prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1275</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00383-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34627560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8497028</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Evans RA, McAuley H, Harrison EM, Shikotra A, Singapuri A, Sereno M, et al. Physical, cognitive, and mental health impacts of COVID-19 after hospitalisation (PHOSP-COVID): a UK multicentre, prospective cohort study. Lancet Respir Med. 2021;9(11):1275–87.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34627560</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00383-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8497028</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baraff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahoumian</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Hare</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rates and factors associated with documentation of diagnostic codes for long COVID in the National Veterans Affairs Health Care System</article-title><source>JAMA Network Open.</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e2224359</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.24359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35904783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9338411</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Ioannou GN, Baraff A, Fox A, Shahoumian T, Hickok A, O’Hare AM, et al. Rates and factors associated with documentation of diagnostic codes for long COVID in the National Veterans Affairs Health Care System. JAMA Network Open. 2022;5(7):e2224359.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35904783</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.24359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9338411</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavem</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanima</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilboe</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Einvik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistent symptoms 1.5–6 months after COVID-19 in non-hospitalised subjects: a population-based cohort study</article-title><source>Thorax.</source><year>2021</year><volume>76</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-216377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33273028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7716295</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Stavem K, Ghanima W, Olsen MK, Gilboe HM, Einvik G. Persistent symptoms 1.5–6 months after COVID-19 in non-hospitalised subjects: a population-based cohort study. Thorax. 2021;76(4):405–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33273028</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-216377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7716295</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alperin</surname><given-names>MNP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fagherazzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeegers</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of multimorbidity and socio-economic characteristics as potential risk factors for long Covid: evidence from the multilevel analysis of the Survey of Health, Ageing and Retirement in Europe's corona surveys (2020–2021)</article-title><source>Age Ageing.</source><year>2023</year><volume>52</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>afad225</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/afad225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38124254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10733586</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Wilk P, Moran V, Alperin MNP, Bohn T, Fagherazzi G, Zeegers MP, et al. The role of multimorbidity and socio-economic characteristics as potential risk factors for long Covid: evidence from the multilevel analysis of the Survey of Health, Ageing and Retirement in Europe’s corona surveys (2020–2021). Age Ageing. 2023;52(12):afad225.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38124254</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ageing/afad225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10733586</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coste</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delpierre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alleaume</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tebeka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of long COVID in the general adult population according to different definitions and sociodemographic and infection characteristics. A nationwide random sampling survey in France in autumn 2022</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect.</source><year>2024</year><volume>30</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38527615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cmi.2024.03.020</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Coste J, Delpierre C, Richard JB, Alleaume C, Gallay A, Tebeka S, et al. Prevalence of long COVID in the general adult population according to different definitions and sociodemographic and infection characteristics. A nationwide random sampling survey in France in autumn 2022. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2024;30(7):924–9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38527615</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cmi.2024.03.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IPSOS. [May 22, 2024]. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ipsos.com/fr-fr">https://www.ipsos.com/fr-fr</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e102</fpage><lpage>e107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Soriano JB, Murthy S, Marshall JC, Relan P, Diaz JV. A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022;22(4):e102–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nirantharakumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gokhale</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symptoms and risk factors for long COVID in non-hospitalized adults</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1706</fpage><lpage>1714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01909-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35879616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9388369</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Subramanian A, Nirantharakumar K, Hughes S, Myles P, Williams T, Gokhale KM, et al. Symptoms and risk factors for long COVID in non-hospitalized adults. Nat Med. 2022;28(8):1706–14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35879616</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-022-01909-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9388369</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Akker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buntinx</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knottnerus</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity or multimorbidity: what's in a name? A review of literature</article-title><source>European Journal of General Practice</source><year>1996</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/13814789609162146</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">van den Akker M, Buntinx F, Knottnerus JA. Comorbidity or multimorbidity: what’s in a name? A review of literature. European Journal of General Practice. 1996;2(2):65–70.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Future of multimorbidity research: how should understanding of multimorbidity inform health system design?</article-title><source>Public Health Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03391611</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Boyd CM, Fortin M. Future of multimorbidity research: how should understanding of multimorbidity inform health system design? Public Health Rev. 2010;32(2):451–74.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertzmark</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Easy SAS calculations for risk or prevalence ratios and differences</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>162</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwi188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987728</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Spiegelman D, Hertzmark E. Easy SAS calculations for risk or prevalence ratios and differences. Am J Epidemiol. 2005;162(3):199–200.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987728</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/aje/kwi188</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>VanderWeele</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knol</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Tutorial on Interaction</article-title><source>Epidemiol Methods</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/em-2013-0005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">VanderWeele TJ, Knol MJ. A Tutorial on Interaction. Epidemiol Methods. 2014;3(1):33–72.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>JKL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuja-Halkola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hägg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jylhävä</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frailty and comorbidity in predicting community COVID-19 mortality in the U.K. Biobank: The effect of sampling</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc.</source><year>2021</year><volume>69</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1128</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.17089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33619733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8013405</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Mak JKL, Kuja-Halkola R, Wang Y, Hägg S, Jylhävä J. Frailty and comorbidity in predicting community COVID-19 mortality in the U.K. Biobank: The effect of sampling. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2021;69(5):1128–39.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33619733</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jgs.17089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8013405</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McQueenie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>HME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jani</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katikireddi</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sattar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pell</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multimorbidity, polypharmacy, and COVID-19 infection within the UK Biobank cohort</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e0238091</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0238091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32817712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7440632</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">McQueenie R, Foster HME, Jani BD, Katikireddi SV, Sattar N, Pell JP, et al. Multimorbidity, polypharmacy, and COVID-19 infection within the UK Biobank cohort. PLoS ONE. 2020;15(8):e0238091.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32817712</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0238091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7440632</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chudasama</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaccardi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razieh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloecker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Patterns of multimorbidity and risk of severe SARS-CoV-2 infection: an observational study in the U.K. BMC Infect Dis.</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>908</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34481456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-021-06600-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8418288</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Chudasama YV, Zaccardi F, Gillies CL, Razieh C, Yates T, Kloecker DE, et al. Patterns of multimorbidity and risk of severe SARS-CoV-2 infection: an observational study in the UK BMC Infect Dis. 2021;21(1):908.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34481456</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-021-06600-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8418288</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosconi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stival</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lugo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Signorelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amerio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalieri d'Oro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determinants of SARS-CoV-2 Infection in the older adult population: data from the LOST in Lombardia study</article-title><source>Vaccines (Basel).</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>989</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines10070989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35891155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9324825</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Mosconi G, Stival C, Lugo A, Signorelli C, Amerio A, Cavalieri d’Oro L, et al. Determinants of SARS-CoV-2 Infection in the older adult population: data from the LOST in Lombardia study. Vaccines (Basel). 2022;10(7):989.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35891155</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vaccines10070989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9324825</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Our World In Data. [31/01/2024]. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/daily-covid-19-tests-smoothed-7-day?time=earliest..2020-05-27&amp;country=ITA~GBR">https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/daily-covid-19-tests-smoothed-7-day?time=earliest..2020-05-27&amp;country=ITA~GBR</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant: recent progress and future perspectives</article-title><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>141</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-022-00997-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35484110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047469</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Fan Y, Li X, Zhang L, Wan S, Zhang L, Zhou F. SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant: recent progress and future perspectives. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022;7(1):141.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35484110</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41392-022-00997-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047469</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alarcón</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palomo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune system dysfunction in the elderly</article-title><source>An Acad Bras Cienc</source><year>2017</year><volume>89</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0001-3765201720160487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28423084</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Fuentes E, Fuentes M, Alarcón M, Palomo I. Immune system dysfunction in the elderly. An Acad Bras Cienc. 2017;89(1):285–99.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28423084</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/0001-3765201720160487</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pellegrino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macerola</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murace</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibba</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>How can biology of aging explain the severity of COVID-19 in older adults</article-title><source>Clin Geriatr Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>38</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cger.2022.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35868666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9023334</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Gallo A, Pero E, Pellegrino S, Macerola N, Murace CA, Ibba F, et al. How can biology of aging explain the severity of COVID-19 in older adults. Clin Geriatr Med. 2022;38(3):461–72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35868666</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cger.2022.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9023334</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaï</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nassany</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randriamampianina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vernay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with compliance with barrier gestures and social distancing measures in France</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Popul Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>72</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>202194</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jeph.2024.202194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38523401</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Metzger C, Yaï J, Nassany O, Randriamampianina S, Vernay M. Factors associated with compliance with barrier gestures and social distancing measures in France. J Epidemiol Popul Health. 2024;72(2):202194.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38523401</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jeph.2024.202194</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Modern epidemiology</source><year>2008</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott, Williams Wilkins</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="book">Rothman KJ, Greenland S, Lash TL. Modern epidemiology. 3rd ed. Philadelphia, PA: Lippincott, Williams Wilkins; 2008.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mielke</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thumé</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Facchini</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multimorbidity and mortality in older adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Arch Gerontol Geriatr</source><year>2016</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.archger.2016.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27500661</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Nunes BP, Flores TR, Mielke GI, Thumé E, Facchini LA. Multimorbidity and mortality in older adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Arch Gerontol Geriatr. 2016;67:130–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27500661</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.archger.2016.07.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">l'Assurance Maladie. Les données de la vaccination contre la Covid-19 [Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://datavaccin-covid.ameli.fr/pages/synthese/">https://datavaccin-covid.ameli.fr/pages/synthese/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makovski</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeegers</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stranges</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Akker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multimorbidity and quality of life: systematic literature review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Ageing Res Rev</source><year>2019</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>100903</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2019.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31048032</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Makovski TT, Schmitz S, Zeegers MP, Stranges S, van den Akker M. Multimorbidity and quality of life: systematic literature review and meta-analysis. Ageing Res Rev. 2019;53:100903.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31048032</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arr.2019.04.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steptoe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller Thomson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of long-term conditions and comorbidity patterns on COVID-19 infection and hospitalisation: a cohort study</article-title><source>Gerontology</source><year>2023</year><volume>69</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1200</fpage><lpage>1210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000531848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37696249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10614230</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Huang YT, Steptoe A, Patel RS, Fuller Thomson E, Cadar D. The impact of long-term conditions and comorbidity patterns on COVID-19 infection and hospitalisation: a cohort study. Gerontology. 2023;69(10):1200–10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37696249</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000531848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10614230</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>EDS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Passos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>MAB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>APA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>MCC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multimorbidity associated with anxiety symptomatology in post-COVID patients</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>114427</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2022.114427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35124546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8801057</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Azevedo MN, Rodrigues EDS, Passos E, Filho MAB, Barreto APA, Lima MCC, et al. Multimorbidity associated with anxiety symptomatology in post-COVID patients. Psychiatry Res. 2022;309:114427.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35124546</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.psychres.2022.114427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8801057</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychosocial vulnerabilities to upper respiratory infectious illness: implications for susceptibility to Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19)</article-title><source>Perspect Psychol Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1745691620942516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32640177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7345443</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Cohen S. Psychosocial vulnerabilities to upper respiratory infectious illness: implications for susceptibility to Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19). Perspect Psychol Sci. 2021;16(1):161–74.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32640177</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1745691620942516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7345443</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-de-las-Peñas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pellicer-Valero</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro-Pardo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios-Ceña</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Florencio</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guijarro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symptoms experienced at the acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection as risk factor of long-term post-COVID symptoms: the LONG-COVID-EXP-CM multicenter study</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2022.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35017102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8743274</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Fernández-de-las-Peñas C, Pellicer-Valero OJ, Navarro-Pardo E, Palacios-Ceña D, Florencio LL, Guijarro C, et al. Symptoms experienced at the acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection as risk factor of long-term post-COVID symptoms: the LONG-COVID-EXP-CM multicenter study. Int J Infect Dis. 2022;116:241–4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35017102</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijid.2022.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8743274</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsampasian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elghazaly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Debski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naing</surname><given-names>TKP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with post-COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>183</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10037203</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Tsampasian V, Elghazaly H, Chattopadhyay R, Debski M, Naing TKP, Garg P, et al. Risk factors associated with post-COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Intern Med. 2023;183(6):566–80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951832</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10037203</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coste</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valderas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carcaillon-Bentata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating and characterizing the burden of multimorbidity in the community: a comprehensive multistep analysis of two large nationwide representative surveys in France</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e1003584</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33901171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8109815</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Coste J, Valderas JM, Carcaillon-Bentata L. Estimating and characterizing the burden of multimorbidity in the community: a comprehensive multistep analysis of two large nationwide representative surveys in France. PLoS Med. 2021;18(4):e1003584.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33901171</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8109815</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valderas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Starfield</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibbald</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salisbury</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining comorbidity: implications for understanding health and health services</article-title><source>Ann Fam Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2713155</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Valderas JM, Starfield B, Sibbald B, Salisbury C, Roland M. Defining comorbidity: implications for understanding health and health services. Ann Fam Med. 2009;7(4):357–63.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597174</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1370/afm.983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2713155</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>