<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ERJ Open Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ERJ Open Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3083</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">erjor</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ERJOR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ERJ Open Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2312-0541</issn><publisher><publisher-name>European Respiratory Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12434486</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12434486.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12434486</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12434486</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40959166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.01387-2024</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">01387-2024</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Pulmonary Vascular Diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>4</subject><subject>7</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long-term in-hospital mortality and chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension after COVID-19-associated pulmonary embolism in France: a nationwide study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tankéré</surname><given-names initials="P">Pierre</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="af3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="af4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lajeune</surname><given-names initials="E">Emilie</given-names></name><xref rid="af5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0134-1248</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariet</surname><given-names initials="AS">Anne-Sophie</given-names></name><xref rid="af5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="af6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><xref rid="af7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottenet</surname><given-names initials="J">Jonathan</given-names></name><xref rid="af5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2830-5642</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Beltramo</surname><given-names initials="G">Guillaume</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af7" ref-type="aff">7</xref><xref rid="af8" ref-type="aff">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Georges</surname><given-names initials="M">Marjolaine</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af7" ref-type="aff">7</xref><xref rid="af9" ref-type="aff">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonniaud</surname><given-names initials="P">Philippe</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af7" ref-type="aff">7</xref><xref rid="af8" ref-type="aff">8</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Favrolt</surname><given-names initials="N">Nicolas</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quantin</surname><given-names initials="C">Catherine</given-names></name><xref rid="af5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="af6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><xref rid="af7" ref-type="aff">7</xref><xref rid="af10" ref-type="aff">10</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label>Institut Universitaire du Poumon, Centre de référence Constitutif des Maladies Pulmonaires Rares (OrphaLung), Centre de Compétence de l'Hypertension Pulmonaire (PulmoTension), Centre Hospitalo-Universitaire Dijon-Bourgogne, Dijon, France</aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label>Center for Sleep Medicine and Respiratory Diseases, Hospices Civils de Lyon, Lyon, France</aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label>HP2 Laboratory, INSERM U1042, Grenoble, France</aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label>CNRS UMR 5292, INSERM U 1028, Université Lyon 1, Lyon, France</aff><aff id="af5"><label>5</label>Biostatistics and Bioinformatics (DIM), University Hospital, Dijon, France</aff><aff id="af6"><label>6</label>INSERM, CIC 1432, Module Épidémiologie Clinique Dijon, France</aff><aff id="af7"><label>7</label>Université Bourgogne Europe, Faculté de Médicine et Pharmacie, Dijon, France</aff><aff id="af8"><label>8</label>Inserm U1231 CTM, HSP-pathies team, Faculty of Medicine and Pharmacy, Dijon, France</aff><aff id="af9"><label>9</label>Centre des Sciences du Goût et de l'Alimentation, INRA, UMR 6265 CNRS 1234, Université Bourgogne Europe, Dijon, France</aff><aff id="af10"><label>10</label>Université Paris-Saclay, UVSQ, Univ. Paris-Sud, Inserm, High-Dimensional Biostatistics for Drug Safety and Genomics, CESP, Villejuif, France</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Philippe Bonniaud (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="philippe.bonniaud@chu-dijon.fr">philippe.bonniaud@chu-dijon.fr</email>)
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">495934</issue-id><elocation-id>01387-2024</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-09-17 09:25:15.000"><day>17</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©The authors 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This version is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence 4.0. For commercial reproduction rights and permissions contact <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:permissions@ersnet.org">permissions@ersnet.org</email></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="01387-2024.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Although long-term effects of coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19) such as dyspnoea are frequent, the mechanisms are often poorly understood. The endothelial effects of COVID-19, such as venous or arterial thrombosis, are also well documented. Thus, the incidence of chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH) following COVID-19 is an issue with many implications, particularly for screening in patients with long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>From the French National Hospital Discharge database (March 2020 to December 2021), we included all adults hospitalised for pulmonary embolism (PE). To study the hospital incidence of CTEPH, we excluded patients with previous pulmonary hypertension diagnoses. Then, in the 2 years following the admission for PE, we compared the hospital incidence of CTEPH between PE patients with COVID-19 (COVID-PE) and without (non-COVID-PE). We also studied in-hospital mortality.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Among the 136 505 patients included, 1.68% were diagnosed with CTEPH in the following 2 years with a significant difference between COVID-PE and non-COVID-PE (0.77% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 1.82%; p&lt;0.0001). The 2-year in-hospital mortality was significantly lower in COVID-PE than in non-COVID-PE (4.82% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 13.34%; p&lt;0.0001). These results were confirmed by multivariate analyses. Among COVID-PE, we found no difference in the hospital incidence of CTEPH between 2020 and 2021, while after the initial discharge, in-hospital mortality was significantly higher in 2020 compared with 2021.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>When investigating chronic dyspnoea in patients hospitalised for COVID-19 associated with PE, the risk of CTEPH should not be considered higher than for other PE. COVID-19 associated with hospitalised PE should not be considered an additional harmful factor if not associated with initial in-hospital mortality.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="short"><title id="title-1">Shareable abstract</title><p><bold>2-year mortality and incident CTEPH associated with pulmonary embolism in a COVID-19 context is less prevalent than for other pulmonary embolisms. The strategy of complementary examinations in long COVID-19 should be determined accordingly.</bold>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://bit.ly/4iwQBvL" ext-link-type="uri">https://bit.ly/4iwQBvL</ext-link></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The global prevalence of pulmonary hypertension (PH) is around 1% and has been consistently rising, probably due to previous underdiagnosis [<xref rid="C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It may be idiopathic, drug-induced or associated with various cardiac and pulmonary causes, with the current classification including five groups. The fourth group covers PH associated with pulmonary artery obstruction, among which chronic-thrombo-embolic-PH (CTEPH) is the main cause [<xref rid="C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Identifying CTEPH is essential as it is the only curable cause of PH [<xref rid="C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>CTEPH prevalence is estimated at 3.8% in the 2-year follow-up after PE occurs and does not increase thereafter [<xref rid="C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Median time from first symptoms to diagnosis of CTEPH is approximately 14 months, a delay that has a negative impact on CTEPH prognosis [<xref rid="C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>COVID-19 infection and its associated vasculopathy have dramatic consequences on both micro- and macro-circulations, arterial and venous alike, which in turn lead to increases in acute thrombosis [<xref rid="C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. It has been reported that COVID-19 induces major endothelial activation with an intense inflammasome response triggering neutrophil extracellular traps and finally platelet activation with subsequent thrombosis [<xref rid="C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>The complex physiopathology of CTEPH results from chronic thrombi and small vessel impairment, which then results in chronic dysfunction of pulmonary circulation [<xref rid="C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Current understanding of CTEPH includes incomplete resolution of PE, fibrotic scarring, microvasculopathy involvement and remodeling of peripheral pulmonary vascular resistance [<xref rid="C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. This fibrotic scarring is thought to be influenced by factors such as inflammation, fibrinogen anomaly or circulating phospholipids [<xref rid="C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>As COVID-19, PH and all CTEPH mechanisms involve vasculopathy, a natural question arises concerning the incidence of PH and CTEPH in PE associated with COVID-19 infections.</p><p>Long-term sequelae of COVID-19 such as dyspnoea are among the most frequent clinical issues but the associated mechanisms are often poorly understood [<xref rid="C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–<xref rid="C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Dyspnoea affects 4.6–46% of COVID-19 patients, depending on the disease severity and the time of follow-up [<xref rid="C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Therefore, long-term dyspnoea investigations are a daily clinical issue and the rationale for screening for complications including CTEPH.</p><p>Previous studies, mainly from small samples or from a national interventional reference centre, indicate inconsistent results with wide variations in CTEPH frequencies after COVID-19 PE (COVID-PE) ranging from 0–23% [<xref rid="C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–<xref rid="C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Therefore, CTEPH consequences of COVID-PE remain uncertain and need to be investigated on larger datasets [<xref rid="C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Our main objective was to assess the impact of COVID-PE on CTEPH diagnosis in a national database. Using the French National Hospital Discharge database, we estimate and compare the 2-year hospital incidence of CTEPH in adult patients admitted with a diagnosis of PE between March 2020 and December 2021, with COVID-19 (COVID-PE) or without (non-COVID-PE). Our secondary objective was to compare in-hospital mortality between the same groups.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>Our retrospective cohort study uses the national hospital database (PMSI), which is designed to include discharge abstracts for all patients hospitalised in public and private hospitals in France including hospitalisations following emergency department admission and day hospitalisations. Diagnoses identified during the hospital stay are coded according to the tenth edition of the International Classification of Diseases (ICD-10), and procedures performed are coded according to the French Common Classification of Medical Procedures (CCAM). Therefore, these hospital data have been used in medical research for many years [<xref rid="C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and their quality has been confirmed in recent studies, particularly in the field of pneumology [<xref rid="C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>We included all adults hospitalised for pulmonary embolism (PE) and discharged alive in France from 1 March 2020 to 31 December 2021. PE was identified by the primary, related or associated diagnoses with ICD-10 codes I26 or O88.2.</p><p>To look for new cases of CTEPH, we excluded patients with primary or secondary PH (ICD-10 codes I27.0 or I27.2) in the 6 years preceding the PE stay.</p><p>Two analyses were conducted based on two different populations.</p><p>In analysis 1, all patients corresponding to the inclusion and exclusion criteria were considered. Analysis 1 represents the maximum number of PH cases in which PE could be involved whatever comorbidities potentially inducing mixed causes of PH. Thus, it provides the maximum estimation of CTEPH number.</p><p>In analysis 2, patients with other comorbidities inducing PH in the 6 years preceding the admission for PE were excluded. These were mainly patients with documented left ventricular failure (ICD-10 code I50.1), sarcoidosis (D86), chronic respiratory failure (J96.1), interstitial lung disease (J84), emphysema (J43.9), portal hypertension (K76.6), systemic disease of connective tissues including systemic scleroderma (M30–M36) and HIV (R75, Z21, B20–B24). An exhaustive list of the codes used here is provided (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.01387-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table S1</ext-link>). We also excluded patients with a right heart catheter (RHC) procedure in the 6 years preceding the PE stay. Therefore, it provides the minimum estimation of CTEPH number.</p><p>Our primary outcome included:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>CTEPH (ICD-10 code I27.2) during the admission for PE associated with an RHC procedure (CCAM codes EQQF001, EQQF003, EQQF006 and EQQH001) in the following year</p></list-item><list-item><p>Any hospitalisation related to CTEPH in the 2 years following the admission for PE.</p></list-item></list>Our secondary outcome was in-hospital mortality in the 2 years following the admission for PE.</p><p>The exposure concerns COVID-19 during the admission for PE with the ICD-10 codes U0710–U0715 (except U0713) used in previous studies [<xref rid="C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. We created two groups: the group with COVID-19 during the PE stay (named COVID-PE) and the group without COVID-19 during the PE stay (non-COVID-PE) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). The other variables considered for each inpatient were: age, sex and obesity. We also retrieved other characteristics identified as CTEPH risk factors in CTEPH literature in the 6 years preceding the admission for PE: previous hospital stay for PE, previous stay with deep venous thrombosis (DVT), cancer (with or without metastasis), inherited coagulopathies, inflammatory conditions, hypothyroidism and hypersplenism.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Study design. Step 1: identification of patients hospitalised with pulmonary embolism (PE) between March 2020 and December 2021, discharged alive and with no comorbidity-inducing pulmonary hypertension (PH) of groups 1, 2, 3 and 5 and no previous PH diagnosis. Step 2: follow-up of hospitalisations in the patients identified at step 1, focused on chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH) diagnosis and/or death.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="01387-2024.01.jpg"/></fig><p>To take into account the initial severity of PE, we created a “severe PE” variable if the pulmonary embolism initial stay codes included either a transfer to an intensive care unit, an acute pulmonary heart disease (PE-APH; ICD-10 code I26.0), shock (ICD-10 code R57) or thrombolysis/thrombectomy therapy (TTT; CCAM codes).</p><p>Statistically, we first described COVID-PE and non-COVID-PE . The we computed the number and frequency of patients diagnosed with CTEPH and 2-year in-hospital mortality for the whole population and depending on COVID-19 exposure. Also, univariate and multivariate analyses adjusted the COVID-19 exposure effect for the covariables described above using Cox as well as Fine and Gray regressions. Qualitative variables were summarised as frequencies (percentages), and quantitative variables were summarised as mean±<sc>sd</sc>. To compare the characteristics between our groups, we used the chi-squared test for qualitative variables and the t-test or Mann–Whitney U-test for quantitative variables.</p><p>We then compared the rate of outcomes between 2020 and 2021 to study the influence of pandemic management recommendations.</p><p>Finally, we performed a sensitivity analysis with restriction of CTEPH cases to the one identified with RHC up to 1 year after CTEPH diagnosis.</p><p>The statistical significance threshold was set at p&lt;0.05. All analyses were performed using SAS (SAS Institute, v.9.4, Cary, NC, USA).</p><p>To verify the consistency of our data on CTEPH selection, we also used our local CTEPH diagnosis register. We compared the number of cases in our local register with the number of CTEPH cases selected from the national hospital database according to the selection criteria described above, restricted to our university hospital.</p><p>The study was conducted according to Declaration of Helsinki principles and approved by the French Data Protection Authority (CNIL): declaration of conformity with reference methodology 05 obtained on 7 August 2018 under no. 2204633 v.0.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>CTEPH and in-hospital mortality in COVID-PE and non-COVID-PE patients without excluding comorbidity-inducing PH (analysis 1)</title><p>The population identified is composed of 136 505 PE patients between March 2020 and December 2021, among whom 18 110 COVID-PE (13.27%) and 118, 395 non-COVID-PE (<xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). In these patients with no previous diagnosis of PH diagnosis (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.01387-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table S2</ext-link>), 49.93% were men, mean age 67.93 (17.0) years and 7.62% were patient with obesity.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TB1" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>CTEPH and mortality after the 1- and 2-year follow-up for patients hospitalised with PE between March 2020 and December 2021 discharged alive.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">PE</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">COVID-PE</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Non-COVID-PE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 1</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=136 505</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=18 110</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=118 395</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTEPH</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 1-year follow-up</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1723 (1.26)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">87 (0.48)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1636 (1.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 2-year follow-up</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2299<sup>#</sup> (1.68)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">140 (0.77)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2159 (1.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mortality</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 1-year follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 589</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 2-year follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 672</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">873</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 799</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 2</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=94 372</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=13 361</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=81 011</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTEPH</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 1-year follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">795</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">759</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 2-year follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1081<sup>¶</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mortality</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 1-year follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7969</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7623</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 2-year follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9926</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">480</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9446</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(11.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Analysis 1: patients with no previous PH diagnosis. Analysis 2: patients with no comorbidity-inducing pulmonary hypertension, no previous PH diagnosis and no previous right heart catheter procedure. Data are presented as n (%). COVID-PE: hospitalised pulmonary embolism associated with COVID-19 infection; CTEPH: chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension; PE: pulmonary embolism. <sup>#</sup>: Among which, 98.6% were identified with hospitalisation related to CTEPH in the 2 years following the admission for PE. <sup>¶</sup>: Among which, 98.3% were identified with hospitalisation related to CTEPH in the 2 years following the admission for PE.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Incidence of CTEPH in the following 2 years is estimated to 1.68% in the whole PE population. We found a significantly lower incidence of CTEPH in COVID-PE compared with non-COVID-PE patients (0.77% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 1.82%; p&lt;0.01; <xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>).</p><p>The study of CTEPH population characteristics showed less prior cancer and hypothyroidism in the context of CTEPH involving COVID-PE <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> non-COVID-PE (<xref rid="TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). The frequency of other characteristics or CTEPH risk factors did not differ with COVID-PE context. Also, multivariate analysis confirmed that COVID-PE is correlated with a lower incidence of CTEPH when adjusted on risk for CTEPH particularly initial PE severity (<xref rid="TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). Sensitivity analysis on CTEPH patients identified with RHC up to 1 year after CTEPH diagnosis (28.9% of patients) provided similar figures (data not shown).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TB2" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>CTEPH population characteristics for patients hospitalised with PE between March 2020 and December 2021 and discharged alive.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">CTEPH</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">COVID-PE CTEPH</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Non-COVID-PE CTEPH</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 1</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=2299</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=140</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=2159</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Population characteristics</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex, male</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1130 (49.15)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">67 (47.86)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1063 (49.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, years</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">70.77±14.87</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">71.61±15.95</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">70.71±14.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI&gt;30 kg·m<sup>−2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTEPH risk factors</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Younger age, 18–50 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe PE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1068</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(46.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(41.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(46.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>In the 6 years preceding the admission of PE</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DVT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coagulopathy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypothyroidism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hyposplenism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cancer without metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">406</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(17.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cancer with metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Inflammatory conditions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 2</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=1081</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=66</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=1015</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Population characteristics</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex, male</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">522 (48.29)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">32 (48.48)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">490 (48.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, years</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">69.85±15.16</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">69.85±17.07</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">69.95±15.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI&gt;30 kg·m<sup>−2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTEPH risk factors</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Younger age, 18–50 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe PE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">501</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">475</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>In the 6 years preceding the admission of PE</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DVT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coagulopathy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypothyroidism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hyposplenism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cancer without metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cancer with metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Inflammatory conditions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Analysis 1: among 136 505 patients with no previous pulmonary hypertension (PH) diagnosis. Analysis 2: among 94 372 patients with no comorbidity-inducing PH, no previous PH diagnosis and no previous right heart catheter procedure. Data are presented as n (%) or mean±<sc>sd</sc>. BMI: body mass index; COVID-PE: hospitalised pulmonary embolism associated with COVID-19 infection; CTEPH: chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension; PE: pulmonary embolism; DVT: deep venous thrombosis; NA: not applicable.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TB3" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Multivariate analyses to estimate the adjusted hazard ratio of COVID-PE on CTEPH (Fine and Gray regression) and mortality (Cox regression) in patients hospitalised with PE between March 2020 and December 2021 and discharged alive.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1<sup>#</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2<sup>¶</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTEPH</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.325 (0.262–0.404)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.325 (0.261–0.404)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399 (0.336–0.474)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.401 (0.337–0.476)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mortality</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.436 (0.401–0.473)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.434 (0.400–0.471)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.479 (0.447–0.513)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.477 (0.445–0.511)</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTEPH</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272 (0.194–0.381)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267 (0.191–0.375)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.374 (0.291–0.481)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369 (0.287–0.475)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mortality</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.424 (0.38–0.473)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.422 (0.378–0.470)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At 2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.451 (0.411–0.495)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449 (0.409–0.492)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Analysis 1 among 136 505 patients with no previous pulmonary hypertension (PH) diagnosis. Analysis 2 among 94 372 patients with no comorbidity-inducing pulmonary hypertension, no previous PH diagnosis and no previous right heart catheter procedure. Data are presented as hazard ratio. COVID-PE: hospitalised pulmonary embolism associated with COVID-19 infection; CTEPH: chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension; PE: pulmonary embolism. <sup>#</sup>: Model 1: adjustment for age, sex, severity of PE, cancer and body mass index. <sup>¶</sup>: Model 2: adjustment for age, sex, severity of PE, cancer, body mass index and history of PE, deep venous thrombosis, inherited coagulopathy, inflammatory conditions, hypothyroidism and hyposplenism.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Mortality analysis after discharge of initial stay shows 16.676 (12.21%) deaths in the 2 years following the admission (from discharge). In-hospital mortality was significantly lower in COVID-PE compared with non-COVID-PE patients (4.82% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 13.34%; p&lt;0.0001; <xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). The 1-year follow-up showed similar results (<xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). Deceased COVID-PE patients were significantly older and had significantly less previously diagnosed cancer than deceased non-COVID-PE patients (<xref rid="TB4" ref-type="table">table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TB4" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Deceased population characteristics for patients hospitalised with PE between March 2020 and December 2021 and discharged alive.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Deceased PE</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Deceased COVID-PE</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Deceased non-COVID-PE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 1</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=16 672</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=873</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=15 799</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Population characteristics</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex, male</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8670 (52)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">449 (51.43)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8221 (52.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7284</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, years</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">72.3±13.32</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">75.15±12.91</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">72.14±13.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI&gt;30 kg·m<sup>−2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">931</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2332</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PE mortality risk factors</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Older age, &gt;70 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9679</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">576</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex, male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8670</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">449</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7284</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cancer<sup>#</sup> without metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4570</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4353</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cancer<sup>#</sup> with metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5469</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5311</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 2</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=9926</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=480</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n=9446</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Population characteristics</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex, male</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4847 (48.83)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">248 (51.67)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4599 (48.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2027</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, years</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">71.23±13.43</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">73.99±12.71</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">71.09±13.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI&gt;30 kg·m<sup>−2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">388</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7174</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PE mortality risk factors</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Older age, &gt;70 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5464</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex, male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4847</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4599</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2027</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cancer<bold><sup>#</sup></bold> without metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2713</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2600</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cancer<bold><sup>#</sup></bold> with metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3623</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3519</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Analysis 1: among 136 505 patients with no previous PH diagnosis. Analysis 2: among 94 372 patients with no comorbidity-inducing PH, no previous PH diagnosis and no previous right heart catheter procedure. Data are presented as n (%) or mean±<sc>sd</sc>. COVID-PE: hospitalised pulmonary embolism associated with COVID-19 infection; CTEPH: chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension; PE: pulmonary embolism. <sup>#</sup>: for the 6 years preceding the admission for PE.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>2020 and 2021 comparison showed that CTEPH frequencies at 2-year follow-up were not significantly different (<xref rid="TB5" ref-type="table">table 5</xref>) in COVID-PE patients (0.71% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 0.86%; p=0.28) or non-COVID-PE patients (1.82% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 1.82%; p=0.98). However, the rate of in-hospital mortality at 2-year follow-up was significantly lower for COVID-PE patients in 2021 than in 2020 (4.46% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 5.34%; p=0.01; <xref rid="TB5" ref-type="table">table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TB5" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 5</label><caption><p>CTEPH and mortality comparison of 2020 and 2021 after 2-year follow-up for patients hospitalised with PE between March 2020 and December 2021 and discharged alive.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">COVID-PE</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Non-COVID-PE</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=7448</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=10 662</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=53 772</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=64 623</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CTEPH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (0.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (0.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">981 (1.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1178 (1.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mortality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">398 (5.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">475 (4.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7230 (13.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8569 (13.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=5334</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=8027</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=36 772</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=44 239</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CTEPH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (0.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (0.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">444 (1.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">571 (1.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mortality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217 (4.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">263 (3.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4343 (11.81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5103 (11.54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Analysis 1: among 136 505 patients with no previous PH diagnosis. Analysis 2: among 94 372 patients with no comorbidity-inducing PH, no previous PH diagnosis and no previous right heart catheter procedure. Data are presented as n (%). COVID-PE: hospitalised pulmonary embolism associated with COVID-19 infection; CTEPH: chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension; PE: pulmonary embolism.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>CTEPH and in-hospital mortality in COVID-PE and non-COVID-PE patients with no comorbidity-inducing PH (analysis 2)</title><p>Analysis 2 designed to capture the CTEPH with no aetiologies possibly leading to a mixed PH show very similar results.</p><p>Global hospital incidence of CTEPH in the following 2 years is estimated to 1.15%, which was significantly lower in COVID-PE compared with non-COVID-PE patients (0.49% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 1.25%; p&lt;0.001; <xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). The 1-year follow-up showed similar results (<xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>).</p><p>There was a lower rate of in-hospital 2-year mortality in COVID-PE than in non-COVID-PE (3.59% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 11.66%; p&lt;0.001; <xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). Patient characteristics also showed differences in previous cancer diagnosis (<xref rid="TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).</p><p>These results for CTEPH and mortality according to COVID status of PE were also consistent to after adjustment for confounding factors (<xref rid="TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>) or restriction to CTEPH patients identified with a RHC (sensitivity analysis, data not shown).</p><p>Comparison between 2020 and 2021 also show lower 2-year-mortality in 2020 than 2021.</p><sec id="s3b1"><title>Consistency of CTEPH selection</title><p>In our independent local CTEPH diagnosis register, we found 20 newly diagnosed CTEPH from March 2020 to December 2023. When we used the selection of CTEPH cases (see Methods section for analysis 1) from the national hospital database restricted to our centre (Dijon University Hospital), we found the same number (29 admissions corresponding to 20 patients with CTEPH).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Leveraging a French nationwide hospital database covering the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020 and 2021 with respective follow-up of 24 months, we showed that:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>1) CTEPH was lower in COVID-PE than in non-COVID-PE patients.</p></list-item><list-item><p>2) In-hospital mortality was lower in COVID-PE than in non-COVID-PE patients.</p></list-item><list-item><p>3) There was no difference in CTEPH hospital incidence between 2020 and 2021 in COVID-PE patients.</p></list-item><list-item><p>4) COVID-PE diagnosed in 2020 was associated with significantly higher in-hospital mortality than COVID-PE diagnosed in 2021.</p></list-item></list>First, this study reveals a paradox of COVID-19 as an endothelial disease with a high post-acute cardiovascular burden but low CTEPH hospital incidence.</p><p>The data presented in analysis 1 (which represents the maximum number of PH cases in which PE could be involved) and analysis 2 (which represents the minimal estimation for CTEPH, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> PH with no other cause than PE history) showed similar results.</p><p>Indeed, our study shows a nationwide frequency of CTEPH at 2 years that is 2.5-times lower compared with non-COVID-PE. The overall hospital incidence of CTEPH is 1.68% at 2-year follow-up which, together with the subgroup incidence of 0.77% in COVID-PE and 1.68% in non-COVID-PE, falls within the wide range 0.1–4% reported at 2 years in the literature [<xref rid="C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Previous data on post-COVID-PE CTEPH incidence indicate inconsistent results with a small study describing 23% of CTEPH (three out of 13 patients) and another study describing no CTEPH in 300 COVID-PE cases [<xref rid="C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. A further cohort suggested an 0.75% incidence rate in a tertiary hospital at 2-year follow-up in a 133-patient cohort, albeit with 18% persistent defects on lung imaging [<xref rid="C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A decrease in UK referrals to CTEPH reference centres has also been described during the first months of the pandemic [<xref rid="C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Analysis from a national reference centre for interventional CTEPH treatment suggests that out of 277 CTEPH referral cases, only four are potentially associated with COVID-PE [<xref rid="C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. A later report does, however, miss CTEPH cases that have not been referred for interventional treatment, does not have the necessary 2-year hindsight and does not consider all hospitalised COVID-PE patients, and therefore cannot provide a CTEPH incidence rate [<xref rid="C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p>This contrasts with the high post-acute cardiovascular burden of COVID-19 disease, which has been described at the 1-year follow-up on a wide national dataset including thromboembolic events [<xref rid="C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>Chronic dyspnoea following PE has also been described and could be responsible for some long COVID cases [<xref rid="C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Our finding indicates, as suggested by R<sc>eddy</sc>
<italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> [<xref rid="C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], that CTEPH as currently defined is not more prevalent than in other PE but does not exclude the possible implication of a “residual clot burden”, which may lead to post-thrombotic sequelae without formal CTEPH [<xref rid="C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>Second, this study highlights low COVID-PE long-term mortality compared with non-COVID-PE. A three-fold increase in COVID-PE mortality was previously shown in a study that included the first hospitalisation. For our analysis we excluded the initial hospital stay PE mortality so as to focus on the long-term effect of COVID-19 PE [<xref rid="C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p>It has been demonstrated that PE is associated with increased long-term mortality, with approximately 40% due to cardiovascular causes ahead of malignancy and sepsis [<xref rid="C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Therefore, given that COVID-19 cardiovascular mortality is high, it would have been expected that COVID-PE could lead to higher mortality than non-COVID-PE [<xref rid="C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>Our results show the opposite and COVID-PE should not be considered as a supplementary pejorative factor compared with non-COVID-PE if not associated with initial mortality. As the main driver of long-term PE mortality is silent malignancy, this might be explained by lower malignancy rates in COVID-PE, which should be investigated with long-term data [<xref rid="C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–<xref rid="C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p><p>Third, there is no significant difference either in COVID-PE hospital incidence or in COVID-PE-induced CTEPH between 2020 and 2021, albeit 2-year in-hospital mortality in COVID-PE is lower in 2021 than in 2020.</p><p>Our results show similar CTEPH outcomes even though 2020 and 2021 were different periods in terms of COVID-19 variants (alpha, delta and omicron), anticoagulation policy (although enhanced quite early in the pandemic), lockdowns and perhaps healthcare systems. This advocates for the absence of long-term CTEPH consequences of these cumulative changes. However, the lower 2-year mortality of COVID-PE in 2021 compared with 2020 indicates the cumulative benefit of anticoagulation policy, variants and healthcare system reorganisations.</p><p>A key strength of this study is that it is the widest dealing with COVID-PE-associated CTEPH. The large scale is essential to detect CTEPH, which is a rare event [<xref rid="C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Therefore, we provide a nationwide report covering all of 2020 and 2021, including different COVID-19 waves. It distinguishes between COVID-PE and non-COVID-PE. Our work is unique for the large number of patients included and the comprehensiveness of the data. The national hospital database is used for the allocation of hospital budgets and encourages high levels of data coherence, accuracy and exhaustiveness.</p><p>Furthermore, the relevance of the CTEPH estimation provided is also ensured by the 2-year follow-up. Indeed, it has been previously described that CTEPH is diagnosed within the 2 years following PE and most often (&gt;80%) within the year[<xref rid="C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. It should be mentioned that our algorithm to identify CTEPH is inspired from previous work on CTEPH using the same database, which could not be strictly applied since we evaluated the hospital CTEPH incidence rather than prevalence and because of changes to the healthcare system during the pandemic [<xref rid="C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Besides, diagnoses of CTEPH in France include day hospitalisations, during which the diagnosis of CTEPH is made. Therefore, we consider that data from the PMSI database are almost complete regarding CTEPH diagnosis estimation.</p><p>Moreover, a national external quality assessment program has been implemented to verify the quality of discharge abstracts in each hospital. Although we only have access to our own independent local register and do not know if other centres have such a local register, we believe it is a useful validation tool as national data rarely benefit from a local validation.</p><p>Finally, this study is the only nationwide scale to include COVID-PE 2-year in-hospital mortality with an emphasis on the long-term consequences, excluding initial PE in-hospital mortality.</p><p>We acknowledge some limitations, as this study covers a period during which the definition of PH evolved [<xref rid="C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This leads to a possible greater number of PH diagnoses with both incident PH and catchup of former misdiagnosed cases [<xref rid="C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. However, this could lead to a greater estimation of incident PH for both COVID-PE and non-COVID-PE, which would therefore avoid a differential bias.</p><p>As for previous CTEPH studies based on PE history, our study also misses PE patients who were not hospitalised and out of hospital mortality. This could lead to a 25% underestimation of CTEPH [<xref rid="C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] but is intrinsic to the methodology used and affects COVID-PE and non-COVID-PE cases equally, which may avoid a differential bias.</p><p>Moreover, our study has the usual limitations of medico-administrative studies, including the absence of clinical variables and the stage of cancer. However, for the latter we were able to include metastatic stage in our analyses. In addition, given the reliance on ICD-10 codes for the selection of patients and the ascertainment of outcomes, there was a potential for misclassification-related or under-detection-related bias, especially for comorbidities. Coding practices may vary among institutions as the people who perform the coding of diagnoses can be clinicians or information system technicians. Nevertheless, the quality of coding is checked in a standardised way by medical information professionals in each hospital to correct diagnoses (internal quality assessment).</p><p>Finally, the COVID-19 pandemic and associated lockdowns created significant difficulties in planned procedures such as right heart catheterisation. Therefore, the data studied might be affected by the catchup phenomenon described in other areas [<xref rid="C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], although our 2 years of hindsight prevent short-term variations in hospital activity.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Using a nationwide PE cohort, our data suggest that incident CTEPH is not more prevalent in the subgroup of hospitalised PE associated with COVID-19 than in other PE. This finding contrasts with intuition over the vascular component in the physiopathology of COVID-19 and its known long-term global burden of cardiovascular complications.</p><p>We also show that hospitalised COVID-PE is associated with less in-hospital mortality at the 2-year follow-up than other (non-COVID) PE, and that the 2-year mortality of PE associated with COVID-19 was even lower in 2021 compared with 2020. This may imply a positive impact of cumulative changes of enhanced anticoagulation policy, COVID-19 variant aggressivity and healthcare system reorganisations.</p><p>Our findings have essential consequences for both the follow-up of COVID-PE and the strategy of complementary examinations in long COVID-19, for which the risk of CTEPH should not be considered higher than for other PE. Therefore, we suggest that usual recommendations using perfusion imaging and echocardiography should apply.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Suzan Rankin (Direction de la Recherche Clinique et de l’Innovation, University Hospital, Dijon, France) for reviewing the English, and Gwenaëlle Periard (Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, University Hospital, Dijon, France) for help with the layout and coordinating the preparation of this Article.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Provenance: Submitted article, peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn><p>Author contributions: All authors were involved in the conception and design of the study. C. Quantin and P. Bonniaud were the coordinators of the study. J. Cottenet, E. Lajeune and C. Quantin were responsible for the data collection. P. Tankéré, J. Cottenet, P. Bonniaud and C. Quantin wrote the first draft. J. Cottenet, E. Lajeune and C. Quantin were in charge of the analysis, accessed and verified the data. All authors were involved in the interpretation, critically reviewed the first draft, and approved the final version. The corresponding author had full access to all of the data and the final responsibility to submit the publication. All authors had access to all the data reported in the study. C. Quantin, E. Lajeune and J. Cottenet had access to the raw data. The corresponding author had full access to all the data in the study and had final responsibility for the decision to submit for publication.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflicts of interest: P. Tankéré reports support for attending meetings from Asdia Medical, Linde and Resmed. A-S. Mariet reports grants from Fondation de France 2023, and participation on a data safety monitoring or advisory board with Inserm SNDS Scientific Committee and Data Reuse Ethics Committee of the Dijon University Hospital. G. Beltramo reports payment or honoraria for lectures, presentations, manuscript writing or educational events from Boehringer Ingelheim; support for attending meetings from Boehringer Ingelheim, Sanofi and Asdia Medical; and receipt of equipment, materials, drugs, medical writing, gifts or other services from AstraZeneca. M. Georges reports payment or honoraria for lectures, presentations, manuscript writing or educational events from GSK, Fischer Paykel, Elivie and Oxylis; and support for attending meetings from Asten. P. Bonniaud reports grants from AstraZenecca; payment or honoraria for lectures, presentations, manuscript writing or educational events from Sanofi, AstraZeneca and GSK; support for attending meetings from AstraZeneca, Novartis, Sanofi, Boehringer, Stallergene and GSK; participation on a data safety monitoring board or advisory board with AstraZeneca, Novartis, Sanofi, GlaxoSmithKline and Boehringer. N. Favrolt reports support for attending meetings from MSD, GSK, AstraZeneca and Chiesi. C. Quantin participation on a data safety monitoring board or advisory board with CSE PAISAGE External Advisory Board of the HealthData@EU Pilot project. The remaining authors have nothing to disclose.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="supplementary" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.01387-2024.Supp1</object-id><p><bold>Please note:</bold> supplementary material is not edited by the Editorial Office, and is uploaded as it has been supplied by the author.</p><p>Supplementary material <fig id="SS1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="01387-2024.SUPPLEMENT.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig>01387-2024.SUPPLEMENT</p></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The PMSI database was made available by the French national agency for the management of hospitalisation data (Agence Technique de l'Information sur l'Hospitalisation (ATIH)). The use of these data by our department was approved by CNIL. We are not permitted to share these data. PMSI data are available from ATIH to researchers who meet the criteria for access (requests for access are evaluated by CNIL).</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="C1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Humbert</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeper</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>2022 ESC/ERS Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of pulmonary hypertension</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>3618</fpage>–<lpage>3731</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehac237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36017548</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McNeil</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dunning</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH)</article-title>. <source>Heart</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1152</fpage>–<lpage>1158</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/hrt.2004.053603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17699182</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1955041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeper</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Madani</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nakanishi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>582</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(14)70089-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24898750</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pengo</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lensing</surname>
<given-names>AWA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prins</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Incidence of chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension after pulmonary embolism</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>350</volume>: <fpage>2257</fpage>–<lpage>2264</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa032274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15163775</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pepke-Zaba</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Delcroix</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH): results from an international prospective registry</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1973</fpage>–<lpage>1981</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.015008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21969018</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klok</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barco</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Konstantinides</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Determinants of diagnostic delay in chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension: results from the European CTEPH Registry</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>1801687</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01687-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30409820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Libby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lüscher</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>COVID-19 is, in the end, an endothelial disease</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>3038</fpage>–<lpage>3044</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehaa623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32882706</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7470753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flaumenhaft</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Enjyoji</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmaier</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Vasculopathy in COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood.2021012250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34986238</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8736280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Birnhuber</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fließer</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gorkiewicz</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Between inflammation and thrombosis: endothelial cells in COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>2100377</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00377-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33958433</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8112008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ip</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Association of COVID-19 with major arterial and venous thrombotic diseases: a population-wide cohort study of 48 million adults in England and Wales</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>892</fpage>–<lpage>906</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.122.060785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36121907</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9484653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tankere</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cottenet</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tubert-Bitter</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Impact of COVID-19 and lockdowns on pulmonary embolism in hospitalized patients in France: a nationwide study</article-title>. <source>Respir Res</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-021-01887-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34801044</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8605779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega-Paz</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Talasaz</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghipour</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>COVID-19-associated pulmonary embolism: review of the pathophysiology, epidemiology, prevention, diagnosis, and treatment</article-title>. <source>Semin Thromb Hemost</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>816</fpage>–<lpage>832</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0042-1757634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36223804</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simonneau</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Torbicki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dorfmüller</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The pathophysiology of chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir Rev</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>160112</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0112-2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28356405</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkens</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Konstantinides</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH): Updated Recommendations from the Cologne Consensus Conference 2018</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>272S</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2018.08.079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30195840</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fortman</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morgenstern</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Short- and long-term mortality risk after acute pulmonary embolism</article-title>. <source>Curr Cardiol Rep</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11886-018-1084-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30311090</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crook</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raza</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nowell</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Long covid-mechanisms, risk factors, and management</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>374</volume>: <fpage>n1648</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n1648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34312178</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Long COVID or post-COVID-19 syndrome: putative pathophysiology, risk factors, and treatments</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis (Lond)</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>754</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23744235.2021.1924397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34024217</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8146298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castanares-Zapatero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chalon</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Pathophysiology and mechanism of long COVID: a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>Ann Med</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>1473</fpage>–<lpage>1487</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07853890.2022.2076901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35594336</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9132392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grewal</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carlsten</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Post-COVID dyspnea: prevalence, predictors, and outcomes in a longitudinal, prospective cohort</article-title>. <source>BMC Pulm Med</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-023-02376-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36907855</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10008721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Caguana-Vélez</surname>
<given-names>OA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khilzi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Piccari</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension after pulmonary embolism in SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source>Respiration</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000536064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38325355</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname>
<given-names>CMM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Visser</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bemelmans</surname>
<given-names>RHH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension and clot resolution after COVID-19-associated pulmonary embolism</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>2300171</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00171-2023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37080574</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10116061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cueto-Robledo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roldan-Valadez</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Graniel-Palafox</surname>
<given-names>L-E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension (CTEPH): a review of another sequel of severe post-covid-19 pneumonia</article-title>. <source>Curr Probl Cardiol</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>101187</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2022.101187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35346727</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8956357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leavy</surname>
<given-names>OC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension is an uncommon complication of COVID-19: UK national surveillance and observational screening cohort studies</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>2301742</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01742-2023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39060016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11358513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mariet</surname>
<given-names>A-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giroud</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Benzenine</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Hospitalizations for stroke in France during the COVID-19 pandemic before, during, and after the national lockdown</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>1362</fpage>–<lpage>1369</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.120.032312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33626900</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Piroth</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cottenet</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mariet</surname>
<given-names>A-S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of the characteristics, morbidity, and mortality of COVID-19 and seasonal influenza: a nationwide, population-based retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30527-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33341155</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7832247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Beltramo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cottenet</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mariet</surname>
<given-names>A-S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic respiratory diseases are predictors of severe outcome in COVID-19 hospitalised patients: a nationwide study</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>2004474</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.04474-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34016619</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8135927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Avot</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lévy-Bachelot</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Identifying chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension through the French national hospital discharge database</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2019</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>e0214649</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0214649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30998690</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6472741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boubriak</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Rising COVID-19 related acute pulmonary emboli but falling national chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension referrals from a large national dataset</article-title>. <source>ERJ Open Res</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>00431-02021</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00431-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8419584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34646880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term cardiovascular outcomes of COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01689-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35132265</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8938267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klok</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tijmensen</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haeck</surname>
<given-names>MLA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Persistent dyspnea complaints at long-term follow-up after an episode of acute pulmonary embolism: results of a questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Eur J Intern Med</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>629</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejim.2008.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19046730</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sista</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klok</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Late outcomes of pulmonary embolism: the post-PE syndrome</article-title>. <source>Thromb Res</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.thromres.2017.06.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28641836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dhawan</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gopalan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Beyond the clot: perfusion imaging of the pulmonary vasculature after COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30407-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33217366</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7833494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hobohm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sagoschen</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barco</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>COVID-19 infection and its impact on case fatality in patients with pulmonary embolism</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>2200619</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00619-2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35981745</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9411730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>ACC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname>
<given-names>ASC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term cardiovascular and noncardiovascular mortality of 1023 patients with confirmed acute pulmonary embolism</article-title>. <source>Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.110.958397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21098781</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eckelt</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hobohm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Merten</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term mortality in patients with pulmonary embolism: results in a single-center registry</article-title>. <source>Res Pract Thromb Haemost</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>100280</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rpth.2023.100280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37601025</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10439384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ebner</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eckelt</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hobohm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Causes of death and predictors of long-term mortality after pulmonary embolism</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>ehac544.1896</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehac544.1896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Madsen</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Strange</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Short- and long-term mortality for patients with and without a cancer diagnosis following pulmonary embolism in Denmark, 2000 to 2020: a nationwide study</article-title>. <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>e030191</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.123.030191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38014671</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10727333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carley</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>An introduction to power and sample size estimation</article-title>. <source>Emerg Med J</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/emj.20.5.453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12954688</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1726174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Held</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeuffer-Jovic</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkens</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Frequency and characterization of CTEPH and CTEPD according to the mPAP threshold&gt;20 mm Hg: retrospective analysis from data of a prospective PE aftercare program</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>210</volume>: <fpage>107177</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2023.107177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36868431</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>