<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int Arch Otorhinolaryngol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int Arch Otorhinolaryngol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2661</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">iaorl</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Archives of Otorhinolaryngology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1809-9777</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1809-4864</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Thieme Medical Publishers</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12133385</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12133385.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12133385</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12133385</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40470173</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0045-1809026</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IAORL-2024-09-1853-OR</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">s00451809026</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><series-title>April</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Symptoms and Otorhinolaryngological Sequalae in Long Covid</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loli</surname><given-names initials="A">Alessandra</given-names></name><xref rid="AF241853-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3429-5412</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names initials="JVC">João Victor Costa</given-names></name><xref rid="AF241853-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6988-572X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>de Azevedo</surname><given-names initials="ES">Eric Schneider</given-names></name><xref rid="AF241853-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0772-1962</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names initials="RHG">Regina Helena Garcia</given-names></name><xref rid="AF241853-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="CO241853-1" ref-type="author-notes"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF241853-1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Ophthalmology, Otorhinolaryngology, and Head and Neck Surgery, Universidade Estadual Paulista Julio de Mesquita Filho, Botucatu Medical School, Unesp, São Paulo, SP, Brazil</institution></aff><aff id="AF241853-2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Surgical Specialties and Anesthesiology, Universidade Estadual paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho, Botucatu Medical School, Unesp, São Paulo, Brazil</institution></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CO241853-1"><bold>Address for correspondence </bold>Regina Helena Garcia Martins, MD, PhD <institution>Department of Ophthalmology, Otorhinolaryngology, and Head and Neck Surgery, Botucatu Medical School, Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho, Distrito de Rubião Junior s/n</institution><addr-line>18618-970, Botucatu, SP</addr-line><country>Brazil</country><email>regina.g.martins@unesp.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">487169</issue-id><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-05 10:25:55.420"><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>
The Author(s). This is an open access article published by Thieme under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, permitting copying and reproduction so long as the original work is given appropriate credit (
<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>
)
</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s).</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10-1055-s-0045-1809026.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>After the pandemic caused by the coronavirus, many patients have presented remaining otorhinolaryngological symptoms, but most of them are unknown to health professionals.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>To characterize otorhinolaryngological symptoms and sequelae in hospitalized patients for Covid-19.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We made a recall to patients hospitalized between April 2020 and April 2022 due to Covid-19. Demographic data, initial and remaining symptoms, days of hospitalization, intubation and/or tracheostomy, and vaccination data were collected.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>845 patients were hospitalized, 441 died, 404 patients were contacted by telephone, but only 109 responded to the questionnaire about initial and remaining otorhinolaryngological symptoms after 1.5 to 2 years of illness, 59 men and 50 women, with an average age of 58.61 years (20 to 94). Two study groups were composed: G 1 (n- 44; with remaining symptoms) and G 2 (n- 65; without remaining symptoms). 81% of patients in G1 and 67% of patients in G2 had been hospitalized for up to 20 days. Intubation occurred in 17 patients (G1–7; G2–10). Seven patients underwent tracheostomy. The most prevalent initial and remaining otorhinolaryngological symptoms, respectively, were dyspnea (68.8%; 14.6%), cough (65.1%; 11.92%), nasal obstruction (47.7%; 5.58%), smell dysfunction (44%; 11%), taste dysfunction (42%; 4.58%). Vaccination was reported by 54 patients (G1–21; G2–34).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Otorhinolaryngological symptoms were common in patients hospitalized for Covid-19, especially dyspnea, cough, nasal obstruction, smell, and taste dysfunction. Although there was a favorable long-term evolution, 40% of patients maintained permanent symptoms, such as smell and taste dysfunction and dizziness, unrelated to the vaccine doses.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>long covid</kwd><kwd>otorhinolaryngological sequelae</kwd><kwd>otorhinolaryngological symptoms</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>
Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) was a viral pandemic that emerged from the city of Wuhan, China, in December 2019 and quickly spread to the rest of the world.
<xref rid="JR241853-1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
The virus is transmitted from person to person through droplets and aerosols, as well as direct contact with the oral, nasal, and ocular mucous membranes.
<xref rid="JR241853-2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
The virus uses the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptor to infect cells and cause tissue damage. The S protein (Spike) present on the surface of the viral capsule recognizes the ACE2 receptor and interacts with it, enabling the virus replication. It penetrates the mucous membranes of the nose, mouth, and eyes and can progress to the trachea, bronchi, and lungs.
<xref rid="JR241853-2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
Otorhinolaryngological symptoms such as cough, fever, expectoration, dyspnea, smell and taste dysfunction, rhinorrhea, and sore throat are common in patients with Covid-19. Among these, loss in the sense of smell (anosmia) (47.8% to 52%) and taste (ageusia) (43%) stand out.
<xref rid="JR241853-3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<xref rid="JR241853-4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<xref rid="JR241853-5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
</p><p>
With increased patient survival and a better understanding of the disease's progress, it was noted that some initial symptoms of the infection caused by COVID-19 persisted, becoming chronic. Covid disease encompasses three phases of signs and symptoms: (I) acute, persisting for up to 4 weeks; (II) subacute, from 4 to 12 weeks; and (III) post-COVID syndrome, lasting more than 12 weeks, known as long COVID. In the acute phase of the disease, symptoms of chemosensory dysfunction such as anosmia and ageusia appear.
<xref rid="JR241853-6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<xref rid="JR241853-7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
Hyposmia may be present without any other systemic symptom, suggesting direct viral damage to the chemosensory system. Olfactory symptoms may begin suddenly or have a mild progression, persisting for days or years.
<xref rid="JR241853-8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<xref rid="JR241853-9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</p><p>
The same pathophysiology of viral neurotropism applies to the impact of coronavirus in the vestibulocochlear system, which is responsible for symptoms such as deafness, vertigo, and tinnitus. In addition, the virus directly invades the cochlear nerve or the membranous labyrinth of the inner ear.
<xref rid="JR241853-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
Viral neurotropism can also compromise the vagus nerve, resulting in sudden or progressive dysphonia, secondary to paresis or paralysis of one or both vocal folds.
<xref rid="JR241853-11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
Oral lesions
<xref rid="JR241853-12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
and dysphagia
<xref rid="JR241853-13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
may also occur.
</p><p>Our study is justified by the many symptoms related to COVID-19 and its different courses, in addition to the relevance of the topic for specialists, as well as the scarcity of substantial studies with long-term follow-up. The objective of this study was to characterize the otorhinolaryngological symptoms of patients admitted to a university hospital due to COVID, evaluate the course of these symptoms, identify possible sequelae, and correlate them with vaccination.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Adult patients who had been admitted to our university hospital due to COVID-19 between April 2020 and April 2022 and who survived the infection were initially identified. The survivors were then contacted by telephone to collect data on age, gender, length of hospital stay, need for intubation and/or tracheostomy, vaccination, and number of doses. The patients were then actively questioned about having had specific otorhinolaryngological symptoms in the initial stages of the disease, as well as about symptoms that persisted to the day of the inquiry (between 1.5 and 2 years after the onset of the disease), namely, dyspnea, cough, nasal obstruction, rhinorrhea, smell and/or taste dysfunction, headache, pain or difficulty in swallowing, changes in salivation (dry mouth or sialorrhea), hoarseness/dysphonia, vertigo, tinnitus, otalgia, deafness, lesions in oral mucosa, sleep apnea, and facial paralysis. Other relevant symptoms reported by patients were also recorded. Based on the responses, two study groups were created: G1 (patients with symptoms remaining until the day of the interview) and G2 (patients with no remaining symptoms, considered completely free of otorhinolaryngological symptoms).</p><p>Exclusion criteria: patients with previous symptoms or history of treatment for otorhinolaryngological conditions before COVID-19, such as recurrent upper airway infections, chronic sinusitis, allergic rhinitis, previous otorhinolaryngological surgeries, history of deafness, chronic otitis, episodes of vertigo and tinnitus, patients diagnosed with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome, patients with previous facial paralysis, long-term dysphonic patients before the Covid infection, patients diagnosed with or undergoing treatment for oncological diseases in the head or neck, users of inhaled illicit drugs, and workers exposed to intense noise.</p><p>
The data were arranged in tables and analyzed descriptively and numerically. For frequency analysis, the chi-square test was applied, considering a significance level of
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
 &lt; 0.05.
</p><p>The project was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee of the School of Medicine of Botucatu, under protocol number: 4899436 (CAAE: 50479421. 3. 0000. 5411).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>During the study period, 845 adult patients were hospitalized due to Covid-19, of which 441 (52.2%) died, telephone contact was made to 404 patients, and 109 patients agreed to participate in the study. Two study groups were created: G1 (n-44; patients with remaining symptoms) and G2 (n-65; patients without remaining symptoms).</p><sec><title>Gender and Age</title><p><xref rid="TB241853-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
shows the distribution of patients about gender and age group. A total of 59 (54.13%) patients were men and 50 (45.88%) were women. The average age was 58.61 years (ranging from 20 years to 94 years). The age group from 21 to 70 years concentrated the largest number of patients, both in G1 (79%) and G2 (73%). There was no statistical difference between the groups about gender or age.
</p><table-wrap id="TB241853-1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Sex and age range of both groups</title></caption><table rules="all"><colgroup align="left" span="4"><col align="left" width="106.15pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.15pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.2pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.2pt" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex and Age range (years)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G1 (44)<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G2 (65)<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P*</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27(61.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (49.24))</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.293</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17(38.64)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (50.76)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 20</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.08)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.654</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 a 50</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (29.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25(38.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4511</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 a 70</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (50.00)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23(35.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O.186</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;70</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9(20.45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15(23.08)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9284</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="FN241853-1"><label>*</label><p>Chi-square test. P no significant (p &gt; 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Hospitalization Days</title><p><xref rid="TB241853-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
presents information regarding the number of days in the hospital for both groups. Many patients in both groups remained hospitalized for less than 10 days. Both groups had similar lengths of stay, with no statistical difference.
</p><table-wrap id="TB241853-2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Days of hospitalization</title></caption><table rules="all"><colgroup align="left" span="4"><col align="left" width="106.15pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.15pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.2pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.2pt" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days of hospitalization</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G1<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G2<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
*
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
value
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 10</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (43.18)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28(43.08)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 a 20</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17(38.63)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16(24.61)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.176</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 a 30</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2(4.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11(16.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.097</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;30</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6(13.64)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10(15.39)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="FN241853-2"><label>*</label><p>Chi-square test. P no significant (p &gt; 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Days of Endotracheal Intubation</title><p>
Endotracheal intubation was necessary in 17 patients (G1–7; G2–10). The minimum intubation time was one day and the maximum was 50 days. Tracheotomy was performed in 7 patients (G1–3; G2–4).
<xref rid="TB241853-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
.
</p><table-wrap id="TB241853-3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Days of intubation</title></caption><table rules="all"><colgroup align="left" span="4"><col align="left" width="106.15pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.15pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.2pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.2pt" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days of intubation</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G1(44)<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G2(65)<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
*
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
value
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 7</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3418</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 a 15</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5363</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 a 30</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;30</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="FN241853-3"><label>*</label><p>Chi-square test. P no significant (p &gt; 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Initial and Remaining Otorhinolaryngological Symptoms</title><p><xref rid="TB241853-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
shows the initial and remaining symptoms reported by the 109 patients. These symptoms decreased drastically over the years, however, some of them persisted in 44 patients (40%; G1). (
<xref rid="TB241853-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
and
<xref rid="FI241853-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
).
</p><table-wrap id="TB241853-4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Characterization of initial and remaining otorhinolaryngological symptoms</title></caption><table rules="all"><colgroup align="left" span="4"><col align="left" width="106.15pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.15pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.2pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="106.2pt" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptoms</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Initial symptoms<break/>N (%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remaining symptoms<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
*
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
value
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75 (68.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (14.68)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cough</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (65.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (11.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nasal obstruction</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (47.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5(4.58)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Olfactory dysfunction</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (44.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (11.01)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Taste dysfunction</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (42.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4.58)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rhinorrhea</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (35.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headage</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (31.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odynophagia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (19.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dysphonia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (16.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (3.67)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0034*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dysphagia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (13.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (2.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0067*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vertigo</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (11.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (7.34)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3585</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Xerostomia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (10.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0076*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tinnitus</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (6.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (2.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3314</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stomatitis</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6138</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sleep apnea</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (3.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6789</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sialorrhea</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2449</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Otalgia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypoacusis</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (2.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="FN241853-4"><label>*</label><p>Chi-square test. P significant &lt;0.05 (*).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="FI241853-1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>
Initial and remaining otorhinolaryngological symptoms.
</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10-1055-s-0045-1809026-i241853or-1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Vaccination</title><p><xref rid="TB241853-5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>
depicts the number of patients vaccinated, as well as the number of doses. A total of 54 patients (49.5%) had taken the vaccine before becoming ill (G1–20; G2–34), 27% of patients from G1 and 32% from G2 had received 2 or 3 doses. There was no relationship between the number of doses and the presence of otorhinolaryngological sequelae.
</p><table-wrap id="TB241853-5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Vaccine doses in both groups</title></caption><table rules="all"><colgroup align="left" span="4"><col align="left" width="95.4pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="85.05pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="104.6pt" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1.05in" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dose</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G1 (n-44)<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G2 (n-65)<break/>N(%)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
*
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
value
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (13.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12(18.45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.882</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8(18.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11(16.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4(9.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10(15.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.632</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2(4.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1(1.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.645</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>20(45.5)</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>34(52.3)</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="FN241853-5"><label>*</label><p>Chi-square test. P no significant (p &gt; 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>
In this study, most patients were between 21 and 70 years old (67%). Patients over 70 represented only 20% of the cases. There was a slight predilection for males (54% versus 46%), without statistical significance. Intubation was required in 17 patients (15.5%). Vaccination was reported by 54 patients (49.5%), of which 33 (30%) had received two or three doses. The effectiveness of vaccination has been questioned, and some publications highlight possible side effects of the vaccine such as tinnitus, vestibular changes, sensorineural hearing loss, facial paralysis, and epistaxis.
<xref rid="JR241853-14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
However, it should be noted that these correlations have not been confirmed until now.
</p><p>
Otorhinolaryngological symptoms in patients with Covid-19 are frequent, as also demonstrated by Qiu et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
in a systematic review that included 16,478 patients. The authors highlighted, among the main symptoms, olfactory dysfunction (47%), sneezing (27%), nasal congestion (19%), expectoration (22%), sore throat (16%), rhinorrhea (14%), dyspnea (12%), and dizziness. (9%). These symptoms corroborate our results, in which dyspnea and cough stood out (68.8% and 65.1%) respectively, followed by nasal obstruction (47.7%), anosmia (44%), and ageusia (42.2%). Salepci et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
interviewed 223 patients diagnosed with Covid-19 and the main otorhinolaryngological symptoms were anosmia (34.5%), and ageusia (31.8%), percentages slightly lower than those found in our study.
</p><p>
With viral attenuation and more effective vaccination, the survival rate of patients infected with the coronavirus has increased, enabling a better understanding of the course of the symptoms and sequelae of “post-covid-19 syndrome,” even though much about it is unknown until today. Xiong et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
described respiratory, cardiovascular, psychosocial sequelae, and alopecia three months after hospital discharge of patients with Covid-19. In our study, 44 patients (40%) persisted with at least one symptom after 1.5 to 2 years, mainly dyspnea (14.6%), cough (11.92%), nasal obstruction (4.58%), anosmia (11%) and ageusia (4.6%), and vertigo (7.3%).
</p><p>
ENT symptoms tend to improve considerably after the acute phase of the disease, as evidenced in our results, however, abnormal smell, taste, balance, and dysphonia, are more resistant symptoms. Boscolo-Rizzo et al.,
<xref rid="JR241853-18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
demonstrated the stages of recovery of smell and taste disorders in 168 patients with post-covid-19 symptoms such as symptoms present in the acute phase (n-119), after four weeks (n-64), after eight weeks (n-29), after six months (n-27) and after two years (n-14). According to these authors, in general, 28% of patients presented some remaining symptoms of Covid-19 after two years, a rate lower than that found by us (40%) in hospitalized patients.
</p><p>
The pathophysiology of olfactory disorders in Covid-19 includes direct toxic action of SARS-COV-2 on epithelial cells, via angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), expressed in the nasal ciliated epithelium and olfactory bulb; destruction of the olfactory nerve due to the neurotropic action of the virus; viral ascension through the cribriform plate of the olfactory bulb to the structures of the central nervous system, resulting in chronic dysfunction. Leukocytes and inflammatory cytokines were identified in the olfactory epithelium, responsible for the acute symptoms. The destruction of the structures of the olfactory bulb would be responsible for the typical symptoms, however, the exact course of olfactory disorders is still uncertain.
<xref rid="JR241853-19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<xref rid="JR241853-20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
<xref rid="JR241853-21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
</p><p>
In an interesting review that evaluated the effects of smell and taste after Covid, Liao et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
found an incidence of 33% to 85% for smell disorders and 64% to 88% for taste disorders. This large variation in percentages is due to the heterogeneity of data collection (questionnaires, objective tests, or intensity scales), as well as the profile of patients (outpatient or hospitalized). Studies with follow-up between three and 12 months indicated variable rates of symptom persistence, between 2.8% and 58%. Studies with longer follow-ups, over 12 months, recorded lower rates of symptoms, ranging from 3.1% to 25% for smell disorders and from 1.75% to 21.3%. % for taste disorders. In our study, our rates of persistence for both symptoms were 11% and 4.6%, respectively.
</p><p>
Otoneurological symptoms are also common in patients with Covid-19, such as conductive or sensorineural deafness, tinnitus, and vertigo, due to involvement of the inner ear. Viral neurotropism has been considered responsible for the symptoms of deafness and vertigo. The hematogenous route is also suggested, with hemoglobin as the virus vector, affecting all tissues, as it requires receptors for the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), which is found in abundance in the brain, medulla oblongata, temporal lobe, where the auditory centers must be affected by inflammatory mediators. Furthermore, deoxygenation of erythrocytes may occur, culminating in hypoxia in the auditory centers. Another possibility would be ischemia of these centers, secondary to episodes of vasculitis and direct inflammatory effect on the brain caused by the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, compromising the auditory centers and the inner ear through neuroinflammation, resulting in thrombotic and ischemic events and, consequently, local hypoxia.
<xref rid="JR241853-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<xref rid="JR241853-22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
</p><p>
Cochleovestibular symptoms are reported by patients in the acute, subacute, and chronic phases of the disease. Aydin et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
demonstrated higher audiometric thresholds in post-Covid-19 patients than in control patients, especially for high frequencies, as well as changes in vestibular exams, indicating possible vestibular sequelae. A systematic review on neurological manifestations in Covid patients included 24 studies and highlighted the prevalence of dizziness (7%), changes in smell (19%), changes in taste (21%), hearing deficits (3%), and tinnitus (5%).
<xref rid="JR241853-23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
In our study, except for hearing deficit, all other symptoms were more relevant in the acute phase of the disease than those presented by these authors. Tan et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
conducted a prospective study on cochleovestibular symptoms in patients who had Covid-19 for at least 30 days (26 patients with Covid-19 and 27 controls). An increase in audiometric thresholds was found in the covid group at frequencies of 4,000 Hz and 8,000 Hz, without changes in otoacoustic emissions. Significant differences were seen in vestibular tests between the groups, confirming the impairment of the cochleovestibular system by Covid-19. De Luca et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
reported a prevalence of vertigo in post-Covid syndrome of 7.2%, a percentage close to that of our study.
</p><p>
Few studies presented results from post-Covid evaluations with follow-up longer than one year. According to the global analysis of the cumulative prevalence of “long Covid,” the rate of sequelae varies between 9% and 63%, much higher than that of any other virus. The extensive prevalence range depends on the duration of follow-up, hospitalization, comorbidities, smoking status, and patient age. O'Mahoney et al.,
<xref rid="JR241853-26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
in a recent systematic review, identified sequelae in 52.6% of hospitalized patients, 34.4% of non-hospitalized patients, and 38% in both conditions (hospitalized and nom-hospitalized). Fatigue (28.4%; 34%; 25.2%), dyspnea (23.4%; 20.4%; 18.2%), and cough (10.2%; 6.5%; 10.6%) were the main remaining symptoms in the three groups, respectively. The most frequent otorhinolaryngological sequelae were anosmia (6.3%; 12.6%; 14.9%), ageusia (4.6%; 6.7%; 14.1), and nasal obstruction (4.1; 5 0.28; 9.9). Our rates of remaining olfactory symptoms were higher (11%), but for taste disorders, they were similar (4.6%). Some authors have studied the incidence of smell or taste disturbance in covid covariants (Delta, Alfa e Omicron) post-pandemic wave and observed a considerable decrease in these symptoms.
<xref rid="JR241853-27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
</p><p>
Arjun et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
contacted post-Covid patients (hospitalized or outpatient) by telephone at 44 and 223 days of follow-up. Persistence of symptoms was reported by 29.2% and 9.4% of patients, respectively, rates lower than ours (40%). The sequelae were more frequent in hospitalized patients in both periods. Olfactory symptoms were present at 4.2% and 0%, and abnormal sense of taste in 2.8% and 2.9%. Bianco et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
also highlight that olfactory disorders are important symptoms in the acute and chronic phases.
</p><p>
Dysphonia in patients with Covid-19 is another symptom widely described. Some authors such as Lechien et al.
<xref rid="JR241853-30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
(26.8%) and Cantarella et al. (43.7%)
<xref rid="JR241853-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
highlight a high prevalence. In our study, dysphonia was more prevalent in the acute phase of the disease (16%) than in the prolonged phase (1.8%), indicating a good recovery rate.
</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations of the Study</title><p>The limitations of this study were: the lack of otorhinolaryngological exams which would enable diagnostic confirmation of possible structural changes in the airway; difficulties in collecting data related to comorbidities, both in telephone contacts and when consulting medical records, making it difficult to establish a correlation between these variables and sequelae.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Otorhinolaryngological symptoms were common in patients hospitalized for Covid-19, notably dyspnea, cough, nasal obstruction, and olfactory and taste disorders. Although with a favorable long-term course, 40% of patients remained symptomatic, notably with abnormal sense of smell, taste, and balance. The rates of sequelae were not related to the number of vaccine doses.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>To São Paulo State Research Support Foundation (Fapesp) for the scholarship of academics.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="d35e103"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest</bold> None.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="JR241853-1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Clinical Characteristics of Coronavirus Disease 2019 in China. N Engl J Med</article-title><source>J Emerg Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jemermed.2020.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7092819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamadian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiti</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoghli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biglari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsamanesh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esmaeilzadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19: Virology, biology and novel laboratory diagnosis</article-title><source>J Gene Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>23</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>e3303</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jgm.3303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33305456</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7883242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krajewska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krajewski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zub</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zatoński</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 in otolaryngologist practice: a review of current knowledge</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2020</year><volume>277</volume><issue>07</issue><fpage>1885</fpage><lpage>1897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-020-05968-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32306118</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7166003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elibol</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Otolaryngological symptoms in COVID-19</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2021</year><volume>278</volume><issue>04</issue><fpage>1233</fpage><lpage>1236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-020-06319-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32875391</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7461752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Özçelik Korkmaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eğilmez</surname><given-names>O K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Özçelik</surname><given-names>M A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Güven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Otolaryngological manifestations of hospitalised patients with confirmed COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2021</year><volume>278</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>1675</fpage><lpage>1685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-020-06396-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33011957</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7532931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pottinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anosmia and loss of smell in the era of covid-19</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2020</year><volume>370</volume><fpage>m2808</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m2808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32694187</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitcroft</surname><given-names>K L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hummel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Olfactory Dysfunction in COVID-19: Diagnosis and Management</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><volume>323</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>2512</fpage><lpage>2514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.8391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32432682</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lechien</surname><given-names>J R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiesa-Estomba</surname><given-names>C M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Siati</surname><given-names>D R</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Olfactory and gustatory dysfunctions as a clinical presentation of mild-to-moderate forms of the coronavirus disease (COVID-19): a multicenter European study</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2020</year><volume>277</volume><issue>08</issue><fpage>2251</fpage><lpage>2261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-020-05965-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32253535</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7134551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meduri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Symptomatology in head and neck district in coronavirus disease (COVID-19): A possible neuroinvasive action of SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Am J Otolaryngol</source><year>2020</year><volume>41</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>102612</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjoto.2020.102612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32574896</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7301823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>K M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Favre</surname><given-names>N M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>C C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>M M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic Review of Sensorineural Hearing Loss Associated With COVID-19 Infection</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e19757</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.19757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34938632</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8684886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Ani</surname><given-names>R M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>R A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of dysphonia due to COVID-19 at Salahaddin General Hospital, Tikrit City, Iraq</article-title><source>Am J Otolaryngol</source><year>2021</year><volume>42</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>103157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjoto.2021.103157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34246025</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8240449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martín Carreras-Presas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amaro Sánchez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>López-Sánchez</surname><given-names>A F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jané-Salas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somacarrera Pérez</surname><given-names>M L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral vesiculobullous lesions associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Oral Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume>(Suppl 3, Suppl 3)<fpage>710</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/odi.13382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32369674</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7267423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Regan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walshe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Dysphagia, Dysphonia, and Dysarthria Outcomes Among Adults Hospitalized With COVID-19 Across Ireland</article-title><source>Laryngoscope</source><year>2022</year><volume>132</volume><issue>06</issue><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.29900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34622966</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8662217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colizza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ralli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turchetta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Vincentiis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Otolaryngology adverse events following COVID-19 vaccines</article-title><source>Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>26</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4113</fpage><lpage>4116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26355/eurrev_202206_28981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35731083</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Prevalence and prognosis of otorhinolaryngological symptoms in patients with COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2022</year><volume>279</volume><issue>01</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-021-06900-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34032909</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8147593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salepci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozcan</surname><given-names>S N</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Symptomatology of COVID-19 from the otorhinolaryngology perspective: a survey of 223 SARS-CoV-2 RNA-positive patients</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2021</year><volume>278</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-020-06284-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32794002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7426010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Clinical sequelae of COVID-19 survivors in Wuhan, China: a single-centre longitudinal study</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><issue>01</issue><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.09.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32979574</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7510771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boscolo-Rizzo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabbris</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polesel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Two-Year Prevalence and Recovery Rate of Altered Sense of Smell or Taste in Patients With Mildly Symptomatic COVID-19</article-title><source>JAMA Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2022</year><volume>148</volume><issue>09</issue><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoto.2022.1983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35925596</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9353700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>B KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Prognosis and persistence of smell and taste dysfunction in patients with covid-19: meta-analysis with parametric cure modelling of recovery curves</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2022</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>e069503</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj-2021-069503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35896188</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9326326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnakumar</surname><given-names>H N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Momtaz</surname><given-names>D A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Pathogenesis and progression of anosmia and dysgeusia during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2023</year><volume>280</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-022-07689-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36209486</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9548302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term Consequences of COVID-19: Chemosensory Disorders</article-title><source>Curr Allergy Asthma Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11882-022-01062-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36574210</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9792936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koca</surname><given-names>C F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Celik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oguzturk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of the severity of COVID-19 on the sequelae of the audiovestibular system</article-title><source>Ear Nose Throat J</source><year>2023</year><volume>102</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01455613221083826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35331030</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8960747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolappa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Frequency of Neurologic Manifestations in COVID-19: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2021</year><volume>97</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>e2269</fpage><lpage>e2281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000012930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34635561</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8665434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cengiz</surname><given-names>D U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demir</surname><given-names>İ</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Effects of Covid-19 on the audio-vestibular system</article-title><source>Am J Otolaryngol</source><year>2022</year><volume>43</volume><issue>01</issue><fpage>103173</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjoto.2021.103173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34392022</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8352672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Luca</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Stadio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colacurcio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Long COVID, audiovestibular symptoms and persistent chemosensory dysfunction: a systematic review of the current evidence</article-title><source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source><year>2022</year><volume>42</volume><supplement>01</supplement><fpage>S87</fpage><lpage>S93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14639/0392-100X-suppl.1-42-2022-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35763279</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9137376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Mahoney</surname><given-names>L L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Routen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Corrigendum to “The prevalence and long-term health effects of long Covid among hospitalised and non-hospitalised populations: a systematic review and meta-analysis”</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2023</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>101959</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37096187</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10115131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>N3C Consortium </collab><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>E R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>D H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>French</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costanzo</surname><given-names>R M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19-Associated Chemosensory Loss Continues to Decline</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2023</year><volume>169</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>1386</fpage><lpage>1389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ohn.384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37232470</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10615675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arjun</surname><given-names>M C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Characteristics and predictors of Long COVID among diagnosed cases of COVID-19</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e0278825</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0278825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36538532</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9767341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>M R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ralli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Vincentiis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allegra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of olfactory dysfunction persistence after COVID-19: a prospective study</article-title><source>Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>26</volume><issue>03</issue><fpage>1042</fpage><lpage>1048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26355/eurrev_202202_28014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35179771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lechien</surname><given-names>J R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiesa-Estomba</surname><given-names>C M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabaraux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Features of Mild-to-Moderate COVID-19 Patients With Dysphonia</article-title><source>J Voice</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvoice.2020.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32600873</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7269945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR241853-31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantarella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldè</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Consonni</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Prevalence of dysphonia in non hospitalized patients with COVID-19 in Lombardy, the Italian epicenter of the pandemic</article-title><source>J Voice</source><year>2023</year><volume>37</volume><issue>04</issue><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvoice.2021.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33766419</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7955941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>