<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">IJID Reg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">IJID Reg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4239</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijregi</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>IJID Regions</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2772-7076</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12538035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12538035.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12538035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12538035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41127487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijregi.2025.100761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2772-7076(25)00196-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100761</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Real-world evidence on long COVID-19 in Greece: A multicenter, cross-sectional study (LONCOV2)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulakou</surname><given-names initials="G">Garyphallia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michailidis</surname><given-names initials="V">Vasileios</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gogali</surname><given-names initials="A">Athina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutlas</surname><given-names initials="S">Stylianos</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavousanaki</surname><given-names initials="M">Melina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0006"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giouleka</surname><given-names initials="P">Paschalina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0007"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanidis</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexandros</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0008"><name name-style="western"><surname>Styliara</surname><given-names initials="P">Panagiota</given-names></name><email>pstyliara@menarini.gr</email><xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">8</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0009"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiropoulos</surname><given-names initials="P">Paschalis</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0009" ref-type="aff">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tzouvelekis</surname><given-names initials="A">Argyris</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">10</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>3rd Department of Internal Medicine and Laboratory, School of Medicine, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, Athens General Hospital for Chest Diseases “Sotiria”, Athens, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Pulmonology Department, St. Luke’s Hospital, Thessaloniki, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Respiratory Medicine Department, School of Medicine, University of Ioannina, University Hospital of Ioannina, Ioannina, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Thessaly, General University Hospital of Larissa, Larissa, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label>1st Department of Internal Medicine, General Hospital of Heraklion "Venizeleio-Pananeio", Heraklion, Crete, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label>Pulmonary Department, Bioclinic Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label>1st Cardiology Department, General Hospital of Nikaia Piraeus “Agios Panteleimon”, Piraeus, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label>Menarini Hellas S.A., Athens, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0009"><label>9</label>Department of Pulmonology, Medical School, Democritus University of Thrace, University General Hospital of Alexandroupolis, Alexandroupolis, Greece</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>10</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, University Hospital of Patras, Patras, Greece</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. <email>pstyliara@menarini.gr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">497283</issue-id><elocation-id>100761</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-23 09:25:15.713"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0001"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="celist0001"><list-item id="celistitem0001"><label>•</label><p id="para0001">Real-world data on long COVID were collected from over 1000 adults in Greece.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0002"><label>•</label><p id="para0002">Fatigue/malaise (69.9%) was the most common long-term COVID-19 manifestation.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0003"><label>•</label><p id="para0003">Respiratory, nervous, and musculoskeletal symptoms, and daily living issues were common.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0004"><label>•</label><p id="para0004">Most patients (74.4%) had been vaccinated prior to infection.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0005"><label>•</label><p id="para0005">Vaccination was protective against nervous and musculoskeletal symptoms.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0006"><label>•</label><p id="para0006">Multisystem involvement supports the need for multidisciplinary long COVID care.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0002"><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>This study aimed to provide real-world data on the clinical presentation and management of long COVID in Greece.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This non-interventional, nationwide, multicenter, cross-sectional study included adults with a history of symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection who presented with suspected long-term COVID-19 manifestations ≥4 weeks after acute infection.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Among 1011 patients (mean ± SD age: 55.95 ± 15.74 years; 56.18% female; 5.04% hospitalized) enrolled between December 2022 and May 2023, the most affected Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA) System Organ Class (SOC) was General disorders and administration site conditions (75.67%), with fatigue/malaise as the predominant symptom (69.93%). This was followed by Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders (60.34%), with cough (50.64%) and dyspnea (24.83%) as leading symptoms. Social circumstances, specifically impairments in daily living activities (44.21%), Nervous system disorders (40.26%), mainly headache (23.24%), and Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders (27.70%), mainly myalgia (24.63%), were also prominent. The majority (74.38%) had been vaccinated prior to infection, with vaccination shown to be protective against nervous and musculoskeletal symptoms. Females were more prone to systemic, psychiatric, nervous, and musculoskeletal symptoms and impairments in daily activities, but less prone to respiratory symptoms.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Multisystem long-term COVID-19 complications were observed, underscoring the importance of multidisciplinary management of this complex, multifaceted condition.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Long-term COVID-19 complications</kwd><kwd>Multisystem involvement</kwd><kwd>Multidisciplinary management</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0001"><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0011">SARS-CoV-2, responsible for COVID-19, has spread globally as a pandemic, with over 770 million confirmed cases and more than seven million deaths reported worldwide as of November 2024 [<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The clinical presentation of COVID-19 varies widely, ranging from asymptomatic cases to severe, life-threatening illness [<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p id="para0012">While most individuals recover fully within two to four weeks, a growing body of evidence indicates that acute SARS-CoV-2 infection can result in long-term sequelae involving both the pulmonary system and a broad array of extrapulmonary organ systems, collectively termed post-COVID conditions (also known as long COVID) [<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Recent meta-analyses estimate that the global prevalence of long COVID among individuals with a history of COVID-19 is as high as 45%, though substantial variability exists across studies [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>].</p><p id="para0013">Defining the clinical presentation of long COVID has proven challenging due to its diverse and fluctuating manifestations. Consequently, varying definitions, differing mainly in the timing of post-infection symptom onset, have been proposed by major health organizations, including the United States (US) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), the World Health Organization (WHO) and the United Kingdom (UK) National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>]. The most common clinical manifestations of long COVID encompass systemic symptoms such as fatigue and malaise; neuropsychiatric symptoms, including brain fog, sleep disorders, memory impairment, anxiety, and depression; respiratory symptoms such as dyspnea and cough; cardiac symptoms, including chest pain and palpitations; and musculoskeletal symptoms, primarily myalgia and arthralgia. These symptoms can range from mild to severe, often require comprehensive care, and in some cases may even result in disability [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>].</p><p id="para0014">Although the pathophysiological mechanisms underlying long COVID remain poorly understood [<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], certain risk factors have been identified<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> These include female gender, older age, higher body mass index (BMI), smoking, and pre-existing conditions such as anxiety, depression, asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), diabetes, ischemic heart disease, and immunosuppression. A history of hospitalization or intensive care unit (ICU) admission has also been associated with an increased risk of developing long COVID [<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Conversely, vaccination has demonstrated a protective effect [<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p id="para0015">Five years since the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic, long COVID remains a major public health concern and continues to hold significant scientific interest, underscoring the urgent need to deepen our understanding of its underlying mechanisms, clinical presentation, and management. The persistent challenge of diagnosing this condition, characterized by its diverse and often multisystemic manifestations, further highlights the importance of addressing these gaps to guide comprehensive care strategies and improve patient outcomes. Within this context, the present study aimed to gather real-world data on the profile of this often “vague” health condition and to examine how it is perceived and managed in routine clinical practice in Greece.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec0003"><title>Study design</title><p id="para0016"><bold>LONCOV2</bold> (“<bold>L</bold>ong-term outcomes of C<bold>O</bold>VID-19 in Greece. A <bold>N</bold>on-interventional, multicenter, <bold>C</bold>ross-sectional epidemiological study to provide real-w<bold>O</bold>rld evidence on long-sequelae of SARS-Co<bold>V</bold>-<bold>2</bold> infection”) was a non-interventional, nationwide, multicenter, cross-sectional study involving Greek adults with a history of laboratory-confirmed symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection, who had recovered from the acute phase and presented with suspected long-term COVID-19 manifestations. The study was conducted between December 16, 2022, and May 4, 2023, by 120 investigators across Greece, comprising 108 private-sector primary healthcare physicians and 12 hospital-based physicians (internists, general practitioners, cardiologists, and pulmonologists), based either in the Athens Metropolitan area (40.6%) or in other prefectures of the country (59.4%).</p></sec><sec id="sec0004"><title>Study population</title><p id="para0017">Eligible participants were adults (≥18 years, male or female) with an established diagnosis of acute symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection (confirmed by antigen test and/or reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction [RT-PCR]) within the past six months, who had recovered from the acute phase of the infection and presented with suspected long-term COVID-19 manifestations, These were defined as new, persistent, worsening, or recurrent symptoms or signs present at least four weeks after the acute infection onset [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], as determined by their physician during a routine clinical visit unrelated to COVID-19 (a “random” visit) or during an initial or follow-up clinical assessment of their post-acute infection status, initiated either by the physician or at the patient’s request. Exclusion criteria included a positive SARS-CoV-2 laboratory test (antigen and/or RT-PCR) at the time of the study visit or participation in an interventional study.</p></sec><sec id="sec0005"><title>Data collection</title><p id="para0018">The study collected data during a single study visit (enrolment visit), coinciding with a routine clinical visit as defined above. Data were collected through routine clinical and laboratory assessments, medical chart abstraction, and patient self-report using an electronic data capture (EDC) system. No additional diagnostic, monitoring, or therapeutic procedures beyond those of routine clinical practice were performed. Data collected included patient demographics, acute SARS-CoV-2 infection history (e.g., clinical manifestations, severity, vaccination status, hospitalization status, reinfection status), comorbidities, medications, and suspected long-term COVID-19 manifestations (new, persistent, recurrent, or worsening). A predefined list of suspected long-term COVID-19 manifestations, based on prior evidence of post-acute sequelae, was utilized. Information on any recommended follow-up diagnostic and therapeutic plans for suspected long COVID after the study visit was also recorded.</p></sec><sec id="sec0006"><title>Study outcomes</title><p id="para0019">The primary outcome of the study was the prevalence of suspected long-term COVID-19 manifestations (symptoms and/or signs), categorized using the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA) System Organ Class (SOC) and Preferred Term (PT) or Lowest Level Term (LLT). Secondary outcomes included potential associations between such manifestations and acute SARS-CoV-2 infection or patient characteristics, as well as recommended diagnostic and/or therapeutic strategies.</p></sec><sec id="sec0007"><title>Statistical methods</title><p id="para0020">Statistical analyses were conducted using R version 4.3.1 (R Core Team, Austria). All analyses were based on the full analysis set, comprising all patients who had provided informed consent. Continuous variables are summarized as mean, standard deviation (SD), median, and range, while categorical variables are presented as absolute and relative frequencies with 95% confidence intervals (CIs). For the primary outcome, relative frequencies are presented with Wilson score 95% CIs, using continuity correction. Logistic regression was used to identify associations for the secondary outcomes, with the presence of each long-term COVID-19 manifestation (MedDRA SOC) as the dependent variable (provided the prevalence exceeded 15%), and acute infection characteristics (severity [mild/moderate vs severe/critical], vaccination status [unvaccinated vs vaccinated], hospitalization status [outpatient vs inpatient], patient characteristics (age, gender [male vs female], smoking status [current vs ex-smoker/current vs non-smoker], BMI [normal vs overweight/normal vs obese]), and the presence of comorbidities (COPD, heart failure, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, coronary artery disease, stroke, asthma, autoimmune disease, and cancer) included as fixed factors. The magnitude of associations was expressed as odds ratios (ORs) with 95% CIs and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0008"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec0009"><title>Patient demographics and clinical characteristics</title><p id="para0021">A total of 1011 patients were enrolled in this study, with a mean ± SD age of 55.95 ± 15.74 years, and the majority were female (56.18%) (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The mean BMI was 27.26 ± 4.89 kg/m², with most patients classified as either overweight or obese (65.18%). Over half of the patients were non-smokers (55.19%), while 22.95% were ex-smokers and 21.86% were actively smoking. At the time of the study visit, 51.53% had at least one comorbidity, with hypertension (29.18%) and dyslipidemia (24.63%) being the most common.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographics and comorbidity profile of patients with suspected long COVID, full analysis set.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1011</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age (years),</bold> mean ± SD</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.95 ± 15.74</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender,</bold> n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">443 (43.82)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">568 (56.18)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>),</bold><xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref> mean ± SD</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.26 ± 4.89</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Normal</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">352 (34.82%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Overweight</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">414 (40.95%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Obese</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">245 (24.23%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Smoking status,</bold> n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Non-smoker</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">558 (55.19%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Ex-smoker</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232 (22.95%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Current smoker</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">221 (21.86%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Comorbidities,</bold> n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hypertension</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">295 (29.18%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dyslipidemia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">249 (24.63%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Diabetes mellitus</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102 (10.09%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Asthma</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (9.50%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 (7.12%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Coronary artery disease</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (4.35%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Heart failure</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (4.35%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Autoimmune disease</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (3.36%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Cancer</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (3.36%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Neuromusculoskeletal disease</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (1.38%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Renal dysfunction/impairment</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (1.38%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Peripheral artery disease</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.99%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Stroke</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.89%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (7.32%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb1fn1"><label>a</label><p id="notep0001">BMI categories: Normal: BMI &lt;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; Overweight: BMI = 25–&lt;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; Obese: BMI ≥30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p><p id="notep0002">BMI, body mass index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>Acute SARS-CoV-2 infection history</title><p id="para0022">The median time since the onset of acute SARS-CoV-2 infection was 2.7 months (range: 0.9-5.9). For most patients (83.28%), this was their first infection, while 16.72% had a history of at least one prior infection (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The vast majority (94.96%) were managed on an outpatient basis, indicating mild infection, with only 5.04% requiring hospitalization. A very small proportion (0.49%) were admitted to the ICU, with a median ICU stay of 12 days (range: 7-15).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Acute SARS-CoV-2 infection history, full analysis set.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1011</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Hospitalization status</bold>, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Outpatient</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">960 (94.96%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Inpatient</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (5.04%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>ICU admission</bold>, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.49%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Severity,</bold><xref rid="tb2fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref> n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Mild/Moderate</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">993 (98.22%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Severe/Critical</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (1.78%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>First-time SARS-CoV-2 infection</bold>, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">842 (83.28%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">169 (16.72%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Number of previous infections</bold>, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120 (11.87%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 2</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (4.15%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> More than 3</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Vaccination status</bold>, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unvaccinated</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">259 (25.62%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Vaccinated</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">752 (74.38%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Number of vaccine doses</bold>, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1 dose</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (2.47%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 2 doses</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115 (11.37%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3 doses</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">491 (48.57%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 4 doses</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111 (10.98%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 5 doses</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.99%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Clinical manifestations</bold>, n (%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Fever or chills</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">792 (78.34%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Cough</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">791 (78.24%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Fatigue</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">702 (69.44%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Myalgia (muscle or body aches)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">590 (58.36%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Headache</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">516 (51.04%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Oropharyngeal pain (sore throat)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">348 (34.42%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Arthralgia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">314 (31.06%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Nasal congestion/ rhinorrhea (runny nose)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">289 (28.59%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dyspnea (shortness of breath)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">279 (27.60%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Ageusia/anosmia (loss of taste or smell)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">261 (25.82%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Chest pain</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">242 (23.94%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Diarrhea</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62 (6.13%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Nausea or vomiting</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (4.65%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (2.27%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>ICU, Intensive care unit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb2fn1"><label>a</label><p id="notep0004">For this study, severity was defined based on the level of medical care required as follows: mild/moderate (no hospital admission [outpatient care] or non-ICU hospitalization lasting &lt;10 days) and severe/critical (non-ICU hospitalization lasting ≥10 days or requiring ICU admission).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="para0023">COVID-19 vaccination prior to the acute infection was common, with 74.38% of patients having received at least one dose (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The median number of doses was 3 (range: 1-5), with 48.57% receiving exactly three doses. The most common clinical manifestations of acute infection, observed in over 50% of patients, were fever or chills (78.34%), cough (78.24%), fatigue (69.44%), myalgia (58.36%), and headache (51.04%).</p></sec><sec id="sec0011"><title>Suspected long COVID manifestations</title><p id="para0024">The prevalence of specific long-term clinical manifestations suspected to be associated with long COVID, categorized by MedDRA SOC and PT/LLT, is presented in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The most commonly affected SOC was General disorders and administration site conditions (75.67%), with fatigue/malaise as the predominant symptom, affecting 69.93% of patients (mild: 49.65%; moderate: 16.82%; severe: 3.46%).<fig id="fig0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Prevalence of suspected long COVID manifestations (a) by MedDRA system organ class and (b) by MedDRA PT/LLT (≥5%).</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0001" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/><attrib>LLT, lowest preferred term; MedDRA, Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities; PT, preferred term.</attrib></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Suspected long COVID manifestations by MedDRA SOC and PT/LLT, full analysis set.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">SOC category</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptom/sign (PT/LLT)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">% (95% CI)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">New</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Persistent</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Relapsed</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Worsening</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>General disorders and administration site conditions</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue/Malaise</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">707</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.93% (66.98–72.73%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173 (17.11%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">458 (45.30%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (6.33%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (1.19%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pyrexia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.77% (9.88–13.96%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (4.75%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (3.36%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (2.97%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.69%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">765</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.67% (72.88–78.26%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chest pain</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.10% (7.43–11.08%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (3.17%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (3.07%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (2.37%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.49%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chest discomfort</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.01% (6.45–9.90%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (2.97%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (3.26%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (1.19%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (0.59%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brain fog</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.75% (3.56–6.29%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (1.58%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (2.57%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cough</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">512</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.64% (47.52–53.77%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">106 (10.48%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">284 (28.09%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89 (8.80%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (3.26%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">251</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.83% (22.22–27.63%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70 (6.92%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (12.86%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (3.76%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (1.29%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">610</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.34% (57.24–63.36%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oropharyngeal pain</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.03% (12.92–17.42%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (3.76%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (6.63%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (3.56%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (1.09%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wheezing/rales/rhonchi</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.09% (8.34–12.15%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (2.87%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (4.35%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (2.08%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.79%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Exacerbation of asthma</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.32% (5.83–9.15%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (2.27%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (3.17%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (1.19%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.69%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Social circumstances</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Activities of daily living impaired</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">447</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">44.21% (41.13–47.34%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">118 (11.67%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">272 (26.90%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">38 (3.76%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">19 (1.88%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">447</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.21% (41.13–47.34%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Nervous system disorders</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">235</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.24% (20.70–26.00%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (6.03%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (9.79%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (5.93%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (1.48%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disturbance in attention</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.85% (11.81–16.17%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (5.04%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (7.32%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.69%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.79%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">407</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.26% (37.23–43.36%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Olfactory dysfunction /hypogeusia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.88% (9.06–13.00%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (2.77%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (6.82%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.79%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.49%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Memory impairment</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.80% (7.16–10.76%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (2.67%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (4.45%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.79%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.89%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Balance disorder</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.78% (1.09–2.86%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (0.59%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.79%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paresthesia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40% (0.13–1.08%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Myalgia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">249</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.63% (22.03–27.43%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (6.43%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119 (11.77%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (5.14%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (1.29%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arthralgia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.06% (11.07–15.33%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (2.57%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70 (6.92%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (2.77%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.79%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">280</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.70% (24.98–30.59%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unspecified disorder of joint</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59% (0.24–1.36%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Psychiatric disorders</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sleep disorder</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">137</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.55% (11.53–15.85%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (4.85%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (6.43%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (1.78%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.49%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.25% (11.26–15.54%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (4.95%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (5.84%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (1.48%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.99%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.95% (20.41–25.69%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Depression</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.63% (5.21–8.39%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (2.18%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (2.27%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (1.19%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.99%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Cardiac disorders</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Palpitations</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.97% (10.06–14.17%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (4.95%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (3.96%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (2.67%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tachycardia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.04% (3.81–6.63%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (1.98%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (2.27%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (0.59%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.54% (12.37–16.71%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.47% (1.64–3.68%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (1.09%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.99%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bradycardia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59% (0.24–1.36%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Decreased appetite</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">94</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">9.30% (7.61–11.30%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">37 (3.66%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">34 (3.36%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">12 (1.19%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">11 (1.09%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.30% (7.61–11.30%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hair loss</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.22% (5.74–9.04%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (3.26%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (2.57%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.99%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rash</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19% (0.64–2.13%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (0.59%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.51% (6.90–10.44%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nail disorder</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59% (0.24–1.36%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Investigations</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight decreased</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.74% (4.42–7.40%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (2.67%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (1.88%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.49%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.69%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiac murmur</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49% (0.18–1.22%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.13% (4.77–7.84%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Ear and labyrinth disorders</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vertigo</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.26% (2.29–4.61%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (1.38%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (1.09%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.49%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hearing loss</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.18% (1.40–3.33%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.69%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (1.09%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.54% (4.25–7.18%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tinnitus</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89% (0.44–1.75%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Gastrointestinal disorders</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nausea</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.37% (1.56–3.57%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (1.38%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>% (95% CI)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gastrointestinal motility disorder</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.18% (1.40–3.33%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.69%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.69%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.30%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.49%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.45% (3.30, 5.96%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abdominal pain</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.58% (0.94–2.62%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.69%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (0.59%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.20%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.10%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Other symptoms/signs</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.78% (1.09–2.86%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.49%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.89%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.40%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CI, confidence interval; LLT, lowest level term; PT, preferred term; SOC, system organ class.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="para0025">The second most affected SOC was Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders (60.34%), with cough (50.64%) and dyspnea (24.83%) as the leading symptoms. Social circumstances, specifically impairments in activities of daily living, followed, with a prevalence of 44.21%. Nervous system disorders affected 40.26% of patients, with headache (23.24%) and attention disturbance (13.85%) being the most common neurological symptoms.</p><p id="para0026">Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders affected 27.70% of patients, with myalgia (24.63%) and arthralgia (13.06%) being the most common symptoms, while Psychiatric disorders were noted in 22.95% of patients, with sleep disturbances (13.55%) and anxiety (13.25%) being the most frequent mental health issues. All other SOCs were present in fewer than 15% of patients.</p></sec><sec id="sec0012"><title>Acute SARS-CoV-2 infection, demographics, and comorbidities as predictors of long COVID manifestations</title><p id="para0027">Multivariate logistic regression revealed significant associations between patient demographics, acute infection characteristics, certain comorbidities, and the presence of various suspected long COVID manifestations. Hospitalization during acute SARS-CoV-2 infection (inpatient management) was significantly associated with an increased likelihood of developing symptoms within the SOC General disorders and administration site conditions (OR 4.12, 95% CI: 1.20-14.2, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.025) and Social circumstances (OR 4.56, 95% CI: 1.81-11.5, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001). In contrast, COVID-19 vaccination prior to acute infection was a protective factor against Nervous system disorders (OR 0.73, 95% CI: 0.55-0.98, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.038) and Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders (OR 0.62, 95% CI: 0.46-0.85, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003), with unvaccinated individuals more likely to experience such symptoms.</p><p id="para0028">Gender was also a significant factor, with females being more likely to develop General disorders and administration site conditions (OR 1.40, 95% CI: 1.04-1.91, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.028), Social circumstances impairments (OR 1.42, 95% CI 1.08-1.87, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.012), Psychiatric disorders (OR 1.60, 95% CI: 1.15-2.21, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005) and Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders (OR 1.51, 95% CI: 1.11-2.03, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008), but less likely to experience Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders (OR 0.73, 95% CI: 0.55-0.96, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.026).</p><p id="para0029">Increasing age was associated with a higher risk of General disorders and administration site conditions (OR 0.99, 95% CI: 0.98-1.00, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.023) and Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders (OR 1.01, 95% CI: 1.00-1.02, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.030). Non-smokers were found to have a reduced risk of developing Nervous system disorders (OR 0.65, 95% CI: 0.47-0.90, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.009) and Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders compared to current smokers (OR 0.64, 95% CI: 0.45-0.92, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014).</p><p id="para0030">Regarding comorbidities, patients with COPD and asthma were significantly more likely to experience Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders (OR 2.90, 95% CI: 1.46-5.76, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002, and OR 5.28, 95% CI: 2.87-9.71, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively). Hypertension was associated with increased risks of both General disorders and administration site conditions (OR 1.59, 95% CI: 1.07-2.36, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.020) and Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders (OR 1.60, 95% CI: 1.11-2.32, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.011). Patients with coronary artery disease (OR 3.24, 95% CI: 1.19-8.80, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.021) and autoimmune disease (OR 3.78, 95% CI: 1.13-12.7, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.031) were at higher risk of developing General disorders and administration site conditions, and those with a history of stroke or cancer had increased odds of experiencing psychiatric disorders (OR 5.11, 95% CI: 1.20-21.7, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.027 and OR 2.45, 95% CI: 1.18-5.06, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.016, respectively).</p></sec><sec id="sec0013"><title>Diagnostic tests for suspected long COVID symptoms</title><p id="para0031">Nearly one quarter of patients (24.73%) had undergone at least one diagnostic test for suspected long COVID prior to the study visit. The most common tests were complete blood count and biochemical tests (17.90% each), chest X-rays (14.24%), and pulmonary function tests (i.e., spirometry; 11.47%). Other tests, such as chest computed tomography (CT) (5.74%), electrocardiogram (8.41%), and echocardiography (5.84%), were less frequently performed.</p></sec><sec id="sec0014"><title>Medications</title><p id="para0032">At the time of the study visit, 45.8% of patients were taking at least one medication for suspected long COVID symptoms, with inhalers being the most common (30.27% overall; 22.65% initiated prior to the study visit and 7.62% during the study visit). Other medications, including angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, angiotensin II receptor blockers, beta-blockers, statins, oral antithrombotics, antidiabetics, oral corticosteroids, and antiarrhythmics, were taken by fewer than 3% of patients.</p><p id="para0033">Additionally, 41.94% of patients were taking at least one medication for conditions unrelated to specific long COVID symptoms. The most commonly used were statins (22.06%), angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (11.37%), and beta-blockers (11.28%).</p></sec><sec id="sec0015"><title>Diagnostic and therapeutic follow-up of suspected long-term COVID-19 manifestations</title><p id="para0034">During the study visit, physicians recommended further diagnostic evaluations for suspected long COVID symptoms, with at least one imaging test in 53.81% of the patients, chest X-ray being the most common (33.83%). Pulmonary function tests (48.86%), complete blood count or biochemical tests (50.05%), and electrocardiogram (35.41%) were also frequently recommended (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).<fig id="fig0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Recommended follow-up diagnostic and therapeutic procedures during the study visit.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0002" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/><attrib>CBC, complete blood count; CT, computed tomography; ECG, electrocardiogram; Cardiac echo, cardiac echocardiography; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; PFT, pulmonary function test.</attrib></fig></p><p id="para0035">Therapeutic recommendations were primarily focused on lifestyle changes (44.41%), whereas pulmonary rehabilitation and mental health support were advised to a smaller subset (11.18% and 11.08%, respectively) (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Only 26.90% of patients were referred to other specialists, with cardiologists being the most common referral (14.14%).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0016"><title>Discussion</title><p id="para0036">This study provides real-world insights into the clinical presentation and management of long COVID in a large cohort of adults with a history of symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection, managed in routine clinical practice in Greece. Participants experienced suspected long-term COVID-19 manifestations affecting multiple body organ systems, with General disorders and administration site conditions being the most affected MedDRA SOC (76%), followed by Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders (60%), Social circumstances (44%), and Nervous system disorders (40%). While similar patterns of multisystem involvement have been documented, few studies have utilized organ systems (e.g., MedDRA SOCs) to describe long COVID manifestations [<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. These findings align with contemporary evidence recognizing multisystem involvement as a hallmark of long COVID [<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. By focusing on affected organ systems rather than isolated symptoms, the use of MedDRA SOC terms allows for better capture of the condition’s complexity and multisystemic nature, supporting a multidisciplinary approach to patient care.</p><p id="para0037">Fatigue and malaise emerged as the most prevalent symptoms, affecting approximately 70% of participants, followed by impairments in daily activities (51%) and cough (44%). Dyspnea, myalgia, and headache were less frequent, affecting nearly 25%. These symptoms are consistently documented in the literature [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>,<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>], and are among those endorsed by both the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (US) [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and WHO [<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], reinforcing their prominence as core features of long COVID. Focusing on Greece, two smaller studies have been conducted—a single-center observational study using a similar definition for long COVID symptoms and an online survey conducted within a long COVID Greek support group, also reporting fatigue as the leading symptom, with a prevalence closely matching that observed in our cohort [<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p id="para0038">Despite the overwhelming volume of research, a clearly defined set of symptoms for accurately identifying long COVID remains elusive, and a universally agreed-upon definition is still lacking [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This ambiguity introduces considerable variation when translating findings into clinical practice, particularly when determining follow-up timing and standardized diagnostic strategies. In this study, we adopted the CDC’s definition in place at the time [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], defining long COVID symptoms as those extending beyond four weeks and up to six months post-acute infection. Nevertheless, although long COVID symptoms generally decline with time, some may persist for up to three years post-acute infection [<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], indicating a longer-lasting risk horizon for COVID-19, similar to that observed in previous coronavirus outbreaks [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p id="para0039">The hospitalization rate during acute infection was low (5%), consistent with evidence that long COVID predominantly affects non-hospitalized patients with mild acute disease, who represent the majority of COVID-19 cases [<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Therefore, it is of the utmost importance to recognize potentially suspicious long COVID symptoms early and ensure proactive follow-up through multidisciplinary outpatient care. Identifying risk factors for long COVID, such as female gender, older age, pre-existing conditions, and hospitalization during acute disease, is also crucial [<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Our multivariate analyses revealed that females were more likely to experience systemic, psychiatric, and musculoskeletal manifestations, as well as impairments in daily activities, while being less prone to respiratory manifestations. This finding aligns with gender differences reported in large meta-analyses [<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Additionally, hospitalization during acute infection increased the risk of systemic symptoms and impaired daily activities, while smoking was associated with nervous system and musculoskeletal symptoms. Hypertension, present in nearly a third of the cohort, was associated with systemic and musculoskeletal symptoms. Asthma and COPD, though less prevalent, were strongly associated with respiratory symptoms, reflecting the vulnerability of these individuals’ respiratory systems to COVID-19.</p><p id="para0040">The majority of patients (83%) in our study experienced long COVID after their first SARS-CoV-2 infection, aligning with evidence that long COVID is more common following initial infections, except for the Omicron BA variant, where reinfections are more frequently implicated. This corresponds with our study period, dominated by earlier variants such as Alpha and Delta, for which this trend is well-documented [<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. While reinfections are less likely to cause long COVID compared to initial infections, they still carry an added risk for persistent symptoms and contribute to the cumulative burden of the condition [<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Notably, approximately 74% of our cohort had been vaccinated (median three doses) prior to their acute infection. Vaccination has demonstrated an overall protective effect against long COVID [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and our data suggest that it may specifically lower the risk of nervous system and musculoskeletal manifestations, likely by reducing severe disease and accelerating viral clearance [<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. These findings indicate that, although vaccination reduces some risks, it does not fully eliminate the burden of long COVID. Thus, further research is essential to understand its interplay with reinfections and long-term COVID-19 complications to guide effective public health strategies.</p><p id="para0041">During our study, further diagnostic evaluations were recommended for about half of the participants, reflecting the physicians’ balanced approach to addressing suspected long COVID manifestations. Respiratory assessments, including imaging (e.g., X-rays) and spirometry, along with routine laboratory tests, were prioritized, consistent with the high prevalence of respiratory and systemic symptoms. Lifestyle modifications were the most frequently recommended intervention (44%), with notably underutilized strategies such as pulmonary rehabilitation and mental health support (11% each)—both crucial for addressing long COVID’s functional and psychological challenges [<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Limited referrals to other specialists (26.9%) suggest a reliance on single-specialty management, potentially overlooking the advantages of addressing the multifaceted nature of this condition through a multidisciplinary approach [<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p id="para0042">Overall, with the growing global population of COVID-19 survivors, the impact of long COVID on individuals, healthcare systems, and society is likely substantial [<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Managing this complex condition is challenging due to the diverse symptoms and multisystem involvement, necessitating a tailored, patient-centered approach. Primary care physicians are central to this effort, playing a pivotal role in screening, diagnosis, and timely referrals to specialized care through well-defined pathways [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. To address long COVID effectively, physicians should remain vigilant for symptoms, especially in high-risk patients, and adopt a comprehensive approach to care that includes mapping current symptoms, assessing COVID-19 history, screening for comorbidities, providing targeted interventions for acute symptoms and underlying conditions, educating patients about potential post-COVID-19 manifestations, ensuring regular follow-up, and encouraging them to seek prompt medical attention if symptoms worsen [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p id="para0043">This study has several limitations inherent to its non-interventional design, including the absence of a control group, selection bias, and information/recall bias. Selection bias at the patient level was mitigated by consecutive enrolment, and at the site level by including both hospital outpatient clinics and private primary care offices. Information/recall bias may arise from patient self-reports, potentially leading to under- or overreporting of clinical manifestations; however, physician assessments were also considered. The cross-sectional design limits the ability to track symptom progression over time and establish causal relationships between risk factors and symptoms. Moreover, as most participants were non-hospitalized during the acute disease, individuals with severe acute disease may be underrepresented, though such cases constitute a minority of the affected population. Limited diagnostic correlations, coupled with potential confounding by comorbidities, suggest that some symptoms may represent exacerbations of pre-existing conditions rather than new manifestations of long COVID. Additionally, the CDC and the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine recently updated the definition of long COVID, now described as a chronic condition arising after SARS-CoV-2 infection and persisting for at least three months [<xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Since our study used the earlier CDC definition with a four-week cutoff, comparability with future studies may be limited. Finally, wide CIs for some associations warrant cautious interpretation and further validation in future studies.</p></sec><sec id="sec0017"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="para0044">LONCOV2 is the largest Greek study to date, providing real-world insights into the clinical presentation of long COVID in a geographically diverse adult population with prior symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection. Our findings confirm that long COVID involves multisystem complications, with fatigue/malaise as the most prevalent symptom. Addressing these challenges requires multidisciplinary care and tailored support for at-risk populations. Future research should focus on standardizing diagnostic criteria, tracking symptom evolution, and developing integrated care pathways to reduce the societal and healthcare burden of long COVID.</p></sec><sec id="sec0018"><title>Funding</title><p id="para0045">The LONCOV2 study was sponsored by Menarini Hellas S.A. The study sponsor was involved in the study conception and design, as well as in the interpretation of the data presented in this publication, but not in data collection or analysis. Menarini Hellas S.A. also funded medical writing support for this publication.</p></sec><sec id="sec0019"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="para0046">The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, the International Society for Pharmacoepidemiology’s (ISPE) Guidelines for Good Pharmacoepidemiology Practices (GPPs), and all applicable local laws. Approval was granted by the Ethics Committees (ECs) of coordinating hospitals, and all participants provided written informed consent prior to inclusion. ECs and approval dates:<list list-type="simple" id="celist0002"><list-item id="celistitem0007"><label>•</label><p id="para0047">EC of University Hospital of Patras (08 Feb 2023)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0008"><label>•</label><p id="para0048">EC of General University Hospital of Larissa (01 Dec 2022)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0009"><label>•</label><p id="para0049">EC of University Hospital of Ioannina (24 Jan 2023)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0010"><label>•</label><p id="para0050">EC of Athens General Hospital for Chest Diseases “Sotiria”: 7th &amp; 9th Pulmonary Departments (05 Dec 2022); 3rd Department of Internal Medicine and Laboratory (23 Dec 2022)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0011"><label>•</label><p id="para0051">EC of St. Luke’s Hospital (30 Jan 2023)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0012"><label>•</label><p id="para0052">EC of University General Hospital of Alexandroupolis (08 Dec 2022)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0013"><label>•</label><p id="para0053">EC of General Hospital of Nikaia Piraeus “Agios Panteleimon” (21 Dec 2022)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0014"><label>•</label><p id="para0054">EC of General Hospital of Heraklion “Venizeleio-Pananeio” (20 Dec 2022)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0015"><label>•</label><p id="para0055">EC of General Hospital of Piraeus “Tzaneio” (13 Dec 2022)</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0016"><label>•</label><p id="para0056">EC of Bioclinic Thessaloniki (28 Feb 2023).</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0001"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="para0057">VM, SB, MK, PG, AS, PS, and AT declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. VM, SB, and PG are Guest Editors for this journal but were not involved in the editorial review or the decision to publish this article. GP has received grants and/or research support and served as a principal investigator for studies sponsored by Pfizer, MSD, Gilead, Menarini, PharmaMar, Fabentech, Bausch, AstraZeneca, the Hellenic Institute for the Study of Sepsis, University College London, and the University of Minnesota. She has also served on advisory boards for Pfizer, AstraZeneca, Gilead, MSD, Menarini, and SOBI. AG has received honoraria and consultancy fees from Boehringer Ingelheim, Chiesi, ELPEN, GSK, and Menarini. P. Sty. is an employee of Menarini Hellas S.A.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic 2024</article-title><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" id="interref0001">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link><year>2024</year><comment>[accessed 21 November 2024]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>O.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raut</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kacimi</surname><given-names>S.E.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huy</surname><given-names>NT.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): comprehensive review of clinical presentation</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><volume>8</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">582932</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2020.582932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7844320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33520910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizrahi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudry</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaks-Manov</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yehezkelli</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalkstein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiva</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long covid outcomes at one year after mild SARS-CoV-2 infection: nationwide cohort study</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>380</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e072529</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj-2022-072529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9832503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36631153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and postacute sequelae associated with SARS-CoV-2 reinfection</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>28</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2398</fpage><lpage>2405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02051-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9671810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haupert</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global prevalence of post-coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) condition or long COVID: a meta-analysis and systematic review</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>226</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>1607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiac136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35429399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Mahoney</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Routen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekezie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welford</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The prevalence and long-term health effects of Long Covid among hospitalised and non-hospitalised populations: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>EClinicalmedicine</source><volume>55</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101762</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9714474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36474804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sk Abd Razak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul Aziz</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suddin</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azzeri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sha’ari</surname><given-names>N.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID syndrome prevalence: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><volume>24</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>1785</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-19264-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38965510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11223303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perlowski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolich</surname><given-names>JŽ.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: a clinical update</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>404</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01136-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39096925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WHO Clinical Case Definition Working Group on Post-COVID-19 Condition. A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>22</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>e102</fpage><lpage>e107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (U.S.)</collab></person-group><part-title>Post-COVID conditions: information for healthcare providers</part-title><year>2022</year></element-citation><note><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://archive.cdc.gov/www_cdc_gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/clinical-care/post-covid-conditions.html" id="interref0002">https://archive.cdc.gov/www_cdc_gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/clinical-care/post-covid-conditions.html</ext-link>. [accessed 21 November 2024].</p></note></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term consequences of COVID-19 at 6 months and above: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><volume>19</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>6865</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19116865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35682448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9180091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roque</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bam</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavares</surname><given-names>A.B.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-COVID-19 clinical and health outcomes: an umbrella review</article-title><source>Ther Adv Infect Dis</source><volume>10</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20499361231198335</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20499361231198335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10501084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37720384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q-D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review and meta-analysis of long term physical and mental sequelae of COVID-19 pandemic: call for research priority and action</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><volume>28</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-022-01614-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35668159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9168643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><volume>21</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parotto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyöngyösi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myatra</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranzani</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shankar-Hari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-acute sequelae of COVID-19: understanding and addressing the burden of multisystem manifestations</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><volume>11</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(23)00239-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37475125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceban</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>L.M.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teopiz</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fatigue and cognitive impairment in post-COVID-19 syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Brain Behav Immun</source><volume>101</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2021.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34973396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8715665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsampasian</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elghazaly</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Debski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naing</surname><given-names>T.K.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with post−COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><volume>183</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10037203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwagami</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuhara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuno</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of COVID-19 vaccination against long COVID syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><volume>41</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>1783</fpage><lpage>1790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2023.02.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36774332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9905096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Notarte</surname><given-names>K.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catahay</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastrana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ver</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pangilinan</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of COVID-19 vaccination on the risk of developing long-COVID and on existing long-COVID symptoms: a systematic review</article-title><source>EClinicalmedicine</source><volume>53</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101624</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9417563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36051247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Re’em</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterizing long COVID in an international cohort: 7 months of symptoms and their impact</article-title><source>EClinicalmedicine</source><volume>38</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101019</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34308300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Déguilhem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malaab</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talmatkadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foulquié</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fagherazzi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying profiles and symptoms of patients with long COVID in France: data mining infodemiology study based on social media</article-title><source>JMIR Infodemiology</source><volume>2</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e39849</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/39849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9685517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36447795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsarou</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iasonidou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osarogue</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalafatis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanatou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pappa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Greek collaborative long COVID study: non-hospitalized and hospitalized patients share similar symptom patterns</article-title><source>J Pers Med</source><volume>12</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>987</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jpm12060987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35743774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9224912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sotiriadou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oikonomidou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Κouzoukidou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mpogiatzidis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First insights from patients presenting with long/post-COVID syndrome in primary care: an exploratory report</article-title><source>Hippokratia</source><volume>26</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37497527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10367945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaichana</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>K.K.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>I.C.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Definition of post–COVID-19 condition among published research studies</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>6</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e235856</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.5856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10077105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37017970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-de-las-Peñas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Notarte</surname><given-names>K.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macasaet</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catahay</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ver</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Persistence of post-COVID symptoms in the general population two years after SARS-CoV-2 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Infect</source><volume>88</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2023.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38101521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0026"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-year outcomes of post-acute sequelae of COVID-19</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>30</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>1564</fpage><lpage>1573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-024-02987-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38816608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11186764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0027">Hadley E, Yoo YJ, Patel S, Zhou A, Laraway B, Wong R, et al. SARS-CoV-2 reinfection is preceded by unique biomarkers and related to initial infection timing and severity: an N3C RECOVER EHR-based cohort study. medRxiv. 05 January 2023. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.01.03.22284042</pub-id> [accessed 21 November 2024].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosworth</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shenhuy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nafilyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alwan</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Hara</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk of new-onset long COVID following reinfection with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2: a community-based cohort study</article-title><source>Open Forum Infect Dis</source><volume>10</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>ofad493</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofad493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37953820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10633780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging trends in management of long COVID with a focus on pulmonary rehabilitation: a review</article-title><source>Clin Respir J</source><volume>18</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e13777</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/crj.13777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11110486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38775379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oronsky</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oronsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lybeck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A review of persistent post-COVID syndrome (PPCS)</article-title><source>Clin Rev Allergy Immunol</source><volume>64</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12016-021-08848-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33609255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7896544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ely</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fineberg</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine Committee on Examining the Working Definition for Long Covid. Long covid defined</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>391</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>1746</fpage><lpage>1753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsb2408466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39083764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687645</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0001"><sec id="sec0020"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="para0058">The authors would like to thank all the participating investigators who enrolled patients in the study and contributed to the collection of data: Elisavet Papalymperi, Evangelia Tsagka, Ioannis Leivaditis, Georgia Kotantoula, Stamatis Andris, Louminitsa Vasileskou, Kostantina Pandi, Dimitra Papandrinopoulou, Eleni Stavrou, Eftychia Chaloulou, Vasiliki Dalaklidou, Chrysavgi Bimpika, Kyriaki Mousoutzani, Eleni Iladi Chamerzekova, Kyriaki Asimomyti, Vasileios Thomopoulos, Fragkiskos Kapitsimadis, Konstantinos Nikas, Kyriakos Nikolaidis, Alexis Samentzas, Ioannis Lampaditis, Michail Symiakakis, Tsilla Zafeiriou, Eleni Kokkotou, Anastasia Samakovli, Georgios Violatos, Konstantinos Paraskevopoulos, Athanasios Chastas, Christos Bampalis, Konstantinos Charitopoulos, Konstantinos Kairis, Christos Liavvas, Despoina Saatzoglou, Christos Ntochas, Theodoros Frengidis, Vasileios Vogas, Panagiotis Doulgeridis, Athanasios Koutsakis, Christos Arampatzis, Giorgos Kotrogiannis, Christos Basagiannis, Theodora Chatziandreou, Theodora Zagka, Georgios Kalfountzos, Stavroula Nouka, Ioannis Skias, Evangelos Almpanis, Konstantinos Manakos, Marios Konstantinou, Charalampos Tsitsaras, Nikolaos Karatzas, Pantelis Avarlis, Dionysios Mantelos, Kosmas Georgopoulos, Christina Leontaridi, Dimitrios Zarifis, Stratos Panselinas, Georgios Tsarouchis, Nikolaos Baritakis, Athanasios Angelopoulos, Christiana Konstantelou, Pantelis Papathanasiou, Thomas Tiligadas, Konstantinos Livanios, Nikolaos Giourtoumas, Dimitrios Gkotsis, Efthymia Stofa, Panagiotis Lampropoulos, Evangelia Plevraki Argiana, Stavros Spanos, Elina Vlachaki, Nikolaos Sertedakis, Nikolaos Meramvelliotakis, Paraschos Toloudis, Evangelia Daniil, Nikolaos Barouchos, Violetta Talou, Andreas Pagkalis, Dimitrios Chrysis, Evgenia Karyanou, Sofia Raftopoulou, Katerina Kleftaki-Manta, Sofia Koufopoulou, Panagiotis Chinelis, Panagiotis Chatziapostolou, Paraskevi Tsafaridou, Paschalis Kakavelas, Efstratios Karanikolas, Alekos Papadopoulos, Anestis Matziridis, Emmanouela Dalamagka, Anna Manousaki, Evangelos Petrovitsios, Emmanouil Toulas, Stavroula Zakesti, Emmanouela Chronaki, Maria Varoucha, Konstantinos Pigakis, Giannis Giannarakis, Manolis Nikitiadis, Andreas Ntanasis, Ioannis Tzinas, Eleftherios Zervas, Myrsini Melachroinidou, Ioanna Papanikolaou, Nikiforos Papatsimpas, Dimitris Chorianopoulos, Antonis Antoniadis, Aikaterini Vagena, Panagiotis Demertzis, and Georgios Chrysos. Moreover, we would like to thank Phaze for medical writing and editorial support, which was funded by Menarini Hellas S.A.</p></sec><sec id="sec0021"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="para0059">All authors have made a significant contribution to the conception and design of this study, as well as the acquisition, analysis and interpretation of data. All authors were also involved in critically revising the manuscript for important intellectual content, have given final approval of the version to be submitted, have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="sec0022"><title>Data availability/sharing statement</title><p id="para0060">The data supporting the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec></ack></back></article></pmc-articleset>