<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">480</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bioinform</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11953547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11953547.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11953547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11953547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40162470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6026/9732063002001529</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9732063002001529</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Integrating MICRORNA941 and T cell subset research into public health strategies for managing inflammaging in elderly and immune-compromised patients</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fotovat</surname><given-names initials="L">Lily</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="COR2" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="K">Kathleen</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="COR3" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiappelli</surname><given-names initials="F">Francesco</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Dental Group of Sherman Oaks, Sherman Oaks, CA - 91403, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>UCLA Center for the Health Sciences, Los Angeles, CA - 90095, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>1</label>Francesco Chiappelli <email>Chiappelli.research@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="COR2"><label>2</label>Lily Fotovat <email>lilyfotovat@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="COR3"><label>3</label>Kathleen Wang <email>katwang14@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">485551</issue-id><fpage>1529</fpage><lpage>1531</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-01 09:25:14.673"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Biomedical Informatics</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. This is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="9732063002001529.pdf"/><abstract><p>As of 2022, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) reported that the average life expectancy for both sexes in the
United States is 77.5 years. While new advances in health have increased life expectancy, aging comes with complications that impact the
development of diseases like cancer, senile dementia (non-Alzheimer), diabetes and Parkinson's. Through aging, the body's immune system
declines, a process recognized as immunosenescence and which contributes to inflammaging, a state of chronic, though non-productive,
inflammation that progresses with advancing age in the absence of overt infection and that contributes to the onset and progression of a
spectrum of age-related pathologies. MicroRNAs are small forms of RNA that control gene expression by binding to messenger RNA (mRNA) in
the cell cytoplasm. In particular, microRNA-941 (miR-941) has been found to play a critical role in the regulation of differentiation of
cell populations, certain T cell subsets responsible for maintaining efficient immune surveillance in normal subjects, immune compromised
individuals as well as the elderly. We propose that concerted research designed to define and characterize interventions targeting the
regulatory effects of miRNA-941 specifically on T-cell subsets will benefit treatment of infectious (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic>, CoViD-19,
H5N1 infection) and chronic illnesses (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic>, diabetes II, diabetes III, Long Covid [<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, Post-Acute
Covid-19 Syndrome, PACS], autoimmune disease), which are most common among the aging and the immune compromised population. It is
possible and even probable that active research in this specific area will proffer new horizons for finding cures, aid in disease
management and improved accessibility and affordability of public health services.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Immunosenescence</kwd><kwd>inflammaging</kwd><kwd>MicroRNA941</kwd><kwd>senescence-associated secretory phenotype (SASP)</kwd><kwd>infectious diseases (CoViD-19, PACS Long Covid)</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background:</title><p>As of 2022, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) reported that the average life expectancy for both sexes in the
United States is 77.5 years [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. While new advances in health have increased life expectancy,
aging comes with complications that impact the development of diseases like cancer, senile dementia (non-Alzheimer), diabetes and
Parkinson's [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Through aging, the body's immune system declines, a process accompanied by,
responsible for and possibly engendered by inflammaging. In addition, the steady increase in life expectancy impacts people's daily
lives and public healthcare. With people living longer, finding affordable, reliable and alternative treatments for age-related diseases
is vital to avoid placing further strain on healthcare systems [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. As people get older and live
longer, new technologies and interventions must be developed to help combat the diseases that arise with old age and promote the concept
of healthy aging while considering environmental and geographical factors [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Therefore, it is urgent to find solutions to combat immunosuppression and inflammaging. MicroRNAs can recognize cancer and develop
disease biomarkers [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Additionally, since the function of certain T-cell subsets decrease with
age, studying T-cells that respond to the CD28 co-stimulus by activation and proliferation can offer insights into the behavior and
survival of this and other T-cell subsets [<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Emerging evidence suggests that looking at
microRNA and T-cell interventions and research can help inform future public health strategies for managing inflammation in the
elderly.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Understanding inflammaging in the elderly:</title><p>Biologically, aging refers to the physiological process of tissue degeneration related to chronic inflammation. This age-related
chronic inflammation is highly associated with inflammaging, an imbalanced immune system that can develop through aging or external
triggers [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Immune cells, vital for identifying and clearing these senescent cells, are
impacted by senescence-associated secretory phenotype (SASP), contributing to the decline in immune function known as immunosenescence
[<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Immunosenescence, a process associated with aging that impairs the immune function, is
responsible for inflammaging [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>The consequences of both mechanisms may lead to increased susceptibility to infection and poor responses to vaccination, as well as
to chronic inflammatory and degenerative diseases in the elderly [<xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Moreover, the accumulation
of senescent cells can trigger inflammation in organs, leading to organ damage and an increased risk of age-related diseases like cancer
[<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This process is heightened by positive feedback loops that promote the build-up of
inflammation and organ damage, amplifying inflammation and increasing the risk of age-related diseases [<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
As people grow older, more persistent illnesses, including Alzheimer's disease (now sometimes referred to as Type III diabetes) and
cancer, significantly affect people's quality of life. People with high socioeconomic status (SES) can afford treatment or newer
technologies to combat diseases that affect them, while those with lower SES cannot: the higher the SES, the higher the life expectancy,
as disparity in SES becomes an issue of resource access [<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. A key result is that in older age,
those with the most significant health needs are often the ones with the least access to resources to manage their care
[<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>MicroRNA941:</title><p>MicroRNAs are a class of small noncoding RNAs which function in post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression [<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
They are powerful regulators of various cellular activities, including cell growth, differentiation, development and apoptosis
[<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. MicroRNA expression profiling is used to classify several different human cancers and can
also distinguish malignant tumors from benign tumors [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. MicroRNA-941 (miR-941) is found in high
amounts in cells that can potentially become any type of cell (pluripotent cells). Still, its levels drop when these cells begin the
process of differentiated specialization [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In humans, miR-941 affects brain cells and
influences genes involved in neurotransmitter signaling, which helps control how brain cells communicate. The observation that miR-941
is associated with certain cancers (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic>, breast, liver, lung, laryngeal), cardiovascular inflammation and certain
autoimmune diseases (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic>, psoriatic arthritis) suggests that it also plays a critical role in regulating cellular
immunity. Taken together, these lines of evidence confirm that miR-941 is a key biological regulator in human cell development, immune
surveillance and brain function [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>To be clear, miR-941 inhibitors - <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, chemically-modified oligonucleotides that hybridize with mature miRNAs - can
significantly lower miR-941 levels in breast cancer cells, depending on the dose used [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Data
show that miR-941 regulates cancer cell growth by modulating histone phosphorylation and consequentially gene expression. MiR-941
inhibitor showed strong anticancer effects in lab-grown cancer cell growth and proliferation in vitro [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
In other studies, miRNA-pathway network analysis showed that miR-941 can regulate T-cell receptor signaling, insulin signaling and MAPK
signaling. MiR-941 may act as a reliable biomarker of Acute Coronary Syndrome and could predict the severity and progression of coronary
heart disease [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. While miR-941 may have evolved to
enhance human longevity by maintaining stem cells, it may also inadvertently increase cancer risk, highlighting a trade-off between
longer life and vulnerability to disease [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This dichotomy further suggests that miR-941 may
support longevity but at the cost of making cells more susceptible to cancerous changes [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
Additional studies have shown that the pattern of miRNA expression is a reliable tool for predicting therapeutic outcomes in cancers
such as leukemia and colon cancer. Levels of miR-143 and miR-145, related to miR-941, are often lower in many types of cancer
[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. When researchers restored these miRNAs in prostate or colorectal tumors, they saw a
significant reduction in tumor growth in lab-grown cells and living organisms [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Additionally,
the role of miRNAs can vary depending on the type of cell they are in. For example, miR-29a can act either as a cancer-promoting gene
(oncogene) or as a cancer-suppressing gene (tumor suppressor), depending on the specific environment within the cell
[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>T cell subset research:</title><p>T-cells, otherwise known as T-lymphocytes, are highly specialized immune system cells. Like many other specialized cells, T-cells
develop from stem cells in the bone marrow and finalize their maturation as thymocytes [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
T-cells are responsible for cellular immunity and produce and regulate the cytokines that mediate inflammation. Cytokines are signaling
proteins that trigger immune system activity to control cell growth and maintain the body's immune and inflammatory responses
[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Previous studies have uncovered an array of differentiated CD4+ T-cells such as T helper 1
(TH1), TH2, TH17 and T follicular helper (Tfh). These cell subsets possess developmental and regulatory pathways that play critical
roles in immunity [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In addition, the proportion of naïve T-cells in the CD4+ and CD8+
T-cell subsets sharply decreases with aging, particularly for the CD8+ population [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. During
aging, the thymus, the organ responsible for generating self-tolerant and immune-competent T-cells, undergoes thymic involution
[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. When this occurs, new naïve T-cell production decreases. T-cell subset reservoir
severely decreases with age. The functional response of T cells may also decrease in aging, in addition to their numbers. Together, the
drop in T cell number and function may severely impact immune function in the aging population. A decrease in the generation of
functional T-cells with advancing age in humans may significantly contribute to the onset of several types of cancer and chronic or
infectious diseases [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>One mechanism that may bring about aging-associated loss of T cell activity may be due to their decreased response to co-stimulation
by the 90KDa constitutive membrane-associated glycoprotein referred to as cluster of differentiation #28 (CD28), an essential
co-stimulatory molecule for T cell activation and proliferation [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. With aging, CD28 response
decreases, as consequentially does overall reduced immune surveillance and, specifically with respect to current threats of infectious
diseases including SARS-CoV2 and influenza H5N1, decreased response to vaccinations [<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In
addition, CD4+ T-cells play a role in the pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis (RA), an autoimmune disease characterized by joint pain,
stiffness and swelling [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Studies observed that RA patients have an increased frequency of
aged T-cells. Chronically activated T-cells derived from inflamed joints may be due to prolonged exposure to pro-inflammatory cytokines
such as tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
Observations of a model of T-cell activation in chronic inflammation predicted that the environment of inflamed joints is significantly
different from that of a small inflammatory episode. Chronic exposure of T-cells to TNF uncouples T-cell receptor (TCR) signaling
pathways and thus impairs T-cell subset functionality [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
CD28-memory T-cell subsets contribute to inflammation and may also aggravates the disease severity of RA upon stimulation by increasing
the production of inflammatory factors [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Indeed, a
reduction of CD8+ CD28-T-cells in RA patients was distributed and favorable clinical responses resulted
[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>Memory T-cells in aging individuals exhibit the pro-inflammatory phenotype SASP, which causes chronic inflammation
[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. These memory-like T-cells show diminished
expression and response to co-stimulatory molecules, including CD28, which regulate T-cell activation and preventative functions within
the body's immune system [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Without the continual
support of such co-stimulatory molecules, the memory T-cells show decreased telomerase activity and increased DNA damage
[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The age-dependent preferential accumulation of
memory T-cells contributes to inflammaging and tissue deterioration. By contrast to miR-941, another micro-RNA form (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>,
miR-155) is required to accumulate active CD4+ T and Tfh cells [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similarly, miR-146a blunts
severe inflammation by decreasing the activation of T-cells [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
Nonetheless, miR-146a-/- (knockout) mice undergo a significant life expectancy decrease due to extreme immune dysfunction and chronic
inflammation caused by the early activation of CD4+ T-cells [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Additionally, when miR-155 is
expressed and miR-146a is not expressed, miR-155 is responsible for the accumulation of CD4+ T and Tfh cells, the spontaneous formation
of B cells within the germinal centers and cell-attacking autoantibodies. Thus, because miR-155 initiates age-dependent pro-inflammatory
responses in T-cells, it plays a crucial role in inflammaging in the murine model [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The implications of these findings in treating inflammaging in humans remain to be tested.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Future strategies:</title><p>As a society, aging and having a longer life span should be viewed in a good light as it allows young people to plan their lives with
greater security [<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Healthcare needs to address the multidimensional demands of older age in an
integrated way instead of primarily focusing on services that treat disease independently to meet the needs of older adults and impose
significant costs on them and the health system [<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Further research should be conducted, like
comparing blood tests across four test groups in elderly populations, all in the same nursing home: cancer, senile dementia
(non-Alzheimer's), diabetes II and Parkinson's disease. A recent study tested how biomarkers might differentiate between various health
conditions in an elderly population [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The study compared two groups of individuals aged 70 to
82: one group with chronic illnesses from significant cardiovascular, neurodegenerative and chronic pulmonary diseases, diabetes II and
cancers (referred to as non-healthy aging, NHA). The control group consisted of age-matched individuals in good health (referred to as
healthy aging, HA). The study performed quantitative analysis on forty pro-inflammatory cytokines in blood plasma and over 500 proteins
in urine to identify and establish significant differences in potential biomarkers and understand the biological pathways associated
with healthy aging [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Similar study designs in further research could refine the approach to
monitoring and managing chronic diseases in aging individuals.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Since people are living longer, investing in technologies and a healthcare infrastructure that supports the influx of people aging is
essential. Aging involves physiological tissue degeneration driven by chronic inflammation, linked to an imbalanced immune response
known as inflammaging. This process leads to immunosenescence and increases vulnerability to infections and age-related diseases
[<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. These effects are further intensified by socioeconomic disparities that limit access to
essential healthcare resources for those most in need. Understanding and targeting the pathways of T-cells and microRNAs should lead to
new and improved strategies and therapies to alleviate inflammaging and chronic diseases. For example, research should test novel modes
of implementation and integration of microRNAs to control and regulate the expression of CD28 and other co-stimulator proteins
[<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In addition, ensuring gene expression of miR-146a, miR-155, miR-941 and other anti-inflammatory
microRNAs should tested for improving treatment interventions of auto-immunity, chronic diseases and immune deficiencies
[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Case in point, exploring treatments in miRNA-941 and T-cell subset research can be
beneficial to understanding and treating aging-associated chronic illnesses. Researching these areas at an evidence-based transactional
public health level will open up new possibilities for finding cures, aiding in disease management and hopefully improving accessibility
and affordability. Such progress could improve the quality of life, reduce healthcare costs and enhance community health and resilience.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="FN" fn-type="other"><p>
<bold>Edited by Francesco Chiappelli</bold>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Citation: </bold>Fotovat <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Bioinformation 20(11):1529-1531(2024)</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN3" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Declaration on Publication Ethics:</bold> The author's state that they adhere with COPE guidelines on publishing ethics as described elsewhere at https://publicationethics.org/.
The authors also undertake that they are not associated with any other third party (governmental or non-governmental agencies) linking with any form of unethical issues connecting to this publication. The authors also declare
that they are not withholding any information that is misleading to the publisher in regard to this article.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN4" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Declaration on official E-mail: </bold> The corresponding author declares that official e-mail from their institution is not available for all authors.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN5" fn-type="other"><p><bold>License statement: </bold> This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
credited. This is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN6" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Comments from readers: </bold> Articles published in BIOINFORMATION are open for relevant post publication comments and criticisms, which will be published immediately linking to
the original article without open access charges. Comments should be concise, coherent and critical in less than 1000 words.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN7" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Bioinformation Impact Factor:</bold>Impact Factor (Clarivate Inc 2023 release) for BIOINFORMATION is 1.9 with 2,198 citations from 2020 to 2022 taken for IF calculations.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN8" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold>The views and opinions expressed are those of the author(s) and do not reflect the views or opinions of Bioinformation and (or) its publisher Biomedical Informatics. Biomedical Informatics
remains neutral and allows authors to specify their address and affiliation details including territory where required. Bioinformation provides a platform for scholarly communication of data and information to create knowledge in the Biological/Biomedical
domain.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/life-expectancy.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/life-expectancy.htm</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano-López</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martín-Antonio</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cells. </source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2562</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34685542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cells10102562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8533838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>BMC Cardiovasc Disord. </source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>227</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28830367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12872-017-0653-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5568367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther. </source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>239</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37291105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41392-023-01502-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10248351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Front Immunol. </source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>579972</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33262758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2020.579972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7688519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Nutr. </source><year>2020</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>663</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31758189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jn/nxz268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7317613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Lancet. </source><year>2016</year><volume>387</volume><fpage>2145</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26520231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)00516-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4848186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saliminejad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Cell Physiol. </source><year>2019</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>5451</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30471116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jcp.27486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Surapaneni</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Sci Rep. </source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>17954</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33087811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-020-74847-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7578795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Nat Commun. </source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1145</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23093182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ncomms2146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3493648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis-Dusenbery</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genes Cancer. </source><year>2010</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1100</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21533017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1947601910396213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3083114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/t-cell" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/t-cell</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Annu Rev Immunol. </source><year>2021</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>51</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33428453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-immunol-061020-053702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Immun Ageing. </source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>24</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31528179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12979-019-0165-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6739976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiappelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><source>Permafrost Immunity. </source><year>2024</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Nova</publisher-name><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.52305/MLDQ0655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Aging Cell. </source><year>2022</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>e13671</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35822239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/acel.13671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9381902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Arthritis Res. </source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>S197</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12110140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/ar557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3240133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther. </source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>200</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37179335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41392-023-01451-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10182360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soto-Heredero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Annu Rev Immunol. </source><year>2023</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>181</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37126417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-immunol-101721-064501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Oncotarget. </source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>32295</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26452135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.6025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4741685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurosaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat Rev Immunol. </source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37400644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41577-023-00897-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Geroscience. </source><year>2021</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>593</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32974878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11357-020-00269-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8110643</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>