<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="brief-report" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Public Health Pract (Oxf)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Public Health Pract (Oxf)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4289</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">puhip</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Public Health in Practice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-5352</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12768953</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12768953.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12768953</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12768953</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41502583</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhip.2025.100696</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-5352(25)00115-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100696</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Short Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A short version of the post-COVID-19 condition stigma questionnaire</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rourke</surname><given-names initials="L">Liam</given-names></name><email>liam.rourke@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Damant</surname><given-names initials="R">Ronald</given-names></name><email>ronald.damant@ualberta.ca</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>15-757 Orwell Street, North Vancouver, British Columbia, V7J 3K6, Canada</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. <email>liam.rourke@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Both authors contributed equally to the manuscript.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503892</issue-id><elocation-id>100696</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-08 09:25:13.073"><day>08</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>The purpose of this study was to develop a short version of the 40-item Post-COVID-19 Condition Stigma Questionnaire (PCCSQ) while preserving its factor structure, reliability, and validity. The PCCSQ is a sound tool for assessing the discrimination experienced by people with a diagnosis of long covid, but a shorter version would be less demanding of respondents experiencing fatigue and brain fog and easier for clinicians and researchers to administer.</p></sec><sec><title>Study design</title><p>This was an observational study.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>From the original 40-items measuring the 6-factor construct <italic toggle="yes">long covid stigma</italic>, we assembled 12 items that represented the factors and discriminated among participants with high and low levels of stigma. We administered the shorter questionnaire to 99 long covid patients and assessed several of its measurement properties.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The 12-item instrument maintains the 6-factor structure of long covid stigma, has a mean discrimination index of 0.40 (sd = 0.08; range 0.22–0.48), an internal consistency of α = 0.89, a split-half reliability of 0.86, and it correlates predictably with theoretically-related variables.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The PCCSQ-12 is a feasible, reliable and valid means of assessing patients’ experience of long covid stigma.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Health-related stigma</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Post-COVID-19 Condition</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Health-related stigma is the labeling, stereotyping, othering, and discrimination of people with diagnoses and symptoms of various health conditions. These conditions include mental health concerns [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], HIV [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], lung cancer [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and others. Most recently, it has been experienced by people with post-COVID-19 condition or <italic toggle="yes">long covid</italic> [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</p><p id="p0015">An early survey of people with long covid [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] found that nearly 80 % of respondents experienced stigma <italic toggle="yes">often</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">always</italic>. Most often they experienced <italic toggle="yes">anticipated stigma</italic>, operationalized with questionnaire items such as, “I worry that people will judge me negatively when they learn I have long covid.” They also experienced <italic toggle="yes">internalized stigma</italic>, which was operationalized with items such as “I feel that I have been tainted by long covid and have less value than others”. Respondents also reported <italic toggle="yes">enacted stigma</italic>, defined as direct overt experiences of discrimination.</p><p id="p0020">As this data was being gathered in the United Kingdom, we were engaged in a similar project in Canada [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. We too found that participants agreed with questionnaire items that portrayed experiences of stereotyping, social and physical isolation, and self-stigma. We also demonstrated relationships between participants’ scores on our <italic toggle="yes">post-COVID-19 Condition Stigma Questionnaire</italic> (PCCSQ) and symptoms, functional status, and health-related quality of life.</p><p id="p0025">The PCCSQ consists of 40-items representing 6 dimensions of long covid stigma (negative self-image, social isolation, disclosure concerns, fear of PCC, COVID-19 stereotyping, and concerns with public attitudes), This is considerably more items than other instruments use to measure health related stigmas. The HIV Stigma Questionnaire [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], for instance, which is the template for many subsequent stigma questionnaires, measures its construct reliably and validly with 12 items. Superfluous items are a particular concern with our population whose most common symptoms include difficulties concentrating, memory loss, and tiredness [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Excessively lengthy instruments are also a burden for health researchers whose studies often include multiple instruments [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], with each increasing the strain on recruitment and analysis. Irrespective of these concerns, researchers consistently find that longer questionnaires are associated with diminished response quality [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p id="p0030">The purpose of this study was to shorten the PCCSQ while maintaining its factor structure, reliability, and validity.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><p id="p0035">This study drew on a set of data and analyses conducted during our development of the 40-item PCCSQ. The data was gathered from a convenience sample of 145 patients recruited from a long covid clinic in Alberta Canada. Their mean age was 48.2 (sd = 12.2), and 66.2 % identified as female. One-hundred and eight (74.5 %) were white; 28 (19.3 %) were non-white, non-indigenous; 8 (5.5 %) identified as Indigenous (First Nations/Inuit/Metis). Body Mass Index (BMI) ranged from 18.3 to 60.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, with a mean (SD) of 31.7 (8.3).A full description of that project is available [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. To build a 12-item version of the questionnaire, we.<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>●</label><p id="p0040">Calculated a discrimination index for all 40 items and selected two from each factor that most clearly discriminated between respondents with high (upper third) and low (lower third) stigma scores.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>●</label><p id="p0045">Assembled these items into a 12-item version of the questionnaire (PCCSQ-12):<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>1.</label><p id="p0050">Most people are uncomfortable around someone with my health problems.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>2.</label><p id="p0055">Stereotypes about people with my health problems are true.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>3.</label><p id="p0060">I worry that people will discriminate against me because of my health problems.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0025"><label>4.</label><p id="p0065">I have been hurt by how people react to my health problems.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0030"><label>5.</label><p id="p0070">In general, telling someone about my health problems is a mistake.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0035"><label>6.</label><p id="p0075">People don't want their children to be around me because of my health problems.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0040"><label>7.</label><p id="p0080">I have stopped socializing with some people because of my health problems.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0045"><label>8.</label><p id="p0085">People seem afraid of me once they learn about my health problems.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0050"><label>9.</label><p id="p0090">People are afraid of someone who has post-acute or long COVID-19 (recovered from the acute COVID-19 infection, no longer on isolation, persistent non-infectious health problems).</p></list-item><list-item id="o0055"><label>10.</label><p id="p0095">People treat me like I have an infectious (contagious) disease.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0060"><label>11.</label><p id="p0100">I feel isolated from the rest of the world because of my health problems.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0065"><label>12.</label><p id="p0105">Telling someone about my health problems is risky.</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0110">(Responses are registered with a 5-point Likert-style scale anchored at either end by <italic toggle="yes">Disagree strongly</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Agree strongly.</italic>)<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015"><list-item id="u0020"><label>●</label><p id="p0115">Administered the PCCSQ-12 to 99 participants from the original study (1.6 years after the initial administration), and from their responses, calculated a total stigma score (TSS-12), Cronbach's alpha, split-half reliability, and correlations between TSS-12 and seven health variables theoretically-related to the long covid stigma. These variables (and the instruments used to measure them) were: post-COVID-19 functional status (post-COVID-19 functional status scale), depression, anxiety, and number of symptoms (Edmonton Symptom Assessment Scale-Revised), symptom burden (participants' ratings of the ESAS items on a visual analogue scale), and health-related quality of life (Patient Health Questionnaire-9 and EQ 5D5L).</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p id="p0120">The mean of the discrimination indices for all 12 items was 0.40 (sd = 0.08; range 0.22–0.48). Discrimination indices of 0.40 and above are generally considered to discriminate effectively between groups.</p><p id="p0125">The internal consistency of the scale was evaluated using Cronbach's alpha, which yielded a coefficient of α = 0.89. This indicates a high level of internal consistency among the items. The split-half reliability for the questionnaire was 0.86 indicating a strong positive relationship between the two halves.</p><p id="p0130">Correlations between the PCCSQ-12 and theoretically-relevant variables ranged from r = 0.40 to r = 0.73, all of which were significant p &lt; 0.001: Post-COVID-19 Functional Status r = 0.59, p &lt; 0.001; number of symptoms r = 0.60, p &lt; 0.001, symptom burden r = 0.63, p &lt; 0.001, ESAS-r depression r = 0.45, p &lt; 0.001, ESAS-r anxiety r = 0.40, p &lt; 0.001; PHQ-9 r = 0.42, p &lt; 0.001; EQ 5D5L r = 0.73, p &lt; 0.001.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0135">The purpose of this study was to build a version of the PCCSQ that is less demanding on respondents and easier for clinicians and researchers to administer. The PCCSQ-12 is 70 % shorter than the original instrument; yet it maintains the latent six-factor structure of long covid stigma and yields estimates of respondents’ experiences that, provisionally, are reliable and valid.</p><p id="p0140">Our findings are similar to those of others who have shortened questionnaires designed to measure various forms of health related stigma. Shortened versions of the HIV-Stigma Questionnaire and the Lung Cancer Stigma Scale have psychometric properties comparable to their originals’, and they have increased the volume of research on both forms of health-related stigma.</p><p id="p0145">Our conclusions about the reliability and validity of the PCCSQ-12 derive from its use with one convenience sample of volunteers, so they are limited. Successive administrations would support or contradict our assessment of the soundness of interpretations that arise from participants’ responses.</p><p id="p0150">Regarding suggestions for practice and research, we point to the strong relationship between the PCCSQ-12, health outcomes, and general well-being. Administering the questionnaire more widely could produce insights into the confounding biomedical phenomena of long covid and into the broader social phenomenon of stigma.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Ethical statement</title><p id="p0155">The protocol for our original research and follow up studies were approved by the University of Alberta Research Ethics Board (Pro 00107350).</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0160">The authors wish to acknowledge the Long COVID Web for its role in supporting the completion of this Research Project. The Long COVID Web is funded by the <funding-source id="gs1">Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</funding-source> grant #<award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">185352</award-id>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0165">We declare that we have no conflicts of interest related to this research, including any financial, professional, or personal affiliations that could influence the collection, analysis, or reporting of data. We commit to maintaining transparency and adhering to institutional policies for the management of conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurung</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subedi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohrt</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahid</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornicroft</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gronholm</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a mental health-related structural stigma measurement framework in the healthcare system setting: a modified Delphi study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025 Jan 31</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0316999</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0316999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11785284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39888878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donastorg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karver</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galai</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibinga</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrington</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerrigan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal analysis of the role of mindfulness on HIV stigma, depression, substance use and HIV outcomes among female sex workers living with HIV in the Dominican Republic</article-title><source>AIDS Care</source><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025 Jan 2</year><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39652821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09540121.2024.2437695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11783368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brymwitt</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter-Bawa</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emard</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omachi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tefera</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mindful self-compassion for lung cancer (MSC-LC): incorporating perspectives of lung cancer patients, clinicians, and researchers to create an adapted intervention to reduce lung cancer stigma</article-title><source>Transl. Behav. Med.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025 Jan</year><comment>ibae074</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/tbm/ibae074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11770822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39868945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Damant</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rourke</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>G.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuhr</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varughese</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laratta</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>E.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reliability and validity of the post COVID-19 condition stigma questionnaire: a prospective cohort study</article-title><source>eClinicalMedicine</source><volume>55</volume><year>2023 Jan 1</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9694932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36447641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pantelic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziauddeen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Hara</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alwan</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long Covid stigma: estimating burden and validating scale in a UK-based sample</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>17</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2022 Nov 23</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0277317</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0277317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9683629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36417364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrans</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lashley</surname><given-names>F.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring stigma in people with HIV: psychometric assessment of the HIV stigma scale</article-title><source>Res. Nurs. Health</source><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2001 Dec</year><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11746080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/nur.10011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Public Health Agency of Canada</collab></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 condition (long Covid)</article-title><comment>Retrieved, November 25 2024 from</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/diseases/2019-novel-coronavirus-infection/symptoms/post-covid-19-condition.html" id="intref0010">https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/diseases/2019-novel-coronavirus-infection/symptoms/post-covid-19-condition.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holtom</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baruch</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguinis</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>A Ballinger</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survey response rates: trends and a validity assessment framework</article-title><source>Hum. Relat.</source><volume>75</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2022 Aug</year><fpage>1560</fpage><lpage>1584</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sammut</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griscti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies to improve response rates to web surveys: a literature review</article-title><source>Int. J. Nurs. Stud.</source><volume>123</volume><year>2021 Nov 1</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104058</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2021.104058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34454334</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>