<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ERJ Open Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ERJ Open Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3083</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">erjor</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ERJOR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ERJ Open Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2312-0541</issn><publisher><publisher-name>European Respiratory Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12134929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12134929.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12134929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12134929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40470145</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00769-2024</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00769-2024</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original research article</subject><subj-group><subject>Long COVID</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>4</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long COVID-19 and longer sick leave: longitudinal study of economically active patients</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallo González</surname><given-names initials="V">Virginia</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8858-1070</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>López-Padilla</surname><given-names initials="D">Daniel</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4543-573X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>de Miguel Díez</surname><given-names initials="J">Javier</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suárez Escudero</surname><given-names initials="S">Sergio</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ojeda Castillejo</surname><given-names initials="E">Elena</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1086-4131</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zichen</given-names></name><xref rid="af3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8501-0117</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Puente Maestu</surname><given-names initials="L">Luis</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label>Respiratory Department, Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón, Madrid, Spain</aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Avenida Complutense, Madrid, Spain</aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label>Instituto de Investigación Sanitaria Gregorio Marañón, Madrid, Spain</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Daniel López-Padilla (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="lopez.padilla84@gmail.com">lopez.padilla84@gmail.com</email>)
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">488021</issue-id><elocation-id>00769-2024</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-05 11:25:42.047"><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©The authors 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This version is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence 4.0. For commercial reproduction rights and permissions contact <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:permissions@ersnet.org">permissions@ersnet.org</email></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="00769-2024.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Sick leave was one of the numerous consequences of the COVID-19 pandemic. Given the relevance of occupational status for any individual, the aim of the study was to evaluate the impact of persistent symptoms after active infection and determine factors associated with longer sick leaves (LSLs).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This observational study focused on economically active patients attending a post-COVID outpatient clinic for persistence of symptoms or radiological alterations after active infection. The LSL temporal cut-off point was defined by the third tertile of total leave days. Median leave time was compared with the optimal sick leave time for any other viral pneumonia, estimated by the local Ministry of Employment. To determine factors associated with LSL, multivariate models were ultilised.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 248 patients were included. The median sick leave time for the entire population was 53 days (interquartile range (IQR) 37.0–126.5), global sum of 30 169 days; the median optimal sick leave time was 21.9 days (IQR 19.7–25.9) (p&lt;0.05). The third tertile cut-off point for LSL was 83 days and multivariate analysis showed a significant association with dyspnoea (OR 3.26, 95% CI 1.59–6.70, p=0.0001), while physical exercise of at least 10 min·day<sup>−1</sup> was significantly associated with shorter sick leave durations (OR 0.45, 95% CI 0.20–0.98, p=0.04).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>COVID-19 sick leave was considerably longer than that stipulated for nonsevere acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 viral pneumonia. Long-COVID syndrome, especially dyspnoea, seems to be a very present factor in these patients’ inability to work.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="short" id="abstract-1"><title id="title-1">Shareable abstract</title><p><bold>COVID-19 sick leave is considerably longer than that for any other viral pneumonia. Long-COVID respiratory symptoms such as dyspnoea or chest pain may be associated with longer sick leave, whereas daily exercise may reduce it.</bold>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://bit.ly/4fvcbiz" ext-link-type="uri">https://bit.ly/4fvcbiz</ext-link></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>On 11 March 2020, the World Health Organization declared a global pandemic of a new disease known as coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). It initially led to an exponential rise in cases in China, followed by global spread from December 2019 onward [<xref rid="C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It was originally considered to be a respiratory disease, as the main organ affected was the lung [<xref rid="C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]; however, it is now recognised as a multisystemic disease with various clinical manifestations [<xref rid="C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Most cases were mild, although about 15% of patients required hospital admission due to the development of respiratory failure, among other organ damage, and up to 5% of patients developed acute respiratory distress syndrome requiring admission to intensive care units (ICUs) [<xref rid="C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–<xref rid="C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. These percentages gradually decreased thanks to lower virulence and vaccination.</p><p>Despite the high mortality of patients who developed the most severe forms of the disease, many progressively improved until their complete recovery shortly after discharge, while some presented sequelae in one or more organs [<xref rid="C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This sequelae syndrome has received different names, including post-COVID-19 condition and long-COVID [<xref rid="C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This condition affects at least 10–30% of people who test positive [<xref rid="C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], some having 20 or more different symptoms [<xref rid="C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In this way, the pandemic has had a health, economic and social impact without recent precedent [<xref rid="C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], with returning to work also being affected.</p><p>The objective was to evaluate the occupational impact of persistent symptoms after a COVID-19 infection in an economically active population in terms of sick leave time and determine the factors associated with longer sick leave (LSL).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methodology</title><p>A longitudinal study was conducted in patients infected with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), starting from their first visit to a post-COVID-19 outpatient clinic of a tertiary hospital following hospitalisation or active infection. Enrolment started on 1 July 2020 and ended on 28 September 2021. This outpatient clinic was established in mid-2020 between the first and second waves of the pandemic in Spain, and followed a multidisciplinary protocol leaded by pulmonologists, including visits every 3–6 months according to the patients’ characteristics, which included a thorough anamnesis and respiratory functional and/or radiological tests if considered appropriate. This protocol is summarised in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref> and is based on those proposed by the British Thoracic Society [<xref rid="C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and the Spanish Society of Pneumology and Thoracic Surgery [<xref rid="C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], adapted to our centre resources at the time. For the main objective of our study, follow-up ended when sick leave was terminated. However, most patients continued attending the outpatient clinic until their symptoms were reasonably stable or resolved and no further radiological or functional tests were needed. The inclusion criteria were as follows: 1) over 18 years old; 2) persistent respiratory symptoms after active infection, treated on an outpatient or inpatient basis; and 3) persistent radiological alteration after active infection. The exclusion criteria were 1) retired patients, 2) students and 3) individuals with permanent work disability prior to COVID-19 infection. Patients provided informed consent and the study protocol was approved by the local ethics committee (record 02/2021, 22 February 2021).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Post-COVID-19 outpatient clinic protocol and dates of enrolment, follow-up and study termination. <sup>#</sup>: With or without hospitalisation. <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>LCO</sub>: diffusing capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide; <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>CO</sub>: transfer coefficient of the lung for carbon monoxide; CT: computed tomography.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="00769-2024.01.jpg"/></fig><p>The outcome variable was LSL and, to determine its temporal cut-off point, the study population was divided into tertiles. LSL was considered for the third tertile, as it corresponded almost exactly to a 12-week period after hospital discharge or active infection, which was also in line with a cut-off point for long-COVID sequelae [<xref rid="C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Demographic variables collected included sex assigned at birth, age and body mass index. Medical history and cardiovascular risk factors included high blood pressure, dyslipidaemia, diabetes, asthma, obstructive sleep apnoea, COPD, ischaemic heart disease and heart failure. Regarding hospital admission, the date of admission, date of discharge and ICU admission were recorded. Clinical variables at the time of admission were recorded dichotomously, including the following: dyspnoea, temperature, desaturation by pulse oximetry ≤93% in patients ≤50 years and ≤90% in patients over 50 years. Continuous quantitative analytical variables included neutrophils, lymphocytes, platelets, fibrinogen, D-dimer, alanine aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase, bilirubin, lactate dehydrogenase, creatinine, ferritin, C-reactive protein and interleukin-6. Radiological variables included unilateral or bilateral pneumonia. Therapeutic variables included lopinavir/ritonavir, hydroxychloroquine, azithromycin, interferon beta, tocilizumab, anakinra, remdesivir, corticosteroids, antibiotics and type of respiratory support received (conventional oxygen therapy, high-flow therapy with nasal cannula, continuous positive airway pressure, bi-level positive airway pressure and invasive mechanical ventilation). The same analytical variables were also collected at hospital discharge.</p><p>From the follow-up, the most commonly described symptoms of long COVID-19, defined as “a condition that occurs in individuals with a history of probable or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, generally three months after the initial infection, with symptoms that last at least two months and cannot be explained by an alternative diagnosis” [<xref rid="C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], were collected dichotomously in the first evaluation after active infection and/or hospital discharge and included dyspnoea, cough, expectoration, chest pain, asthenia, haemoptysis, orthopnoea, fever, weight loss, mobility alterations, sensory alterations, voice alterations, swallowing alterations, dermatological lesions, hair loss, sleep alterations, cognitive alterations, mood alterations, headaches and arthralgia. With the hypothesis that daily exercise could be associated with a faster recovery, information was also collected dichotomously from those patients who exercised for at least 10 min·day<sup>−1</sup>. Given that the lungs are the most frequently affected organ by COVID-19 and that the sequelae of this disease may include debilitating respiratory symptoms, we consider that physical activity could be a beneficial factor in a potentially chronic respiratory disease.</p><p>Date of medical discharge from primary care, which marks the sick leave, was extracted from the common database of the Community of Madrid (HORUS). Optimal sick leave (OSL) time was estimated following the indications of the 4th edition of the <italic toggle="yes">Manual of Optimal Times of Temporary Disability</italic> of the National Social Security Institute of the Spanish Ministry of Employment and Social Security under code J12, corresponding to “Viral pneumonia, not classified elsewhere”, with correction factors for age, sex and occupation [<xref rid="C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Regarding the correction factor for job occupation, all patients were considered in group 15, corresponding to “Unskilled workers in services (except transportation)”, which generates a correction factor with more sick leave time. Although time off work begins at the day of hospital admission, sick leave time elapsed from hospital discharge was also estimated in those patients who were admitted. Personal history, as well as the rest of the medical data on admission, follow-up and results of complementary tests, were collected.</p><p>Statistical analysis was performed with the STATA 16.1 program (STATACorp LLC, Texas). Qualitative variables are presented as absolute frequencies and percentages, and quantitative variables as means±<sc>sd</sc>, ranges, medians or interquartile ranges (IQRs) according to their distribution evaluated with the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test. The difference between dichotomous characteristics was analysed with the chi-square test with Fisher's exact correction. Quantitative variables were analysed using the <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test for independent samples or the Mann–Whitney U test if the samples were normally distributed or not, respectively. The Wilcoxon test was used to compare the medians of sick leave time following hospital discharge or active infection and the OSL. To determine the association of the independent variables with LSL, a multivariate logistic regression model was developed including variables with a p-value less than 0.20 in the univariate analysis of the sociodemographic variables, medical history and the symptoms referred to in the first post-COVID follow-up, and those variables considered relevant by the investigators. ICU admission was excluded from the model due to its foreseeable influence on the increase in the time of both hospital admission and the added time off work in the recovery phase upon discharge, considered as the component of functional myopathy. The magnitude of association is presented as an odds ratio with its 95% confidence interval. A p-value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p><p>A subanalysis was performed on the patients included in the study according to the need for hospital admission. Finally, multivariate Bayesian proportional hazard analysis was performed with 12 500 iterations using Markov chain Monte Carlo sampling with default prior distributions to determine the association of factors to time off work. The magnitude of association is presented as a hazard ratio (HR) with its 95% credibility interval.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 248 patients were included, with a mean age of 52.6±10.2 years, of whom 132 were men (53.2%). The patient flowchart is presented in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>. The most common cardiovascular risk factors were obesity (98 patients, 39.5%) and high blood pressure (72 patients, 29.0%). A total of 209 patients (84.3%) required hospital admission and 48 patients (19.4%) required ICU admission. The median real time off work was 53 days (IQR 37.0–126.5), with a global total of 30 169 days. According to the study groups proposed by tertiles, 84 patients (33.9%) presented LSL of at least 83 days. <xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents the sociodemographic characteristics and medical history of the population depending on the duration of sick leave.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Flowchart of patients attended in a post-COVID-19 outpatient clinic. ICU: intensive care unit.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="00769-2024.02.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="TB1" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Sociodemographic characteristics and medical history of patients seen in a post-COVID-19 consultation, according to the temporary duration of their sick leave</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total n=248</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First tertile (≤43 days) n=86</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second tertile (≥44–82 days) n=78</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third tertile (≥83 days) n=84</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age, mean±<sc>sd</sc> years</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3±10.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.4±11.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0±10.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.5±8.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sex, men (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (53.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (51.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (61.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (47.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Obesity, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (39.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (36.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (37.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (45.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Body mass index, mean±<sc>sd</sc> kg·m<sup>−2</sup></bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0±6.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5±7.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5±5.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0±6.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Arterial hypertension, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (29.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (25.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (35.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (26.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dyslipidaemia, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (23.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (20.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (24.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (23.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Asthma, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (12.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (14.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (19.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diabetes, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (10.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (11.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (11.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Obstructive sleep apnoea, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (6.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (7.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (7.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ischaemic heart disease, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Heart failure, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>COPD, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5,1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hospitalisation, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209 (84.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (86.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (80.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (85.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hospitalisation in intensive care unit, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (19.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (12.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (36.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Median OSL time, corrected for sex, age and occupation, was 21.9 days (IQR 19.7–25.9) and the median time off work since hospital discharge or active infection onset for patients not admitted to hospital was 42 days (IQR 27.0–119.8). For hospitalised patients, median sick leave was 51 days since admission (IQR 37.5–130) and 40 days since discharge (IQR 27–127.5), while sick leave for nonadmitted patients was 56 days (IQR 37–113). Statistically significant differences were found when comparing the medians of real time with OSL (p=0.001), as well as time since hospital discharge or active infection with OSL (p=0.001). No differences were found between the sick leave durations of admitted and nonadmitted patients (Mann–Whitney U test, p=0.98). <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> presents the number of days of sick leave and the frequency of patients.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Frequency of post-COVID-19 patients and their sick leave days. The green dotted line shows the optimal sick leave time stipulated by the local Ministry of Employment in the worst-case scenario for viral pneumonia.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="00769-2024.03.jpg"/></fig><p>The median time elapsed until the first assessment in the post-COVID consultation follow-up was 87 days (IQR 49.2–142.0). In this consultation, it was documented that 225 patients (90.7%) had at least one symptom that had lasted for more than 8 weeks after 3 months of active infection, compatible with the definition of long COVID. In this consultation, the average number of symptoms reported was 3.5±2.4 and the most frequent were dyspnoea (144 patients, 58%), asthenia (133 patients, 53.6%), weight loss (109 patients, 44%), sleep disturbances (79 patients, 31.9%) and hair loss (78 patients, 31.5%). Of note, other symptoms such as mood disturbances (43%) or chest pain (41%) were frequent in the LSL tertile group. The rest of the symptoms and their distribution according to the tertiles of time off work are presented in <xref rid="TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>. In the 109 patients who lost weight, a statistically significant difference was observed according to the study groups, such that the third tertile, on LSL, had lost an average of 7.4±6.0 kg, greater than the loss of the first tertile (5.2±3.9 kg) and that of the second (4.6±3.7 kg) (Kruskal–Wallis test, p&lt;0.03).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TB2" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Symptoms reported by patients seen for the first time in a post-COVID-19 consultation, after hospital discharge or active infection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptoms and characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total n=248</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First tertile (≤43 days) n=86</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second tertile (≥44–82 days) n=78</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third tertile (≥83 days) n=84</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dyspnoea, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (58.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (40.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (52.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (81.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cough, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (17.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (12.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (12.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (26.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Expectoration, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (10.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (9.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (15.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Haemoptysis, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Chest pain, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (24.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (16.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (16.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (41.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Orthopnoea, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (4.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (7.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Fever, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Asthenia, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (53.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (43.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (44.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (72.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Weight loss, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (44.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (39.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (42.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (50.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mobility disorders, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (4.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (9.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Paraesthesia, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (15.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (11.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (25.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Voice alterations, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (6.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (10.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Swallowing disorders, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Exanthema, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (5.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hair loss, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (31.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (25.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (26.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (41.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sleep disturbances, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (31.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (25.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (26.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (42.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Deterioration of cognitive abilities, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (16.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (15.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (27.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mood disturbance, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (26.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (19.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (16.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (42.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number of symptoms, mean±<sc>sd</sc></bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5±2.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6±2.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9±1.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1±2.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Arthralgias, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (3.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Headache, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (5.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Physical inactivity, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188 (75.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (72.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (69.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (85.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Multivariate analysis revealed that the factor most associated with LSL was the symptom of dyspnoea reported in the first post-COVID consultation (OR 3.26, 95% CI 1.59–6.70, p=0.0001). On the other hand, physical exercise of at least 10 min·day<sup>−1</sup> was significantly associated with shorter sick leave (OR 0.45, 95% CI 0.20–0.98, p=0.04) (<xref rid="TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). The mean time spent exercising for the entire study population was 40.4±38.6 min.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TB3" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Multivariate analysis by binary logistic regression of factors associated with longer sick leave of patients evaluated in a post-COVID-19 consultation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate analysis (OR)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidence interval</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate analysis (OR)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidence interval</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Men</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42–1.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27–1.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02–1.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99–1.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Obesity</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84–2.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58–2.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Asthma</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03–4.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63–3.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dyspnoea</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63–9.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59–6.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Asthenia</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92–5.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04–3.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Chest pain</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89–6.29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01–3.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hair loss</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15–3.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02–4.55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sleep disturbances</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21–3.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53–2.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mood disturbance</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86–6.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70–3.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Daily physical exercise</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30–0.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20–0.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Arterial hypertension</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45–1.46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dyslipidaemia</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58–1.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diabetes</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54–2.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Obstructive sleep apnoea</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42–3.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hospitalisation</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57–2.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Variables included in the multivariate analysis: sex (men), age, obesity, asthma, dyspnoea, asthenia, chest pain, hair loss, sleep disturbances, mood disturbance and daily physical exercise of at least 10 min·day<sup>−1</sup>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s3a"><title>Subgroup analysis</title><p>In the subgroup of 209 patients requiring hospital admission, a statistically significant association was found between age (p=0.004), asthma (p=0.04), duration of hospitalisation (p=0.0001) and LSL. <xref rid="TB4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> presents the characteristics and medical history of these patients. No laboratory results at the time of hospital admission were significantly associated with LSL, whereas severe respiratory failure and bilateral pneumonia were (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00769-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table 1</ext-link>). When the symptoms reported in the first consultation after admission were analysed, except for cough, hair loss, sleep and voice disturbances, the same results of the association of factors with LSL were replicated in the entire study group (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00769-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table 2</ext-link>). Therapeutic features such as high-flow nasal cannula or tocilizumab were significantly associated with LSL (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00769-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table 3</ext-link>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TB4" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Sociodemographic characteristics and medical history of patients seen in a post-COVID-19 consultation who required hospitalisation, according to the duration of their sick leave</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total N=209</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First tertile (≤43 days) n=74</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second tertile (≥44–82 days) n=63</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third tertile (≥83 days) n=72</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age, mean±<sc>sd</sc> years</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.6<bold>±</bold>10.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5<bold>±</bold>11.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.3<bold>±</bold>10.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.2<bold>±</bold>7.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sex, men (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (57.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (58.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (63.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (31.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Obesity, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (42.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (39.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (41.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (47.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Body mass index, mean±<sc>sd</sc> kg·m<sup>−2</sup></bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4<bold>±</bold>5.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.7<bold>±</bold>5.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.1<bold>±</bold>5.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4<bold>±</bold>6.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Arterial hypertension, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (30.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (24.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (39.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (27.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dyslipidaemia, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (23.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (20.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (25.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (25.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Asthma, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (12.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (13.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (7.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (19.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diabetes, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (11.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (9.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (11.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (12.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Obstructive sleep apnoea, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (6.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (8.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ischaemic heart disease, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Heart failure, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>COPD, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Days of hospital admission, median (IQR)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (7–17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (6.8–11.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (7.0–16.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 (11.0–35.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IQR: interquartile range.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Proportionally, more women and more patients who reported the symptom of dyspnoea were observed in the subgroup of patients who did not have to be admitted (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00769-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table 4</ext-link>). Finally, the Bayesian multivariate analysis determined the probability that younger age, obesity, asthma, symptoms of dyspnoea and asthenia reported in the first post-COVID evaluation were associated with LSL (<xref rid="TB5" ref-type="table">table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TB5" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 5</label><caption><p>Parametric Bayesian proportional hazards analysis of factors associated with longer sick leave of patients evaluated in a post-COVID-19 consultation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazard ratio</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% credibility interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Men</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70–1.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96–0.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Obesity</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05–1.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Asthma</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06–1.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dyspnoea</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50–2.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Asthenia</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01–1.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Chest pain</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87–1.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hair loss</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83–1.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sleep disturbances</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88–1.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mood disturbance</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92–1.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Daily physical exercise</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70–1.16</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The median sick leave time due to COVID-19 almost doubled the longest optimal time proposed for any other viral pneumonia, regardless of hospital admission. In fact, the median sick leave for the subgroup of patients not requiring hospitalisation was close to three times that of the OSL time. Additionally, long-COVID symptoms such as dyspnoea, asthenia, chest pain and hair loss were significantly associated with LSL. On the other hand, physical activity was associated with a reduction in LSL.</p><p>These findings are in line with other population studies, which determined that the duration of COVID-19 sick leave was longer than other infections plausibly of viral aetiology with flu-like symptoms [<xref rid="C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. For practical purposes, factors associated with LSL could be divided into two groups, namely sociodemographic factors (age and sex) and medical history (asthma, obesity), and a second group of long-COVID symptoms.</p><p>Older age has been described as a factor associated with LSL due to COVID-19 [<xref rid="C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In our series, older age was associated with longer sick leaves in the univariate analysis, but not in the multivariate one by a very narrow margin. This might be due to the fact that a good proportion of the patients in our study were from the first and second waves of COVID-19 and presented homogeneous data about their age, with a mean±<sc>sd</sc> age of 52±10 years and a difference of only 4 years between the 60th and 100th percentiles. This age is considerably lower than in another series from the city of Madrid, where the mean age was nearly 65 years [<xref rid="C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. This suggests an underrepresentation of older working-age individuals, who might have skewed the association measure more strongly towards the logical side: the older the patient, the greater the impact of the disease and, consequently, longer sick leave durations. The fact that age appeared as a protective factor in the Bayesian analysis is notable, but it should be noted that the confidence interval is very close to 1 and, in any case, the Bayesian analysis was not the primary analysis of the study but rather an exploratory one.</p><p>Regarding sex, discordant results are also found. Some studies have associated being a woman with LSL [<xref rid="C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], while other authors do not find such an association [<xref rid="C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], as in our sample. Regarding medical history, the pre-existence of lung diseases was significantly associated with LSL [<xref rid="C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In our series, the asthmatic population, almost 13% of the patients studied, a percentage representative of the global prevalence [<xref rid="C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], seemed to be at greater risk of LSL in the Bayesian analysis. It is possible that the overlap of post-COVID respiratory symptoms and asthma has played a role in prolonging this condition. Finally, obesity, a factor associated with poor clinical outcomes such as an increase in mortality [<xref rid="C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] or the probability of hospital admission because it is a more severe clinical condition compared to patients with normal weight [<xref rid="C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], was also associated with LSL in the Bayesian analysis. A similar result was found in a study carried out in Sweden on healthcare personnel in nursing homes not requiring hospitalisation [<xref rid="C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>One of the most important findings of our study was that the sick leave observed was longer than that documented in population-based studies from other countries, such as Sweden (35 days) [<xref rid="C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], the Netherlands (10 days) [<xref rid="C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and Germany (only 6% of patients with sick leaves longer than 4 weeks) [<xref rid="C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The fact that more than 80% of our population was hospitalised could explain this difference, but economic and cultural factors may have also played a decisive role. In Spain, the Social Security Service classified COVID-19 as an occupational accident starting on 10 March 2020, meaning that coverage began on day 0 of the infection, along with recognition of up to 75% of the worker's taxable salary. For healthcare professionals, it was recognised as an occupational disease in February 2021, which not only included the same characteristics of day 0 of the infection and 75% of the salary, but also allowed for retrospective claims if the illness was sufficiently well documented, along with other benefits such as a change in workplace or job duties due to disability caused by COVID-19 or its sequelae [<xref rid="C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In Sweden, the first 2 weeks of sick leave was paid by the employer, after which 60% of the salary was covered by the Swedish social insurance agency. Furthermore, it has been reported that guidelines for COVID-19 were vague due to a lack of knowledge of the prognosis of the disease [<xref rid="C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. All these factors could explain why Swedish workers returned to work sooner than the Spanish ones. The fact that there are significant differences compared to other populations whose social security systems were already generous before the pandemic could be explained by cultural differences. For example, the sick leave for COVID-19 in the Dutch population was 10 days, although it is possible that many patients from the first wave are not sufficiently represented in this study [<xref rid="C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In the Netherlands, employers must pay benefits to workers on sick leave for a period of 2 years at a statutory rate of 70% of the salary, with a maximum of 70% of the daily wage. In many collective labour agreements, this percentage is topped up to 90 or 100% of the salary or maximum daily wage during the first year of sick leave [<xref rid="C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>It is well known that population-based studies can present significant limitations. Selection bias, poor control of potential confounding variables and a lack of standardisation in error measurement are perhaps the most important ones [<xref rid="C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–<xref rid="C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Although our study focuses on a specific moment during the pandemic and is not large enough to be extrapolated to the general population, it included all patients who attended the outpatient clinic and met the inclusion criteria, including microbiological documentation of COVID-19. Population studies acknowledge the limitation of potentially including patients without confirmation of COVID-19 infection or direct comparators, such as influenza, as these studies often relied on clinical symptoms reported by patients due to the shortage of tests at the beginning of the pandemic [<xref rid="C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. It is also important to note that most of the patients in our study were hospitalised and we have detailed information about their clinical, analytical and radiological evolution, a variable not deeply studied in population-based studies and a major limitation recognised by others [<xref rid="C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Our study collected information obtained from a strict follow-up protocol and, while only the symptoms reported in the first consultation are presented, a follow-up was conducted to determine the duration and severity of these symptoms. Finally, since we had no more information than what was collected during the consultation, we decided to present not only the raw data on sick leave due to COVID-19 and its possible associated factors but also to consider the worst-case scenario of any other viral pneumonia recognised by the social security system. We compared this with COVID-19 to demonstrate the pandemic's significance and impact on the economically active population. To our knowledge, no other study has addressed this issue from this perspective, as others have compared COVID-19 sick leave with actual influenza sick leave or flu-like symptoms.</p><p>While it was no surprise that sicker patients who were hospitalised had LSL, we believe that one of the most interesting findings of our study was that sick leave from less severe patients, those who were not hospitalised, was not statistically different from admitted patients, despite this sick leave being calculated since hospital admission or discharge. Furthermore, hospitalisation was not associated with LSL in the univariate analysis and no significant differences were found in the number of symptoms reported by the two groups at their first visit to the outpatient clinic (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00769-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table 4</ext-link>). This addresses the fact that long-COVID symptoms are present not only in patients experiencing the most severe cases in need of hospital treatment, but also in those patients who were less sick during the active infection. In addition, we have demonstrated that these symptoms have a negative impact in their journey back to work. We can only speculate about this result, but we believe that the mandatory lockdown imposed by authorities during most of 2020 and a large part of 2021, which hindered a more favourable physical and mental recovery of nonhospitalised patients, as well as the respiratory and motor rehabilitation programmes that could have better prepared hospitalised patients, may have contributed to this finding. Regarding residual symptoms, there is little literature that associates them with LSL. More than 90% of the patients could fit the definition of long COVID and only a third of them were off sick for more than 12 weeks. This could indicate that a significant percentage of patients returned to work despite continuing to have symptoms. Among these symptoms, the impact of dyspnoea as a relevant disabling factor is predominant, as with other chronic respiratory diseases such as COPD or interstitial diseases. Dyspnoea has also been described in other studies as a symptom associated with LSL [<xref rid="C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], but others in our series, such as asthenia, chest pain and hair loss, have not been documented in other similar studies.</p><p>The role of vaccination in the pandemic is worth mentioning. There are studies associating the first two doses of vaccines with the probability of sick leave due to symptoms such as fever, asthenia or pain at the puncture site [<xref rid="C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Comparing the 1 or 2 days of these sick leaves to the median of almost 42 days in our sample, we take a stance in favour of vaccination as beneficial to society, not just from a health status point of view. Along these lines, the socioeconomic impact is notable not only for the direct and indirect costs that the pandemic entailed in terms of prevention and treatment of the disease, but also in the late return to work. Several articles refer to this long-COVID syndrome scenario and the impact it has had on the workplace. For example, in a longitudinal study of patients with long-COVID criteria, the percentage of people who were still on sick leave after a year of follow-up was practically unchanged, with 20.4% at the beginning of the study and 20.6% at the end of the year. In this study, of the sample analysed, about 27% were fired, had resigned or retired early due to long COVID. As a conclusion to these figures, they estimate that 47% of the sample presented income losses due to this cause [<xref rid="C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Somewhat lower are the figures obtained in a Swedish sample where the percentage of sick leave due to long COVID was 13.3% [<xref rid="C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The percentage of withdrawals recorded in a German study was much lower, with 5.8% of the entire sample [<xref rid="C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], more in line with that obtained in another Swedish study with 5.7% of withdrawals [<xref rid="C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>The benefit of physical activity has been described in various scenarios of respiratory pathology, such as its association with the reduction of mortality due to pneumonia in middle-aged and elderly patients [<xref rid="C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], which could fit with the profile included in the study. In our series, it was determined that those patients who performed at least 10 min·day<sup>−1</sup> of physical activity had a 55% lower probability of having LSL. Evidence of the positive effect of physiotherapy on dyspnoea in patients with long-COVID syndrome has already been described [<xref rid="C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The promotion of healthy habits, including physical activity, is more than justified, but it is worth mentioning that one of the great difficulties of this type of intervention is maintaining the adherence of the potential beneficiary over time.</p><p>The study has several limitations. Its observational nature and a sample size of only 248 patients might have led it to selection bias and loss of data that could overstate its conclusions. To counteract these limitations, the longest OSL time was considered for analysis and multivariate analyses were developed, including one with a Bayesian approach, but attention to all possible confounders is practically impossible. Another limitation is the possible collinearity between some of the variables analysed, especially between symptoms. In this sense, it is important to know that long COVID is a complex and dynamic scenario in which the pathophysiology of the symptoms that simulate respiratory involvement in patients with normal lung function or without manifest parenchymal alterations is still unknown. Regarding physical activity, we acknowledge that asking patients how many minutes per day they exercised was not the best way to address this issue. Some patients show a maladaptive response to exercise, whereas others might have presented reverse causality since those who fully recovered with shorter sick leaves could exercise more, rather than exercise reducing their sick leave duration. Most patients were included during the first waves of the pandemic, when the entire healthcare system collapsed, and we wanted to keep things simple. Nevertheless, we believe that promoting the message that healthy habits, such as daily physical activity, are beneficial for respiratory patients is well-intentioned, despite the potential for maladaptive responses in some individuals, which should be assessed by health professionals. Finally, detailed analysis was not carried out regarding the waves of the pandemic or vaccination status. During the collection and follow-up years, it could be inferred that patients from the first five waves were included, but less than 20% of the patients studied were infected in 2021, the year in which mass vaccination of the population began. Therefore, it is not considered that this would have significantly modified the results.</p><p>The paper also has strengths. It is one of the few studies that has analysed in more detail the presence of symptoms possibly framed in long COVID and analytical alterations with LSL, unlike other more population-based works. In this regard, respiratory symptoms were prevalent and rather debilitating to both admitted and nonadmitted patients, which highlights the socioeconomic impact of returning to work for every person affected by COVID-19 and not only to the most severe cases. We also want to point out that our study is specific to a post-COVID outpatient consultation in one of the hospitals most affected in the world by the pandemic during the first wave [<xref rid="C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and this represents the best of our efforts to accompany our patients throughout their recovery.</p><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5a"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Sick leave due to COVID-19 was considerably longer than that stipulated for non-SARS-CoV-2 viral pneumonia. To the direct impact of the health cost and the economic disaster caused by the need for isolation, the impact on the working life of the infected economically active population should also be added. A series of factors, such as age and obesity, seems to be associated with LSL, while physical activity is presented as a protective factor. Finally, long-COVID syndrome, with its constellation of symptoms, seems to be a very present factor in the inability of these patients to work.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="supplementary" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00769-2024.Supp1</object-id><p><bold>Please note:</bold> supplementary material is not edited by the Editorial Office, and is uploaded as it has been supplied by the author.</p><p>Supplementary material <inline-supplementary-material xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="SS1" xlink:href="00769-2024.SUPPLEMENT.pdf" content-type="local-data">00769-2024.SUPPLEMENT</inline-supplementary-material></p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>ChatGPT Plus was used for text formatting and correction to UK English. No other artificial intelligence interfaces were used for other purposes whatsoever.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p>Provenance: Submitted article, peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn><p>Ethics statement: The patients agreed to participate in the study by signing an informed consent document and the study protocol was approved by the institution's Ethics Committee (minutes recorded 22 February 2021).</p></fn><fn><p>Author contributions: Conception and design of the study: V. Gallo González and D. López-Padilla. Acquisition of data: V. Gallo González and S. Suárez Escudero. Analysis and interpretation of data: V. Gallo González, D. López-Padilla, J. de Miguel Díez and L. Puente Maestu. Drafting the article or revising it critically for important intellectual content: all authors. Final approval of the version to be submitted: All authors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflict of interest: The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="C1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="standard"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical management of severe acute respiratory infection (SARI) when COVID-19 disease is suspected: interim guidance, 13 March 2020</article-title>. <comment>Date last updated: 13 March 2020. Date last accessed: 15 July 2024</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/331446" ext-link-type="uri">https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/331446</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="standard"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Virtual press conference on COVID-19 – 11 March 2020</article-title>. <comment>Date last updated: 11 March 2020. Date last accessed: 16 July 2024</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/transcripts/who-audio-emergencies-coronavirus-press-conference-full-and-final-11mar2020.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/transcripts/who-audio-emergencies-coronavirus-press-conference-full-and-final-11mar2020.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rajkumar</surname></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Lung pathology in COVID-19: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int J Appl Basic Med Res</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>226</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijabmr.IJABMR_381_20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33376694</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7758785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname>
<given-names>ZY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>China medical treatment expert group for COVID-19. Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>382</volume>: <fpage>1708</fpage>–<lpage>1720</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2002032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7092819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical course and outcomes of critically ill patients with SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a single-centered, retrospective, observational study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>481</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30079-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32105632</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>ARDS Definition Task Force</collab></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ranieri</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rubenfeld</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Acute respiratory distress syndrome: the Berlin definition</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>307</volume>: <fpage>2526</fpage>–<lpage>2533</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2012.5669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22797452</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raman</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cassar</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tunnicliffe</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Medium-term effects of SARS-CoV-2 infection on multiple vital organs, exercise capacity, cognition, quality of life and mental health, post-hospital discharge</article-title>. <source>EClinicalMedicine</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>100683</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33490928</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7808914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The pulmonary sequence in discharged patients with COVID-19: a short-term observational study</article-title>. <source>Respir Res</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-020-01385-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32448391</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7245637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>WHO Clinical Case Definition Working Group on Post-COVID-19 Condition. A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>e102</fpage>–<lpage>e107</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez-Ledo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ancochea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Persistent COVID in 2023: definition and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Rev Pat Resp</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24875/RPR.M23000010</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nalbandian</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01283-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753937</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8893149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Munipalli</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seim</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC): a meta-narrative review of pathophysiology, prevalence, and management</article-title>. <source>SN Compr Clin Med</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42399-022-01167-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402784</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8977184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Piroth</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cottenet</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mariet</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of the characteristics, morbidity, and mortality of COVID-19 and seasonal influenza: a nationwide, population-based retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30527-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33341155</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7832247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barratt</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Condliffe</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Respiratory follow-up of patients with COVID-19 pneumonia</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-215314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32839287</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sibila</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Molina-Molina</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzuela</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Spanish Society of Pulmonology and Thoracic Surgery (SEPAR) consensus for post-COVID-19 clinical follow-up</article-title>. <source>Open Respir Arch</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.opresp.2020.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38620714</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7550863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-de-Las-Peñas</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios-Ceña</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Mayordomo</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Defining post-COVID symptoms (post-acute COVID, long COVID, persistent post-COVID): an integrative classification</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>2621</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18052621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33807869</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7967389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Ministry of Employment and Social Security</collab></person-group>. <source>Manual of Optimal Times of Temporary Disability</source>. <edition>4th Edn</edition>
<publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>National Social Security Institute</publisher-name>, <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aben</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kok</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Wind</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Return-to-work rates and predictors of absence duration after COVID-19 over the course of the pandemic</article-title>. <source>Scand J Work Environ Health</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5271/sjweh.4077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36587298</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10621901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>O'Regan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Svalgaard</surname>
<given-names>IB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sørensen</surname>
<given-names>AIV</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A hybrid register and questionnaire study of COVID-19 and post-acute sick leave in Denmark</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>6266</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-42048-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37805514</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10560282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spetz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Natt Oh Dag</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The sociodemographic patterning of sick leave and determinants of longer sick leave after mild and severe COVID-19: a nationwide register-based study in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Eur J Public Health</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckad191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37889580</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10843940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Gonzalez</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chamorro-de-Vega</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Valerio</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>COVID-19 in hospitalised patients in Spain: a cohort study in Madrid</article-title>. <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>106249</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.106249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33259918</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7698681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koyanagi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of, and factors associated with, long-term COVID-19 sick leave in working-age patients followed in general practices in Germany</article-title>. <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.06.063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34224870</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8922990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Calvo-Bonacho</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Catalina-Romero</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Labandera</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>COVID-19 and sick leave: an analysis of the Ibermutua cohort of over 1,651,305 Spanish workers in the first trimester of 2020</article-title>. <source>Front Public Health</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>580546</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2020.580546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33194983</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7604328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abzhandadze</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Westerlind</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Persson</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of pre-pandemic sick leave diagnoses on the length of COVID-19-related sick leave: a nationwide registry-based study</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-023-15115-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36709256</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9884157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Global, regional, and national burden of asthma and its attributable risk factors from 1990 to 2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019</article-title>. <source>Respir Res</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-023-02475-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37353829</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10288698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghezzawi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Puzantian</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Mortality risk in patients with obesity and COVID-19 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>155812</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2024.155812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38360130</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chenchula</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tripathi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of overweight and obesity and their effect on COVID-19 severity and hospitalization among younger than 50 years <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> older than 50 years population: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Obes Rev</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>e13616</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/obr.13616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37574901</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kisiel</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nordqvist</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Westman</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Patterns and predictors of sick leave among Swedish non-hospitalized healthcare and residential care workers with COVID-19 during the early phase of the pandemic</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>e0260652</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0260652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34882720</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8659339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abzhandadze</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Westerlind</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palstam</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Sick leave one year after COVID-19 infection: a nationwide cohort study during the first wave in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>823</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-50413-9</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38177214</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10766961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gil-Blanco</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Jarreta</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Declaration of COVID-19 as an occupational disease in healthcare workers: challenges and reality</article-title>. <source>Med Clin</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.medcle.2021.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8260500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34250245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Westerlind</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palstam</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sunnerhagen</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Patterns and predictors of sick leave after COVID-19 and long COVID in a national Swedish cohort</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1023</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-021-11013-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34059034</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8164957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="standard"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ter Haar</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bennaars</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Netherlands and COVID-19 measures in the field of labour law</article-title>. <comment>Date last updated: December 2020. Date last accessed: 5 September 2024</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.cielolaboral.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/terhaar_bennaars_noticias_cielo_n3_2021.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">www.cielolaboral.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/terhaar_bennaars_noticias_cielo_n3_2021.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rothman</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greenland</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Modern Epidemiology. <edition>3rd Edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>; p. <fpage>758</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hernán</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Robins</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Causal Inference: What If</source>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>; p. <fpage>625</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keyes</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Galea</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Epidemiology Matters: A New Introduction to Methodological Foundations</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>; p. <fpage>272</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reusch</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wagenhäuser</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gabel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Inability to work following COVID-19 vaccination–a relevant aspect for future booster vaccinations</article-title>. <source>Public Health</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>222</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2023.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37562083</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ziauddeen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pantelic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O'Hara</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Impact of long COVID-19 on work: a co-produced survey</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>402</volume>: <issue>Suppl. 1</issue>, <fpage>S98</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)02157-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37997145</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shuai</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The dose–response relationship between physical activity and the risk of death from pneumonia in middle-aged and older adults: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Medicine</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>e38220</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000038220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38787979</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11124747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Michalas</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Katsaras</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spetsioti</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The effect of physiotherapy on dyspnea, muscle strength and functional status in patients with long COVID syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Pers Med</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jpm14050515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38793097</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11121916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Calvache-Mateo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reychler</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heredia-Ciuró</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Respiratory training effects in long COVID-19 patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Respir Med</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17476348.2024.2358933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38800959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="standard"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Valdés</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>El ‘milagro Marañón’ o la multiplicación de las camas y las UCI</article-title><comment>. Date last updated: 16 April 2020. Date last accessed: 12 September 2025</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://elpais.com/espana/madrid/2020-04-16/el-milagro-maranon-o-la-multiplicacion-de-las-camas-y-las-uci.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://elpais.com/espana/madrid/2020-04-16/el-milagro-maranon-o-la-multiplicacion-de-las-camas-y-las-uci.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>