<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">692</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">copd</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">copd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1176-9106</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1178-2005</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12255256</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12255256.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12255256</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12255256</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40655185</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/COPD.S520300</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">520300</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long COVID in Elderly COPD Patients: Clinical Features, Pulmonary Function Decline, and Proteomic Insights</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Li et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Li et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="S">Shuangyan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="H">Hui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="M">Min</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names initials="T">Tingting</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names initials="D">Di</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhengyin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names initials="C">Chengfeng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yanming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7374-7808</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names initials="M">Mingming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Beijing Hospital, National Centre of Gerontology, Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>State Key Laboratory of Pathogen and Biosecurity, Academy of Military Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Radiology, Beijing Hospital, National Center of Gerontology, Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Beijing Hospital, National Center of Gerontology, Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Beijing Hospital, National Center of Gerontology, Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Research Unit of Discovery and Tracing of Natural Focus Diseases, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Mingming Pan, <institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Beijing Hospital, National Center of Gerontology, Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>No. 1 Dongdan Dahua Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +86-13661129402</phone>, Email panmm6@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478627</issue-id><fpage>2337</fpage><lpage>2347</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-14 15:25:24.943"><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 Li et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v4.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="copd-20-2337.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Elderly patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) face a heightened risk of developing long coronavirus disease (COVID); however the exact clinical characteristics and underlying mechanisms remain unclear.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We enrolled 85 elderly COPD patients, of whom 43 reported newly onset persistent fatigue (the most dominant complaint of long COVID) within 1 year after severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection, and they were allocated to the Long-COVID group. The remaining 42 patients were assigned to the Control group. Patients completed questionnaires, pulmonary function tests, chest CT, routine laboratory tests, and blood proteomic analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Long-COVID patients had a longer course of COPD (&gt; 5 years, 76.8% vs 52.4%) and duration of SARS-CoV-2 infection (10.0 days vs 7.0 days) (All <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), higher symptom burden, worse pulmonary ventilation function and a more rapid decrease in DL<sub>CO</sub> (All <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Proteomic analysis indicated disruptions in inflammation and energy metabolism, potentially underlying long COVID in these patients. The machine learning model identified wheezing, the duration of SARS-CoV-2 infection, EIF2S3 (eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2 subunit gamma), current FEV1/FVC (%), and the course of COPD as key features distinguishing Long-COVID patients, and exhibited excellent performance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Elderly COPD patients with a longer COPD course and duration of COVID-19 are more prone to develop long COVID, with decreased pulmonary ventilation and diffusion ability. Disordered inflammation regulation and energy metabolism may be the potential mechanisms, highlighting the importance of monitoring inflammation and metabolic dysregulation in elderly COPD patients after recovery from COVID-19.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>elderly</kwd><kwd>COPD</kwd><kwd>long COVID</kwd><kwd>risk factors</kwd><kwd>proteomics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National High Level Hospital Clinical Research</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by National High Level Hospital Clinical Research Funding (BJ-2023-160).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="43"/><page-count count="11"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) has become the greatest public health crisis of the 21<sup>st</sup> century. It has imposed an unprecedented burden on global health and economy. As of April 20, 2025, more than 777 million individuals were diagnosed with COVID-19, and more than 7.0 million deaths have been reported worldwide according to the World Health Organization (WHO).<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Increasing studies have reported that COVID-19 survivors might develop sustained postinfection sequelae, which are called long-COVID, also known as post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC).<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The latest 2024 NASEM (National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine) definition of long COVID is an infection-associated chronic condition that occurs after SARS-CoV-2 infection and is present for at least 3 months as a continuous, relapsing and remitting, or progressive disease state that affects one or more organ systems.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Fatigue, shortness of breath, and cognitive dysfunction are its most common presentations, and these symptoms usually have an adverse impact on daily functioning.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></p><p>A wide range of comorbidities, including chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), are related to an elevated risk of long COVID.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> COPD patients are reportedly more susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection and are at increased risk of having more severe clinical outcomes.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> A systematic review and meta-analysis reported that pre-existing COPD was associated with 32% increased odds of long COVID.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> COPD prevalence tends to increase with age. Elderly COPD patients may be more susceptible to immune dysregulation, given the chronic inflammation and higher levels of senescent cells, which could predispose them to long COVID.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Despite the growing body of research on long COVID, its pathophysiology in COPD patients is still not well understood. It remains largely unclear which elderly COPD patients will develop long COVID, as well as the medium- and long-term impacts of SARS-CoV-2 infection on this patient group.</p><p>In this study, we recruited a group of elderly COPD patients who were infected with SARS-CoV-2 nearly one year prior, and used fatigue to discriminate COPD patients with long COVID from those without because fatigue is the most common complaint of long COVID.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> While COPD patients can report fatigue as a result of impaired pulmonary function, fatigue due to long COVID is typically more severe and persistent, with a notable impact on daily life. Other long COVID symptoms, such as cough and dyspnoea, are also common clinical manifestations of COPD itself and are thus not suitable for discriminating long COVID in COPD patients. The enrolled COPD patients, with or without long COVID, completed questionnaires, physical examinations, and serum proteomics. The primary endpoints of this study encompassed a comprehensive evaluation of clinical characteristic, pulmonary function assessments, and chest CT imaging analyses. Additionally, proteomic analysis served as the secondary outcome measure, providing further insights into the underlying mechanisms.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Study Design and Participants</title><p>Detailed methods are provided in the <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material</ext-link></underline>. This longitudinal cohort study was conducted between November 2023 and February 2024 at Beijing Hospital in 85 elderly COPD patients, nearly one year after they had been infected with SARS-CoV-2 (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), ensuring that any observed fatigue and other symptoms were persistent and not related to the acute phase of infection. All inclusion and exclusion criteria are provided in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>. Forty-three of the enrolled 85 patients reported persistent and remarkable fatigue within 1 year after SARS-CoV-2 infection and were allocated to the Long-COVID group. The remaining 42 patients without fatigue were assigned to the Control group.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow chart of the study.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="COPD-20-2337-g0001.jpg"/></fig></p><p>The enrolled patients then completed the questionnaire assessment, blood tests, pulmonary function tests (PFTs), and chest CT. Randomly selected 60 patients (30 patients in each group) further performed serum proteomic analysis. The clinical and proteomic data of the 60 patients were used for machine learning model training to identify important features of elderly COPD patients with long COVID (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline>).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Face‒to‒face Follow-up at the Hospital</title><p>The questionnaires were conducted by well-trained medical staff, collecting baseline demographic information and medical history. Other questionnaires included the mMRC dyspnoea scale,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> the EuroQol Visual Analogue Scale (EQ-VAS) to assess quality of life,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7) to screen for anxiety,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> the Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS),<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) to screen for depression,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and the COPD Assessment Test (CAT) to assess the burden of symptoms and their impact on the daily life of COPD patients.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Then the patients performed physical examinations, included routine blood tests, PFTs, and chest CT. Blood tests included complete blood count, biochemical, C-reactive protein (CRP), and serum amyloid A (SAA) analyses. PFTs were performed under the supervision of well-trained technicians, and multiple lung function parameters were assessed. These patients had PFTs at Beijing Hospital within two years before the COVID-19 epidemic, and the corresponding lung function parameters were extracted from electronic medical care data. We calculated the annual variation according to the time interval between the two PFTs. Chest CT was used to evaluate the extent of emphysema, bronchial wall thickening, interstitial changes, and tractive bronchiectasis. Detailed descriptions of chest CT evaluation are provided in the <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material</ext-link></underline>.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>DIA (Data-Independent Acquisition) Proteomic Analysis</title><p>The detailed processes of proteomic analysis can be found in the <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material</ext-link></underline>. Sixty randomly selected serum samples, including 30 samples from the Control group and 30 samples from the Long-COVID group, were processed for DIA proteomic analysis. Proteins with a fold change &gt; 1.2 or &lt; 0.83 and a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; 0.05 (Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test) were identified as differentially expressed proteins (DEPs). Gene Ontology (GO), Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) enrichment analysis, and reactome pathway analysis were used to explore the functions of DEPs.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Machine Learning Model Training</title><p>The detailed flow of machine learning model training is provided in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline>. Briefly, all data underwent initial screening and missing data imputation. Boruta was used to select the important features. Then three machine learning algorithms, including Random Forest, Support Vector Machine (SVM), and Ridge Regression, were used for model training based on the selected important features. Finally, we evaluated the model performance using area under the operating characteristic (ROC) curves (AUC) and analysed the feature importance via SHAP (Shapley Additive exPlanations) values.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Baseline demographic characteristics are presented as medians (IQRs) or means ± SDs for continuous variables and n/N (%) for categorical variables. For continuous variables, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were calculated using Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test or the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test. Categorical variables were compared by Fisher’s exact test or Pearson’s chi(2) test. A two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. Statistical analysis was performed using IBM SPSS Statistics version 25.0.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Baseline Characteristics of the Participants</title><p>A total of 85 patients were ultimately enrolled at the 1-year follow-up visit (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These COPD patients were all clinically stable. Results of routine blood tests, including indicators of acute inflammation, were comparable between the two groups (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link></underline>). Characteristics such as age, sex, BMI (body mass index), cigarette smoking, and vaccination status were matched. Most included patients were male (88.2%) and had a median age of 71.0 years (IQR 69.0–76.0), with a high smoking rate (78.8%). Sixty-two (72.9%) patients had received one or more doses of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination. Besides, comorbidities were also comparable between the two groups (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Hypertension (51.8%) and diabetes (23.5%) were the most common comorbidities. More patients in the Long-COVID group used inhaled corticosteroids (ICSs) than patients in the Control group (74.4% vs 61.9%), but the difference was not statistically significant (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In addition, a greater proportion of patients in the Long-COVID group had COPD for more than 5 years (76.8% vs 52.4%). Lung function was not significantly differ between the two groups before the COVID-19 epidemic according to the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) grades (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The duration of SARS-CoV-2 infection was also longer in the Long-COVID group (10.0 days vs 7.0 days), but the severity of SARS-CoV-2 infection did not differ between the two groups (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline Characteristics of Recruited Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total N=85</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control N=42</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long-COVID N=43</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.0 (69.0–76.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.5 (69.0–76.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.0 (69.0–76.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.558</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/85 (89.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38/42 (90.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38/43 (88.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.753</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5±0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7±3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3±3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cigarette smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.824</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/85 (21.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/42 (23.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/43 (18.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/85 (18.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/42 (19.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/43 (18.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Former smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51/85 (60.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/42 (57.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27/43 (62.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unvaccinated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/85 (27.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/42 (26.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/43 (27.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">One dose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/85 (2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/42 (4.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two or more dose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60/85 (70.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29/42 (69.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/43 (72.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58/85 (68.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/42 (61.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/43 (74.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asthma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/85 (8.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/42 (7.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/43 (9.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bronchiectasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/85 (2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/43 (4.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.494</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulmonary interstitial fibrosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/85 (5.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/42 (4.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/43 (7.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/85 (3.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/43 (7.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.241</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44/85 (51.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/42 (52.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/43 (51.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/85 (23.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/42 (26.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/43 (20.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.568</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic cardiac dysfunction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/85 (3.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/42 (2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/43 (4.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.571</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic kidney disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/85 (7.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/42 (4.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/43 (9.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.676</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/85 (8.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/42 (4.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/43 (11.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.433</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Course of COPD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ 3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/85 (14.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/42 (23.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/43 (4.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/85 (21.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/42 (23.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/43 (18.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–10 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29/85 (34.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/42 (26.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/43 (41.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 10 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/85 (30.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/42 (26.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/43 (34.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GOLD grades*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.608</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GOLD 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/85 (20.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/42 (21.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/43 (18.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GOLD 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49/85 (57.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/42 (61.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/43 (53.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GOLD 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/85 (17.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/42 (14.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/43 (20.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GOLD 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/85 (4.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/42 (2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/43 (7.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Course of SARS-CoV-2 infection, days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (5.0–15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (2.3–10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 (7.0–19.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity of SARS-CoV-2 infection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe<break/>Non-severe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/85 (7.1%)<break/>79/85 (92.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/42 (7.1%)<break/>39/42 (92.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/43 (7.0%)<break/>40/43 (93.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: The date are presented as median (IQR), mean ± SD, or n/N (%). For continuous variables, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were calculated using Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test or the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test. Categorical variables were compared by Fisher’s exact test or Pearson’s chi(2) test. A two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. *GOLD grades based on post-bronchodilator FEV1 values tested before SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; ICS, inhaled corticosteroid; GOLD, Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Clinical Characteristics of Long COVID in Elderly COPD Patients</title><p>Within one year following SARS-CoV-2 infection, the Long-COVID group had a higher rate of hospital visits due to COPD exacerbation (11.9% vs 30.2%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). A significantly higher proportion of patients in the Long-COVID group experienced exacerbations of chest tightness (16.5% vs 4.7%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and wheezing (32.9% vs 11.8%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) compared to those without long-COVID. However, the proportions of patients who experienced cough and sputum production exacerbation were similar between the two groups (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Significant dyspnoea (mMRC ≥ 2) was observed in 72.1% of patients in the Long-COVID group compared with 26.2% of patients in the Control group (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>). The CAT questionnaire aims to assess and quantify the symptom burden of COPD patients. In this study, 90.7% of patients in the Long-COVID group had CAT scores &gt; 10, compared with 42.9% in the Control group, indicating a higher symptom burden associated with COPD in the Long-COVID group (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2b</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Hospital Visits and Symptom (Cough, Sputum Production, Chest Tightness, and Wheezing) Exacerbation Within One year After SARS-CoV-2 Infection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long-COVID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital visits due to COPD exacerbation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/42 (11.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/43 (30.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough exacerbation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/42 (8.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/43 (12.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum production exacerbation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/42 (10.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/43 (9.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest tightness exacerbation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/42 (4.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/43 (16.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheezing exacerbation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/42 (11.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28/43 (32.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: The date are presented as n/N (%). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were calculated using Pearson’s chi(2) test. A two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Patients in the Long-COVID group had higher mMRC and CAT scores. (<bold>a</bold>) mMRC scores; (<bold>b</bold>) CAT scores. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were calculated by Fisher’s exact test or Pearson’s chi (2) test. A two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="COPD-20-2337-g0002.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: mMRC, modified Medical Research Council dyspnoea scale; CAT, COPD Assessment Test.</attrib></fig></p><p>All enrolled patients completed a series of questionnaires to assess their health-related quality of life (EQ-VAS), anxiety (GAD-7), depression (PHQ-9) (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link></underline>). The EQ-VAS is used to assess the patients’ own perceptions of their own overall health. Patients in the Long-COVID group had significantly lower EQ-VAS scores, indicating impaired health-related quality of life after SARS-CoV-2 infection. The GAD-7 score, which is usually used to screen for generalized anxiety disorder (GAD), did not markedly differ between the two groups. More than half of patients in the Long-COVID group experienced various degrees of depression, ranging from mild to moderately severe, as indicated by the PHQ-9 scores. These questionnaires collectively demonstrated that COPD patients with long COVID had lower health-related quality of life and signs of depression.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Pulmonary Function and Chest CT Evaluation</title><p>All enrolled COPD patients underwent PFTs to evaluate their current status of lung function (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, the severity of airflow obstruction was not significantly differ between the two groups before SARS-CoV-2 infection. However, multiple pulmonary function parameters were lower in the Long-COVID group than in the Control group one year after SARS-CoV-2 infection, including FEV1% pred (FEV1/estimated value of FEV1), PEF % pred (PEF/estimated value of PEF), MEF75% pred (MEF75/estimated value of MEF75), MEF50% pred (MEF50/estimated value of MEF50), and MVV % pred (MVV/estimated value of MVV) (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Several Pulmonary Function Test Parameters Were Lower in the Long-COVID Group Than in the Control Group at the 1-year Follow-up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long-COVID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FVC (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.20 (76.68 to 98.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.20 (69.50 to 96.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.377</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEV1 (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.85 (54.45 to 78.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.70 (42.20 to 70.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEV1/FVC (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.49 (51.12 to 66.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.30 (41.21 to 65.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEF (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.60 (65.05 to 95.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.80 (48.30 to 87.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEF improvement rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30 (0.30 to 8.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90 (−0.30 to 12.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.312</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEF 75 (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.75 (24.23 to 58.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.20 (12.60 to 48.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEF 50 (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.15 (14.48 to 28.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.50 (9.70 to 26.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEF 25 (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.75 (12.93 to 23.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.50 (12.45 to 36.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.840</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMEF 75/25 (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.20 (14.28 to 26.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.40 (10.20 to 22.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MVV (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.30 (46.80 to 70.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.60 (37.03 to 62.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TLC (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.35 (76.08 to 91.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.40 (72.30 to 90.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.242</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RV (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.35 (85.73 to 111.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.30 (81.30 to 109.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.450</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RV/TLC (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.89 (43.76 to 52.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.67 (43.16 to 54.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DL<sub>CO</sub> (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.75 (61.08 to 85.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.70 (52.30 to 85.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DL<sub>CO</sub>/VA (% of predicted)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.40 (73.45 to 108.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.80 (63.60 to 107.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.437</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: The date are presented as the median (IQR). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were calculated using the Mann-Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test. A two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>The DL<sub>CO</sub> % pred (DL<sub>CO</sub>/estimated value of DL<sub>CO</sub>) was slightly lower in the Long-COVID group than that in the Control group, but the difference was not statistically significant (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). According to the calculated annual variation rate, DL<sub>CO</sub> declined faster annually in the Long-COVID group (−0.14 mmol/min/kPa/year, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; 0.05) (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link></underline>). Thus, SARS-CoV-2 infection may significantly impair pulmonary ventilation function, small airway function, and diffusion ability in the Long-COVID group, which may partially account for the exacerbation in COPD-associated symptoms, such as chest tightness and wheezing.</p><p>Additionally, we assessed the severity of emphysema, bronchial wall thickening, and interstitial changes through chest CT and found no significant differences between the two groups (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 5</ext-link></underline>), indicating that long COVID may not predominantly result in structural abnormalities on lung imaging.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>Proteomic Profiling of Serum Revealed Dysregulated Inflammation and Metabolic Processes in the Long-COVID Group</title><p>A total of 1868 comparable proteins were identified, and 28 proteins were identified as DEPs, including 23 up-regulated proteins and 5 down-regulated proteins (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2a</ext-link></underline>). Several inflammation-related proteins were dysregulated. Suppressor of cytokine signalling 5 (SOCS5), which has been reported to inhibit inflammation in both a COPD mouse model and an influenza mouse model,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> was decreased in the Long-COVID group. High mobility group box 3 (HMGB3) can promote monocyte recruitment and inflammatory responses.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Enhanced HMGB3 expression was observed in the Long-COVID group. EIF2S3 encodes the largest subunit of eukaryotic initiation factor 2 (eIF2), which is involved in the early steps of protein synthesis. White blood cells infected with the SARS-CoV-2 beta variant expressed higher levels of EIF2S3 than cells infected with the alpha variant.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> We observed higher expression of EIF2S3 in the Long-COVID group.</p><p>GO enrichment analysis of the up-regulated DEPs revealed several metabolism-related pathways, including the NADH metabolic process, NAD metabolic process, and dicarboxylic acid metabolic process (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2b</ext-link></underline>). NAD<sup>+</sup>/NADH metabolism participates in regulating multiple pathophysiological processes, such as mitochondrial functions, energy metabolism, antiviral defence, and inflammation regulation.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Elevated levels of dicarboxylic acids may facilitate physical and cognitive fatigue.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> KEGG enrichment analysis of up-regulated proteins revealed pathways involved in the citrate cycle, ribosome, and coronavirus disease-COVID-19 (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2c</ext-link></underline>). In the citrate cycle pathway, isocitrate dehydrogenase (NAD(+)) 3 catalytic subunit alpha (IDH3A) and phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase 2, mitochondrial (PCK2) were up-regulated. Ribosomal protein L35 (RPL35), ribosomal protein L31 (RPL31), and ribosomal protein L7a (RPL7A) were enriched in both the ribosome pathway and coronavirus disease-COVID-19 pathway (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2c</ext-link></underline>). Additionally, the reactome pathway analysis of the DEPs identified pathways such as disease of glycosylation, viral infection pathways, nervous system development, platelet activation, interferon signalling, and signalling by interleukins (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3</ext-link></underline>). Multiple studies have reported associations between these pathways and long COVID.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27–31</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Five Important Features Were Identified Between the Two Groups via Machine Learning Model Training</title><p>The clinical and proteomics data of 60 patients were used to train a machine learning model. Five of the 31 filtered features were selected by Boruta for model training, including wheezing, duration of SARS-CoV-2 infection, EIF2S3, current FEV1/FVC (%), and course of COPD. Three machine learning algorithms, Ridge Regression, SVM, and Random Forest, were subsequently used for model training based on the five selected important features (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3a, 3b and 3c</xref>). The SVM had the highest AUC of 0.86 (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3b</xref>). The feature importance was measured via SHAP values, and the five important features were presented in descending order of their SHAP values (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3d</xref>), elucidating the predictions made by the SVM model. The details of the five important features were shown in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/article/supplementary_file/520300/Supplementary_materials_revised.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 4</ext-link></underline>, which revealed more severe wheezing, a longer duration of SARS-CoV-2 infection, higher EIF2S3 expression, lower FEV1/FVC (%), and a longer course of COPD in the Long-COVID group. The five identified features were of great significance, and models based on these features had good discriminative performance in differentiating COPD patients with long COVID from those without long COVID.
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Machine learning analysis of clinical and proteomics data from 60 patients. Model performance evaluation using ROC curves for (<bold>a</bold>) Ridge Regression, (<bold>b</bold>) SVM, and (<bold>c</bold>) Random Forest. (<bold>d</bold>) SHAP feature importance plot showing the five key features identified by the SVM machine learning model.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="COPD-20-2337-g0003.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to focus on long COVID only in elderly COPD patients. Briefly, the course of COPD and duration of SARS-CoV-2 infection were significantly longer in the Long-COVID group than in the Control group. COPD patients with long COVID mainly presented with exacerbations in chest tightness and wheezing, and they were more likely to develop depression, to have a lower quality of life and higher CAT scores. Additionally, pulmonary ventilation function, small airway function, and diffuse ability were worse in the Long-COVID group one year after SARS-CoV-2 infection. Proteomic analysis revealed dysregulated inflammatory responses and metabolic processes, which might be potential mechanisms of long COVID in elderly COPD patients. Machine learning model training identified five important features for differentiating COPD patients with long COVID from those without long COVID, including wheezing, duration of SARS-CoV-2 infection, EIF2S3, current FEV1/FVC (%), and course of COPD.</p><p>Previous studies reported the 10 most prevalent symptoms of long COVID: fatigue, dyspnoea, myalgia, cough, headache, joint pain, chest pain, altered smell, diarrhoea, and altered taste in order.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> In our study, patients in the Long-COVID group more frequently experienced exacerbations of chest tightness and wheezing. The proportions of patients who experienced cough or sputum production exacerbation were similar between the two groups. This suggests that COPD patients with long COVID predominantly exhibit symptoms associated with ventilation deficiency, such as chest tightness and wheezing, rather than airway inflammation symptoms, such as cough or expectoration. In addition, researches reported that long COVID can impair patients’ quality of life, and contribute to depression.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Patients with long COVID showed lower EQ-VAS score compared to those without long COVID at 90-day after COVID-19 diagnosis.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> PHQ-9 testing revealed that approximate 42% of patients who presented to the Post-COVID-19 clinic showed moderate to severe depression.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Consistent with these previous findings, our study also observed a significant lower EQ-VAS score (60.0 vs 80.0) and a higher proportion of patients exhibited moderate to severe depression (21.0% vs 4.8%) in the Long-COVID group. These results indicated the adverse impact of long COVID on elderly COPD patients, exacerbating symptom burden and negatively affecting their quality of life.</p><p>SARS-CoV-2 infection can have long-term impacts on the pulmonary function of survivors. A study observed a constant decline in lung function from the 1-year to 2-year follow-up.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Approximately 29.4% of COVID-19 survivors showed impaired DL<sub>CO</sub>, and 4.7% had a decrease in lung volume parameters at 6 months postinfection.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In our follow-up study, patients in the two groups had similar lung function before COVID-19. However, after SARS-CoV-2 infection, several parameters of pulmonary function, such as FEV1% pred, PEF % pred, MEF75% pred, MEF50% pred, and MVV % pred, were lower in the Long-COVID group. DL<sub>CO</sub> declined faster in the Long-COVID group and was slightly lower than that in the Control group one year after SARS-CoV-2 infection. Furthermore, FEV1/FVC (%) was identified as an important feature in the machine learning model, and COPD patients with long COVID had slightly lower FEV1/FVC (%) than the Control group. These results suggest that SARS-CoV-2 infection may accelerate ventilation function, small airway function, and diffuse ability decline in some COPD patients.</p><p>The mechanisms of Long COVID remain poorly characterised. Post-acute virus persistence, chronic inflammation, endothelial damage, fibroblast activation, and complement and platelet activation can combine to cause long-term sequelae of COVID-19 in the lungs.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Multiple mechanisms can lead to post-COVID-19 fatigue, such as chronic inflammation of the brain and neuromuscular junctions, sarcolemma damage and skeletal muscle fiber atrophy.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Clearly, chronic inflammation is critical in the pathogenesis of long COVID. Our proteomic analysis revealed several dysregulated inflammation-related proteins, such as SOCS5, HMGB3 and Fc gamma binding protein (FCGBP). Furthermore, SARS-CoV-2 infection can cause mitochondrial dysfunction and metabolic disorders.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Impaired oxidative phosphorylation may contribute to post-COVID-19 exercise limitations and fatigue in long COVID.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> This study also revealed the dysregulation of several metabolic processes, including citrate cycle, and metabolism of NADH, NAD, and dicarboxylic acid. EIF2S3 is an important protein identified by the machine learning model. It encodes the largest subunit of eIF2 and is related to stress responses. EIF2 participates in regulating the integrated stress response activated by various stimuli, such as the ageing process.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> The elevated EIF2S3 in the Long-COVID group may be a response to the ageing process, which is closely related to long COVID.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></p><p>In the context of COVID-19 normalization prevention and control, long-term management is crucial, especially for elderly COPD patients. Identifying those at high risk of long COVID is essential for efficient resource allocation. Based on our findings, elderly patients with a longer course of COPD and a longer duration of SARS-CoV-2 infection may be at greater risk of developing long COVID, emphasizing the need of long-term coping strategies. These patients should prioritize COVID-19 vaccination and adhere to COPD standard treatment to avoid acute exacerbation.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Early antiviral therapy is also of great significance to them, which is reported to reduce the risk of PASC and PASC-related hospitalizations or deaths.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> In addition, long-term follow-up, frequent PFTs, and pulmonary rehabilitation, such as endurance, strength, and inspiratory muscle training, can also be beneficial.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></p><p>Our study has several limitations. First, self-reported data may introduce recall bias, though we minimized this by using multiple well-designed questionnaires. Second, the single-center design and limited sample size may affect generalizability. However, even in non-severe COVID-19 patients and with a relatively small sample size, we still observed remarkable fatigue sequelae in some COPD patients. We obtained rather elaborate data from these enrolled patients, which made our results more convincing. The pathophysiology of long COVID in COPD patients remains inadequately understood, particularly regarding elderly individuals who may have unique responses to the virus and post-infection recovery. Future multi-center studies with larger sample sizes, patients of varying severities, and longer follow-up periods are essential to explore and validate the complex relationship between pre-existed COPD and long COVID development.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study identified longer COPD course and duration of COVID-19 as key long COVID risk factors in COPD patients, with the Long-COVID group exhibiting worsened respiratory symptoms (chest tightness, wheezing) and lung function. Proteomic profiling revealed inflammatory and metabolic protein dysregulation linked to long COVID progression. Integrated clinical-proteomic machine learning models effectively predicted long COVID risk, supporting early screening. Further investigation is required to elucidate the precise roles of these proteins and to delve deeper into the mechanisms of long COVID in COPD patients.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>Shuangyan Li and Hui Zhao are co-first authors for this study. We thank all the patients who participated in this study. And we thank the clinical staff for their dedication to collecting serum samples. We thank the State Key Laboratory of Pathogen and Biosecurity, Beijing Institute of Microbiology and Epidemiology, Academy of Military Medical Sciences.</p></ack><sec id="s0006"><title>Ethical Approval</title><p>This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Beijing Hospital (2023BJYYEC-355-02). Prior to participation, written informed consent was obtained from all study participants. All aspects of the study conformed to the principals of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>WHO coronavirus (COVID-19) dashboard 2024</article-title>
<comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int/table" ext-link-type="uri">https://covid19.who.int/table</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>July</month>
<day>2</day>, 2025</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ely</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fineberg</surname>
<given-names>HV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long covid defined</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>391</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>1746</fpage>–<lpage>1753</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsb2408466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39083764</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a delphi consensus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e102</fpage>–<lpage>e7</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siles</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical characteristics of Long COVID patients presenting to a dedicated academic post-COVID-19 clinic in Central Texas</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21971</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-48502-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38081885</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10713530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nirantharakumar</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Symptoms and risk factors for long COVID in non-hospitalized adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1706</fpage>–<lpage>1714</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01909-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35879616</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9388369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Figueira-Goncalves</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Golpe</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Medium- and long-term consequences of SARS-CoV-2 infection on COPD patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Bronconeumol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arbres.2022.05.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35697563</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9151457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Awatade</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wark</surname>
<given-names>PAB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>ASL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The complex association between COPD and COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3791</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12113791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37297985</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10253799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Terry</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heidel</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>AQ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Risk of long covid in patients with pre-existing chronic respiratory diseases: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open Respir Res</italic></source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2024-002528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11784193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39884720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharpless</surname>
<given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Senescence in health and disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1000</fpage>–<lpage>1011</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.05.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28575665</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5643029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sandler</surname>
<given-names>CX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wyller</surname>
<given-names>VBB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moss-Morris</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long COVID and post-infective fatigue syndrome: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Forum Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>ofab440</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofab440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34631916</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8496765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aiyegbusi</surname>
<given-names>OL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Symptoms, complications and management of long COVID: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J R Soc Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01410768211032850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265229</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8450986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bestall</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garrod</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Usefulness of the Medical Research Council (MRC) dyspnoea scale as a measure of disability in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Thorax</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.54.7.581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377201</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1745516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>EuroQol: the current state of play</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Policy</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-8510(96)00822-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10158943</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Teni</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burstrom</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Devlin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Experience-based health state valuation using the EQ VAS: a register-based study of the EQ-5D-3L among nine patient groups in Sweden</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Qual Life Outcomes</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>34</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12955-023-02115-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37038172</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10084671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kroenke</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A brief measure for assessing generalized anxiety disorder: the GAD-7</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1092</fpage>–<lpage>1097</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.166.10.1092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16717171</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Valko</surname>
<given-names>PO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bassetti</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bloch</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of the fatigue severity scale in a Swiss cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1601</fpage>–<lpage>1607</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/31.11.1601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19014080</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2579971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kroenke</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gen Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>606</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1525-1497.2001.016009606.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556941</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1495268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development and first validation of the COPD assessment test</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00102509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19720809</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sequential inspiratory muscle exercise-noninvasive positive pressure ventilation alleviates oxidative stress in COPD by mediating SOCS5/JAK2/STAT3 pathway</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>385</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-023-02656-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37828534</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10568888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kedzierski</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tate</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Suppressor of cytokine signaling (SOCS)5 ameliorates influenza infection via inhibition of EGFR signaling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Elife</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7554/eLife.20444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5354519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28195529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Macrophage-derived exosomal HMGB3 regulates silica-induced pulmonary inflammation by promoting M1 macrophage polarization and recruitment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Part Fibre Toxicol</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12989-024-00568-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38454505</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10918916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schatz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Knabl</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Machine learning to identify critical biomarker profiles in new SARS-CoV-2 variants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microorganisms</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>798</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12040798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38674742</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11052335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gandhi</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sex and SP-A2 dependent NAD(H) redox alterations in mouse alveolar macrophages in response to ozone exposure: potential implications for COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antioxidants</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>10</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox9100915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7601279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32992843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>NAD(+)/NADH metabolism and NAD(+)-dependent enzymes in cell death and ischemic brain injury: current advances and therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Med Chem</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1239</fpage>–<lpage>1247</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/0929867322666150209154420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25666794</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brydges</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Metabolomic evidence for peroxisomal dysfunction in myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>7906</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms23147906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35887252</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9320121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haslund-Gourley</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woloszczuk</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>IgM N-glycosylation correlates with COVID-19 severity and rate of complement deposition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>404</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-44211-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38195739</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10776791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long covid and impaired cognition - more evidence and more work to do</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>390</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>858</fpage>–<lpage>860</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMe2400189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38416434</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11156184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martins-Goncalves</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palhinha</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Persisting platelet activation and hyperactivity in COVID-19 survivors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>944</fpage>–<lpage>947</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.122.321659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36268747</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9645447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ruf</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Immune damage in Long Covid</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>383</volume>(<issue>6680</issue>):<fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.adn1077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38236985</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Queiroz</surname>
<given-names>MAF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Neves</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cytokine profiles associated with acute COVID-19 and long COVID-19 syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Cell Infect Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>922422</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2022.922422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35846757</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9279918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Malheiro</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardez-Pereira</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parreira</surname>
<given-names>KCJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence, predictors, and patient-reported outcomes of long COVID in hospitalized and non-hospitalized patients from the city of Sao Paulo, Brazil</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1302669</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1302669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38317683</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10839020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuzuki</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazato</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Terada</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of long-COVID on health-related quality of life in Japanese COVID-19 patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Qual Life Outcomes</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12955-022-02033-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35986269</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9388960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lung-function trajectories in COVID-19 survivors after discharge: a two-year longitudinal cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EClinicalMedicine</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>101668</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36188433</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9514976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magdy</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Metwally</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tawab</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term COVID-19 effects on pulmonary function, exercise capacity, and health status</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Thorac Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/atm.atm_82_21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35198046</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8809128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crook</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raza</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nowell</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long covid-mechanisms, risk factors, and management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>374</volume>:<fpage>n1648</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34312178</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.n1648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peluso</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deeks</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mechanisms of long COVID and the path toward therapeutics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>187</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>5500</fpage>–<lpage>5529</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2024.07.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39326415</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11455603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moolamalla</surname>
<given-names>STR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Host metabolic reprogramming in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection: a systems biology approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Pathog</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>158</volume>:<fpage>105114</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2021.105114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34333072</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8321700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Astin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long COVID: mechanisms, risk factors and recovery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/EP090802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36412084</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10103775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shafqat</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Masters</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tripathi</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long COVID as a disease of accelerated biological aging: an opportunity to translate geroscience interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ageing Res Rev</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>102400</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2024.102400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38945306</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Erinoso</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Osibogun</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Balakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long COVID among US adults from a population-based study: association with vaccination, cigarette smoking, and the modifying effect of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prev Med</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>108004</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2024.108004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38754738</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11148848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname>
<given-names>YB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effectiveness of antiviral therapy on long COVID: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>7375</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12237375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38068427</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10707593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nopp</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moik</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klok</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Outpatient pulmonary rehabilitation in patients with long COVID improves exercise capacity, functional status, dyspnea, fatigue, and quality of life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respiration</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000522118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35203084</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9059007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>