<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12003792</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12003792.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12003792</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12003792</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40240378</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-72263-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">72263</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dose–response effect between the number of long COVID symptoms and the use of different health services</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4828-8210</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names initials="YP">Yohana Pereira</given-names></name><address><email>yohanavieira00@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9743-6331</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names initials="JQS">Juliana Quadros Santos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7780-3595</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos Ferreira Viero</surname><given-names initials="V">Vanise</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4496-4122</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names initials="BP">Bruno Pereira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5746-5170</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Facchini</surname><given-names initials="LA">Luiz Augusto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5730-0811</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Duro</surname><given-names initials="SMS">Suele Manjourany Silva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6798-9130</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Neves</surname><given-names initials="RG">Rosália Garcia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3772-9690</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-de-las-Peñas</surname><given-names initials="C">César</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7225-1552</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira Saes</surname><given-names initials="M">Mirelle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05hpfkn88</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411598.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8540 6536</institution-id><institution>Postgraduate Programme in Health Sciences, Federal University of Rio Grande, </institution></institution-wrap>Visconde de Paranaguá, 102, bairro Centro, Rio Grande, Rio Grande do Sul 96203-900 Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05hpfkn88</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411598.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8540 6536</institution-id><institution>Postgraduate in Health Sciences, Federal University of Rio Grande, </institution></institution-wrap>Rio Grande, Rio Grande do Sul Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05msy9z54</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411221.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2134 6519</institution-id><institution>Postgraduate in Nursing, </institution><institution>Federal University of Pelotas, </institution></institution-wrap>Pelotas, Rio Grande do Sul Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Brazilian Collective Health Association, Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>State Health Department, Pelotas, Rio Grande do Sul Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01v5cv687</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.28479.30</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2206 5938</institution-id><institution>Department of Physical Therapy, Occupational Therapy, Rehabilitation and Physical Medicine, </institution><institution>Universidad Rey Juan Carlos, </institution></institution-wrap>Alcorcón, Madrid, Spain </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478255</issue-id><elocation-id>13104</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-18 00:25:28.467"><day>18</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2024_Article_72263.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">This study aims to identify the use of health services by individuals with long COVID residing in South Brazil 6 months after the acute phase of a SARS-CoV-2 infection. A cross-sectional cohort study of individuals who survived coronavirus disease was conducted in Rio Grande, Brazil. The participants were asked about their use of health services during the 6–10 months following recovery from SARS-CoV-2 infection. Data on the overall use of primary healthcare services, general practitioner services, emergency services, specialist doctors’ services, and specialized services were collected. Individuals with long COVID reported more frequent use of primary healthcare services, emergency services, specialist doctors’ services, and specialized services than those without long COVID. The musculoskeletal, neurological, and respiratory symptoms of long COVID were associated with frequent use of primary healthcare services, whereas the neurological, digestive, and respiratory symptoms were associated with frequent use of emergency services. Finally, the use of specialist doctors’ services and specialized services was more frequent in participants with neurological symptoms than in those without these symptoms. Individuals with long COVID used more healthcare services than those without long COVID in South Brazil. Participants with a greater number of symptoms used more health services than those with fewer symptoms. Healthcare services use depends on the type of the long COVID symptoms. Health services in Brazil need to be reorganized and adapted to provide adequate treatment and care to people with long COVID.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Brazil</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Cross-sectional studies</kwd><kwd>Health services research</kwd><kwd>Health services</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Health care</kwd><kwd>Health services</kwd><kwd>Public health</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Health services use is an indirect method of verifying the accessibility of and equity in healthcare systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> Due to the complexity of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) affecting multiple systems of the human body<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>, it is necessary to restructure and increase the provision of health services at all levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, to meet the demands of the infected people<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Some individuals exhibit symptoms after acute infection, a condition called long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> or post-COVID-19 condition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> (e.g., the continuation or development of new symptoms 3 months after the initial SARS-CoV-2 infection, with these symptoms lasting for at least 2 months with no other explanation)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Therefore, such individuals require specialized medical care services or specialized services<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> due to the presence of long-lasting symptoms, including headache, dyspnea, cough, ageusia, anosmia, fatigue, sore throat, memory loss, attention loss, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, joint pain, myalgia, and skin alterations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">In Brazil, the Unified Health System (SUS) regulates services such as basic sanitation and others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, with the entire population depending on SUS in some capacity. Regarding healthcare services, there are both public and private options available, and 70% of the population relies exclusively on SUS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, which includes primary healthcare (PHC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Medical and specialized consultation services can be either public (secondary and tertiary care) or private<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Studies in the non-pandemic period have shown the frequency of use of health services from PHC to specialized services. For instance, in Espírito Santo State (Brazil), 50.1% of the population used medical services (general practitioner [GP] services) in PHC in 2019<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Additionally, the prevalence of using emergency care units and visiting emergency rooms in public service<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> was 2.3% and 2.5%, respectively, in Espírito Santo State. For specialized services, Wang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> indicated that 10.1% of respondents used mental health services (psychology and psychiatry) in the previous 12 months, also in public service. Moretto et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> reported that the use of physical therapy services reached 33.2%. Similarly, a national study conducted in Brazil compared the use of speech therapy services in public and private healthcare and noted that people with health insurance used these services more frequently than those without health insurance (19.6% vs. 9.0%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Only a few studies have investigated the use of health services by individuals experiencing long COVID. A study in Switzerland showed that 52% of individuals with long COVID symptoms consulted a GP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Similarly, the use of emergency services by individuals with complaints after COVID-19 in the United States was 14.6%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Whittaker et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> evaluated the probability of using health services in the United Kingdom according to the long COVID symptoms and showed that the loss of smell or taste and muscle pain were the most common symptoms associated with GP consultation. In a survey conducted in Germany with participating GPs, the most common symptoms of long COVID observed in consultations were fatigue (63.0%) and reduced performance (75.7%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Identifying healthcare utilization could be useful in guiding the decision-making of managers in the organization of health services to assess the impact of long COVID on the health services; Additionally, understanding current health care utilization among those with long COVID helps both allocate resources more efficiently and determine gaps in health disparities. Therefore, this study aimed to identify the use of health services by individuals with long COVID residing in South Brazil 6 months after acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 (severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2) infection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par7">This cross-sectional cohort study was conducted in the city of Rio Grande in the south of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil. Rio Grande is a port city with an area of 2817 km<sup>2</sup>, a population of 212,881 inhabitants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, and a high human development index of 0.744, which is close to the value estimated for Brazil overall. This study was approved by the Health Research Ethics Committee of the Federal University of Rio Grande (CAAE: 39081120.0.0000.5324).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Participants</title><p id="Par8">The study sample included individuals residing in this municipality, aged ≥ 18 years, who were diagnosed with SARS-CoV-2 infection between December 2020 and March 2021, using a real-time reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) test. Individuals with functional limitations (cognitive) and/or advanced neurological diseases with no caregivers at the time of the interview, those deprived of liberty (prisons), and those from the rural areas of the municipality were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Procedure</title><p id="Par9">The Epidemiological Health Surveillance of Rio Grande was contacted to identify adults and elderly people who had SARS-CoV-2 infection during the investigation period, creating a list of individuals with positive RT-PCR results. Data were collected via telephone calls from individuals eligible for the study. In addition to telephone interviews, face-to-face interviews were conducted through home visits, if necessary. Individuals who could not be reached after five attempts of telephone calls, one attempt via WhatsApp, and three home visits were considered “losses.”</p><p id="Par10">After reading the free and informed consent terms, the interviewees agreed to participate voluntarily. Data were collected from June to October 2021. The questionnaires were collected electronically on tablets using the REDCap program through telephone calls using smartphones. For the safety of the researcher and interviewees, all calls were recorded using a free mobile application (Callmarter) and stored in an email account. The questionnaire administration lasted approximately 20 min.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par11">Participants were asked if they used health services following SARS-CoV-2 infection for any long-lasting symptoms experienced 6–10 months after the infection. The use of PHC (Unidade Básica de Saúde in Portuguese), GP services (medico generalista privado in Portuguese), emergency services (emergency care unit [Unidade de pronto atendimento in Portuguese]), and private emergency services (pronto atendimento privado in Portuguese) was investigated by asking the question, “After your SARS-CoV-2 infection, how many times did you need to avail of health services?” The question was answered with a continuous response option (number of times the service was used) dichotomized into “No” (0 visits) and “Yes” (one or more visits).</p><p id="Par12">The use of specialized services, e.g., pulmonologists, neurologists, cardiologists, psychiatrists, physiotherapists, psychologists, and speech therapists, were investigated using the question “After your SARS-CoV-2 infection, did you need to seek specialized care (you can tick as many options as you want) for a long-lasting symptom associated with the infection?” The question could be answered with a dichotomous answer option of “Yes/No.” For the aggregated variables, the “specialist doctors” outcome was constructed from the combination of “pulmonologist, neurologist, cardiologist, and psychiatrist” variables. For the “specialized services” outcome from the combination of the “pulmonologist, neurologist, cardiologist, psychiatrist, physiotherapist, psychologist, and speech therapist” variables, both outcomes were dichotomized (Yes/No), considering “Yes” for the use of at least one of the investigated services.</p><p id="Par13">The presence of long-lasting symptoms after the infection was evaluated using the question, “Which of these symptoms had you started to experience after the SARS-CoV-2 infection?” The response options were “Yes/No” for the following 19 symptoms: headache, dyspnea, dry cough, mucus, breathing discomfort, ageusia, anosmia, Altered sensitivity (sensations of numbness, tingling, needles, pressure, cold/heat), fatigue, rhinorrhea, nasal congestion, nausea/vomiting, diarrhea, joint pain, myalgia, memory loss, and attention loss. The presence of long COVID was defined as the presence of at least one long-lasting symptom. The symptoms were also grouped by number (one, two, three or more symptoms), quartile (one, two, three/four, five or more symptoms) and according to the affected system as follows: digestive (nausea/vomiting and diarrhea), neurological (headache, memory loss, loss of attention, ageusia, and anosmia), musculoskeletal (myalgia and joint pain), respiratory (dyspnea, dry cough/mucus, breathing discomfort, runny nose, nasal congestion, and rhinorrhea).</p><p id="Par14">The following covariates were collected as potential confounders: sex (male or female), age (18–59 years or ≥ 60 years), marital status (married, living with partner, single, separated, or widowed), educational level (elementary school, high school, or college education), self-reported medical diseases (hypertension, diabetes mellitus, asthma, bronchitis, emphysema, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, or heart diseases), and hospitalization for COVID-19 (yes or no).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par15">Descriptive data are presented as proportions with 95% confidence intervals (95%CI). Poisson regression was used to evaluate the relationship between the use of healthcare services and long-lasting symptoms after SARS-CoV-2 infection. Adjusted analyses were performed using Poisson regression with robust variance adjustment. All associations with 95%CI without any overlap between categories were considered statistically significant. Data were analyzed using the statistical package StataCorp. 2019. <italic toggle="yes">Stata Statistical Software: Release 16</italic>.1. College Station, TX: StataCorp LLC.</p><p id="Par16">To assess the impact of long COVID on each outcome, the attributable fraction or etiological fraction (EF) was calculated only for the dichotomized long COVID responses. This measure elicits the maximum reduction in the use of services if long COVID is eliminated. The EF was calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e408">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{EF }} = \, \left[ {{\text{PO}}*\left( {{\text{PR}}{-}{1}.0} \right)} \right]/{1} + [\left( {{\text{PO}}*\left( {{\text{PR}} - {1}} \right)} \right]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e413" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>EF</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PO</mml:mtext><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PR</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PO</mml:mtext><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PR</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2024_72263_Article_Equa.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where, PO = prevalence of the outcome; PR = crude prevalence ratio.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><p id="Par17">Of the 4,014 participants who tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 between December 2020 and March 2021, 3,822 were eligible to participate in the study (192 were excluded due to incomplete telephone number/address data). After losses (n = 631) and refusals (n = 272), we interviewed 2,919 participants (58.6% were female; mean age: 43.2 ± 15.3 years). Participants were interviewed at a mean of 192.9 ± 42.7 days after acute infection. Of the total number of individuals interviewed, 1,395 people reported the persistence of at least one long COVID symptom, resulting in a long COVID prevalence of 48.3% (95%CI 46.5–50.1). The prevalence of using PHC services was 27.8% (95%CI 26.2–29.5); GP services, 26.3% (95%CI 24.7–28.0); emergency services, 14.3% (95%CI 13.1–15.6); specialist doctors’ services, 20.3% (95%CI 18.9–21.9); and specialized services, 9.4% (95%CI 8.4–10.6).</p><p id="Par18">In the adjusted analysis (prevalence ratio) of health services use, compared to individuals without long COVID, those with long COVID were PR (prevalence ratio) 1.35 (95%CI 1.17–1.56) times more likely to use PHC services, PR 1.49 (95%CI 1.19–1.86) times more likely to use emergency services, PR 1.27 (95%CI 1.06–1.53) times more likely to use specialist doctors’ services, and PR 1.28 (95%CI 1.08–1.50) times more likely to use specialized services (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Association between use of health services and long COVID (n = 1395) in South Brazil (n = 2919).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PHC</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">GP</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Emergency services</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specialist doctors</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specialized services</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Long-COVID (Ref: not)</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>1.35 (1.17–1.56)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 <bold>(</bold>0.82–1.11<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.49 (1.19–1.86)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.27 (1.06–1.53)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.28 (1.08–1.50)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Long-COVID (n = 2919)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No long-COVID*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> One post-COVID symptom</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18 <bold>(</bold>0.96–1.45<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1.06 <bold>(</bold>0.87–1.29<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.34 <bold>(</bold>0.98–1.82<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09 <bold>(</bold>0.93–1.42<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10 <bold>(</bold>0.87–1.39<bold>)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Two post-COVID symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.37 (1.11–1.69)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.95 <bold>(</bold>0.76–1.19<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 <bold>(</bold>0.75–1.56<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13 <bold>(</bold>0–85-1.50<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14 <bold>(</bold>0.89–1.46<bold>)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Three or more post-COVID symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.50 (1.26–1.80)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.87 <bold>(</bold>0.70–1.07<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.92 (1.47–2.51)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.54 (1.23–1.92)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.54 (1.27–1.87)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Number of symptoms (n = 1395)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> One post-COVID symptom*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Two post-COVID symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17 <bold>(</bold>0.91–1.50<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.90 <bold>(</bold>0.70–1.17<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84 <bold>(</bold>0.56–1.27<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05 <bold>(</bold>0.75–1.46<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05 <bold>(</bold>0.78–1.41<bold>)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Three-four post-COVID symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 <bold>(</bold>0.89–1.50<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.89 <bold>(</bold>0.66–1.19<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29 <bold>(</bold>0.88–1.89<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.57 (1.14 2.16)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.57 (1.19–2.06)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Five or more post-COVID symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.45 (1.12–1.89)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.81 <bold>(</bold>0.57–1.13<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.83 (1.26–2.64)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.37 <bold>(</bold>0.98–1.93<bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.39 (1.03–1.90)</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant values are in [bold].</p><p>PHC, primary health care; GP, general practitioner.</p><p>Adjusted by sex, age, marital status, education, medical comorbidities, and hospitalization.</p><p>*Comparison group.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par19">When grouping the number of long COVID symptoms into quartiles, it was observed that compared to individuals with only one long COVID symptom, those with five or more symptoms were PR 1.45 (95%CI 1.12–1.89) times more likely to use PHC services, PR 1.83 (95%CI 1.26–2.64) times more likely to use emergency services, and PR 1.39 (95%CI 1.03–1.90) times more likely to use specialized services (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Compared to individuals without long COVID, those with two and three or more long COVID symptoms were PR 1.37 (95%CI 1.11–1.69) and PR 1.50 (95%CI 1.26–1.80) times more likely to use PHC services, respectively. Furthermore, compared to individuals without long COVID, those with three or more symptoms were PR 1.92 (95%CI 1.47–2.51) times more likely to use emergency services, PR 1.54 (95%CI 1.47–2.51) more likely to use specialist doctors’ services, and PR 1.54 (95%CI 1.27–1.87) times more likely to use specialized services (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par20">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> presents the prevalence of using health services according to the long COVID symptoms. The prevalence of using PHC services ranged from 29.5% in patients with anosmia to 45.2% in those with nausea or vomiting. The prevalence of using GP services ranged from 22.7% in those with mucus to 46.6% in those with rhinorrhea, while that of using emergency services ranged from 2.0% in those with diarrhea to 35.9% in those with breathing discomfort. Using specialist doctors’ services ranged from 21.8% in those with ageusia to 38.2% in those with breathing discomfort, whereas using specialized services ranged from 27.0% in patients with anosmia to 47.3% in those with breathing discomfort (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Prevalence of health service use according to the long COVID symptom type in South Brazil (n = 1395).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PHC</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GP</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Emergency services</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specialist doctors</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specialized services</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.6 (31.6–42.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.4 (22.0–31.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5 (19.3–28.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.4 (20.1–29.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.6 (24.9–34.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.4 (33.9–47.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.5 (22.7–35.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.9 (21.3–33.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.6 (24.7–37.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.8 (32.4–45.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dry cough</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.0 (33.0–49.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.4 (22.3–37.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.7 (17.2–31.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.4 (22.3–37.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.3 (27.7–43.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mucus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.9 (21.9–50.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7 (12.5–37.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.5 (10.8–35.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.5 (17.7–45.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.8 (19.5–47.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Breathing discomfort</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.8 (35.5–52.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.3 (26.7–43.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.9 (28.2–44.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.2 (30.2–46.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.3 (38.9–56.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ageusia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.3 (25.1–36.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.9 (24.8–35.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.3 (14.0–23.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.8 (17.3–27.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8 (22.8–33.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anosmia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.5 (24.8–34.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.5 (23.9–33.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.5 (14.6–23.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.3 (18.1–27.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.0 (22.4–32.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Altered sensitivity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.3 (35.3–51.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.8 (18.432.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0 (22.1–36.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.6 (23.5–38.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.6 (29.9–45.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.1 (32.2–40.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.7 (27.0–34.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.4 (18.2–25.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.2 (25.6–33.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.2 (21.4–29.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rhinorrhea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4 (30.2–49.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.6 (23.5–41.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.0 (19.1–36.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0 (26.2–44.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.4 (31.1–50.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nasal congestion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.3 (27.0–46.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.3 (23.5–42.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.3 (20.9–39.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.4 (21.8–40.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.1 (25.0–44.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nausea/vomiting</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.2 (28.3–63.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.1 (14.9–46.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.4 (19.7–52.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.4 (19.7–52.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.8 (27.4–63.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diarrhea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.4 (16.2–47.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.7 (13.6–43.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.0–3.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.6 (15.8–46.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.4 (17.9–49.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Joint pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.0 (37.1–49.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.2 (23.1–33.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.9 (20.0–30.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.3 (25.0–36.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.1 (30.5–42.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Myalgia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.9 (38.3–49.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.0 (25.9–36.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.2 (20.5–30.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.6 (22.8–33.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.9 (29.7–40.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Memory loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.9 (28.9–37.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.1 (25.3–33.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.6 (15.4–22.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0 (25.3–33.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.2 (30.3–38.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Attention loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.4 (30.9–40.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.2 (26.9–35.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.9 (12.7–19.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0 (24.8–33.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.3 (31.7–41.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Post-COVID Symptom grouped by affected system</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Musculoskeletal<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.1 (28.9–33.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.7 (24.6–28.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.6 (13.9–17.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.4 (20.4–24.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.4 (9.0–12.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Neurological<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3 (30.4–36.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.1 (25.4–31.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.1 (15.8–20.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.1 (22.5–27.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.4 (11.4–15.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Digestive<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.3 (27.7–52.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.0 (17.3–39.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.6 (18.6–41.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.7 (21.3–44.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.0 (11.6–32.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Respiratory<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.6 (34.2–43.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.2 (25.2–33.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.7 (20.8–28.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.7 (24.7–33.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.8 (12.7–19.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant values are in [bold].</p><p>Adjusted by sex, age, marital status, education, medical comorbidities and hospitalization.</p><p>PHC, primary health care; GP, general practitioner.</p><p><sup>a</sup>Digestive (nausea/vomiting and diarrhea); <sup>b</sup>Musculoskeletal (myalgia, joint pain); <sup>c</sup>Neurological (headache, memory loss, loss of attention, ageusia an anosmia); <sup>d</sup>Respiratory (dyspnea, dry cough/mucus, breathing discomfort, runny nose, nasal congestion, rhinorrhea).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par21">The adjusted analysis revealed that individuals with breathing discomfort were PR 1.58 (95%CI 1.20–2.09) times more likely to use PHC services than those without it. Individuals who had altered sensitivity were PR 1.59 (95%CI 1.24–2.04) times more likely to use PHC services than those who did not have them. Individuals with breathing discomfort were PR 2.61 (95%CI 1.86–3.67) times more likely to use emergency services than those without it. Individuals with nasal congestion were PR 2.62 (95%CI 1.81–3.80) times more likely to use emergency services than those without it. Moreover, individuals with nasal congestion were PR 1.51 (95%CI 1.03–2.21) times more likely to visit doctors than those without it. Individuals who had memory loss were PR 1.49 (95%CI 1.21–1.82) times more likely to visit specialist doctors than those who did not have it. Individuals with myalgia were PR 2.06 (95%CI 1.43–2.95) times more likely to use specialized services than those without it. Individuals who had altered sensitivity were PR 1.91 (95%CI 1.17–3.14) times more likely to use specialized services than those who did not have them (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Association between health services use and long COVID symptoms in South Brazil, 2021 (n = 2919).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PHC</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GP</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Emergency services</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specialist doctors</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specialized services</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.35 (1.11–1.64)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87 (0.68–1.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.53 (1.15–2.04)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27 (0.96–1.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29 (0.86–1.96)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.35 (1.06–1.71)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.70 (0.49–1.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.02 (1.48–2.76)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05 (0.76–1.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36 (0.86–2.17)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dry cough</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.37 (1.04–1.80)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.70 (0.45–1.10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.43 (0.93–2.20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04 (0.71–1.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49 (0.89–2.49)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mucus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 (0.53–1.74)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34 (0.09–1.23)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22 (0.53–2.82)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 (0.41–1.82)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44 (0.07–2.74)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Breathing discomfort</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.58 (1.20–2.09)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02 (0.70–1.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.61 (1.86–3.67)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27 (0.87–1.84)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.73 (1.00–3.01)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ageusia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97 (0.76–1.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 (0.66–1.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30 (0.93–1.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04 (0.79–1.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07 (0.67–1.72)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anosmia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06 (0.85–1.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84 (0.66–1.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28 (0.93–1.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">099 (0.74–1.30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14 (0.74–1.73)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Altered sensitivity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.59 (1.24–2.04)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 (0.58–1.29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.97 (1.39–2.82)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.37 (0.96–1.94)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.91 (1.17–3.14)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue / asthenia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.22 (1.03–1.44)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 (0.81–1.18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.48 (1.15–1.89)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.29 (1.05–1.59)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.59 (1.16–2.19)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rhinorrhea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31 (0.91–1.88)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 (0.66–1.47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.30 (1.56–3.37)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41 (0.99–2.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.84 (1.09–3.10)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nasal congestion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.49 (1.05–2.12)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 (0.60–1.58)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.62 (1.81–3.80)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.51 (1.03–2.21)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.37 (0.70–2.69)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nausea/vomiting</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.57 (0.91–2.73)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13 (0.57–2.30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.33 (1.22–4.50)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68 (0.94–2.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00 (0.67–5.91)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diarrhea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (0.50–2.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20 (0.68–2.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.91 (0.94–3.89)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60 (0.21–1.70)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47 (0.07–3.28)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Joint pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.57 (1.29–1.90)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83 (0.61–1.12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.87 (1.39–2.53)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26 (0.96–1.64)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.50 (0.98–2.29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Myalgia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.42 (1.16–1.74)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95 (0.72–1.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.66 (1.23–2.23)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.75–1,31)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.06 (1.43–2.95)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Memory loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13 (0.94–1.36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (0.82–1.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17 (0.88–1.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.49 (1.21–1.82)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.45 (1.04–2.03)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Attention loss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.27 (1.06–1.54)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (0.82–1.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 (0.69–1.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.32 (1.06–1.65)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.64 (1.16–2.31)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Post-COVID Symptom grouped by affected system</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Musculoskeletal<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.26 (1.09–1.45)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (0.87–1.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10 (0.88–1.36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 (0.96–1.37)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24 (0.93–1.64)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Neurological<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.27 (1.10–1.47)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 (0.82–1.12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.31 (1.05–1.64)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.35 (1.13–1.61</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.44 (1.07–1.93)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Digestive<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31 (0.85–2.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21 (0.77–1.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.24 (1.38–3.64)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18 (0.72–1.93)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18 (0.44–3.15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Respiratory<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.45 (1.22–1.71)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 (0.69–1.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.06 (1.63–2.61)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18 (0.94–1.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28 (0.90–1.83)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant values are in [bold].</p><p>Adjusted by sex, age, marital status, education, medical comorbidities and hospitalization.</p><p>PHC, primary health care; GP, general practitioner;</p><p><sup>a</sup>Digestive (nausea/vomiting and diarrhea); <sup>b</sup>Musculoskeletal (myalgia, joint pain; <sup>c</sup>Neurological (headache, memory loss, loss of attention, ageusia an anosmia; <sup>d</sup>Respiratory (dyspnea, dry cough/mucus, breathing discomfort, runny nose, nasal congestion, rhinorrhea).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par22">The use of health services by long COVID symptom cluster is also summarized in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, which shows that individuals reporting respiratory symptoms were PR 1.45 (95CI% 1.22–1.71) times more likely to use PHC services than those with other types of long COVID symptoms. Participants who had digestive symptoms were PR 2.24 (95%CI 1.38–3.64) times more likely to use emergency services than those with other symptoms, whereas those with neurological symptoms were PR 1.35 (95%CI 1.13–1.61) and PR 1.44 (95%CI 1.07–1.93) times more likely to visit specialist doctors and use specialized services, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par23">When calculating the EF, if long COVID were eliminated, it would be possible to reduce the demand for PHC services by 14.0%, emergency services by 18.6%, specialized services by 11.7%, and specialist doctors’ services by 11.8%.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">This study revealed a higher use of overall health services, including PHC services, emergency services, specialist doctors’ services, and specialized services, by individuals with long COVID in South Brazil. Attending specialist doctors’ services and specialized services were frequently used by people with neurological symptoms of long COVID. A dose–response effect was observed between the number of long COVID symptoms and the high tendency to use PHC services, emergency services, specialist doctors’ services, and specialized services.</p><p id="Par25">In contrast to the results of our study, previous studies have shown a lower prevalence of using health services by individuals with COVID-19. Similarly, the prevalence of the use of emergency services after SARS-CoV-2 infection was 14.6% in the United States<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The comparison between the data from our research and the previous studies mentioned should be conducted cautiously, given the methodological differences between the studies, such as the temporality of data collection, the symptom profile of the respondents, the sociocultural and economic differences and the different health care models between countries.</p><p id="Par26">Whittaker et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> reported a higher tendency of using PHC services in individuals with long COVID 12 months after infection, corroborating the results of our study. Furthermore, this study revealed a specific pattern of symptoms, with individuals with musculoskeletal, respiratory, and neurological post-COVID symptoms showing a higher tendency to use PHC and specialized services. Notably, studies before the pandemic had highlighted deficiencies in the provision of certain care in PHC, which led to greater use of emergency services, and even specialized services during the COVID-19 pandemic. This further reinforced the fragility of PHC in keeping up with patient demands and the need for investment to expand the supply, access, and resoluteness of the PHC services to treat the musculoskeletal, respiratory, and neurological problems associated with long COVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Similar to our findings, previous studies have shown increased use of specialized services due to long COVID, highlighting the need for expanding the access and training of services to meet this demand<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. However, in Brazil, access to free specialized health services by SUS is a historical bottleneck that aggravated during the pandemic due to insufficient supply and healthcare professionals, in addition to the concentration of assistive devices in the private sector<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par27">An important finding of this study is the identification of a dose–response effect, where individuals with more long COVID symptoms are more likely to utilize healthcare services. Although the association between greater severity of acute SARS-COV-2 infection and the development of COVID-19 symptoms is found in the literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> this does not mean that those with asymptomatic or mild infections have zero or low risk of developing Long COVID. Accordingly, strategies decreasing the risk of severe COVID-19, such as vaccination, could be associated with reduced healthcare use. Whittaker and colleagues identified that PHC consultation rates decreased after vaccination for some long-lasting COVID-19 symptoms, such as ageusia, anosmia, and respiratory distress. They also found that patients who received at least one dose of the COVID-19 vaccine had low rates of usage of all health resources, including PHC and emergency services, after vaccination. This reinforces the relevance of vaccination as a public health strategy to not only protect from severe acute infection but also reduce the long COVID severity, thereby reducing potential use of healthcare services<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Therefore, new studies evaluating the capacity of health services to meet the new demands to manage long COVID as well as obtaining investments to expand their potential according to the utilization pattern of each service in long COVID cases are warranted. (2) In item 18, include the use of a mask, which remains an accessible form of protection against transmission and is especially relevant in healthcare settings. The sentence should be like this: “lack of COVID protection policies (e.g. masking, air filtration systems specifically improved to prevent infections)” Data from this study are relevant given the high burden and costs of managing COVID-19 in Brazil and the current experiences of several countries, which have led to delays in vaccine acquisition, lack of COVID-protective policies (e.g., masking, air filtration systems specifically improved to prevent infections), instability in healthcare management, encouragement of treatment without scientific efficacy and lack of increased funding for healthcare services. The strengths of this study are its representative sample of non-hospitalized individuals with SARS-COV-2 infection with a high response rate, thorough diagnosis using the gold standard RT-PCR test, and the inclusion of a comparison group of people who had SARS-CoV-2 infection but did not develop long COVID. About limitations, first, data collection was conducted during the second wave of the pandemic in Brazil, with tighter social restrictions, which could have underestimated the use of health services, since health services were used by those with severe long COVID symptoms. Second, this study may have survival bias, as infected individuals with more severe illnesses may have died in the months following acute infection, leading to an underestimation of health service utilization. Third, this study was planned in February 2021, when research on long COVID was beginning, so our study design did not include some relevant symptoms of long COVID, such as post-exertional malaise. Fourth, due to the temporality of the study, it may present recall bias, as some individuals may not clearly remember the use of health services and symptoms of long COVID. Finally, health services were not analyzed between the SUS and the use of private services. Additionally, no expenditure on medicines was recorded.</p><p id="Par28">This study shows the use of health services by individuals with long COVID, especially PHC services, emergency services, and specialized services in South Brazil. Moreover, it was observed that the greater the number of long COVID symptoms, the greater the tendency to use PHC and emergency services. Different strategies to ensure qualified care to individuals with long COVID could decrease the economic and healthcare burden, like re-composition of the healthcare teams to meet the new demand, training and continuing education of healthcare professionals, teleconsultation to provide equitable and comprehensive healthcare where there is a shortage of professionals, shared consultation of certain long COVID symptoms, avoiding unnecessary referrals.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>YPV and JQSR were financed by the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior—Brasil (CAPES). BPN receives a level 2 Research Productivity grant from National Council for Scientific and Technological Development – CNPq (process number 308772/2022-9).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors contributed to the study concept and design. YPV and JQSR collected data. YPV performed all statistical analyses. MOS supervised the study. YPV, JQSR, VFSV wrote the article. YPV, JQSR, VFSV, BPN, LAF, SMSD, RGN, CFLP revised the final version. All authors contributed to interpretation of data. All authors contributed to drafting the paper. All authors revised the text for intellectual content and have read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Rio Grande do Sul (FAPERGS), Brazil (grant number: 21/2551-0000107-0), SUS Research Program: Shared Management in Health (PPSUS).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par29">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par30">This research involves human participants and was carried out in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations of the Declaration of Helsinki and this study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee in Health Research of the Federal University of Rio Grande (Certificate of Submission for Ethical Evaluation nº 39081120.0 0.0000.5324). This research complied with the specific resolution of the National Health Council (466/2012) and informed consent was obtained from all subjects in accordance with the resolution of the Free and Informed Consent Term of the National Health Council.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Assis</surname><given-names>MMA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jesus</surname><given-names>WLA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Access to health services: Approaches, concepts, policies and analysis model</article-title><source>Cien Saude Colet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2865</fpage><lpage>2875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1413-81232012001100002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23175292</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Assis, M. M. A. &amp; de Jesus, W. L. A. Access to health services: Approaches, concepts, policies and analysis model. <italic toggle="yes">Cien Saude Colet.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 2865–2875 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23175292</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/s1413-81232012001100002</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viacava</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>RAD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laguardia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellido</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SUS: Supply, access and use of health services in the last 30 years</article-title><source>Cien. Saude Colet</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1751</fpage><lpage>1762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1413-81232018236.06022018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972484</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Viacava, F., de Oliveira, R. A. D., Carvalho, C. C., Laguardia, J. &amp; Bellido, J. G. SUS: Supply, access and use of health services in the last 30 years. <italic toggle="yes">Cien. Saude Colet</italic><bold>23</bold>, 1751–1762 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972484</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1413-81232018236.06022018</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabaan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smajlović</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tombuloglu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ćordić</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajdarević</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kudić</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 infection and multi-organ system damage: A review</article-title><source>Bosn. J. Basic Med. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17305/bjbms.2022.7762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9901898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36124445</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Rabaan, A. A. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> SARS-CoV-2 infection and multi-organ system damage: A review. <italic toggle="yes">Bosn. J. Basic Med. Sci.</italic>10.17305/bjbms.2022.7762 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veruttipong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winget</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship of socio-demographics, comorbidities, symptoms and healthcare access with early COVID-19 presentation and disease severity</article-title><source>BMC Infect. Dis.</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>40</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-05764-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33421991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7794633</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Vaughan, L. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Relationship of socio-demographics, comorbidities, symptoms and healthcare access with early COVID-19 presentation and disease severity. <italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect. Dis.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 40 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33421991</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-021-05764-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7794633</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of novel coronavirus COVID-19 on noncommunicable disease patients and health systems: A review</article-title><source>J. Intern. Med.</source><year>2021</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joim.13184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33020988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7675448</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Chang, A. Y., Cullen, M. R., Harrington, R. A. &amp; Barry, M. The impact of novel coronavirus COVID-19 on noncommunicable disease patients and health systems: A review. <italic toggle="yes">J. Intern. Med.</italic><bold>289</bold>, 450–462 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33020988</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/joim.13184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7675448</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falvey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrante</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flattening the disability curve: Rehabilitation and recovery after COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>Hear Lung.</source><year>2020</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hrtlng.2020.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7211743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32457005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Falvey, J. R. &amp; Ferrante, L. E. Flattening the disability curve: Rehabilitation and recovery after COVID-19 infection. <italic toggle="yes">Hear Lung.</italic><bold>49</bold>, 440–441 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.hrtlng.2020.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7211743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32457005</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>KOB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Labor, health and vulnerability in the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Cad Saude Publ.</source><year>2021</year><volume>2021</volume><fpage>36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/0102-311X00178320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33331542</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Santos, K. O. B. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Labor, health and vulnerability in the COVID-19 pandemic. <italic toggle="yes">Cad Saude Publ.</italic><bold>2021</bold>, 36 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/0102-311X00178320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33331542</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>EAS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Challeges in the fight againt the COVID-19 pandemic in university hospitals</article-title><source>Rev. Paul Pediatr.</source><year>2020</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1984-0462/2020/38/2020086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7176336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32320999</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Medeiros, E. A. S. Challeges in the fight againt the COVID-19 pandemic in university hospitals. <italic toggle="yes">Rev. Paul Pediatr.</italic><bold>38</bold>, 2 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1984-0462/2020/38/2020086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7176336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32320999</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-de-las-Peñas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: Current definition</article-title><source>Infection</source><year>2022</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s15010-021-01696-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34519974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8438555</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Fernández-de-las-Peñas, C. Long COVID: Current definition. <italic toggle="yes">Infection</italic><bold>50</bold>, 285–286 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34519974</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s15010-021-01696-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8438555</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus</article-title><source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>e102</fpage><lpage>e107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Soriano, J. B., Murthy, S., Marshall, J. C., Relan, P. &amp; Diaz, J. V. A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet Infect. Dis.</italic><bold>22</bold>, e102–e107 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Post COVID-19 condition (Long COVID). Disponible in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition">https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition</ext-link> (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tozato</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>BFC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalavina</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molinari</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dos Santos Alves</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiopulmonary rehabilitation in post-COVID-19 patients: Case series</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Ter. Intensiva.</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33886866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5935/0103-507X.20210018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8075336</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Tozato, C., Ferreira, B. F. C., Dalavina, J. P., Molinari, C. V. &amp; Dos Santos Alves, V. L. Cardiopulmonary rehabilitation in post-COVID-19 patients: Case series. <italic toggle="yes">Rev. Bras. Ter. Intensiva.</italic><bold>33</bold>, 167–171 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33886866</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5935/0103-507X.20210018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8075336</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabowski</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joynt Maddox</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postacute care preparedness for COVID-19</article-title><source>JAMA.</source><year>2020</year><volume>323</volume><fpage>2007</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.4686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32211831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9901818</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Grabowski, D. C. &amp; Joynt Maddox, K. E. Postacute care preparedness for COVID-19. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA.</italic><bold>323</bold>, 2007 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32211831</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2020.4686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9901818</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sculthorpe</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>More than 100 persistent symptoms of SARS-CoV-2 (Long COVID): A scoping review</article-title><source>Front. Med.</source><year>2021</year><volume>2021</volume><fpage>8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2021.750378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8591053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34790680</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Hayes, L. D., Ingram, J. &amp; Sculthorpe, N. F. More than 100 persistent symptoms of SARS-CoV-2 (Long COVID): A scoping review. <italic toggle="yes">Front. Med.</italic><bold>2021</bold>, 8 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2021.750378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8591053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34790680</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SUS 30 anos: o início, a caminhada e o rumo</article-title><source>Ciênc. Saúde Coletiva.</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1729</fpage><lpage>1736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1413-81232018236.06092018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972482</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">dos Santos, N. R. SUS 30 anos: o início, a caminhada e o rumo. <italic toggle="yes">Ciênc. Saúde Coletiva.</italic><bold>23</bold>(6), 1729–1736. 10.1590/1413-81232018236.06092018 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1413-81232018236.06092018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972482</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">BRASIL. Ministry of Health. Secretary of Health Care. In <italic toggle="yes">Department of Primary Care. National Primary Care Policy/Ministry of Health. Secretary of Health Care. Department of Primary Care. Brasília</italic> (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bleicher L, Bleicher T. Esse-tal-de SUS. In <italic toggle="yes">Saúde para todos, já! EDUFBA</italic> 15–40 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ugá</surname><given-names>MAD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porto</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The public-private mix in the Brazilian Health System: funding, supply and use of health services</article-title><source>Cien Saude Colet.</source><year>2008</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1431</fpage><lpage>1440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1413-81232008000500009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18813646</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Santos, I. S., Ugá, M. A. D. &amp; Porto, S. M. The public-private mix in the Brazilian Health System: funding, supply and use of health services. <italic toggle="yes">Cien Saude Colet.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 1431–1440 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18813646</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/s1413-81232008000500009</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of assistance in the Primary Care service in a municipality in Espírito Santo according to sociodemographic profile and health conditions</article-title><source>Rev. APS.</source><year>2022</year><volume>2022</volume><fpage>25</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Barros, C. A., da Silva, K. S. &amp; Ramos, E. G. Use of assistance in the Primary Care service in a municipality in Espírito Santo according to sociodemographic profile and health conditions. <italic toggle="yes">Rev. APS.</italic><bold>2022</bold>, 25 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poças</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perillo</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernal</surname><given-names>RTI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malta</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First choice for use of health services by the adult population of the Federal District, 2015: A population-based survey</article-title><source>Epidemiol. Serv. Saúde.</source><year>2019</year><volume>2019</volume><fpage>28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5123/S1679-49742019000200017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31365688</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Poças, K. C., Perillo, R. D., Bernal, R. T. I., Malta, D. C. &amp; Duarte, E. C. First choice for use of health services by the adult population of the Federal District, 2015: A population-based survey. <italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol. Serv. Saúde.</italic><bold>2019</bold>, 28 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5123/S1679-49742019000200017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31365688</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiavegatto Filho</surname><given-names>ADP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campanha</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogadouro</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cambraia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patterns and predictors of health service use among people with mental disorders in São Paulo metropolitan area, Brazil</article-title><source>Epidemiol. Psychiatr. Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S2045796016000202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27066821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6998653</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Wang, Y.-P. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Patterns and predictors of health service use among people with mental disorders in São Paulo metropolitan area, Brazil. <italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol. Psychiatr. Sci.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 89–101 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27066821</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S2045796016000202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6998653</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moretto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boing</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of the use of physiotherapy services among the urban adult population of Lages, Santa Catarina</article-title><source>Braz. J. Phys. Ther.</source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1413-35552009005000023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Moretto, L., Longo, G., Boing, A. &amp; Arruda, M. Prevalence of the use of physiotherapy services among the urban adult population of Lages, Santa Catarina. <italic toggle="yes">Braz. J. Phys. Ther.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 130–135 (2009).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rech</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bulgarelli</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Condessa</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilgert</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Goulart</surname><given-names>BNG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Access and use of speech therapy services in Porto Alegre, Brazil: population study</article-title><source>Cien Saude Colet.</source><year>2020</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1413-81232020253.17212018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32159652</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Rech, R. S. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Access and use of speech therapy services in Porto Alegre, Brazil: population study. <italic toggle="yes">Cien Saude Colet.</italic><bold>25</bold>, 817–825 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32159652</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1413-81232020253.17212018</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menges</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballouz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anagnostopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aschmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domenghino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Burden of post-COVID-19 syndrome and implications for healthcare service planning: A population-based cohort study</article-title><source>PLoS One.</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>e0254523</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0254523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34252157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8274847</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Menges, D. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Burden of post-COVID-19 syndrome and implications for healthcare service planning: A population-based cohort study. <italic toggle="yes">PLoS One.</italic><bold>16</bold>, e0254523 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34252157</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0254523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8274847</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Folk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravichadran</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maric</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donlan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emergency department bounceback characteristics for patients diagnosed with COVID-19</article-title><source>Am. J. Emerg. Med.</source><year>2021</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2021.04.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33945978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8054547</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Haag, A. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Emergency department bounceback characteristics for patients diagnosed with COVID-19. <italic toggle="yes">Am. J. Emerg. Med.</italic><bold>47</bold>, 239–243 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33945978</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajem.2021.04.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8054547</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gulea</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koteci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kallis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwundu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GP consultation rates for sequelae after acute covid-19 in patients managed in the community or hospital in the UK: population based study</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2021</year><volume>2021</volume><fpage>e065834</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj-2021-065834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8715128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34965929</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Whittaker, H. R. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> GP consultation rates for sequelae after acute covid-19 in patients managed in the community or hospital in the UK: population based study. <italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic><bold>2021</bold>, e065834 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj-2021-065834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8715128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34965929</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrimpf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braesigk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleckwenn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management and treatment of long COVID symptoms in general practices: An online-based survey</article-title><source>Front. Public Heal.</source><year>2022</year><volume>2022</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2022.937100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9513068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36176520</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Schrimpf, A., Braesigk, A., Lippmann, S. &amp; Bleckwenn, M. Management and treatment of long COVID symptoms in general practices: An online-based survey. <italic toggle="yes">Front. Public Heal.</italic><bold>2022</bold>, 10 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2022.937100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9513068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36176520</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Provision of primary care by specialist physicians: A systematic review</article-title><source>Fam. Med. Commun. Heal.</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e000247</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/fmch-2019-000247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7046372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32148734</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Hashim, M. J. Provision of primary care by specialist physicians: A systematic review. <italic toggle="yes">Fam. Med. Commun. Heal.</italic><bold>8</bold>, e000247 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/fmch-2019-000247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7046372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32148734</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sounderajah</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashrafian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and predictors of acute and chronic post-COVID syndrome: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>eClinicalMedicine.</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>100899</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34036253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8141371</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Iqbal, F. M. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Characteristics and predictors of acute and chronic post-COVID syndrome: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic toggle="yes">eClinicalMedicine.</italic><bold>36</bold>, 100899 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34036253</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8141371</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massuda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hone</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leles</surname><given-names>FAG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Castro</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Brazilian health system at crossroads: Progress, crisis and resilience</article-title><source>BMJ Glob. Heal.</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e000829</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2018-000829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6035510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29997906</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Massuda, A., Hone, T., Leles, F. A. G., de Castro, M. C. &amp; Atun, R. The Brazilian health system at crossroads: Progress, crisis and resilience. <italic toggle="yes">BMJ Glob. Heal.</italic><bold>3</bold>, e000829 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjgh-2018-000829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6035510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29997906</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Claudia Marques Canabrava. Acesso à atenção hospitalar especializada no SUS na pandemia de COVID-19: Expansão, insuficiências e iniquidades. In <italic toggle="yes">Acesso e cuidados especializados/Organizadoras: Santos, Alethele de Oliveira Lopes, Luciana Tolêdo Conselho Nacional dos Secretários de Saúde. Brasília</italic> 324 (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Burdens of post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 by severity of acute infection, demographics and health status</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>6571</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-26513-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34772922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8589966</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Xie, Y., Bowe, B. &amp; Al-Aly, Z. Burdens of post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 by severity of acute infection, demographics and health status. <italic toggle="yes">Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 6571 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34772922</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-021-26513-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8589966</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Victora</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurzenda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>França</surname><given-names>GVA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>AJD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the early impact of vaccination against COVID-19 on deaths among elderly people in Brazil: Analyses of routinely-collected data on vaccine coverage and mortality</article-title><source>eClinicalMedicine.</source><year>2021</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>101036</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34308302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8283303</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Victora, C. G. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Estimating the early impact of vaccination against COVID-19 on deaths among elderly people in Brazil: Analyses of routinely-collected data on vaccine coverage and mortality. <italic toggle="yes">eClinicalMedicine.</italic><bold>38</bold>, 101036 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34308302</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8283303</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasileiou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of first dose of COVID-19 vaccines against hospital admissions in Scotland: National Prospective Cohort Study of 5.4 Million People</article-title><source>SSRN Electron. J.</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3789264</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Vasileiou, E. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Effectiveness of first dose of COVID-19 vaccines against hospital admissions in Scotland: National Prospective Cohort Study of 5.4 Million People. <italic toggle="yes">SSRN Electron. J.</italic>10.2139/ssrn.3789264 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>