<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">63</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcph</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12487085</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12487085.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12487085</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12487085</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41029357</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-025-24446-w</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">24446</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluating post-acute COVID-19 sequelae in younger population using symptom burden questionnaire (SQL)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhariwal</surname><given-names initials="R">Rupal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakkar</surname><given-names initials="K">Krishna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaghela</surname><given-names initials="K">Kritagnasinh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names initials="M">Mukul</given-names></name><address><email>mukul.jain19640@paruluniversity.ac.in</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/024v3fg07</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.510466.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 5998 4868</institution-id><institution>Research and development Cell, </institution><institution>Parul University, </institution></institution-wrap>Vadodara, Gujarat 391760 India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/024v3fg07</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.510466.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 5998 4868</institution-id><institution>Department of Life Sciences, Parul Institute of Applied Sciences, </institution><institution>Parul University, </institution></institution-wrap>Vadodara, Gujarat 391760 India </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Parul Institute of Medical Science and Research, Vadodara, Gujarat 391760 India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478168</issue-id><elocation-id>3195</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-02 10:25:43.597"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12889_2025_Article_24446.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The COVID-19 pandemic, declared by the World Health Organization on March 11, 2020, has led to over 650 million infections globally and a significant burden of long-term health issues, termed post-COVID-19 condition (PCC) or long COVID or post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC). This cross-sectional study assesses the prevalence and distribution of persistent symptoms among individuals aged 18–25 years using the Symptom Burden Questionnaire™ for Long COVID (SBQ™-LC), which evaluates 123 symptoms across 17 health domains. Our hypothesis interprets that the pandemic has laid mental health challenges among younger populations, evidenced by increased rates of depression and anxiety. Data from participants revealed high rates of mental health issues, sleep disturbances, and cognitive dysfunctions, even among those with mild or asymptomatic infections. Notably, female participants reported higher symptom severity across most domains. This research underscores the necessity for targeted assessments of post-acute sequelae in young adults to enhance understanding and management of long COVID-related health issues.</p><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12889-025-24446-w.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Long-COVID</kwd><kwd>Symptom burden</kwd><kwd>Mental health</kwd><kwd>Clinical characteristics</kwd><kwd>Cognitive health</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Parul University</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">On 11 March, the World Health Organization (WHO) declared the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS‐CoV‐2) a pandemic. Globally, more than 650 million people have been infected with SARS-CoV-2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. While the leading symptoms during coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) are acute and the majority of patients fully recover, a significant fraction of patients now increasingly experience long-term health consequences. In October 2021, the World Health Organization (WHO) proposed a definition for what they referred to as “Post COVID-19 condition”. The condition was defined as the presence of symptoms lasting for at least 2 months in individuals with a history of probable or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The most recent estimate of people living with post-COVID-19 condition (also known as long COVID) globally has surpassed 65 million and, without a clear diagnostic criterion and with more than 200 reported symptoms including major ones such as fatigue, dysopnea, and neurocognitive decline are found to be associated with long COVID, affecting every organ system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The main disease hypotheses for the root causes of long COVID include viral persistence (infectious virus, viral RNA, or viral proteins), mitochondrial fatigue, autoimmunity triggered by the infection, reactivation of latent viruses, and inflammation-triggered chronic changes leading to microvascular damage and endothelial dysfunction. These conditions being more prominently found in middle-aged or older patients with clinical history has limited the research and focus on other minor but significantly impacting issues such as general health and lifestyle habits in daily routine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In addition, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), the prevalence of infection, hospitalization, and mortality among adults is significantly lower based on age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Thus, the younger adults may not directly exhibit similar patterns of health dysregulations as reported in elderly instead their symptoms may arise from pathways such as persistent low-grade inflammation, psychosocial and psychological stress, and disruption of circadian and metabolic homeostasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Also, long-term social isolation, increased screen time, academic or employment instability, and lifestyle changes during the pandemic may exacerbate mental health symptoms and contribute to long-term dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Through extensive literature survey it has been found that research following post COVID health assessments are more skewed towards elderly, adults with persisting comorbidities with not much larger scale work for younger groups and thus not much scalable volume of study has been specifically conducted to explore the epidemiological and clinical characteristics in younger patients with COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In the current work, we thus intend to analyze the presence of long-term COVID-19 symptoms and health dysfunctions in younger adults. For this purpose, we aim to use the Symptom Burden Questionnaire (SBQ™-LC) that measures symptom burden in adults (18 + years) with post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC), also known as “post COVID-19 condition” or “Long COVID” and is composed of 17 independently functioning scales of health, covering 123 different symptoms of Long COVID. The health parameters assessment could help identify the potential aftermaths prevailing in the specific cohort to provide timely interventions and assistance. A clear impact of Sars-CoV-2 virus on human body has been shown in the Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> below.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Chronic multi-organ health consequences of COVID-19 infection with long lasting negative impact</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methodology</title><p id="Par3">This was a prospective cross-sectional study approved by the Ethics Committee at Parul University, Vadodara (Approval no: PUIECHR/PIMSR/00/081734/7213). This cross-sectional study was carried out at the Parul University (PU), Vadodara from July 01, 2024, to September 20, 2024. The primary objective of the study was to identify the long-term health impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on younger adults. The secondary objectives were to (a) observe the psychological effects in younger adults that may indicate a sign of depression, or anxiety-like symptoms (b) compare the severity of prevailing symptoms and conditions on a gender basis. The workflow that has been considered for achieving these objectives is mentioned in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> above.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Flowchart explaining the survey assessment based patient selection and screening</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Population selection</title><p id="Par4">The questionnaire was evaluated on individuals aged 18 years or above and studied at Parul university, and consented for data collection were interviewed face to face with form filling done by the researchers alongside making it more of a random convenience sampling approach. Our survey included around 500 individuals, but out of this after quality control and exclusion of incomplete forms, 311 participants were included in the final analysis. The sampling was conducted within the university campus to minimize demographic variability and to represent a typical young adult population in a semi-urban Indian setting. For avoiding probable biasness, certain set of protocols were followed:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par5">The researchers i.e. interviewers followed a straight pattern of conversation, avoiding personal interpretations, and maintaining uniform behavior across interviews. No familiar participants were interviewed by any known interviewer.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par6">One-on-one interview was conducted with each participant ensuring no possible social interaction whilst giving the interview, thereby, ensuring comfort of the participants for answering accurately without any feeling of judgement.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par7">To prevent knowledge related biasness, participants who were previously enrolled or been a part of any post-COVID assessment survey or research were excluded.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par8">Thus, maximum care was taken to reduce disparity, enhance neutrality and maintain consistency throughout the questionnaire survey.</p><p id="Par9">The inclusion and exclusion criteria are being mentioned below:</p><p id="Par10">Inclusion:</p><p id="Par11">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par12">Individuals aged 18–25 years and present within the campus at the time of questionnaire.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par13">Individuals who volunteered to participate and committed to complete all the questionnaire.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par14">Individuals who had not previously engaged in any long COVID research were opted to ensure that the sample was unbiased by any prior knowledge or participation in similar studies.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par15">Exclusion:</p><p id="Par16">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par17">Individuals who had not properly completed all their questions were excluded.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par18">This research did not include individuals above 25 years of age.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">Individuals with ongoing COVID-19 infection were excluded to focus on post-acute COVID-19 symptoms.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par20">This survey involved the use of a SBQ™-LC that has been specially designed to target the individuals for assessing long-term COVID symptoms and their severity at the time of examination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. It has been applied here for the first time to a well-defined cohort of young adults aged 18–25 years after obtaining the non-commercial license free of charge for academic research purposes. SBQ™-LC assesses 123 different symptoms of PASC and comprises 17 scales covering all the aspects of human health. It took around 20 min to collect the data and information from each individual. Data on the education status, age, and medical history, including chronic disease, acute COVID-19 symptoms, COVID‐19 vaccine dosage status such as double/single dose, and any new condition developed were collected. As mentioned, participants reported their data, promoting high consistency in the collection process. The questionnaire was divided into sections, each targeting a specific symptom category, such as breathing, fatigue, circulation, mental health, and related problems. Each of the SBQ™-LC’s 17 scales returns a raw score which can be transformed to a linear 0-100 score. We have attached our questionnaire file in the supplement, in which we have mentioned various parameters and their symptoms, as well as the questions related to those parameters and their symptoms. This approach enabled the assessment of symptom frequency and severity across various health domains, including physical, mental, and neurological health.</p><p id="Par21">For data analysis purposes, normal descriptive statistics that summarized data, namely median and standard deviation(SD) were used. For numerical variables that were normally distributed, the median, and counts and percentages for categorical variables were utilized. Firstly, the analysis of each health parameter was done using Principle Component Analysis by considering them as independent variables helped us examine whether variance is detectable within the two different groups used. Afterwards, the relation between the dependent variables on independent variables were established using Pearson correlation coefficients, regression analysis for continuous variables by using Origin, Graph Pad Prism, and, Microsoft Excel 2019.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec5"><title>Demographics and basic characteristic profiling of the participants</title><p id="Par22">On analyzing the basic parameters, it was found that the age group of participant span from 18 to 25 years of age with median age of 22 years as evident in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Out of 311 patients analyzed in the study, there were 143 (45.9%) men and 168 (54.0%) women, with no significant differences in mean ages between the two (21.91 vs. 21.0, respectively). Further, while evaluating the impact of pandemic on the participating population, it was found that in total only 17.2% reported having contracted or being diagnosed with COVID-19 before the present diagnosis (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The data further suggests that majority of participants had only mild to moderate severity of acute COVID‐19 (18%) and around 82% didn’t develop the symptoms and were negative for infection, and only 1.6% of them have been admitted to the hospital. Broader infection status has been shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, depicting major (82%) population being uninfected and 4.5% infected during 1 st wave and 13.5% being infected during second wave respectively.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of participating population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total count</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Percent frequency</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean age count</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">143</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.0 ± 0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">168</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.91 ± 0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age group</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18–20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20–22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22–25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.4%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gender based infection status during COVID pandemic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.00%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.01%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">Regarding COVID-19 vaccinations, 93.2% of participants reported receiving two doses, and a small percentage (0.32%) had received the third or the precautionary dose <bold>(</bold>Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref><bold>).</bold> The most common vaccine received by the participants was Covishield (72.34%).<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Health characteristics profiling of the participating population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaccination type</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Individuals (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>) (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participants who received both dosages of the Covishield</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">188 (60.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participants who received both dosage of Covaxin</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (21.22%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participants who received one dosage of the Covishield and another of Covaxin</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (1.28%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participants who received both dosages of any of the vaccines along with a booster dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.32%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No vaccination</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (3.53%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Single dosage of Covaxin received</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (7.07%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Single dosage of Covishield received</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (6.10%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"> Infection rate prevalence in participants</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Positive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalized</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Post-COVID-19 Symptom Burden Across Health Domains</title><p id="Par24">The analysis of multiple health parameters’ as depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> indicates the dysregulation pattern being seen in the participating population. It has been evident that Mental Health &amp; Wellbeing, Sleep dysregulation were most prominently found. Based on these findings, these parameters were further evaluated in depth within all population sets.<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3 </label><caption><p>Graphical chart depicting the patterns of post-COVID-19-associated dysregulations in participating populations. Each symbol represents a different symptom or health-related domain assessed. The x-axis shows the median raw score, while the y-axis represents each domain. Higher median score represents higher dysregulations or dysfunction reporting</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Exploring gender-based health burden: analysis of contributing factors and their impact on overall health and well-being</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Analysis of the health burden impact on gender basis</title><p id="Par25">The major health factors raising concerns post-COVID-19 infection era majorly include mental health and well-being on the top, with sleep and Memory, Cognition, and Thinking also being highly affected. The total score of mental health &amp; well-being for males was 4276, and for females was 5592 [population average (M) = 4934] which means that a higher frequency of difficulties in functioning was seen in the female population. Within this parameter, the most frequently reported difficult and worsened functions were: feelings of loneliness, mood swings, and feeling of sadness. Similarly, the sleep patterns have been severely dysregulated in the women group with a total scoring of 5240 which is much higher as compared to the 4137 score of men [population average (M) = 4688]. Within the sleep domain, individuals reported frequent abruptions in sleep and slept shorter than usual. In terms of Memory, Thinking, and Communication, it was found that the total score of males i.e. 1871 was lesser than the reported score of females i.e. 2727 (Supplementary Fig. 1). A maximum of 17.68% of individuals reported difficulty in concentrating on their daily tasks and learnings that had an effect on their learning and academic performance. Also, 11.57% population indicating feeling confused about their surrounding events at times which is sometimes evident from the lack of attention in lectures and the indecisive nature of campus students. Further, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> reports the in depth description of problem being reported in highest percentage amongst the dysregulated parameters.<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Frequency distribution of reported issues across different health parameters (A) Mental health and well-being parameters, with the highest reporting for the prevalence in hopelessness category (B) Memory, Thinking, and Communication parameters showing concentration issue as the most frequently reported issue (C) Sleep parameters with insomnia/shorter sleeps being the most common concerns</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>The related factors and their impact on normal health and well-being</title><p id="Par26">Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the Pearson correlation coefficient matrix-based relation analysis to elaborate on the dependency and role of the dysfunctional health factors in the study population. We found that MCT positively correlated (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.52) with the sleep patterns dysregulations with an <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01 incidence suggesting highly significant positive rationale impact of one on another. MCT also show strong positive correlations with both mental health and wellbeing (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.63) and ENT scores (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.63), indicating that cognitive task performance may be supported by both psychological state and health factors. Such findings have been previously reported by Sharp J. et al., 2018 suggesting that even slightest of the stressors (i.e. mental stress) could affect performance on complex cognitive tasks in university aged people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Additionally, Sleep showed moderate associations with ENT (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.45) and a weaker relationship with mental health (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.33), suggesting that while sleep contributes positively to overall wellness and functioning, it may not severely align with these factors.<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Correlation matrix analyzing the interrelatedness of dysregulated health parameters being expressed in terms of correlation coefficient (Dark red showing most relatedness to dark blue showing least correlation)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Correlation matrix for gender specific parameters</title><p id="Par27">The Pearson correlation matrices (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>- A and B) provided a detailed insight into the interrelationships among key behavioral and cognitive parameters such as Sleep quality, MCT, Mental Health and Well-being, and ENT. It was found that MCT shows a highly positive relation with sleep patterns at <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.72 (95% CI) as evident briefly from Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> (A). The female matrix (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>- A) revealed consistently stronger and more interdependent correlations among all four variables, with the strongest association found between Sleep and MCT (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.73), followed closely by MCT and Mental Health (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.69). These findings suggest that in females, cognitive efficiency is highly sensitive to sleep quality and emotional state, supporting studies of enhanced neurocognitive plasticity in response to behavioral and emotional wellness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Correlation matrix depicting the inter-relatedness amongst the highly dysregulated health parameters in the young population (<bold>A</bold>) Female (<bold>B</bold>) Male. Females show stronger and more interconnected correlations across all domains, especially between MCT, mental health, and ENT variables. In contrast, males exhibit weaker associations, indicating more distinct and less integrated psychophysiological patterns</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">In respect to male population, it was found that MCT show a highly positive relation with sleep patterns at <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.64 (95%CI) and with Mental Health <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.52 as evident from Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>(B). However, the correlation between Sleep and Mental Health dropped to <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.31, and that between Mental Health and ENT declined sharply to <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.27 indicating unrelatedness between psychosocial-cognitive health. In conclusion, the higher interrelatedness between female factors depicts greater systemic sensitivity to internal and external stressors making them more responsive to sleep disruption, emotional fatigue, and environmental influences as also cited in Della et al., 2018 and Brubaker, et al., 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Regression analysis</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Linear regression analysis</title><p id="Par29">Linear regression analysis demonstrates a statistically significant, moderately strong positive correlation between sleep quality and ENT health in Fig. 7-A. While the model show R² = 0.26, suggesting 26% of the variance in ENT health, the upward linear incline shows the relevance of sleep hygiene in influencing ENT symptomatology. Thus, as individuals report better sleep patterns, they tend to exhibit fewer ENT-related health complaints. This show how systemic behaviors like sleep regulation can influence in somatic domains possibly by reducing inflammation, enhancing mucosal immunity, and modulating circadian-driven ENT functions.</p><p id="Par30">Similarly, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>-B depicts the linear regression relationship between Sleep Pattern and MCT reflecting a moderately strong positive linear relationship with a R² = 0.386. This suggests that 38% variance in Cognitive abilities is associated with sleeping patterns and style. This finding aligns with reports of Robbert Havekes et al., 2016 showing sleep’s role in synaptic plasticity, hippocampal activity, and executive processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p><bold>A</bold> The slope indicates a strong, statistically significant positive association between sleep and ENT health with slope value corresponding to 0.8439 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001; 95% CI); (<bold>B</bold>) The slope indicates a strong, statistically significant positive association between sleep and MCT with slope value corresponding to 1.037 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0005; 95% CI); (<bold>C</bold>) The slope indicates a strong, statistically significant positive association between sleep and Mental health with slope value corresponding to 0.637 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0009; 95% CI). Each red dot in the scatterplot represents an individual data point, the red regression line models the trend, and, grey shaded region shows the 95% confidence band</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO7" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">Likewise, Fig. 7-C shows a statistically significant and clinically relevant positive linear relationship between sleep pattern and mental health, supported by strong regression indicators, R² = 0.2444. This concludes on suggesting sleep as a non-negotiable factor for overall health wellbeing in participating population.</p><sec id="Sec14"><title>Multivariate regression analysis</title><p id="Par32">In this part, multivariate linear regression analysis was employed to evaluate the combined effect of multiple independent variables namely cognitive health, sleep pattern, ENT symptoms, and mental health outcomes. For Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, I(A), (B) it show that apart from mental health having the strongest negative correlation, cognitive health (β2) and sleep pattern (β3) also moderately negatively correlated (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>= −0.33 and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>= −0.45) with Mental Health. ENT pattern show a very weak correlation (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>= −0.02), aligning with its regression insignificance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.65, 95% CI). This regression model effectively shows that Cognitive Health is the strongest predictor of Mental Health and Wellbeing, followed by Sleep Pattern (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.047). ENT issues and gender (β4), while biologically relevant, do not show strong statistical support with significance of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.68, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.09 respectively.<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>I(A) Scatter plot with mental health as dependent variable depicting moderate clustering along the diagonal axis with a positive linear relationship, I(B) The correlation matrix of predictors showing dependency and independency with mental health having the strongest negative correlation with gender β4 <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>= −0.60 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value &lt; 0.0001, 95% CI) (β0: mental health, β1: cognitive health, β2: sleep pattern, β3: ENT pattern, β4: Gender). II(A) Scatter plot from a multivariate regression analysis, where the ENT pattern is the dependent variable shows residuals are fairly symmetric around the horizontal line indicating normal distribution, II(B); ENT dysfunction have strongest yet non-significant negative relationship with mental health (β3) (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>= −0.64, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.658, 95% CI) and strongest and significant relationship with cognitive health (β1) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt; 0.0001, 95% CI). (β0: ENT pattern, β1: Cognitive health, β2: Sleep pattern, β3: Mental health, β4: Gender). III(A)Scatter plot with cognitive health as a dependent variable showing predicted vs. observed values, closely aligned along the diagonal with less outliers, III(B); Heat map analysis indicates cognitive health as a dependent variable having non-significant weakest collinearity with gender (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>=−0.060, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.85, ns). (β0: Cognitive health, β1: Sleep pattern, β2: ENT pattern, β3: Mental health, β4: Gender). IV(A) Scatter plot of predicted vs. actual residual scores with sleep pattern as dependent variable indicating moderate spread around the line, suggesting residual variance and errors, IV(B): Correlation heat map of predictor variables (Mental health, Cognitive health, ENT, Gender) show minimal multi collinearity, with mental health (β3) (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.68). (β0: Sleep pattern, β1: Cognitive health, β2: ENT pattern, β3: Mental health, β4: Gender)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO8" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_Fig8_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par33">For II(A), (B), it was found that ENT health doesn’t rely and imply with mental health (β3) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.658, ns), gender (β4) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.1420, ns), however, found strongest relationship with cognitive health (β1) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt; 0.0001, CI 95%), sleep pattern (β2) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0002, 95% CI) indicating significant impact of ENT health on cognition, sleeping.</p><p id="Par34">For III(A), (B), the cognitive health parameter as a dependent variable non-significantly align with gender indicating least impact or coincidence with gender (β4) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.85, CI 95%). Similar to the findings of ENT dependency, it was found that cognitive health significantly relates with ENT health (β2) (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.13, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt; 0.001, 95% CI) as also evident from II(A), (B). Herein also, gender have no to least linearity with the ENT health (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.06, ns) and mental health (β3) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value &lt; 0.0001, 95% CI) also.</p><p id="Par35">For IV(A), (B), the sleep parameter as a dependent variable non-significantly align with gender indicating least impact or coincidence with mental health (β3) (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>= −0.68). Cognitive Health (β1) show strongest collinearity (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.27, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, 95% CI) with the sleep parameter alignment.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Development of new conditions in the participating community</title><p id="Par36">Nearly 8 (2.57%) of respondents reported the emergence of at least one new condition post-COVID-19 pandemic era. It has been noted that the prevalence of running nose and sneezing problems has risen after the COVID-19 pandemic era. This could relate to the fact that the olfactory system is the most prone, and affected by the infection. New or additional health incompatibilities were being noted in females, and no experience was reported from males:</p><p id="Par37">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par38">PCOS: This is a hormonal disorder common among women of reproductive age, characterized by irregular menstrual cycles, excess androgen (male hormone) levels, and polycystic ovaries. Post-COVID-19 era, the participating women have reported a rise in PCOS symptoms, possibly linked to stress, lifestyle changes, and potential endocrine impacts from the virus. Being a student stress and lifestyle may be considered as the major factor of all the possible reasons.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par39">Skin-related issues: Since the COVID-19 pandemic, skin conditions such as acne, dermatitis, and dryness have become more prevalent as the pandemic era led to prolonged mask covering, and constant sanitization that may have led to changes in skin health in long term.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par40">Hair fall: Major respondents have reported severe hair fall issues at the current time. This problem has been reported in both the symptomatic and asymptomatic population and may have become adverse due to increased level of stress hormones (like cortisol) and emotional distress related to the pandemic and post pandemic.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par41">Anosmia: Anosmia, or the loss of sense of smell, was a widely reported symptom of COVID-19, even among asymptomatic or mild cases.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par42">In our study, while over, 95% of the population had COVID-19 antibodies, 17.36% population reported testing positive for COVID-19 at any point. This gap is likely due to the high prevalence of asymptomatic infection, vaccination-induced antibodies, as well as low testing and potentially, stigma associated with reporting a positive test. To detail the health parameters impacted, the major health dysregulations reported have been in the factors corresponding to mental health and well-being, Sleep, Cognition &amp; Communication, and, ENT-related issues. Research by Garrigues E. et al., 2020 has reported that 30 to 40% of individuals with PASC are more susceptible to depression, post-traumatic stress disorder, and, anxiety owing to the long-term and destructive nature of the illness and the uncertainty of its outcome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Moreover, we find more significant associations in women, a growing area of research on the sex-specific effects of COVID-19, and gendered differences in disease experience. Of all the psychiatric symptoms found in studies, loneliness was the most prevalent symptom in participants with PASC, followed by mood swings, and anxiety. Similar research has been found where a higher proportion of PASC were noted in the female groups compared to male [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Zakia et al., 2023 reported anxiety, depression, and sleep difficulties are the most prevalent psychiatric symptoms as the most prevalent PASC and also concluded the fact that being female puts the population at higher risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Other research articles on Long COVID have also reported females, older children, and those with mental or physical comorbidities as risk factors for having more symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. As the prevalence of pain syndromes is higher in females (the presence of pre-existing pain was also associated with some of the post-COVID symptoms associated with sex), it is also possible that other factors such as higher psychological stress could play a role in the development of post-COVID symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Our analyses also show that participants experience symptoms that were not commonly mentioned in public discussion of PASC, and may benefit from further research. Our participating population reported a broad spectrum and severity of long-lasting symptoms, with fatigue, loss of interest, and mental wellness issues being the most common ones. These include but are not limited to new allergies, depression, hair loss, and skin health issues. We observed both entirely new complaints in addition to the previously existing symptoms whose characteristics (intensity, frequency, and quality) worsened after the acute COVID-19. We found individuals with new complaints and with a duration of symptoms for at least 1 year at the time of our survey. Since PASC is a newly emerged condition, it is yet to be determined how long these effects can last. Our analysis confirms prior findings that, except for a change in smell and taste, symptoms are not significantly different between those who test positive for SARS-CoV-2 and those who test negative (or have not been tested), but who otherwise show strongly suggestive symptoms. Similar findings have been previously reported in work by Louie et al., 2022, Gao et al., 2021 have also reported similar symptom profiles in asymptomatic and COVID-infected individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. It shows that there are chances of false negatives being generated due to inadequate access to diagnostic tests in the early stages of the pandemic which was notably limited, and that may have contributed to respondents in this cohort being unable to be tested or being tested later in their illness. Together, these findings indicate that absent or negative SARS-CoV-2 diagnostic and antibody tests should not be used as an indicator to rule out PASC in patients who otherwise have suggestive symptoms. The COVID-19 pandemic has imposed a considerable impact on the mental health of individuals, particularly those affected by PASC. Our work offers a well-structured and validated way to assess the wide-ranging health effects of PASC, we recognize that combining it with clinical tests or biomarker data in future studies could help paint a more complete picture.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Limitations of the study</title><p id="Par43">Our sample of 311 young adults is large enough to support meaningful analysis within this group, but we acknowledge it may not fully represent the broader young adult population. Since all participants came from a single university, there’s a chance of sampling bias. At the same time, this consistency in background helps reduce variability and allows for clearer insights into trends within this specific cohort. Also, in terms of questionnaire evaluation on university students’, the retrospective nature of the study exposes the possibility of recall bias from students, which could impact the reliability of symptom prevalence estimates. As the participants were asked to report any symptoms experienced within the designated periods, both over-reporting and underreporting of symptoms are possible from them. Alongside, working with university students who are considered as a healthy age group compared to older adults or individuals with pre-existing comorbidities causes an underrepresentation of post-COVID symptom severity. Additionally, the lack of control for confounding factors such as academic stress, screen time, sleep hygiene, comorbid conditions, and socioeconomic status presents a major limitation. Many of these variables independently affect physical and mental health and may have influenced the symptom burden reported, regardless of COVID-19 history. The observed high frequency of mental health complaints in our dataset could at least partly be an indicator of this phenomenon. Further clarification is required to determine which of these symptoms has driven from the physiopathology of SARS-CoV-2 infection and which from the psychological effects of the disease burden, worsened by the restrictions of the pandemic. Also, the students might have over or under reported their issue depending on the impact at their personal level. To add on, several psychological (e.g., post-traumatic stress), social (e.g., isolation, stigmatization), or familiar (e.g., infection or death of a familiar) stressors, which could influence the presence of some post-COVID symptoms were not evaluated. Lastly, the absence of objective clinical or laboratory assessments prevents us from validating the reported symptoms with physiological markers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>ESM 1</label><caption><p>(DOCX 260 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12889_2025_24446_MOESM2_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>ESM 2</label><caption><p>(DOCX 260 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge all the participants who took part in the study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>RD: Methodology; Data curation; Formal Analysis; Writing–original draft. KV: Methodology; Data analysis; KT: Formal Analysis; Software; Writing–review &amp; editing. MJ: Conceptualization; Methodology; Supervision; Writing–review &amp; editing. All the authors collaborated on the article and gave their approval for the final submitted version.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The present study is a part of a student doctoral dissertation, and funding was received from Parul University for this study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The authors will make the raw information supporting the conclusions of this article available without reservation.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par44">This study was conducted in accordance with the ethical standards of the Declaration of Helsinki (as revised in 2013). Informed consent was obtained from all participants prior to their involvement in the study. Participation was entirely voluntary, and respondents were assured of the confidentiality and anonymity of their responses. Ethical approval for this study was obtained from the Parul University institutional ethical committee for human research (PU-IECHR) and approved under the Approval No: PUIECHR/PIMSR/00/081734/7213). All data were handled in a secure and confidential manner, and no personally identifiable information was collected.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par45">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par46">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shivanika</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ragunathan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumitha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular docking, validation, dynamics simulations, and pharmacokinetic prediction of natural compounds against the SARS-CoV-2 main-protease</article-title><source>J Biomol Struct Dyn</source><year>2020</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>585</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32897178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/07391102.2020.1815584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7573242</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Shivanika C, Kumar D, Ragunathan V, Tiwari P, Sumitha A. Molecular docking, validation, dynamics simulations, and pharmacokinetic prediction of natural compounds against the SARS-CoV-2 main-protease. J Biomol Struct Dyn. 2020;40:585.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32897178</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/07391102.2020.1815584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7573242</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaichana</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Definition of post–COVID-19 condition among published research studies</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e235856</fpage><lpage>235856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37017970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.5856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10077105</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Chaichana U, Man KK, Chen A, Wong IC, George J, Wilson P, Wei L. Definition of post–COVID-19 condition among published research studies. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(4):e235856–235856.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37017970</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.5856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10077105</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ala’Aldeen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duric</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeinah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and multiorgan response: the long-term impact</article-title><source>Curr Probl Cardiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>48</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>101756</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37088175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2023.101756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10122551</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Harky A, Ala’Aldeen A, Butt S, Duric B, Roy S, Zeinah M. COVID-19 and multiorgan response: the long-term impact. Curr Probl Cardiol. 2023;48(9):101756.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37088175</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2023.101756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10122551</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical features of COVID-19 in elderly patients: A comparison with young and middle-aged patients</article-title><source>J Infect</source><year>2020</year><volume>80</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e14</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32171866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102640</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Liu K, Chen Y, Lin R, Han K. Clinical features of COVID-19 in elderly patients: A comparison with young and middle-aged patients. J Infect. 2020;80(6):e14–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32171866</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102640</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Torjesen I. (2021). Covid-19: Middle aged women face greater risk of debilitating long term symptoms.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.n829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33766927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danielson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Town</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenlund</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirley</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)–associated hospitalization: COVID-19–associated hospitalization surveillance network and behavioral risk factor surveillance system</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>72</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e695</fpage><lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32945846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cid/ciaa1419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7543371</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Ko JY, Danielson ML, Town M, Derado G, Greenlund KJ, Kirley PD, Kim L. Risk factors for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)–associated hospitalization: COVID-19–associated hospitalization surveillance network and behavioral risk factor surveillance system. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;72(11):e695–703.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32945846</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cid/ciaa1419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7543371</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Selvakumar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Havdal</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drevvatne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodwall</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berven</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stiansen-Sonerud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wyller</surname><given-names>VBB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and characteristics associated with post–COVID-19 condition among nonhospitalized adolescents and young adults</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e235763</fpage><lpage>235763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36995712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.5763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10064252</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Selvakumar J, Havdal LB, Drevvatne M, Brodwall EM, Berven LL, Stiansen-Sonerud T, Wyller VBB. Prevalence and characteristics associated with post–COVID-19 condition among nonhospitalized adolescents and young adults. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(3):e235763–235763.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36995712</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.5763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10064252</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sit</surname><given-names>CHP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SHS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 pandemic brings a sedentary lifestyle in young adults: a cross-sectional and longitudinal study</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>6035</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32825092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph17176035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7503726</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Zheng C, Huang WY, Sheridan S, Sit CHP, Chen XK, Wong SHS. COVID-19 pandemic brings a sedentary lifestyle in young adults: a cross-sectional and longitudinal study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(17):6035.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32825092</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph17176035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7503726</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordström</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordström</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for COVID-19 diagnosis, hospitalization, and subsequent all-cause mortality in sweden: a nationwide study</article-title><source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33704634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10654-021-00732-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7946619</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Bergman J, Ballin M, Nordström A, Nordström P. Risk factors for COVID-19 diagnosis, hospitalization, and subsequent all-cause mortality in sweden: a nationwide study. Eur J Epidemiol. 2021;36:1–12.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33704634</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10654-021-00732-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7946619</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haroon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>mcmullan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiyegbusi</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>mcnamara</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camaradou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ormerod</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of the symptom burden questionnaire for long Covid (SBQ-LC): Rasch analysis</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2022</year><volume>377</volume><fpage>e070230</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj-2022-070230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35477524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9043395</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Hughes SE, Haroon S, Subramanian A, mcmullan C, Aiyegbusi OL, Turner GM, Jackson L, Davies EH, Frost C, mcnamara G, Price G, Matthews K, Camaradou J, Ormerod J, Walker A, Calvert MJ. Development and validation of the symptom burden questionnaire for long Covid (SBQ-LC): Rasch analysis. BMJ. 2022;377:e070230. 10.1136/bmj-2022-070230.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35477524</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj-2022-070230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9043395</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiyegbusi</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMullan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><collab>TLC Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Symptoms, complications and management of long COVID: a review</article-title><source>J R Soc Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>114</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/01410768211032850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8450986</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Aiyegbusi OL, Hughes SE, Turner G, Rivera SC, McMullan C, Chandan JS, TLC Study Group. Symptoms, complications and management of long COVID: a review. J R Soc Med. 2021;114(9):428–42.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265229</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/01410768211032850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8450986</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theiler</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><collab>Review of Psychological Distress Among University Students</collab></person-group><article-title>Pervasiveness, implications and potential points of intervention</article-title><source>Int J Adv Counselling</source><year>2018</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10447-018-9321-7</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Sharp J, Theiler SA, Review of Psychological Distress Among University Students. Pervasiveness, implications and potential points of intervention. Int J Adv Counselling. 2018;40:193–212. 10.1007/s10447-018-9321-7.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toschi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Passamonti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep quality relates to emotional reactivity via intracortical myelination</article-title><source>Sleep</source><year>2021</year><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>zsaa146</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32770244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/sleep/zsaa146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7819832</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Toschi N, Passamonti L, Bellesi M. Sleep quality relates to emotional reactivity via intracortical myelination. Sleep. 2021;44(1):zsaa146.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32770244</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/sleep/zsaa146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7819832</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Della Monica</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atzori</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groeger</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijk</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid eye movement sleep, sleep continuity and slow wave sleep as predictors of cognition, mood, and subjective sleep quality in healthy men and women, aged 20–84 years</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>255</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29988413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6024010</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Della Monica C, Johnsen S, Atzori G, Groeger JA, Dijk DJ. Rapid eye movement sleep, sleep continuity and slow wave sleep as predictors of cognition, mood, and subjective sleep quality in healthy men and women, aged 20–84 years. Front Psychiatry. 2018;9:255.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29988413</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6024010</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brubaker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beverly</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A brief intervention to reduce burnout and improve sleep quality in medical students</article-title><source>BMC Med Educ</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12909-020-02263-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7539390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33023594</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Brubaker JR, Swan A, Beverly EA. A brief intervention to reduce burnout and improve sleep quality in medical students. BMC Med Educ. 2020;20:1–9.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12909-020-02263-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7539390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33023594</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Havekes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tudor</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luczak</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep deprivation causes memory deficits by negatively impacting neuronal connectivity in hippocampal area CA1</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e13424</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27549340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7554/eLife.13424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4996653</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Havekes R, Park AJ, Tudor JC, Luczak VG, Hansen RT, Ferri SL, Abel T. Sleep deprivation causes memory deficits by negatively impacting neuronal connectivity in hippocampal area CA1. Elife. 2016;5:e13424.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27549340</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7554/eLife.13424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4996653</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrigues</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janvier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kherabi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gouze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-discharge persistent symptoms and health-related quality of life after hospitalization for COVID-19</article-title><source>J Infect</source><year>2020</year><volume>81</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e4</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7445491</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Garrigues E, Janvier P, Kherabi Y, Le Bot A, Hamon A, Gouze H, Nguyen Y. Post-discharge persistent symptoms and health-related quality of life after hospitalization for COVID-19. J Infect. 2020;81(6):e4–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853602</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7445491</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Safan AS, Imam Y, Khatib MY, Wraidat MA, Altermanini MM, Al-Mughalles SA, Al-Assaf A, Olish M, Elshafei MS, Nashwan AJ. COVID-19-associated neurological sequelae: A case series on cerebral microbleeds and encephalopathy. Qatar Med J. 2023;2023(4):29.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5339/qmj.2023.29</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10618109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37920783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pradana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iskandar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for psychiatric symptoms in patients with long COVID: A systematic review</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e0284075</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37027455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0284075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10081737</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Zakia H, Pradana K, Iskandar S. Risk factors for psychiatric symptoms in patients with long COVID: A systematic review. PLoS ONE. 2023;18(4):e0284075.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37027455</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0284075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10081737</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigfrid</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jesudason</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olliaro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillesen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McPeake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long COVID in adults discharged from UK hospitals after COVID-19: A prospective, multicentre cohort study using the ISARIC WHO clinical characterisation protocol</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Eur</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>100186</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34386785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lanepe.2021.100186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8343377</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Sigfrid L, Drake TM, Pauley E, Jesudason EC, Olliaro P, Lim WS, Gillesen A, Berry C, Lowe DJ, McPeake J, et al. Long COVID in adults discharged from UK hospitals after COVID-19: A prospective, multicentre cohort study using the ISARIC WHO clinical characterisation protocol. Lancet Reg Health Eur. 2021;8:100186.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34386785</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lanepe.2021.100186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8343377</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sounderajah</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashrafian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and predictors of acute and chronic post-COVID syndrome: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>100899</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34036253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8141371</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Iqbal FM, Lam K, Sounderajah V, Clarke JM, Ashrafian H, Darzi A. Characteristics and predictors of acute and chronic post-COVID syndrome: A systematic review and meta-analysis. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;36:100899.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34036253</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8141371</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Louie JK, Stoltey JE, Scott HM, Trammell S, Ememu E, Samuel MC, Aragon TJ, Masinde G. Comparison of symptomatic and asymptomatic infections due to severe acute respiratory coronavirus virus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) in San Francisco long-term care facilities. Infection Control &amp; Hospital Epidemiology. 2022;43(1):123-4.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/ice.2020.1371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7783077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33308337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of asymptomatic infections with COVID-19</article-title><source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source><year>2021</year><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32425996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jmii.2020.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7227597</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Gao Z, Xu Y, Sun C, Wang X, Guo Y, Qiu S, Ma K. A systematic review of asymptomatic infections with COVID-19. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2021;54(1):12–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32425996</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jmii.2020.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7227597</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>