<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Neurol Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Neurol Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4001</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjno</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjno</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Neurology Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2632-6140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12207140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12207140.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12207140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12207140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40589563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjno-2024-000995</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjno-2024-000995</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Contemporary positive signs of functional limb weakness in post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2: an exploratory analysis of their utility in diagnosis and follow-up</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2754-7212</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names initials="M">Masayuki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-2241-2846</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Osada</surname><given-names initials="T">Takashi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names initials="H">Hiroaki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8967-5984</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Sano</surname><given-names initials="T">Terunori</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takao</surname><given-names initials="M">Masaki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of General Internal Medicine and Clinical Laboratory</institution>, <institution>National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Kodaira</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Department of General Internal Medicine</institution>, <institution>National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry National Center Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Kodaira</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><p>Additional supplemental material is published online only. To view, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjno-2024-000995" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjno-2024-000995</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>None declared.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Dr Masayuki Ohira; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ohira-jscn@umin.ac.jp">ohira-jscn@umin.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480209</issue-id><elocation-id>e000995</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>26</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-01 19:25:36.487"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2025. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjno-7-1.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjno-7-1.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>Sequelae of the acute phase of coronavirus disease-19, termed long COVID, are characterised by numerous indicators, including neurological symptoms. Functional neurological disorder (FND) can occur with or without various structural diseases. No previous study has examined the relationship between long COVID and FND, with positive signs for FND. This study confirmed positive signs of functional limb weakness (hereafter positive signs) in patients with long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This was an observational, retrospective, single-centre study at an outpatient clinic conducted from 1 June 2021 to 31 May 2024. We collected patients’ clinical data, including positive signs. The primary outcome was the prevalence of positive signs. Patients with positive signs were followed up over 2 months, and subjective patient perceptions of symptomatic improvements and changes in positive signs were analysed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Overall, 502 were diagnosed with long COVID, and 100 assessed patients had positive signs. Female sex, time of infection after 2022, comorbidity of psychiatric diseases, fatigue, headache and muscle weakness were statistically significant in patients with positive signs compared with those in patients without positive signs. 89 patients (41 with positive signs and 48 without positive signs) were followed up, and 28 (68.3%) with positive signs and 33 (68.8%) without positive signs reported improvements. Positive signs disappeared in patients with symptomatic improvements but not in patients without symptomatic improvements (p=0.0001).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Positive signs were found in over one-third of patients (33.9%) who were investigated in this study. Some positive signs disappeared concurrently with their symptomatic improvement.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>FUNCTIONAL NEUROLOGICAL DISORDER</kwd><kwd>EPIDEMIOLOGY</kwd><kwd>CLINICAL NEUROLOGY</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the Intramural Research Grant for Neurological and Psychiatric Disorders (NCNP)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>6-8</award-id></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100009619</institution-id><institution>Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>JP23fk0108586</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="disclaimer"><p>NCNP had no involvement in the study design.</p></notes></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec><title>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Postacute sequelae of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 infection (long COVID) are characterised by numerous symptoms and remain a target of intensified research worldwide.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A potential pathogenic mechanism of long COVID is its contribution to functional neurological disorder (FND); however, a relationship between them is controversial.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>As an important key factor in diagnosis, positive signs of FND have been examined in daily medical practice for long COVID at our hospital, where possible and appropriate.</p></list-item><list-item><p>We clarified the prevalence of positive signs of functional limb weakness in patients with long COVID and suggested their potential utility for future investigations of the pathogenic mechanism of long COVID.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, PRACTICE OR POLICY</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>To design a proper and cost-effective medical service, special attention should be paid to patients who have positive signs, especially when their symptoms do not respond to conventional treatment.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) leads to various long-term symptoms in numerous organs.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The definitions of these long-term symptoms are not unified. For convenience, we have used the term ‘long COVID’ in this report. The WHO defines long COVID as the display of symptoms 3 months after infection with SARS-CoV-2, which lasts at least 2 months, and the condition cannot be explained by other diagnoses.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Intensive past research has investigated the cellular and physiological mechanisms involved in long COVID; however, causative relationships between pathophysiology and symptoms inadequately explain this chronic health condition.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></p><p>Long COVID is a heterogeneous condition that can be categorised into several subtypes, including neurological disorders.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4 5</sup></xref> A recent study reported a long COVID-mimicking condition in individuals without previous COVID-19 infection, with symptoms undistinguishable from neurological long COVID.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> This mimicking condition may be explained by functional neurological disorder (FND), where some of the symptoms of COVID-19 are caused by FND. FND is associated with the significant use of healthcare resources, resulting in high economic costs, and it has gained increasing recognition globally as a valid and potentially treatable disorder.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Recent studies have suggested that FND can occur in conjunction with other neurological conditions.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> FND has multiple clinical subtypes and is now a rule-in diagnosis using bedside clinical tests, which are called ‘positive signs’.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Recently, reliable and easy-to-implement tests for positive signs with good sensitivity and specificity have been developed.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14 15</sup></xref></p><p>The National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry (NCNP) in Tokyo, Japan, focuses on treating mental, neurological, muscular and developmental disorders; an outpatient clinic specialising in long COVID and various conditions related to COVID-19 was established in June 2021.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> The aim of this study was to describe the details and characteristics of the positive signs of functional limb weakness (hereafter positive signs) and to analyse the possible effect of FND on patients with long COVID and the role of positive signs as an indicator of symptomatic changes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study design and participants</title><p>This retrospective, observational, single-centre study was conducted at the NCNP, Tokyo, Japan. Patients were included in this study when they fulfilled the following criteria: (1) long COVID diagnosis between 1 June 2021 and 31 May 2024, based on the definition of long COVID by the WHO Delphi consensus criteria (2021);<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> (2) confirmation of past COVID-19 infection by PCR or antigen test; (3) aged older than 15 years and visited the clinic and (4) checked for positive signs as detailed below. If necessary, a diagnosis of long COVID was confirmed through additional tests, including blood tests and head MRI, to check whether a patient’s condition could be explained by other diagnoses. Confirmation of past infection was necessary to exclude the so-called ‘long COVID mimic condition’.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Exclusion criteria were no neurological examination or no check of whether a patient had positive signs. A flow chart detailing the inclusion process is shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Study flowchart. WHO = World Health Organization. COVID = Coronavirus disease</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjno-7-1-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Clinical data assessment</title><p>At the clinic, all patients were examined by physicians certified as fellows of the Japanese Society of Internal Medicine and as board-certified neurologists of the Japanese Society of Neurology (MO, TO, HK, TS and MT). Data for this study were collected from medical records by MO. To guarantee the quality of this procedure and to address potential bias, all the information was double-checked by TO after reviewing patients’ medical records. The information gathered included patient demographics, comorbidities and clinical and neurological characteristics, including positive signs. We categorised the year of acute infection as before or after 2022 because the Omicron COVID-19 variant became dominant after January 2022, and the number of patients in Japan increased markedly after 2022.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> ‘Fatigue’ included postexercise malaise and patients who described their symptoms as ‘brain fog’, including ‘memory or concentration disturbances’. ‘Comorbidity of psychiatric diseases’ covered instances when psychiatrists diagnosed patients with depression, adjustment disorder, autism spectrum disorder, Asperger’s syndrome, bipolar disorder, developmental disorders, emotionally unstable personality disorder, generalised anxiety disorder, panic disorder, social anxiety disorder or schizophrenia before COVID-19 infection. We did not use any cross-database linkage; the data were drawn solely from the NCNP medical records.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Neurological examination and positive signs of functional limb weakness</title><p>Patients at the clinic underwent neurological examinations unless their neurologist deemed it unnecessary. For example, in a case with long COVID symptoms that only encompassed hair loss, a neurological examination was sometimes not performed. Checking for positive signs was at the discretion of each neurologist. Positive signs in this study consisted of drift without pronation, give-way weakness, paradoxical wrist flexion, ‘gluteus maximus weakness and weak iliopsoas with normal gluteus maximus’ sign (weak gluteus maximus), Hoover’s sign and Sonoo abductor sign (for a detailed feature of each positive sign, see the <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental material</xref>).<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12 14 15 18 19</sup></xref> Combinations of these signs were used because they are easily checked during routine neurological examination; moreover, their positivity or functional features can be determined easily by general neurologists. In addition, recently reported positive signs, including paradoxical wrist flexion and weak gluteus maximus, were demonstrated to have high sensitivity and specificity for diagnosing functional weakness without a precondition of symptomatic laterality.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14 15</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Evaluation of symptomatic improvement and positive signs after the follow-up period</title><p>In addition to these data, we collected information on patients’ perceptions of their symptoms and changes in positive signs during the follow-up period, when available. The follow-up period was at least 2 months based on the clinical characteristics of long COVID, whereby its symptoms can fluctuate with variable characteristics over a few months.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> After the follow-up period, symptomatic changes were noted purely according to patients’ subjective perceptions. We counted ‘improvement’ only when patients indicated that their symptoms had ameliorated or resolved completely. Polysymptomatic characteristics and fluctuations were reported in patients with long COVID, which makes it difficult to focus on one symptom.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20 21</sup></xref> At the same time, if available, changes in the positive signs were also confirmed when patients already had positive signs at their first visit.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Study outcomes</title><p>First, the presence of positive signs was assessed at the first visit to the clinic, and depending on this positivity, patients with long COVID were separated into two groups: long COVID patients with and without positive signs.</p><p>Second, we collected patients’ subjective perceptions of symptoms and changes in positive signs after a defined follow-up period had passed, if available. Patients with positive signs who were successfully followed up were then divided into two groups depending on their perception of their symptoms: those who did and did not perceive an improvement in symptoms.</p><p>Finally, the presence of positive signs was also assessed at the follow-up visit, if possible.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>First, clinical characteristics were compared between patients with and without positive signs on their first visit to the clinic. Standard descriptive statistics were used to summarise the patient characteristics. Continuous variables are expressed as medians (IQRs 25%–75%), and categorical variables are presented as frequencies and percentages. The Mann-Whitney U-test was used to compare continuous variables between two independent groups. Fisher’s exact test was used to compare categorical variables. In all statistical analyses, a p value &lt;0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance.</p><p>Second, variables that are generally considered predictors for FND, such as female sex, young age and psychiatric disease, were analysed using multivariate logistic regression analysis to determine factors associated with the presence of positive signs in patients with long COVID.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref></p><p>Finally, to gain more insight into the correlation between positive signs and symptoms of long COVID, we compared whether the initially observed positive signs remained or were resolved between patients who perceived and did not perceive a symptomatic improvement after the follow-up period had passed.</p><p>All statistical analyses were performed using EZR (Saitama Medical Center, Jichi Medical University, Saitama, Japan), a graphical user interface for R (The R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria).<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref></p><p>No missing data on clinical features were present among patients included in this study. Patients who failed to be followed up or missed checks for positive signs were excluded from each analysis when the related data were necessary (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Standard protocol approvals, registrations and patient consent</title><p>This study received approval from the NCNP Clinical Research Review Committee (No. A2021-101). Signed patient informed consent was not requested from the NCNP Clinical Research Review Committee in accordance with Japanese laws and regulations, given the retrospective nature of the study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s2-8"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. All data and materials used in the analysis will be available in some form to any researcher for purposes of reproducing or extending the analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>No patient and public involvement.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Overall, 892 patients (412 men and 480 women) visited the clinic from 1 June 2021 to 31 May 2023. Of these, 502 patients (246 men and 256 women) were diagnosed with long COVID according to the WHO criteria with confirmation of previous infection of COVID-19, and 390 patients were excluded because they did not fulfil the WHO criteria or lacked confirmation of previous infection. Of the 502 patients, 295 long COVID patients (58.8%) were assessed for positive signs, and 207 (41.2%) were excluded. These patients were excluded because, in 18 patients (3.6%), positive signs were not confirmed, and a neurological examination was not conducted. Furthermore, positive signs were not checked in the remaining 189 excluded patients (37.6%).</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>Patient characteristics</title><p>Positive signs were present in 100/295 patients (33.9%), 38 men and 62 women (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). The prevalence of individual positive signs among those who presented with any positive sign is shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. Paradoxical wrist flexion was the most frequently observed positive sign, followed by the give-way weakness.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Prevalence of individual positive signs for functional limb weakness in long COVID patients</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive signs</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n=100)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paradoxical wrist flexion</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (90.0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Give-way weakness</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (76.0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weak gluteus maximus</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (29.0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional pattern in the Hoover’s test</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (7.0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional pattern in the Sonoo abductor test</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (6.0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drift without pronation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.0%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Comparison between patients with and without positive signs</title><p>The characteristics of the 295 patients included in the study are presented in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>. 141 patients were male (48.8%) and 154 (52.2%) were female. The median age at the time of visiting the clinic was 42 years (range 30–51 years). Regarding the comparison between patients with and without positive signs, more women than men had positive signs (OR 0.55, 95% CI 0.32 to 0.92, p=0.019). The time of infection after 2022 (OR 1.94, 95% CI 1.15 to 3.28, p=0.0097) and comorbidity of psychiatric diseases (OR 2.32, 95% CI 1.30 to 4.13, p=0.003) were dominant in patients with positive signs. The number of months from infection to the first visit was significantly higher in patients with positive signs than in those without positive signs (p=0.035). Regarding the comparison of symptoms between these two groups, fatigue (OR 2.29, 95% CI 1.36 to 3.90, p=0.0009) and headache (OR 2.51, 95% CI 1.32 to 4.82, p=0.004) were significantly dominant in patients with positive signs. The number of patients who claimed muscle weakness was 24, whereas the number of patients with positive signs was 100. Among the 24 patients who noticed weakness, 16 had positive signs and eight did not (OR 4.43, 95% CI 1.71 to 12.4, p=0.001). Asymmetrical muscle weakness was noted in seven patients, and a further nine patients had symmetrical muscle weakness. The frequencies of other symptoms were not significantly different between the two groups (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Characteristics of patients with long COVID included in the study (n=295)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long COVID with positive signs n=100</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long COVID without positive signs n=195</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: N (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (38.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (52.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.32 to 0.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: N (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (62.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (47.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age in years: median (IQR)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0 (30.0–53.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.0 (30.0–48.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<xref rid="T2_FN3" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalisation: N (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (18.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (21.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.65 to 2.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time of infection until 2021: N (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (26.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (73.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (1.15 to 3.28)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0097<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidity of psychiatric diagnosis: N (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (36.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (19.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 (1.30 to 4.13)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Months from infection to first visit: median (IQR)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3–10)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3–8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035<xref rid="T2_FN3" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (60.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (42.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 (1.36 to 3.90)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0009<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.21 to 3.74)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression or anxiety</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (8.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (7.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.39 to 2.74)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disorder</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (16.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (11.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 (0.70 to 3.16)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Memory or concentration disturbance</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (28.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (26.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.61 to 1.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smell/taste disturbance</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (20.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (25.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.39 to 1.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shortness of breath or cough</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (14.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (8.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 (0.74 to 3.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (28.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (13.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51 (1.32 to 4.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dizziness</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (8.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (8.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.35 to 2.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain or numbness</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (16.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (15.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.50 to 2.11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle weakness</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (16.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43 (1.71 to 12.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hair loss</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (4.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.19 to 3.18)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest pain</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 (0.31 to 7.53)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Successfully followed over 2 months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (41.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (25.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07 (1.20 to 3.57)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>Positive signs=positive signs of functional limb weakness.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN2" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>Fisher’s exact test.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN3" fn-type="other"><label>†</label><p>Mann-Whitney U<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>test.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>95% CI, 95% confidence interval; IQR, interquartile 18 range; OR, odds ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Factors related to positive signs in patients with long COVID</title><p>Previous studies have reported that female sex, younger age and personality disorders are predisposing factors for FND.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> In our multivariate analysis including these variables, factors that were significantly associated with positive signs were months from infection to first visit (OR 1.06, 95% CI 1.01 to 1.11, p=0.02) and comorbidity of psychiatric diagnosis (OR 2.29, 95% CI 1.31 to 3.98, p=0.0035). Although there was a trend for female sex, this did not reach significance (OR 1.66, 95% CI 1.00 to 2.76, p=0.052; <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Multivariate analysis of predictors of positive signs in patients with long COVID (n=295)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 to 2.76</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 to 1.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalisation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 to 1.44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection time after 2022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 to 1.59</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidity of psychiatric diagnosis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 to 3.98</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0035</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Months from infection to first visit</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 to 1.11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>Positive signs=positive signs of functional limb weakness.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>95% CI, 95% confidence interval; OR, odds ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Association between the clinical course and change in positive signs</title><p>89 patients were followed up with supportive care only or without any medication. Of these, 41 patients with positive signs were followed up for 13.0 months (range 7–20 months), and 48 patients without positive signs were followed up for 6.5 months (range 4–14.25 months). The difference in follow-up duration was significantly different (p=0.01; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). Of the patients with positive signs who were followed up, 41 were positive for paradoxical wrist flexion, 38 (92.7%) had give-way weakness, 31 (75.6%) had a weak gluteus maximus, 11 (26.8%) had Sonoo abductor sign, 3 (7.3%) had Hoover’s sign, 3 (7.3%) had Sonoo abductor sign and 1 (2.4%) had drift without pronation. There was no significant difference in the noted improvements between patients with (n=28) and without positive signs (n=33; OR 0.98, 95% CI 0.36 to 2.66, p=1).</p><p>Two of the 41 patients with long COVID and positive signs were not followed up for positive signs; thus, 39 patients were successfully followed up regarding their clinical course and change in positive signs. 27 patients perceived an improvement in their symptoms, and 12 did not. In those perceiving an improvement, 19 patients reported that their positive signs had diminished. In contrast, positive signs did not diminish in patients who did not perceive an improvement in their symptoms (OR infinite, 95% CI 4.11 to infinite, p=0.0001; <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Positive signs change in patients with long COVID at follow-up. Positive signs=positive signs of functional limb weakness.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjno-7-1-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Some of the patients in this study exhibited positive signs. In general, positive signs do not directly indicate that a patient has FND. However, when patients who fulfil the WHO criteria used to define a post-COVID-19 condition (ie, muscle weakness and/or muscle fatigue) show positive signs of FND, they are highly likely to fulfil the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-5 criteria for FND.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11 24</sup></xref> The reason for this is unclear.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> One possible explanation is that FND can coexist alongside long COVID, which leads to the modification or exacerbation of FND symptoms, similarly to other comorbid neurological conditions.<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26 27</sup></xref> An alternative explanation is a common pathological mechanism underlying FND and long COVID.</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, no previous studies have focused on the positive signs of long COVID. In this study, paradoxical wrist flexion, give-way weakness and weak gluteus maximus were relatively common in patients with long COVID, whereas Hoover’s sign and Sonoo abductor sign were relatively rare. Some of the positive signs assessed in this study have also only been reported recently and thus have not been fully validated. In addition, the difference in the prevalence of positive signs may be attributed to several factors. Hoover’s sign and Sonoo abductor sign can be confirmed easily, especially when there is asymmetrical weakness of the lower limbs, whereas other signs do not require such asymmetry.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18 28</sup></xref> Second, paradoxical wrist flexion and give-way weakness can be detected in the upper limbs, whereas Hoover’s and Sonoo abductor signs can be detected in the lower limbs. These differences may have affected the frequency of positive signs observed in this study.</p><p>Several dominant features of patients with positive signs are compatible with FND, including female sex.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> In Japan, the Omicron variant of COVID was dominant, and the number of COVID-19 cases increased dramatically after January 2022.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> The prevalence of post-Omicron COVID-19 conditions was lower than that of the other strains before 2022.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Assuming that patients with positive signs had FND, the prevalence of FND coexisting with long COVID is likely to not depend on which variant of COVID patients were infected with but solely on the number of patients infected with COVID-19, as observed in this study. The reason for the significant difference in duration between the end of infection and the first visit to the clinic is unclear. One possibility is that long COVID symptoms affected by FND might be more persistent than those unrelated to FND.</p><p>The dominance of comorbidity with psychiatric diseases in patients with positive signs aligns with the features of FND. Rates of psychological comorbidity in FND are consistently higher than in comparable neurological disorders.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> The tendency for comorbid psychiatric diseases in our study is in agreement with previous reports on FND.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31 32</sup></xref> We postulate that long COVID might trigger, or be overlaid by, FND more frequently in patients with psychiatric illnesses, including abnormal illness beliefs and a perception of symptoms being irreversible, than in those without psychiatric illnesses.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref></p><p>Fatigue, headache and muscle weakness were more common in patients with positive signs than in those without positive signs. The dominance of muscle weakness in patients with positive signs is natural because positive signs are used to form a diagnosis of functional limb weakness.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Fatigue and headache also accompany FND.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Therefore, the dominance of fatigue and headache was plausible when patients with positive signs had coexisting FND, and their symptoms may have been caused or exacerbated by it. Patients with long COVID who experience these symptoms should receive treatment for coexisting FND when supportive treatments are ineffective. In addition, this finding may shed light on the overall characteristics of long COVID. Some of the most common neurological symptoms of long COVID may be caused by FND. This could underpin the idea that long COVID consists of heterogeneous pathological conditions. Therefore, all symptoms that develop after COVID-19 should not be defined by one disorder, such as long COVID.</p><p>In this study, we verified the disappearance of positive signs in some patients during the follow-up period of 2 months and found that positive signs were associated with the perceived symptomatic improvement in patients, even though they were treated with supportive care alone. The association between positive signs and symptomatic amelioration was not decisive because the number of patients who were successfully followed up was small. However, we speculate that FND contributes to some of the symptoms of long COVID, one of the most common being chronic fatigue.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5 34</sup></xref> The correlation between general improvement and the disappearance of positive signs indicated that some of the symptoms of those with long COVID may be caused by FND. If so, positive signs may be a useful indicator for symptoms of long COVID in certain patients. In addition, recognising the possible coexistence of FND with long COVID is a good strategy to avoid delayed treatment and unnecessary medical costs. Of note, positive signs in this study were confirmed by general neurologists easily and rapidly in daily medical settings and were without cost. Routine tests in conventional medical settings, such as blood tests, have not been useful for forming a diagnosis of long COVID.<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35 36</sup></xref> Therefore, positive signs will be of some use, at least in part, for physicians as an objective, cost-effective and practical method to assess the clinical course of long COVID.</p><p>In summary, our study showed that long COVID, accompanied by positive signs, is not rare and that this phenomenon indicates the possibility of the coexistence of long COVID and FND. Therefore, some patients with long COVID may present with symptoms of FND. If positive signs are observed in long COVID patients, they are a useful indicator of the coexistence of FND in those with long COVID. The identification of FND symptoms may help us to understand the cause of symptomatic heterogeneity in patients with long COVID.</p><p>A limitation of our study is its single-centre, retrospective design, which may have resulted in the under-reporting of the subtypes of long COVID other than neurological long COVID. Our institution specialises in mental, neurological, muscular and developmental disorders, and this specialisation might have led to bias because patients with no neurological or psychiatric symptoms do not visit the NCNP. Therefore, the result of this study primarily applies to neurological long COVID. We excluded 207 patients (41.2%) who fulfilled the WHO criteria for long COVID in this study. First, checking for positive signs was overlooked in 189 patients because the physician did not know about the possibility of or forgot to check for comorbid FND. Second, 17 patients experienced symptoms that were not neurological. Third, one parent visited the clinic instead of the patient. Positive signs for weakness were included in this study; however, paradoxical wrist flexion and weak gluteus maximus have not been as extensively validated as other positive signs.<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> The discrepancy in frequency between the new positive signs and the more conventional positive signs remains a limitation. Therefore, a comparison and a solid validation of these signs using large cohorts are necessary in the future. The outcome measures of symptomatic improvements were assessed based purely on patients’ subjective perceptions because this was a retrospective study based on a medical chart review of routine medical practice. Polysymptomatic characteristics and fluctuations were reported in patients with long COVID, which makes it difficult to focus on one symptom.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20 21</sup></xref> Finally, a comparison of clinical changes between positive signs and the patient’s subjective perceptions was based on a relatively small number of patients. In addition, patients with positive signs were followed up more frequently than those without positive signs, which may have introduced substantial bias. Follow-up at the clinic was continued when patients requested it or did not refuse the clinic’s appointment. Whether patients were followed was independent of their symptoms or medication.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjno-2024-000995</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjno-7-1-s001.docx" id="d67e861" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank J Ludovic Croxford, PhD, from Edanz (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jp.edanz.com/ac" ext-link-type="uri">https://jp.edanz.com/ac</ext-link>) for editing a draft of this manuscript. We also thank Masahiro Sonoo, MD, and Kohta Suzuki, MD, PhD, MPH, for useful advice.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This research was supported in part by The Intramural Research Grant for Neurological and Psychiatric Disorders (NCNP) (6-8) and the Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development (grant number JP23fk0108586).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> The principal author has full access to the data used in the analyses described in this manuscript. Anonymised data will be made available on reasonable request to the corresponding author from qualified and non-commercial entities.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> This study received approval from the NCNP Clinical Research Review Committee (No. A2021-101). Signed patient informed consent was not requested from the NCNP Clinical Research Review Committee in accordance with Japanese laws and regulations, given the retrospective nature of the study.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>6-month consequences of COVID-19 in patients discharged from hospital: a cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2023</year><volume>401</volume><fpage>e21</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00810-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37321233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10258565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>
</person-group><source>A clinical case definition of post COVID-19 condition by a delphi consensus</source><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bendstrup</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A new paradigm is needed to explain long COVID</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e12</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(22)00501-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36620963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blankestijn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Aziz</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baalbaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID exhibits clinically distinct phenotypes at 3-6 months post-SARS-CoV-2 infection: results from the P4O2 consortium</article-title><source>BMJ Open Respir Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e001907</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2023-001907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11043734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38663887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Takao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Neurological post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source><year>2023</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.13481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36148558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9538807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Osada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 mimic: An important neurological condition</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>465</volume><fpage>123199</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2024.123199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39182422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>O’Mahony</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baxendale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Economic Cost of Functional Neurologic Disorders: A Systematic Review</article-title><source>Neurology (ECronicon)</source><year>2023</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>e202</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000207388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10351557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37339887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Osada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Functional Neurological Disorder Overlapping Paroxysmal Kinesigenic Dyskinesia Confirmed by Genetic Diagnosis</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e42693</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.42693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37649944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10465170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tinazzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Functional Movement Disorder as a Prodromal Symptom of Parkinson’s Disease-Clinical and Pathophysiological Insights</article-title><source>Mov Disord</source><year>2024</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1952</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.29958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39119738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carle-Toulemonde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goutte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Do-Quang-Cantagrel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Overall comorbidities in functional neurological disorder: A narrative review</article-title><source>Encephale</source><year>2023</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>S24</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.encep.2023.06.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37414721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aybek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and management of functional neurological disorder</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2022</year><volume>376</volume><elocation-id>o64</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.o64</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35074803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aybek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Functional limb weakness and paralysis</article-title><source>Handb Clin Neurol</source><year>2016</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-801772-2.00018-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27719840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aybek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dworetzky</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Functional neurological disorder: new subtypes and shared mechanisms</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2022</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(21)00422-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35430029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9107510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sonoo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Paradoxical wrist flexion: A new test to detect functional weakness of the upper limb</article-title><source>eNeurologicalSci</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><elocation-id>100302</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ensci.2020.100302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33344786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7735966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sonoo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kanbayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Weak gluteus maximus and weak iliopsoas with normal gluteus maximus: Two complementary new signs to diagnose lower limb functional weakness</article-title><source>Brain Behav</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e3135</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/brb3.3135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37366603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10454349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Takao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical features of patients who visited the outpatient clinic for long COVID in Japan</article-title><source>eNeurologicalSci</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><elocation-id>100418</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ensci.2022.100418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35919910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9335519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Edouard Mathieu</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rodés-Guirao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Japan: Coronavirus pandemic country profile</article-title><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus/country/japan" ext-link-type="uri">https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus/country/japan</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>20-Feb-2024</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sonoo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Abductor sign: a reliable new sign to detect unilateral non-organic paresis of the lower limb</article-title><source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source><year>2004</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14707320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1757483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Squillace</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cogliandro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A multidisciplinary approach to screen the post-COVID-19 conditions</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>54</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-023-08006-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36694110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9872735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-de-Las-Peñas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pellicer-Valero</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martín-Guerrero</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Investigating the fluctuating nature of post-COVID pain symptoms in previously hospitalized COVID-19 survivors: the LONG-COVID-EXP multicenter study</article-title><source>Pain Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e1153</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PR9.0000000000001153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38646658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11029971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sivan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID Clinical Severity Types Based on Symptoms and Functional Disability: A Longitudinal Evaluation</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e1153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm13071908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11012375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38610673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lehn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Epidemiology</article-title><source>Handb Clin Neurol</source><year>2016</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-801772-2.00005-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27719864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Investigation of the freely available easy-to-use software 'EZR' for medical statistics</article-title><source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source><year>2013</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bmt.2012.244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23208313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3590441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>
</person-group><source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders: DSM-5™</source><edition>5th</edition><comment>edn</comment><publisher-loc>Arlington, VA, US</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Psychiatric Publishing, Inc</publisher-name><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Teodoro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gelauff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Functional neurological disorder in people with long COVID: A systematic review</article-title><source>Eur J Neurol</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1505</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ene.15721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36719069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walzl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Functional neurological disorder and multiple sclerosis: a systematic review of misdiagnosis and clinical overlap</article-title><source>J Neurol</source><year>2022</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-021-10436-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33611631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8782816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pareés</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Functional movement disorder comorbidity in Parkinson’s disease: Unraveling the web</article-title><source>Parkinsonism Relat Disord</source><year>2021</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.parkreldis.2020.10.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33092981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A new sign for the detection of malingering and functional paresis of the lower extremities</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1908</year><volume>LI</volume><fpage>746</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1908.25410090028001h</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Akaishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kushimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Katori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>COVID-19-Related Symptoms during the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron (B.1.1.529) Variant Surge in Japan</article-title><source>Tohoku J Exp Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>258</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1620/tjem.2022.J067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36002251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long-term sequelae of different COVID-19 variants: The original strain versus the Omicron variant</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Glob Health Med</italic>
</source><year>2022</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.35772/ghm.2022.01069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36589219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9773225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crimlisk</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Slater revisited: 6 year follow up study of patients with medically unexplained motor symptoms</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>1998</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.316.7131.582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9518908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC28460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ringbauer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Do medically unexplained symptoms matter? A prospective cohort study of 300 new referrals to neurology outpatient clinics</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</italic>
</source><year>2000</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.68.2.207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10644789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1736779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fobian</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A review of functional neurological symptom disorder etiology and the integrated etiological summary model</article-title><source>J Psychiatry Neurosci</source><year>2019</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/jpn.170190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30565902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6306282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Michelen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elkheir</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Characterising long COVID: a living systematic review</article-title><source>BMJ Glob Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e005427</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2021-005427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8478580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34580069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Erlandson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaggi</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Differentiation of Prior SARS-CoV-2 Infection and Postacute Sequelae by Standard Clinical Laboratory Measurements in the RECOVER Cohort</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>1209</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M24-0737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39133923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11408082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vasilev</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blokhin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khoruzhaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Routine Brain MRI Findings on the Long-Term Effects of COVID-19: A Scoping Review</article-title><source>Diagnostics (Basel)</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>2533</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diagnostics13152533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37568896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10417725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gasca-Salas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Neurologic diagnostic criteria for functional neurologic disorders</article-title><source>Handb Clin Neurol</source><year>2016</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-801772-2.00017-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27719839</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data are available upon reasonable request.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>