<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2786</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12262939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12262939.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12262939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12262939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40660536</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000043333</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-25-02049</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>6000</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Clinical Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Successful treatment of long-COVID postural tachycardia syndrome with epipharyngeal abrasive therapy in an adolescent patient: A case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0006-2752-1211</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Takezawa</surname><given-names initials="H">Hiroyuki</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label> Takezawa ENT Clinic, Obihiro, Hokkaido, Japan.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: Hiroyuki Takezawa, Takezawa ENT Clinic, 3-35-4, Nishi 19-jo Minami, Obihiro 080-2469, Hokkaido, Japan (e-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="take-cli@blue.ocn.ne.jp">take-cli@blue.ocn.ne.jp</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>104</volume><issue>28</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">493019</issue-id><elocation-id>e43333</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-16 10:25:13.303"><day>16</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY)</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="medi-104-e43333.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="medi-104-e43333.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Rationale:</title><p>Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) is a type of autonomic dysfunction that can occur following coronavirus disease (COVID-19) infection, particularly in adolescents. Treatment options are limited and often ineffective. We report a case of long COVID-associated POTS that responded favorably to epipharyngeal abrasive therapy (EAT), a treatment targeting chronic inflammation in the epipharynx.</p></sec><sec><title>Patient concerns:</title><p>A previously healthy adolescent developed persistent fatigue, headache, dizziness, insomnia, and orthostatic intolerance lasting over 3 months after a COVID-19 infection. The symptoms severely impaired daily functioning, rendering the patient bedridden.</p></sec><sec><title>Diagnoses:</title><p>Based on clinical symptoms and a positive orthostatic test showing excessive postural tachycardia without hypotension, the patient was diagnosed with POTS associated with long COVID. Chronic epipharyngitis was also noted upon endoscopic examination.</p></sec><sec><title>Interventions:</title><p>The patient underwent weekly sessions of EAT for a total of 120 days. No additional pharmacologic treatment was provided during this period.</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes:</title><p>The patient showed marked improvement in symptoms, including increased tolerance to standing, reduced fatigue, and improved sleep quality. Objective improvement was confirmed through repeat orthostatic testing. The patient resumed school attendance and daily activities without limitation.</p></sec><sec><title>Lessons:</title><p>This case highlights the potential effectiveness of EAT in treating long COVID-related POTS in adolescents. EAT may offer a nonpharmacological treatment option by addressing underlying chronic epipharyngeal inflammation, a possible contributor to autonomic dysfunction.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>epipharyngeal abrasive therapy (EAT)</kwd><kwd>long-COVID</kwd><kwd>postural tachycardia syndrome (POTS)</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>
1. Introduction</title><p>Postural tachycardia syndrome (POTS) has various underlying causes, and its treatment has not yet been established. Recently, long-COVID has garnered significant attention, and it is known that POTS can develop following coronavirus disease (COVID-19). Since the emergence of COVID-19, a growing number of patients have reported persistent symptoms that meet the diagnostic criteria for POTS, even after recovery from the acute phase of infection. Recent studies suggest that POTS may develop in approximately 10% to 30% of individuals with long COVID, particularly among young women.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> However, no standardized treatment has been reported to date. We report a case of post-COVID POTS in which we implemented epipharyngeal abrasive therapy (EAT) to improve autonomic dysfunction and observed a remarkable improvement. EAT is a procedure in which the nasopharynx is visualized using an endoscope, and a cotton swab soaked in 1% zinc chloride solution is inserted transnasally from the contralateral side to abrade the nasopharyngeal mucosa. This therapy aims to reduce nasopharyngeal inflammation and improve autonomic dysfunction through vagus nerve stimulation. EAT has been utilized in Japan for more than 50 years.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>
2. Case presentation</title><p>A 16-year-old boy had been functioning well in daily life, attending school, and engaging in extracurricular activities without any impairment. However, after contracting COVID-19 in May 2022, he developed persistent fatigue, memory impairment, dizziness, headaches, and insomnia, which prevented him from performing these activities. Attempts to attend school exacerbated his symptoms and eventually confined him to bed. Four months postinfection, the patient became nearly completely bedridden and was unable to attend school. Despite a comprehensive evaluation at a local general hospital, brain MRI, neurological examinations, and blood tests relevant to the differential diagnosis of ME/CFS revealed no abnormalities. He was prescribed medications such as midodrine (4 mg/day) from November 2022 to May 2023 for orthostatic dysregulation.</p><p>When symptoms persisted until May 2023, he sought treatment at our clinic specializing in long-COVID. The possibility of myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue (ME/CFS) and orthostatic hypotension was considered, and an orthostatic test was performed. Additional tests, including thyroid function, cortisol levels, and brain magnetic resonance imaging, were conducted by a previous physician, and no abnormalities were detected. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) examination was not performed because no neurological abnormalities were observed. Additionally, 24-hour ambulatory blood pressure and heart rate monitoring were not conducted. The patient had no notable medical history prior to COVID-19. Fatigue and headache caused by long-COVID, as well as ME/CFS, were considered based on the symptoms. However, the orthostatic test revealed an increase in pulse rate, meeting the diagnostic criteria for POTS. In addition, the absence of hypotension further supported the diagnosis. His condition was diagnosed as long-COVID-associated POTS, and EAT was initiated. EAT is expected to ameliorate chronic epipharyngeal inflammation and potentially improve autonomic function through stimulation of the vagus nerve. At the initiation of EAT, transnasal endoscopic examination revealed inflammation of the nasopharynx. EAT was performed once a week for 15 sessions. At the start of the treatment, the patient was unable to attend school or perform daily activities because of fatigue and headaches.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>2.1. Standing test results</title><p>The orthostatic test was conducted by measuring blood pressure and heart rate after 10 minutes in the supine position, immediately after assuming a sitting position, immediately after standing, and after 10 minutes in the standing position. The evaluation was based on the differences relative to the measurements taken after 10 minutes in the supine position.</p><p>Initial visit: Upon standing, the patient demonstrated significant hemodynamic changes: blood pressure increased from 124/61 to 147/80 mm Hg, pulse pressure narrowed from 63 to 25 mm Hg, and heart rate rose markedly from 78 to 139 beats/min (Δ61 beats/min). While hypotension was absent, the pronounced heart rate increase coupled with symptom persistence for 1 year confirmed the POTS diagnosis.</p><p>After 90 days of EAT: Hemodynamic parameters showed improvement with standing: blood pressure changed from 105/51 to 108/59 mm Hg, pulse pressure decreased from 54 to 40 mm Hg, and heart rate increased from 60 to 78 beats/min (Δ18 beats/min). The patient resumed school attendance despite experiencing post-school fatigue.</p><p>After 120 days of EAT (15 sessions): Further improvements in orthostatic response were observed: blood pressure changed from 116/60 to 109/74 mm Hg, pulse pressure decreased from 56 to 40 mm Hg, and heart rate increased from 69 to 89 beats/min (Δ20 beats/min) (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). With stabilized heart rate response and improved concentration, the patient fully resumed school and daily activities, leading to treatment discontinuation in December 2023.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Changes in vital signs during treatment.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial visit</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 90 d EAT</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 120 d EAT</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Blood pressure (mm Hg)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Supine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124/61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105/51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116/60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Standing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147/80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108/59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109/74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Pulse pressure (mm Hg)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Change upon standing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 → 25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 → 40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 → 40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Heart rate (beats/min)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Supine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Standing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Change (Δ)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+20</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>EAT = epipharyngeal abrasive therapy.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>
3. Discussion</title><p>This case report describes a patient who had been functioning well in daily life, attending school, and engaging in extracurricular activities without impairment before contracting COVID-19. The patient did not receive any additional therapy during the EAT. After the infection, the patient developed long-COVID POTS, with symptoms persisting for approximately 1 year. The patient was bedridden during the presentation at our clinic. Following a 120-day course of EAT administered once weekly, the patient demonstrated significant improvement in symptoms and orthostatic test results.</p><p>POTS, a chronic multisystem disorder involving the autonomic nervous system, is characterized by excessive sinus tachycardia upon standing without accompanying hypotension.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> It frequently manifests during adolescence and can be triggered by immune stressors, such as viral infections, including COVID-19.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> The patient also developed fatigue, headache, insomnia, and orthostatic intolerance after COVID-19, which persisted for more than 3 months. Nasopharyngitis was also observed.</p><p>The current treatment landscape for POTS lacks FDA-approved medications, and available therapies often lack robust evidence.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> In this case, EAT, a treatment unique to Japan with a history of more than 50 years, was used. Its mechanisms of action are diverse and include alleviation of local inflammation and regulation of autonomic dysfunction.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup></p><p>EAT may stimulate the vagus nerve located in the nasopharynx, reducing inflammatory cytokines such as IL-6 and TNF-α, which are implicated in long-COVID.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, EAT may directly influence autonomic balance and enhance cerebrospinal fluid drainage through the nasopharyngeal lymphatic plexus,<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> improving symptoms of fatigue, headache, and concentration deficits associated with long-COVID.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> There have been no reports of EAT being applied specifically to treat long-COVID POTS. However, EAT has been reported to be effective in the treatment of long-COVID. Considering that our patient also presented with nasopharyngitis and autonomic dysfunction, an EAT was implemented. The present case represents postinfectious POTS that developed following COVID-19, with presumed underlying mechanisms involving autonomic dysfunction and immune-mediated cytokine activity triggered by viral infection. Recent reports have demonstrated the persistence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA and inflammatory cytokines in epipharyngeal tissue. EAT has been shown to improve the symptoms of long COVID, potentially by facilitating the removal of residual viral RNA and reducing local inflammatory cytokine expression in the epipharynx.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup></p><p>Ito investigated the effects of EAT on autonomic function in patients with chronic epipharyngitis. Using the tilt table test and heart rate variability analysis, they evaluated autonomic activity before and after EAT.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> The results demonstrated a tendency toward suppression of sympathetic activity and improvement in parasympathetic function. Additionally, EAT appeared to enhance baroreceptor reflex function during tilt testing. These findings suggest that EAT may help modulate autonomic balance and serve as a potential therapeutic option for patients with autonomic dysfunction. This report provides important preliminary evidence supporting the autonomic regulatory effects of EAT.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup></p><p>This case report describes a single patient without a control group, limiting generalizability and making the causal relationship between EAT and improvement uncertain. Spontaneous remission cannot be excluded. The POTS diagnosis was clinical, without comprehensive autonomic testing, which reduces the diagnostic precision. Furthermore, the mechanism of action of EAT remains unclear, and its long-term efficacy is unknown.</p><p>This case demonstrated that EAT successfully improved the symptoms and quality of life of a patient with long-COVID POTS without the need for pharmacological intervention. Our findings suggest that EAT is a potential therapeutic option for managing long-COVID POTS.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p><p><bold>Validation:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p><p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p><p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> Hiroyuki Takezawa.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>
<def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p>coronavirus disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EAT</term><def><p>epipharyngeal abrasive therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ME/CFS</term><def><p>myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>POTS</term><def><p>postural tachycardia syndrome</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>The patient provided written informed consent for publication of this case report and any accompanying images.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>As this was a case report in which personal information was not included other than age and gender, ethical approval was not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>The author has no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Takezawa H. Successful treatment of long-COVID postural tachycardia syndrome with epipharyngeal abrasive therapy in an adolescent patient: A case report. Medicine 2025;104:28(e43333).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blitshteyn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitelaw</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) and other autonomic disorders after COVID-19 infection: a case series of 20 patients [published correction appears in Immunol Res. 2021;69(2):212. doi: 10.1007/s12026-021-09191-7.].</article-title>
<source>Immunol Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33786700</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12026-021-09185-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8009458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ståhlberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Runold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-haul post-COVID-19 symptoms presenting as a variant of postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome: the Swedish experience.</article-title>
<source>JACC Case Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33723532</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaccas.2021.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7946344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barboi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>American Autonomic Society</collab>. <article-title>Long-COVID postural tachycardia syndrome: an American autonomic society statement.</article-title>
<source>Clin Auton Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33740207</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10286-021-00798-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7976723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vernino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stiles</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS): State of the science and clinical care from a 2019 National Institutes of Health Expert Consensus Meeting – part 1.</article-title>
<source>Auton Neurosci</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>235</volume>:<fpage>102828</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34144933</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.autneu.2021.102828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8455420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations.</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. Erratum in: Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023;21(6):408.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Postural tachycardia syndrome and long COVID: an update.</article-title>
<source>Br J Gen Pract</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34972793</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3399/bjgp22X718037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8714530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ieiri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Possible mechanisms underlying epipharyngeal abrasive therapy (EAT) with ZnCl2 solution for the treatment of autoimmune diseases and functional somatic syndrome.</article-title>
<source>J Antivir Antiretrovir</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epipharyngeal abrasive therapy (EAT) reduces the mRNA expression of major proinflammatory cytokine IL-6 in chronic epipharyngitis.</article-title>
<source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>9205</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36012469</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms23169205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9409341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nasopharyngeal lymphatic plexus is a hub for cerebrospinal fluid drainage.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>625</volume>:<fpage>768</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38200313</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41586-023-06899-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10808075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Autonomic nervous system regulation effects of epipharyngeal abrasive therapy for myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome associated with chronic epipharyngitis.</article-title>
<source>Cureus</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e33777</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36655156</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.33777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9840732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epipharyngeal abrasive therapy (EAT) has potential as a novel method for long COVID treatment.</article-title>
<source>Viruses</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>907</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35632649</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/v14050907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9147901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Spatial transcriptomics of the epipharynx in long COVID identifies SARS-CoV-2 signalling pathways and the therapeutic potential of epipharyngeal abrasive therapy.</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>8618</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40074801</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-025-92908-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11903674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirobumi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of epipharyngeal abrasive therapy (EAT) on the baroreceptor reflex (BR).</article-title>
<source>Cureus</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e45080</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37705568</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.45080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10496426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>