<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">62</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcpsyc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-244X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11980331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11980331.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11980331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11980331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40200197</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-025-06789-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6789</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Case report: post COVID-19 encephalopathy and oral cenesthopathy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="JI">Ju-I</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="SH">Shwu-Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="PJ">Pei-Jung</given-names></name><address><email>ddgacc.chen@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02verss31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413801.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0711 0593</institution-id><institution>Department of Psychiatry, </institution><institution>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Linkou Branch, No.5, Fuxing St., Guishan Dist, Taoyuan, 333 Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00d80zx46</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.145695.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1798 0922</institution-id><institution>College of Medicine, </institution><institution>Chang Gung University, </institution></institution-wrap>Taoyuan County, Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02verss31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413801.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0711 0593</institution-id><institution>Department of Psychiatry, </institution><institution>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Taoyuan Branch, Taoyuan, Taiwan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478311</issue-id><elocation-id>351</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-10 11:25:39.407"><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12888_2025_Article_6789.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Post-COVID-19 encephalopathy is a neurological complication characterized by cognitive impairment, memory loss, and other neuropsychiatric symptoms in COVID-19 survivors. Oral cenesthopathy, a rare somatic delusion characterized by unusual oral sensations without physical findings, is typically associated with affective disorders and schizophrenia. This case report describes a 73-year-old female who developed post-COVID-19 encephalopathy, presenting initially with cognitive decline, followed by major depression and oral cenesthopathy 16 months after the infection. Comprehensive investigations excluded autoimmune encephalitis, Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, and other structural or vascular abnormalities. Treatment with Aripiprazole and Carbamazepine resulted in partial improvement, though symptom control was limited by medication side effects. This case represents a rare presentation of long COVID syndrome, highlighting the complex neuropsychiatric sequelae of COVID-19. Further research is needed to explore the pathophysiology, treatment strategies, and long-term impacts of such manifestations.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Post COVID-19 encephalopathy</kwd><kwd>Long COVID syndrome</kwd><kwd>Oral cenesthopathy</kwd><kwd>Delusional disorder somatic type</kwd><kwd>Case report</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par2">COVID-19 survivors suffer from neurological and psychiatric sequelae such as cognitive impairment, memory loss, paresthesia, anxiety, depression, and sleep disturbances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Long-term neurodegenerative effects have been reported in COVID-19 survivors; however, the pathophysiology remains largely unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Here, we presented a case with post COVID-19 encephalopathy manifested as marked cognitive decline, followed by major depression and oral cenesthopathy, a rare somatic delusion known to be related to affective disorders and schizophrenia in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], 16 months after COVID-19 infection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par3">Mrs. P, a 73-year-old female, first presented to our Psychiatric Outpatient Department with a history of hypertension and no family history of psychiatric disorders. At age 71, she contracted COVID-19, which was followed by a progressive decline in cognitive function. She was subsequently admitted to the Neurology ward under the initial impression of autoimmune encephalitis or Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD). Nonetheless, extensive investigations for common causes of autoimmune encephalitis, including antinuclear antibody (ANA), NMDA, AMPA, GABA-b, caspr, LGI-1, and DPPx, yielded negative results. Brain Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) revealed old lacunar infarctions at the right centrum semiovale and the left basal ganglion but did not demonstrate the classic cortical ribbon signs indicative of CJD. Electroencephalography (EEG) showed diffuse cortical dysfunction. In the absence of evidence supporting autoimmune encephalitis or CJD, post COVID-19 encephalopathy was considered the underlying etiology for her progressive cognitive decline. 16 months post-infection, Mrs. P developed a major depressive episode characterized by anhedonia, insomnia, decreased appetite, general fatigue, feeling of worthlessness and pervasive negative thoughts. In addition to these core mood symptoms, she reported unusual oral sensations, describing them as “small teeth growing within the gums in my mouth” and “these teeth are squeezing and pulling around, and when I tilt my head, they are coming out of my ear”. Despite these vivid descriptions, she did not report specific taste disturbances such as dysgeusia or ageusia. These sensations prompted multiple dental consultations, none of which identified significant abnormalities. Trigeminal neuralgia was suspected, and Carbamazepine was prescribed, but the response was minimal. Mrs. P was admitted to our psychiatric ward with a working diagnosis of major depression with oral cenesthopathy and post COVID-19 encephalitis. She denied other psychotic symptoms such as auditory or visual hallucination, persecutory or reference delusion, or a history of manic episodes. Comprehensive laboratory work up and physical examination upon admission were unremarkable. Repeat EEG showed no evidence of cortical dysfunction and Magnetic Resonance Angiography (MRA) excluded vascular loop syndrome or mass lesions along the bilateral trigeminal nerve courses. Comprehensive neuropsychological assessment revealed significant cognitive impairment, as indicated by Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) score of 15/30 and Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR) 1. Pharmacological treatment included Aripiprazole 5 mg and Carbamazepine 600 mg were prescribed. This regimen resulted in partial symptom improvement. While Mrs. P remained convinced of the uncontrollable teeth movement in her mouth, the intensity of her discomfort diminished, and she appeared less agitated and depressed. An attempt to titrate Aripiprazole dosage to 7.5 mg for enhanced symptom control led to unsteady gait and a subsequent fall, necessitating a reduction back to 5 mg. Mrs. P was discharged with partial improvement under the same regimen of Aripiprazole 5 mg and Carbamazepine 600 mg daily.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par4">To the best of our knowledge, this is the first case report documenting a patient who initially presented with post-COVID-19 encephalopathy and subsequently developed major depression with oral cenesthopathy 16 months later, representing a rare manifestation of long COVID syndrome.</p><p id="Par5">Long COVID is a multisystemic illness affecting at least 10% of individuals following COVID-19 infection. It is characterized by a wide range of persistent symptoms across multiple organ systems, often lasting months or years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Neurological manifestations are particularly prevalent and persistent in long COVID patients, with the highest prevalence observed within the first 6 months post-infection. Common neurological symptoms include cognitive dysfunction and paresthesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Cognitive dysfunction is often one of the earliest neurological manifestations, while paresthesia is characterized by abnormal sensations such as tingling, numbness, or a “pins and needles” feeling, typically affecting extremities. Although the exact mechanism of paresthesia remains unclear, it is hypothesized to involve nerve damage or inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In Mrs. P’s case, the significant cognitive decline observed post-COVID aligns with the literature on long COVID. However, her later development of abnormal oral sensations with delusional interpretations diverges from typical post-COVID paresthesia and is better described as oral cenesthopathy. Oral cenesthopathy is defined by unusual sensations without corresponding abnormal findings. These sensations may include feeling of a foreign body in the mouth, excessive mucus secretion, slimy or sticky sensations, or more complex perceptions such as squeezing or pulling sensations. Other reported symptoms include sensations of coils or wires, gas or bubbles, misalignment or twisting sensations in the gums, feelings of something about to spout out or taste disturbance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. According to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5), oral cenesthopathy is classified under delusional disorder, somatic type. One previous study has noted oral cenesthopathy predominantly occur in elderly female patients and may be associated with dental treatments during the acute phase of depressive episodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Additionally, oral cenesthopathy has been linked to conditions such as schizophrenia, depression, and burning mouth syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. These symptoms are often chronic, challenging to treat, and significantly impact patients’ quality of life, affecting eating, speaking, and social interactions.</p><p id="Par6">One prior case report documented the co-occurrence of cognitive decline and oral cenesthopathy in a patent with dementia with Lewy Bodies (DLB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The diagnosis of DLB requires the presence of dementia alongside core clinical features including fluctuating cognition, recurrent visual hallucinations, REM sleep behavior disorder (RBD), and spontaneous parkinsonism. Supportive features include sensitivity to antipsychotic agents, severe autonomic dysfunction and systematized delusions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In Mrs. P’s case, the absence of visual hallucinations, RBD, or parkinsonism rendered a diagnosis of DLB less likely. Furthermore, diagnostic tools such as dopamine transporter scans, 123 iodine-metaiodobenzylguanidine (MIBG) myocardial scintigraphy, and polysomnographic were not pursued, as clinical features did not strongly suggest DLB.</p><p id="Par7">The mechanisms linking post-COVID encephalopathy to oral cenesthopathy remain unclear, but persistent neuroinflammation and immune dysregulation may play a role [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Long COVID is associated with prolonged microglial activation, elevated pro-inflammatory cytokines, and structural brain changes, which can disrupt sensory processing and lead to abnormal bodily perceptions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Functional imaging studies in cenesthopathy patients demonstrate hypoperfusion in the prefrontal cortex and hyperperfusion in the somatosensory cortex, patterns potentially exacerbated by COVID-related cytokine storms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Additionally, dopaminergic dysfunction has been implicated, as evidenced by the partial efficacy of dopamine-modulating agents like aripiprazole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In Mrs. P’s case, the progression from post-COVID encephalopathy to oral cenesthopathy may reflect the combined impact of persistent neuroinflammation, sensory misinterpretation, and comorbid depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Similar cases have been reported in neuropsychiatric disorders where sensory disturbances evolve into somatic delusions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Further research is needed to clarify how post-COVID neuroinflammation alters sensory perception and to explore targeted treatments for oral cenesthopathy in long COVID patients.</p><p id="Par8">Treatment of oral cenesthopathy remains challenging. One retrospective chart review identified several medications/therapy with potential efficacy, including paroxetine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] fluvoxamine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] amitriptyline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], sulpiride [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], risperidone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], olanzapine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], aripiprazole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] and electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. These treatments primarily target underlying mood disorders that may exacerbate abnormal oral sensations. However, only 36% of patients demonstrated clinically significant improvement after 6 months of pharmacotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], with aripiprazole being the most effective agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Aripiprazole, a partial dopamine D2 receptor agonist, has demonstrated efficacy in managing psychiatric conditions associated with delusional symptoms. In Mrs. P’s case, the use of aripiprazole at 5 mg/day exceeded the mean dosage of 1.52 mg/day reported in previous cenesthopathy cohorts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], reflecting the severity of her delusional preoccupation and comorbid depression. However, dose escalation was limited by side effects, underscoring the challenges of pharmacotherapy in elderly patients with post-COVID encephalopathy. Notably, the average dose of aripiprazole for delusional disorders is 11.1 mg/day, with a range of 1.5–30 mg/day as reported in one recent systematic review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The relatively low dose used in Mrs. P’s treatment may suggest her symptoms were more likely attributed to underlying central nervous system pathology, such as post-COVID-19 encephalopathy, rather than a primary psychiatric disorder.</p><p id="Par9">On the other hand, Carbamazepine, prescribed for suspected trigeminal neuralgia, demonstrated minimal efficacy in this case. While carbamazepine is effective in managing neuropathic pain and mood lability, its limited impact prompted a reevaluation of the diagnosis in this case, leading to the identification of oral cenesthopathy as the underlying condition. Its role in Mrs. P’s case may extend to mitigating neuropathic pain mechanisms potentiated by COVID-related neuroinflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par10">This case highlights a rare presentation of post-COVID neuropsychiatric manifestations, including cognitive impairment, depression, and oral cenesthopathy. The findings underscore the need for further research to delineate the long-term neurological and psychiatric sequelae of long COVID, as well as the underlying biological mechanisms, such as inflammation and neurotransmitter dysregulation. Additionally, more studies are warranted to explore effective treatment strategies for neuropsychiatric symptoms in long COVID patients.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JIW wrote the main manuscript text. SHL and PJC revised and edited the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data sharing is not applicable to this article as no datasets were generated or analysed during the current study.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par11">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par12">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par13">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Davis HE, et al. Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023;21(3):133–46.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinanović</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muftić</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinanović</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 pandemia: neuropsychiatric comorbidity and consequences</article-title><source>Psychiatr Danub</source><year>2020</year><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24869/psyd.2020.236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32796792</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Sinanović O, Muftić M, Sinanović S. COVID-19 pandemia: neuropsychiatric comorbidity and consequences. Psychiatr Danub. 2020;32(2):236–44.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32796792</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.24869/psyd.2020.236</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinzon</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Persistent neurological manifestations in long COVID-19 syndrome: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Infect Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>856</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2022.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35785594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9221935</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Pinzon RT, et al. Persistent neurological manifestations in long COVID-19 syndrome: A systematic review and meta-analysis. J Infect Public Health. 2022;15(8):856–69.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35785594</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jiph.2022.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9221935</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero-Duarte</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sequelae, persistent symptomatology and outcomes after COVID-19 hospitalization: the ANCOHVID multicentre 6-month follow-up study</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-021-02003-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34011359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8134820</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Romero-Duarte Á, et al. Sequelae, persistent symptomatology and outcomes after COVID-19 hospitalization: the ANCOHVID multicentre 6-month follow-up study. BMC Med. 2021;19(1):129.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34011359</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12916-021-02003-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8134820</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Umezaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oral cenesthopathy</article-title><source>Biopsychosoc Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13030-016-0071-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27293481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4903001</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Umezaki Y, et al. Oral cenesthopathy. Biopsychosoc Med. 2016;10:20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27293481</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13030-016-0071-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4903001</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Umezaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics and course of oral somatic delusions: a retrospective chart review of 606 cases in 5 years</article-title><source>Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2057</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S167527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30147319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6095116</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Umezaki Y, et al. Clinical characteristics and course of oral somatic delusions: a retrospective chart review of 606 cases in 5 years. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. 2018;14:2057–65.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30147319</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/NDT.S167527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6095116</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Umezaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A case of oral cenesthopathy in which dementia with lewy bodies developed during treatment</article-title><source>Psychogeriatrics</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/psyg.12541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32173959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7586958</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Umezaki Y, et al. A case of oral cenesthopathy in which dementia with lewy bodies developed during treatment. Psychogeriatrics. 2020;20(5):766–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32173959</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/psyg.12541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7586958</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKeith</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and management of dementia with lewy bodies: fourth consensus report of the DLB consortium</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2017</year><volume>89</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000004058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28592453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5496518</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">McKeith IG, et al. Diagnosis and management of dementia with lewy bodies: fourth consensus report of the DLB consortium. Neurology. 2017;89(1):88–100.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28592453</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/WNL.0000000000004058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5496518</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperperfusion in primary somatosensory region related to somatic hallucination in the elderly</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source><year>2010</year><volume>64</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1819.2010.02101.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20492558</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Nemoto K, et al. Hyperperfusion in primary somatosensory region related to somatic hallucination in the elderly. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2010;64(4):421–5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20492558</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1440-1819.2010.02101.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aripiprazole for the treatment of delusional disorders: A systematic review</article-title><source>Gen Hosp Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2020.06.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32650190</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Miola A, et al. Aripiprazole for the treatment of delusional disorders: A systematic review. Gen Hosp Psychiatry. 2020;66:34–43.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32650190</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2020.06.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Paroxetine treatment of delusional disorder, somatic type</article-title><source>Hum Psychopharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hup.590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15252828</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Hayashi H, et al. Paroxetine treatment of delusional disorder, somatic type. Hum Psychopharmacol. 2004;19(5):351–2.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15252828</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hup.590</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Delusion of oral parasitosis and thalamic pain syndrome</article-title><source>Psychosomatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>50</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0033-3182(09)70847-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19855040</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Hanihara T, et al. Delusion of oral parasitosis and thalamic pain syndrome. Psychosomatics. 2009;50(5):534–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19855040</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/appi.psy.50.5.534</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uezato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improvement of asymmetrical Temporal blood flow in refractory oral somatic delusion after successful electroconvulsive therapy</article-title><source>J Ect</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/YCT.0b013e31822e581e</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21983760</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Uezato A, et al. Improvement of asymmetrical Temporal blood flow in refractory oral somatic delusion after successful electroconvulsive therapy. J Ect. 2012;28(1):50–1.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21983760</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/YCT.0b013e31822e581e</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spina E, Perugi G. Antiepileptic drugs: indications other than epilepsy. <italic toggle="yes">Epileptic Disord</italic>. 2004;6(2):57–75. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15246950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>