<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Occup Med (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Occup Med (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">769</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">occumed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">occmed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Occupational Medicine (Oxford, England)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0962-7480</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1471-8405</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11973416</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11973416.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11973416</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11973416</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39800813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/occmed/kqae128</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">kqae128</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Papers</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00640</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prevalence and symptoms of Long Covid-19 in the workplace</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohd Yusoff</surname><given-names initials="H">H</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Public Health Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>Jalan Yaacob Latif, Bandar Tun Razak, Cheras, 56000 Kuala Lumpur</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yew</surname><given-names initials="SQ">S Q</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Public Health Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>Jalan Yaacob Latif, Bandar Tun Razak, Cheras, 56000 Kuala Lumpur</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed Nawi</surname><given-names initials="A">A</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Public Health Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>Jalan Yaacob Latif, Bandar Tun Razak, Cheras, 56000 Kuala Lumpur</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Htwe</surname><given-names initials="O">O</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Faculty of Medicine, Universiti Sultan Zainal Abidin</institution>, <addr-line>Gong Badak, 21300 Kuala Nerus, Terengganu</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohd Tohit</surname><given-names initials="N">N</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Family Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>Jalan Yaacob Latif, Bandar Tun Razak, Cheras, 56000 Kuala Lumpur</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names initials="Z">Z</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Negeri Sembilan State Health Department</institution>, <addr-line>Jalan Rasah, Negeri Sembilan, 70300 Seremban</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muhamad Noordin</surname><given-names initials="MA">M A</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Research Management Center, Research and Development Department, National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health</institution>, <addr-line>43650 Bandar Baru Bangi, Selangor</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Che Mohamed</surname><given-names initials="N">N</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Project Management, UKM Pakarunding, Level 3, Bangunan Wawasan, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>43600 Bangi, Selangor</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohd</surname><given-names initials="FH">F H</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Project Management, UKM Pakarunding, Level 3, Bangunan Wawasan, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>43600 Bangi, Selangor</addr-line>, <country country="MY">Malaysia</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence to: S. Q. Yew, Department of Public Health Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Jalan Yaacob Latif, Bandar Tun Razak, Cheras, 56000 Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. Tel: +603-9145 8792; e-mail: <email>shengqian@ukm.edu.my</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-01-11"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>75</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">486116</issue-id><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-08 00:25:37.220"><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society of Occupational Medicine.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="kqae128.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="kqae128.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>The symptoms of Long coronavirus disease 2019 (Covid-19) are heterogeneous, creating uncertainty for employers regarding the diagnosis. The prevalence of Long Covid-19 in the workforce is also unknown. Furthermore, workers affected by Long Covid-19 encounter considerable difficulties in ensuring work safety and returning to their jobs due to this condition.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Aims</title><p>This review is aimed to identify the prevalence of Long Covid-19 in the workplace and to determine the various symptoms of Long Covid-19 experienced by the workers.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Methods</title><p>A meta-analysis was conducted to calculate the pooled estimates for the prevalence of Long Covid-19. Heterogeneity among the estimates was evaluated using the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>² statistic.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Results</title><p>The pooled prevalence of Long Covid-19 among workers across the 11 studies was 38% (95% CI 23–56). A total of 43 symptoms associated with Long Covid-19 were identified in the workplace, with the top five symptoms being dyspnoea at moderate activity (51%, 95% CI 39–62), mental symptoms (38%, 95% CI 6–87), dyspnoea at mild activity (35%, 95% CI 25–47), fatigue (26%, 95% CI 3–78) and effort intolerance (24%, 95% CI 15–35).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The review indicates a significant burden of long-lasting symptoms within the workforce. The top five reported symptoms of Long Covid-19 were dyspnoea during mild and moderate activities, mental symptoms, fatigue and effort intolerance.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>There were 43 symptoms associated with Long coronavirus disease (Covid-19) in the workplace. The prevalence of Long Covid-19 among workers was 38%. Common symptoms include dyspnoea, mental symptoms, fatigue and effort intolerance.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH) Malaysia</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>UKMP-S230424</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s6"><title>Introduction</title><p>Long coronavirus disease 2019 (Covid-19) is a disease condition that has different definitions depending on the organization, country or experts involved. The World Health Organization (WHO) defines Long Covid-19 as the continuation or emergence of new symptoms three months after the initial severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection, with these symptoms lasting for at least 2 months without any other explanation [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. On the other hand, the US Centre for Disease Control and Prevention provides a more specific definition, encompassing signs, symptoms and conditions that persist or develop after 4 weeks or more following the initial phase of Covid-19 infection, potentially leading to severe and life-threatening events even months or years later [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. To further complicate matters, a diverse array of terminologies has been employed to describe this specific disease condition, including Long Covid-19 [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], chronic Covid-19 [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], post-Covid-19 [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], post-acute Covid-19 [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], persistent Covid-19 symptoms [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Irrespective of the varied definitions and terminologies employed, this disease condition has resulted in a significant disease burden worldwide [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. For instance, a recent meta-analysis consisting of 120 studies indicated a high global prevalence of Long Covid-19, in which almost 4 out of 10 (42%) individuals tested positive for Covid-19 infection were found to suffer from Long Covid-19 symptoms [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Of note, individuals affected by Long Covid-19 can present with a wide range of symptoms across multiple body systems [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In most cases, they may experience symptoms including fatigue, malaise and acute illness-induced fever [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Others may experience neurological symptoms such as difficulty in concentration, headache, altered taste and smell, cognitive impairment, memory deficits, as well as dizziness [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Also reported are cardiopulmonary symptoms such as dyspnoea, decreased effort tolerance and palpitations [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Alongside these physical symptoms, individuals affected by Long Covid-19 may also endure symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), anxiety and depression, which can persist beyond a 6-month follow-up period [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The association between Long Covid-19 and these mental symptoms were established using self-administered questionnaires such as the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9), Primary Care PTSD Screen (PC-PTSD), Trauma Screening Questionnaire and Generalized Anxiety Disorder Assessment (GAD-7) [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Owing to the extensive symptoms of Long Covid-19 as abovementioned, many employed individuals with Long Covid-19 face significant challenges when it comes to returning to work [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Coupled with the high workload and work-related stress in their original workplaces [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], as well as the slow pace of recovery from Covid-19, these group of individuals may also have increased rates of sick absenteeism [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. These challenges can further prevent them from returning to work and may even lead to a sense of losing their profession [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Even if these individuals manage to return to work, the symptoms of Long Covid-19 can make it difficult for them to focus on their job tasks, leading to decreased work productivity [<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Not to mention, Long Covid-19 symptoms can give rise to safety concerns for these employed individuals, particularly those who are exposed to multiple occupational hazards. As such, it comes as no surprise that the presence of Long Covid-19 symptoms is associated to a lower likelihood of working full-time (adjusted OR: 0.84, 95% CI 0.74–0.96) and a higher likelihood of unemployment (adjusted OR: 1.23, 95% CI 1.02–1.48) [<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This loss of job and income, in turn, can further contribute to the deterioration of health status among the workers. All these findings collectively highlight the detrimental impacts of Long Covid-19 in the workplace.</p><p>Despite the established negative impacts of Long Covid-19 on the performance of workers across different industries, there remains a dearth of research exploring the prevalence of Long Covid-19 in the working population [<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Additionally, even though Long Covid-19 prevalence has been extensively studied previously, it is important to note that these findings primarily reflect the general population and may not fully encompass the working population [<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In short, it is still unclear what is the prevalence and symptoms of Long Covid-19 experienced by the workers. Recognizing these gaps in the literature, the objective of this review is to systematically appraise and synthesize the evidence on the prevalence of Long Covid-19 in the workplace. Secondly, this review is aimed to determine the various symptoms of Long Covid-19 experienced by the workers. Once the prevalence and symptoms of Long Covid-19 in the workplace are identified, it is hoped that this information will facilitate the employers, policymakers and various stakeholders to implement effective control measures in mitigating the adverse effects of Long Covid-19 in the workplace, while also providing comprehensive support to workers grappling with this disease condition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials" id="s7"><title>Methods</title><p>This systematic review and meta-analysis adhered to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines, ensuring comprehensive and transparent reporting. The research protocol was previously published in the International Prospective Register of Systematic Reviews, PROSPERO (ID CRD42024499679), further enhancing the study’s credibility and accountability.</p><p>Articles were included in the current review if they met the following inclusion criteria: (i) quantitative studies such as case-control, cohort, cross-sectional studies and randomized controlled trials, including preprints; (ii) studies that investigated the prevalence of Long Covid-19 among workers from all sectors; (iii) studies reported in the English language and (iv) studies published from 1 January 2020 onwards. Conversely, articles were excluded if they met any of the following criteria: (i) follow-up period of &lt;12 weeks or unclear follow-up (based on the WHO’s Long Covid-19 definition); (ii) case series, case reports, qualitative studies and secondary analyses (e.g. systematic reviews) and (iii) grey literature.</p><p>A comprehensive search strategy was employed across three databases, namely PubMed, Web of Science and Scopus. PubMed, Web of Science and Scopus are renowned academic databases that collectively offer extensive coverage across various disciplines. Utilizing all three platforms ensures a more comprehensive and inclusive search strategy, allowing researchers to access a diverse range of scholarly articles, journals and conference proceedings relevant to the systematic literature review. To ensure completeness, the search in these databases was complemented by a manual examination of references cited in relevant systematic reviews.</p><p>For the systematic search, a robust Boolean search strategy was implemented, incorporating a blend of Medical Subject Headings and appropriate text words. The search terms were crafted in collaboration with the research team and relevant stakeholders to encompass all relevant aspects of the subject matter. A table outlining the search terms and search strategies for the three databases was presented in the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> (available as Supplementary data at <italic toggle="yes">Occupational Medicine</italic> online).</p><p>All studies identified through the search strategy underwent a rigorous assessment for eligibility. Initially, title and abstract screening were conducted independently by two researchers (S.Q.Y. and H.M.Y.). Subsequently, a full-text screening was performed to further evaluate the suitability of the studies. In cases where multiple publications originated from the same study, only the most recent publication was included in the analysis, ensuring avoidance of duplication.</p><p>A structured data extraction form in Microsoft Office Excel was utilized to extract relevant information from each eligible study. The extracted data encompassed details such as author names, countries, study designs, industrial sectors, details of study population, severity of Covid-19 of study population, sample sizes, participant characteristics (including age and gender), diagnostic method, minimum duration of follow-up and prevalence of Long Covid-19 symptoms. For studies that presented data on the prevalence of individual symptoms without providing an overall prevalence of Long Covid-19, we determined the overall prevalence by referring to the symptom with the highest prevalence. Two researchers (S.Q.Y. and H.M.Y.) independently performed the data extraction, and any discrepancies were resolved through discussions involving a third researcher (A.M.N.).</p><p>The primary outcome of our analysis was the prevalence of Long Covid-19 in the workplace. Subsequently, we conducted further analyses to examine how the prevalence of Long Covid-19 in the workplace varied across different factors, including study designs, industrial sectors, follow-up duration, age of workers, gender of workers, diagnostic method, methods of symptom assessment, presence of a control group or the definition of Long Covid-19.</p><p>To evaluate the quality of the included studies, the Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) Critical Appraisal Checklist for Studies Reporting Prevalence Data was employed [<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The selection of the JBI Critical Appraisal Checklist is grounded in its evidence-based practice focus, versatility across study designs, inclusion of qualitative research criteria, user-friendly format, alignment with systematic review standards, continuous updates, international recognition and comprehensive evaluation of methodological rigor. The checklist consists of nine items, each with four possibilities for assessment. A qualitative assessment was conducted on each of the nine items to determine the overall quality rating of each study, categorized as good, moderate or low. Two researchers (S.Q.Y. and H.M.Y.) independently assessed the quality, and any disagreements were resolved through discussions involving a third researcher (A.M.N.). It is important to note that the studies were not excluded based on their quality. However, a sensitivity analysis was conducted to evaluate the influence of study quality (i.e. risk of bias) on the study outcome, whereby studies with low quality were excluded and the estimated pooled prevalence of Long Covid-19 was recalculated.</p><p>A meta-analysis was conducted to calculate the pooled estimates for the prevalence of Long Covid-19 in the workplace with a 95% CI as an estimated effect across studies. Heterogeneity among the estimates was evaluated using the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>² statistic. Random-effects or fixed-effects models were employed, depending on the level of heterogeneity (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>²). Fixed-effects models were utilized when studies exhibited low heterogeneity (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>² ≤ 50%), while random-effects models were employed for studies with significant heterogeneity (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>² ≥ 50%). Subgroup analyses were conducted to examine the pooled prevalence of Long Covid-19 in relation to study designs, industrial sectors, follow-up duration, age of workers, gender of workers, diagnostic method, methods of symptom assessment, presence of a control group or the definition of Long Covid-19. Publication bias was assessed by visually inspecting funnel plots and using the Egger bias test, with a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 indicative of possible publication bias. All statistical analyses were performed using Comprehensive Meta-Analysis version 2.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 899 titles were identified through database searches for this review but only 11 were deemed suitable for inclusion (see <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). As for the quality assessment, six of the included studies were classified as good and five as moderate. This implies that all 11 studies considered in this review carry a low risk of bias, as indicated in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Quality assessment by the JBI critical appraisal tool for prevalence studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%" border="1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Was the sample frame appropriate to address the target population?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Were study participants sampled in an appropriate way?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Was the sample size adequate?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Were the study subjects and the setting described in detail?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Was the data analysis conducted with sufficient coverage of the identified sample?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Were valid methods used for the identification of the condition?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Was the condition measured in a standard, reliable way for all participants?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Was there appropriate statistical analysis?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9. Was the response rate adequate, and if not, was the low response rate managed appropriately?</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bernas</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gaber</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ladlow</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lemhofer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Martinez</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perisse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pilmis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selvaskandan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shukla</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stufano</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tempany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1Fn1"><p>NA = Not applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="kqae128_fig1.jpg"/></fig><p>The studies encompassed a participant range of 71 to 12 609, totalling 14 979 participants in this review. The time elapsed from Covid-19 infection to participant recruitment varied from 12 to 24 weeks. The age of the cohorts spanned from 31.5 to 50.6 years, with five studies focussing on participants under 40 years old [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24–28</xref>]. Geographically, the research was primarily conducted in Europe (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10) [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24–27</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29–34</xref>] and Asia (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The study designs included eight cross-sectional studies [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28–30</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32–34</xref>] and three prospective cohort studies [<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><p>The participants were drawn from diverse sectors, including healthcare (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>= 6) [<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], general industry (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2) [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], military (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2) [<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and education (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Notably, eight studies had a higher proportion of female participants [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28–32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction was the chosen method for diagnosing Covid-19 infection in seven studies [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], while one study used the enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay [<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Six studies categorized participants based on hospitalization status [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24–26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28–30</xref>], while others classified them according to disease severity [<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] or had undefined categorization [<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. <xref rid="sup2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table 1</xref> (available as Supplementary data at <italic toggle="yes">Occupational Medicine</italic> Online) summarizes the characteristics and primary outcomes of the 11 studies included in this review.</p><p>In this review, the prevalence of Long Covid-19 among workers varied from 10% to 54%, with a pooled prevalence of 38% (95% CI 22.5–56.2) as illustrated in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>. In other words, the overall estimated prevalence across the 11 studies was 38%. Due to substantial heterogeneity among the studies (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 99%), subgroup analyses were conducted. These analyses revealed that the prevalence of Long Covid-19 did not significantly differ based on industrial sectors, follow-up duration, age of workers, gender of workers, diagnostic methods, methods of symptom assessment, presence of a control group, provision of Long Covid-19 definition and study designs. The result of the subgroup analysis was provided as <xref rid="sup3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> (available as Supplementary data at <italic toggle="yes">Occupational Medicine</italic> online).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Pooled prevalence of Long Covid-19 among workers.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="kqae128_fig2.jpg"/></fig><p>Of note, we identified 43 symptoms associated with Long Covid-19 in the workplace, as detailed in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Among the participants, the five most commonly reported symptoms were dyspnoea at moderate activity (51%, 95% CI 39–62, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1), mental symptoms (38%, 95% CI 6–87, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2), dyspnoea at mild activity (35%, 95% CI 25–47, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1), fatigue (26%, 95% CI 3–78, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10) and effort intolerance (24%, 95% CI 15–35, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1). The asymmetry of the funnel plot and the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of &lt;0.05 in Egger’s test suggest the presence of publication bias in this review.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Long Covid-19 symptoms in the workplace</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%" border="1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body systems</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptoms</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Events</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sample size</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pooled prevalence (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">General</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 843</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generalized weakness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">331</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1090</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced appetite</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 548</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disturbance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1844</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 705</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10–34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Psychiatric</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental disorders</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">533</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 701</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 288</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mood disorders</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">258</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Musculoskeletal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arthralgia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">972</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 619</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myalgia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 439</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Musculoskeletal pain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">Nervous</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor concentration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1255</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 105</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confusion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dizziness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">331</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">796</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syncope</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor attention</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor memory</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">839</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 359</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tingling in extremities</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cognitive impairment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13–23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Dermatological</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin rash</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">759</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pruritus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hair loss</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Cardiovascular</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palpitations</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">396</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 619</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest pain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 032</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effort intolerance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15–35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Respiratory</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyspnoea</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">468</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 507</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyspnoea (at rest)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10–27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyspnoea (at mild activity)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25–47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyspnoea (at moderate activity)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39–62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive problems</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">673</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diarrhoea</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 439</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore throat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 439</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdominal pain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 359</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dysphagia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea/vomiting</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 288</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Ear, nose and throat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ear pain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vertigo</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 609</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tinnitus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anosmia/ageusia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1125</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 232</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>–</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">477</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–41</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Discussion</title><p>This systematic review aimed to evaluate the prevalence and symptoms of Long Covid-19 in the workplace, aligning with the original PROSPERO protocol. The findings reveal a significant prevalence of Long Covid-19 among workers, estimated at 38%. Intriguingly, this pooled prevalence is lower than those reported in meta-analyses conducted in the general population (ranging from 42% to 57% for Long Covid-19) [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. This disparity may be attributed to the healthy worker effect, where individuals in better health are more likely to be employed, potentially resulting in a lower prevalence of Long Covid-19 among workers [<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Conversely, those with poor health conditions, including those suffering from Long Covid-19 symptoms, may face challenges in securing and maintaining employment. Additionally, the employed population typically enjoys enhanced access to healthcare services, encompassing preventive care and early treatment, contributing to improved health outcomes compared to the unemployed. Another plausible explanation is that the participants in our review, namely workers, were potentially younger than the general population, potentially resulting in a lower prevalence of Long Covid-19 [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. A third possible rationale could be that our review exclusively enrolled participants who experienced symptoms persisting beyond 12 weeks from the onset of acute Covid-19 infection, in contrast to prior analyses that encompassed participants displaying symptoms within the initial 12-week period [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Moreover, our review revealed that Long Covid-19 imposes a substantial burden of functional impairment, symptoms and pathology affecting various organ systems. This can be attributed to the multifaceted and potentially interconnected pathophysiological mechanisms of Long Covid-19, encompassing persisting viral reservoirs, immune dysfunction, micro-clotting, organ damage and psychological impacts [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The top five prevalent symptoms include dyspnoea at moderate activities (51%), mental symptoms (38%), dyspnoea at mild activities (35%), fatigue (26%) and effort intolerance (24%). Despite the lower overall prevalence of Long Covid-19 as compared to the previous meta-analyses, the prevalences of these top five symptoms were higher compared to the previous analyses. For instance, the prevalence of dyspnoea at moderate activities in our review (51%) exceeded that reported in earlier analyses (20–34%) [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Similarly, our analysis showed a higher prevalence of mental symptoms (38%) among our participants compared to the previous studies (8–19%) [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. A similar trend was observed in symptoms such as dyspnoea at mild activities (35%), fatigue (26%) and effort intolerance (24%), where previous analyses reported a prevalence of 15–24% [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], 22–31% [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and 17% [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], respectively. This discrepancy can be elucidated by the fact that a majority of our participants were drawn from stressful working conditions, such as healthcare and military sectors. These populations are potentially exposed to higher workloads and occupational stress [<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</p><p>Furthermore, our findings lend support to the notion that Covid-19 may result in the persistence of symptoms even after the resolution of acute infection, a phenomenon previously observed with SARS-CoV-1 and Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS)-CoV. The SARS-CoV-1 pandemic initially emerged in Guangdong Province, China in 2003 and subsequently extended its reach to 29 countries [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. A prospective cohort study conducted on individuals who survived SARS-CoV-1 infection revealed notable declines in diffusing capacity for carbon monoxide, exercise capacity and overall health status at 24 months post-infection [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], with healthcare workers experienced a more pronounced negative impact. Regarding psychological effects, workers who contracted SARS-CoV-1 reported significantly elevated levels of burnout, psychological distress and PTSD between 13 and 26 months after infection [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Remarkably, even 18 years later, fatigue remained the predominant symptom among the workers, and their respiratory function was notably lower compared to controls. Nonetheless, it is worth noting that emotional and mental health fully recovered at the 18-year follow-up [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. In the case of MERS-CoV, a pandemic originating in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia in 2012 [<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], a year-long follow-up revealed that 48% of survivors continued to experience fatigue symptoms, which decreased to 33% at 18 months of follow-up [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. While 88% of individuals who survived MERS-CoV returned to work, the study did not specify the proportion engaged in part- or full-time employment [<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Regarding mental health, 27% of survivors reported depression and 42% had PTSD at 12 months post MERS-CoV infection [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Another study conducted in South Korea demonstrated that 57% of nurses who treated MERS-CoV patients suffered from PTSD [<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. This evidence suggests that similar to SARS-CoV-1 and MERS-CoV, we should anticipate the long-term consequences of Covid-19, which will negatively impact the work performance of the workers. More concerning is the possibility that Covid-19 could lead to more extensive long-term consequences, given that SARS-CoV-2 has higher transmissibility and a greater capacity to mutate to different variants compared to SARS-CoV-1 and MERS-CoV [<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>The review has several strengths. First of all, we included an extensive electronic search for pertinent studies and a thorough evaluation of risk of bias, data extraction and verification, all conducted independently by two authors. Additionally, we employed the JBI critical appraisal tool for prevalence studies, ensuring a comprehensive assessment of study quality. The application of this tool indicated that all studies included in our review achieved moderate and/or high quality.</p><p>Nevertheless, it is crucial to acknowledge certain limitations in this review. Firstly, there was a notable heterogeneity between studies and a considerable range in prevalence. While earlier analysis pointed to the high heterogeneity resulting from the diverse array of self-report screening tools used to collect Long Covid-19 symptoms [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], our subgroup analysis did not reveal a similar pattern. Secondly, some prior analyses suggested that the introduction of control groups in certain studies might contribute to heterogeneity [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], yet this aspect is not apparent in our current analysis. Another noteworthy limitation that warrants attention is our use of the most commonly reported symptom estimate for individual studies, without combining multiple individual symptoms into an overall estimate of Long Covid-19 prevalence. Given the variability in the symptom with the highest prevalence across studies, direct comparisons may be challenging. Furthermore, similar to observations in other analyses, the lack of a unified consensus on the definition of Long Covid-19 poses a challenge, particularly concerning the varying time components for persistent symptoms following the infection onset [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. It is essential to acknowledge that certain Long Covid-19 symptoms might be absent in some studies due to non-identification or non-inclusion in patient questionnaires [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In addition, the presence of publication bias in our findings is likely attributed to the decision to screen papers exclusively in English and the utilization of only three databases for screening [<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. By excluding non-English studies, the review may suffer from language bias, which can lead to an overrepresentation of studies from English-speaking countries. This can skew the findings if the results differ systematically by languages and geographical locations. Meanwhile, retrieving articles from a limited number of databases may miss important studies that are indexed in other databases.</p><p>Comprehensive management of Long Covid-19 symptoms, which affect multiple organs, necessitates the involvement of a diverse clinical team rather than relying on a specific specialty. Employers should be capable of identifying Long Covid-19 symptoms in their workers and offer prompt assistance, including potential adjustments to job activities. Insurers must address Long Covid-19, providing financial and vocational support to affected workers. If termination occurs due to Long Covid-19 symptoms, affected individuals should receive compensation.</p><p>This systematic review offers the latest and most extensive insights into the prevalence and symptoms of Long Covid-19 in the workplace, especially in the healthcare setting. The findings highlight that a considerable number of workers continue to grapple with a variety of persistent symptoms, with dyspnoea during mild and moderate activities, mental symptoms, fatigue and effort intolerance emerging as particularly prevalent. It is important to exercise caution in interpreting our prevalence estimates and the symptoms of Long Covid-19, given the substantial heterogeneity among studies resulting from diverse study designs.</p><boxed-text position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Key learning points</title></caption><sec id="s10"><title>What is already known about this subject:</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Workers with Long Covid-19 often report decreased work productivity due to persistent symptoms.</p></list-item><list-item><p>There is a higher rate of sickness absenteeism as workers manage ongoing health issues.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Employers may suffer a rise in healthcare costs due to the long-term medical needs of workers affected by Long Covid-19.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s11"><title>What this study adds:</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>There were 43 symptoms associated with Long Covid-19 in the workplace.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The prevalence of Long Covid-19 among workers was 38%.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Common symptoms include dyspnoea, mental disorders, fatigue and effort intolerance.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s12"><title>What impact this may have on practice or policy:</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Awareness of Long Covid-19 symptoms enables employers to provide accommodations such as flexible hours or remote work.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Addressing mental health impacts encourages better support and access to resources for affected employees.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Early identification and support can reduce absenteeism by helping workers manage symptoms effectively.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>kqae128_suppl_Supplementary_Material</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="kqae128_suppl_supplementary_material.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>kqae128_suppl_Supplementary_Table_S2</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="kqae128_suppl_supplementary_table_s2.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>kqae128_suppl_Supplementary_Table_S1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="kqae128_suppl_supplementary_table_s1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="a1"><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>We would like to thank the Director of NIOSH Malaysia, for their grant and permission to publish this article.</p></ack><sec id="s13"><title>Funding</title><p>National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH) Malaysia (grant number UKMP-S230424) to H.M.Y.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s14"><title>Competing interests</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s15"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data are not publicly available. However, it will be made available upon request.</p></sec><ref-list id="r1"><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>WHO</collab>. <article-title>Post COVID-19 condition (Long COVID) [Internet]</article-title>. <year>2022</year> [cited 2024 June 7]. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>CDC</collab>. <source>Post-COVID Conditions</source>. <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention [Internet]</publisher-name>. <year>2023</year> [cited 2024 June 7]. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/covid/long-term-effects/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/covid/long-term-effects/index.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Moy</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hairi</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>ERJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bulgiba</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Long COVID and its associated factors among COVID survivors in the community from a middle-income country—an online cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e0273364</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0273364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36040960</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9426885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>SJC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nfonsam</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smieja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McArthur</surname><given-names>AG.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic COVID-19 infection in an immunosuppressed patient shows changes in lineage over time: a case report</article-title>. <source>Virol J</source><year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12985-023-02278-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38178158</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10768205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Kerksieck</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ballouz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Post COVID-19 condition, work ability and occupational changes in a population-based cohort</article-title>. <source>Lancet Reg. Health Eur.</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>100671</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanepe.2023.100671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37366496</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10287546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Nalbandian</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01283-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753937</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8893149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Richard</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pollett</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fries</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>; <collab>Epidemiology, Immunology, and Clinical Characteristics of Emerging Infectious Diseases With Pandemic Potential (EPICC) COVID-19 Cohort Study Group</collab>. <article-title>Persistent COVID-19 symptoms at 6 months after onset and the role of vaccination before or after SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title>. <source>JAMA Network Open</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e2251360</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.51360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36652247</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9857077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Thaweethai</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karlson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>; <collab>RECOVER Consortium</collab>. <article-title>Development of a definition of postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>329</volume>:<fpage>1934</fpage>–<lpage>1946</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2023.8823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37278994</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10214179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Lemogne</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pitron</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Shedding light on the work burden of long COVID</article-title>. <source>Lancet Reg. Health Eur.</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>100678</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanepe.2023.100678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37547275</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10398582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Understanding the burden of post-covid-19 condition</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>381</volume>:<fpage>p932</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.p932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37257892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Woodrow</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ziauddeen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Systematic review of the prevalence of long COVID</article-title>. <source>Open Forum Infect. Dis.</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>ofad233</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofad233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37404951</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10316694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>O’Mahoney</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Routen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The prevalence and long-term health effects of Long Covid among hospitalised and non-hospitalised populations: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>101762</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36474804</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9714474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Di Gennaro</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tulone</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Incidence of long COVID-19 in people with previous SARS-Cov2 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis of 120,970 patients</article-title>. <source>Intern Emerg Med</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1573</fpage>–<lpage>1581</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11739-022-03164-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36449260</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9709360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Evan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jayesh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anyelina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Anxiety, depression, insomnia, and trauma-related symptoms following COVID-19 infection at long-term follow-up</article-title>. <source>Brain Behav Immun.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbih.2021.100315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8321961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34345869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>KWA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Long COVID—Challenges in diagnosis and managing return‐to‐work</article-title>. <source>J Occup Health</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>e12401</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1348-9585.12401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37098838</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10132176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Mohd Fauzi</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohd Yusoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Muhamad Robat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mat Saruan</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohd Haris</surname><given-names>AF.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Doctors’ mental health in the midst of COVID-19 pandemic: the roles of work demands and recovery experiences</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>7340</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17197340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33050004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7579590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Descatha</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Evanoff</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fadel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Post-COVID condition or ‘long COVID’, return-to work, and occupational health research</article-title>. <source>Scand J Work Environ Health</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5271/sjweh.4088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36944213</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10621897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Hossain</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Living with ‘long COVID’: a systematic review and meta-synthesis of qualitative evidence</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>e0281884</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0281884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36795701</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9934341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>do Prado</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Emerick</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cevolani Pires</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Salaroli</surname><given-names>LB.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Impact of long-term COVID on workers: a systematic review protocol</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e0265705</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0265705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36054105</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9439188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Perlis</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lunz Trujillo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Safarpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Association of post-COVID-19 condition symptoms and employment status</article-title>. <source>JAMA Network Open</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e2256152</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.56152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36790806</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9932847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Al-Oraibi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naidu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Prevalence of long COVID-19 among healthcare workers: a systematic review and meta-analysis protocol</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e065234</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-065234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9729843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36600349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Reuschke</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The impact of Long COVID on the UK workforce</article-title>. <source>Appl Econ Letters</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2510</fpage>–<lpage>2514</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13504851.2022.2098239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>JBI</collab>. <article-title>The Joanna Briggs institute critical appraisal tools for use in JBI systematic reviews - checklist for prevalence studies [Internet]</article-title>. <year>2017</year> [cited 2024 June 7]. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jbi.global/critical-appraisal-tools" ext-link-type="uri">https://jbi.global/critical-appraisal-tools</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Bernas</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baldauf</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Real</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Post-COVID-19 condition in the German working population: a cross-sectional study of 200,000 registered stem cell donors</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>293</volume>:<fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joim.13587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36373223</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10107314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ladlow</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Holdsworth</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O’Sullivan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Exercise tolerance, fatigue, mental health, and employment status at 5 and 12 months following COVID-19 illness in a physically trained population</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (1985)</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>622</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00370.2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36759161</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10010915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Martinez</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banderet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Labhardt</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Battegay</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term outcome after SARS-CoV-2 infection in healthcare workers: a single centre cohort study</article-title>. <source>Swiss Med Wkly</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>w30094</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4414/smw.2021.w30094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34694107</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Perisse</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Cacqueray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Delarbre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Symptoms of Long-COVID 1-year after a COVID-19 outbreak among sailors on a French aircraft carrier</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Now</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>104673</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idnow.2023.104673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36775065</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9918313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Shukla</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Atal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>An observational multi-centric COVID-19 sequelae study among health care workers</article-title>. <source>Lancet Reg Health Southeast Asia</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>100129</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lansea.2022.100129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36531928</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9744681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gaber</surname>
<given-names>TZK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashish</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Unsworth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Persistent post-covid symptoms in healthcare workers</article-title>. <source>Occup Med (Lond)</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/occmed/kqab043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33830208</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8083525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Lemhöfer</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loudovici-Krug</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Quality of life and ability to work of patients with post-COVID syndrome in relation to the number of existing symptoms and the duration since infection up to 12 months: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1991</fpage>–<lpage>2002</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-023-03369-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36869248</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9984128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Pilmis</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Elkaibi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Péan de Ponfilly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Evolution of anti-SARS-CoV-2 immune response in a cohort of French healthcare workers followed for 7 months</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Now</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idnow.2022.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35063702</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8767912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Selvaskandan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nimmo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Savino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Burnout and long COVID among the UK nephrology workforce: results from a national survey investigating the impact of COVID-19 on working lives</article-title>. <source>Clin Kidney J</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ckj/sfab264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35198158</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8754810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Stufano</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Isgrò</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palese</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Oxidative damage and post-COVID syndrome: a cross-sectional study in a cohort of Italian workers</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>7445</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms24087445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37108606</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10139201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tempany</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The potential impact of post-COVID symptoms in the healthcare sector</article-title>. <source>Occup Med (Lond).</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/occmed/kqab109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34415352</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Mudgal</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rulaniya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Pooled prevalence of Long COVID-19 symptoms at 12 months and above follow-up period: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Cureus</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e36325</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.36325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37077615</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10108372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Chowdhury</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Payal</surname><given-names>AR.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Healthy worker effect phenomenon: revisited with emphasis on statistical methods – a review</article-title>. <source>Indian J Occup Environ Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijoem.IJOEM_53_16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29391741</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5763838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Raveendran</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jayadevan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sashidharan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Long COVID: an overview</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Metab Syndr</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>875</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2021.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33892403</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8056514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Torrance</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacIver</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Lived experience of work and long COVID in healthcare staff</article-title>. <source>Occup Med (Oxf)</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/occmed/kqad117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10875925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38071754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Robles-Villagómez</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Díaz-Castro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vázquez-Guzmán</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of anxiety, depression, and post-traumatic stress in military health personnel in training exposed to COVID-19</article-title>. <source>JoGHNP</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.52872/001c.57742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Cherry</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krogstad</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>SARS the first pandemic of the 21st century</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1203/01.PDR.0000129184.87042.FC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15152053</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7086556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ngai</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>To</surname><given-names>K-W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>DS.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The long-term impact of severe acute respiratory syndrome on pulmonary function, exercise capacity and health status</article-title>. <source>Respirology</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2010.01720.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20337995</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7192220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Maunder</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lancee</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Balderson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Long-term psychological and occupational effects of providing hospital healthcare during SARS Outbreak</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1924</fpage>–<lpage>1932</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1212.060584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17326946</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3291360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Multiomic characterisation of the long-term sequelae of SARS survivors: a clinical observational study</article-title>. <source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>101884</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.101884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36873427</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9969173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>O’Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Long-term sequelae following previous coronavirus epidemics</article-title>. <source>Clin Med (Lond)</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>e68</fpage>–<lpage>e70</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7861/clinmed.2020-0204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33144403</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7850177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Depression as a mediator of chronic fatigue and post-traumatic stress symptoms in middle east respiratory syndrome survivors</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Investig</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30773/pi.2018.10.22.3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6354037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30605995</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Batawi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tarazan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Raddadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Quality of life reported by survivors after hospitalization for Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS)</article-title>. <source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12955-019-1165-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31186042</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6560892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MS.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Assessing the presence of post-traumatic stress and turnover intention among nurses post-middle east respiratory syndrome outbreak: the importance of supervisor support</article-title>. <source>Workplace Health Saf</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2165079919897693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32146875</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7201205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gilbody</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eastwood</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The causes, consequences and detection of publication bias in psychiatry</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>. doi: https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0447.2000.102004241.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11089723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>