<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">658</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jkms</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12865211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12865211.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12865211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12865211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41633328</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2026.41.e54</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="subheading"><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of Post-Acute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 (PASC) Index and a Recent Long COVID Criteria in Korean Long COVID-19 Cohort</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2954-3888</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names initials="K">Kyungsup</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3773-3297</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names initials="CY">Choi Young</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0006-4705-0576</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="W">Woori</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-8018-7036</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names initials="J">JuYeon</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7417-0318</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names initials="E">Euijin</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6596-8253</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="SH">Sung-Han</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">Department of Infectious Diseases, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Address for Correspondence: Sung-Han Kim, MD, PhD, FIDSA. Department of Infectious Diseases, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, 88 Olympic-ro-43-gil, Songpa-gu, Seoul 05505, Korea. <email>kimsunghanmd@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>02</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>41</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">506750</issue-id><elocation-id>e54</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-05 10:25:13.217"><day>05</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2026 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>To compare the post-acute sequelae of severe acute respiratory syndrome-coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection (PASC) index and the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM) criteria in identifying long coronavirus disease (COVID) among adults with confirmed coronavirus disease 2019.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A prospective cohort study was conducted from November 2022 to February 2025 at a single tertiary care hospital in Seoul, Korea. Adults aged 18 years or older with confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection were enrolled, yielding a total of 183 participants. Follow-up assessments took place at 1-, 3-, 6-, and 12-months post-infection. The primary outcome was the prevalence of long COVID at 12 months, measured using the PASC index (≥ 12 points across specified symptoms) and the NASEM criteria (≥ 1 symptom persisting for at least 3 months).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Of 183 participants, 26.2% (48/183) met the PASC index, whereas 47.5% (87/183) fulfilled the NASEM criteria. Of the 48 patients who met the PASC index, 44 (91.7%) also met the NASEM criteria.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The NASEM criteria classified nearly half of participants with long COVID and covered those with PASC index, while the PASC index identified about one quarter. Although the NASEM criteria capture a broader range of persistent symptoms, the PASC index may offer a more stringent threshold, potentially informing targeted research and clinical decision-making.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><p>
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-abf001.jpg"/>
</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Post-Acute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 (PASC) Index</kwd><kwd>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM) Criteria</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source country="KR">
<institution-wrap><institution>Korea Health Industry Development Institute</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="CrossRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100003710</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>HD22C2045</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>According to a report by the WHO, over 700 million people have been infected with the virus since the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Despite the global decline in COVID-19 infections, the disease continues to exert long-term effects on healthcare systems.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> One such long-term effect is “long COVID,” also referred to as post-acute sequelae of severe acute respiratory syndrome-coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection (PASC) or post-COVID conditions.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> This condition affects more than 400 million individuals worldwide and places a substantial burden on both healthcare resources and society.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Nonetheless, its clinical manifestations remain highly heterogeneous and multifaceted, leaving the underlying pathophysiological mechanisms, largely unexplained.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p>The complexity of long COVID is evident in the use of multiple terms and definitions.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Without a gold-standard definition, establishing consistent diagnostic and classification criteria becomes challenging, which in some cases has led to dismissing symptoms.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Such skepticism and delayed recognition of the condition have inevitably impeded research progress.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Compounding this issue, many studies investigating long COVID adopt their own definitions, complicating efforts to develop unified diagnostic criteria or identify reliable biomarkers and therapeutic agents.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> In response, the National Institutes of Health’s Researching COVID to Enhance Recovery (RECOVER) initiative introduced the PASC index, and the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM) also published a novel criteria of long COVID.<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The PASC index was the first scoring system developed to objectively assess long COVID, but it does not account for symptom duration and may be ambiguous for patients whose scores fall just below the diagnostic threshold. The NASEM criteria diagnose long COVID based on the persistence of symptoms for at least three months without requiring diagnostic confirmation of COVID-19 infection and has been adopted by the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention for public health policy purposes.<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Although this definition is broad and inclusive, this broad nature has been reported to limit clinical acceptance among clinicians.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Both approaches have their advantages and limitations, comparative clinical data remain limited.</p><p>Therefore, the present study aimed to classify long COVID cases using both the PASC index and the NASEM criteria, and to assess the clinical profiles associated with each method.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>Study design and population</title><p>This prospective cohort study was conducted at a single tertiary care hospital in Seoul, Korea, from November 2022 to February 2025. Adults (≥ 18 years of age) with COVID-19 confirmed via rapid antigen testing or polymerase chain reaction were eligible for enrollment. Participants were recruited through in-hospital and community advertisements, as well as from outpatient clinics and inpatient wards, following informed consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Data collection and follow-up</title><p>The study protocol included follow-up visits at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months post-acute COVID-19 infection. At each visit, participants underwent clinical evaluations and completed surveys assessing long COVID symptoms. While clinical assessments were conducted in-person, surveys were administered online. At the baseline visit, participants provided demographic information through a questionnaire, including age, sex, vaccination history, number of COVID-19 episodes, and body mass index. Additional information on comorbidities, such as smoking status, chronic lung diseases (asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease), diabetes mellitus, chronic liver disease, and other medical history were obtained through a review of electronic medical records.</p><p>In May 2023, the RECOVER Initiative introduced criteria for the PASC index. Consequently, from July 2023 onwards, an additional questionnaire for PASC index calculation was incorporated into the study protocol. To compensate for the lack of PASC index data for participants enrolled before July 2023, the study also recruited individuals who were in the post-acute phase of COVID-19 (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Study flow diagram of long COVID assessment in a prospective cohort.</title><p>NASEM = National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, PASC = post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection, COVID = coronavirus disease.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Outcomes and definitions</title><p>The primary outcomes of this study were the prevalence of long COVID at 12 months post-infection, assessed using two distinct definitions: the PASC index and the NASEM criteria (<xref rid="S1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="S2" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>). The PASC index, developed as part of the RECOVER Initiative, classifies long COVID based on a symptom score. Participants with a score of 12 or higher across 12 specific symptoms one month after infection were considered to have long COVID according to this definition. The NASEM criteria, in contrast, define long COVID as the presence of at least one common symptom or diagnosable condition persisting intermittently or continuously for three months or longer. For this study, we focused solely on symptoms, excluding diagnosable conditions to maintain consistency with the symptom-based PASC index. To establish symptom persistence, we applied the NASEM long COVID classification when identical symptoms were reported at a minimum of two time points among the one-, three-, six-, and twelve-month assessments. Cases meeting the criteria only at the one- and twelve-month points were excluded to ensure a more robust definition of persistence (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For continuous variables, data were summarized as the median and interquartile range, whereas categorical variables were described using counts and percentages. To compare groups, independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests, Mann-Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> tests, or χ<sup>2</sup> tests were applied, as appropriate. To investigate risk factors for long COVID as defined by each criterion, we conducted a comprehensive statistical analysis. Variables demonstrating statistical significance in univariate analyses, along with those previously identified as risk factors in the literature, were incorporated into multivariate logistic regression models. The final model was refined using a backward stepwise selection process. We assessed the robustness of the final model using the Hosmer-Lemeshow goodness-of-fit test. Potential multicollinearity among predictor variables was examined using the variance inflation factor. Statistical significance was defined as a two-tailed <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value below 0.05. As a sensitivity analysis, we evaluated a complete-case cohort of participants who completed all four follow-up visits at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months (n = 39). In this subgroup, we described the proportions of long COVID according to the NASEM criteria and PASC index definitions and compared these findings with those of the primary analysis to assess robustness. Analyses were conducted using RStudio (version 4.4.1).</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB) of Asan Medical Center (IRB No. 2022–1477). Written informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Clinical characteristics of study participants</title><p>A total of 183 participants were enrolled in this cohort study. As summarized in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, the median age of the cohort was 48.0 years, and 38.3% of the participants were male. At initial presentation, 38.5% required hospitalization. 80.8% of the participants had completed full vaccination.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Baseline and clinical characteristics of participants in the study</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-i001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="3.54%" span="1"/><col width="56.93%" span="1"/><col width="39.53%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Characteristics</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Involved participants (N = 183)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Age, yr, median (IQR)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">48.0 (34.5–62.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Male gender</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">70 (38.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Body mass index, kg/m<sup>2</sup>, median (IQR)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">22.0 (20.1–24.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">No. of COVID-19 episodes<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">144 (79.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">35 (19.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2 (1.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Vaccination status for COVID-19<sup>b,c</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Fully vaccinated</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">13 (7.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Partially vaccinated</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">22 (12.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Unvaccinated</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">147 (80.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Smoking<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Non-smoker</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">138 (75.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Smoker</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">44 (24.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Charlson comorbidity index, median (IQR)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.0 (0.0–4.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Underlying disease<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">89 (48.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">COPD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">6 (3.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Asthma</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">4 (2.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">37 (20.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">CKD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">27 (14.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Chronic liver diseases</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">5 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Solid tumor</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">24 (13.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Hematologic malignancy</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">9 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Hematopoietic stem cell transplant</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">4 (2.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Solid organ transplant</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">29 (15.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Mental health problems</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">6 (3.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Immunosuppressant<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">29 (15.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Hospitalization for COVID-19<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">70 (38.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Hospital treatment<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Oxygen therapy</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">41 (22.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Steroid</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">44 (24.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Remdesivir</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">71 (39.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Tocilizumab</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">10 (5.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Baricitinib</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9 (4.9)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as number (%) of patients, unless otherwise indicated.</p><p>IQR = Interquartile range, COVID-19 = coronavirus disease 2019, COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, CKD = chronic kidney disease.</p><p><sup>a</sup>Data were missing for 2 patients.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Data were missing for 1 patient.</p><p><sup>c</sup>Definition of vaccination: unvaccinated (0 doses), partially vaccinated (1–2 doses), and fully vaccinated (≥ 3 doses).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>During the follow-up period, response rates were recorded at time points as follows: at 1 month, 63 of 183 participants (34.4%); at 3 months, 90 of 183 (49.2%); at 6 months, 106 of 183 (57.9%); and at 12 months, 154 of 183 (84.2%). When classified according to the PASC index and the NASEM criteria, 48 participants (26.2%) met the PASC index, while 87 (47.5%) fulfilled the NASEM criteria. Among these, 44 participants satisfied both criteria (<xref rid="S5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). Among the four individuals who were diagnosed with long COVID based only on the PASC index, three were lost to follow-up and one died.</p></sec><sec><title>Factors associated with the PASC index and NASEM criteria</title><p>A comparison of baseline characteristics according to the PASC index and NASEM criteria is summarized in <xref rid="S3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 3</xref> and <xref rid="S4" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref>. The results of the univariate analysis and the multivariate findings are summarized in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. In the multivariable analysis, when long COVID was defined according to the PASC index, the only significant risk factor for long COVID was age (adjusted odds ratio [aOR], 1.08; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.05–1.12; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Univariate and multivariate analysis of long COVID based on the PASC index</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-i002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="1.97%" span="1"/><col width="20.85%" span="1"/><col width="12.97%" span="1"/><col width="12.97%" span="1"/><col width="12.97%" span="1"/><col width="14.61%" span="1"/><col width="11.82%" span="1"/><col width="11.82%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="2" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Variables</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Univariate analysis</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Multivariate analysis</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Odds ratio</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">95% CI</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Adjusted odds ratio</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">95% CI</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Age</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.09</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.06–1.13</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.08</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.05–1.12</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Sex, male</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">3.75</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.89–7.62</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Vaccination status</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Unvaccinated</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.00</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.00</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Partially vaccinated</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.25</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.04–1.27</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.103</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.16</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.02–1.12</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.074</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Fully vaccinated or boosted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.59</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.19–2.05</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.377</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.58</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.13–2.62</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.469</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Smoking</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2.55</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.23–5.29</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.011<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Charlson comorbidity index</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.54</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.33–1.82</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Body mass index</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.99</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.91–1.01</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.615</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Asthma</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9.00</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.09–185.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.059</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">COPD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">15.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2.45–306.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.013<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">6.14</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.80–128.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.123</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3.97</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.84–8.64</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">CKD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">3.25</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.39–7.62</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.006</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Solid organ transplant</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.21–6.39</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.014<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.38</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.90–6.40</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.081</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Immunosuppressant</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2.34</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.00–5.35</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.049<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Hospitalization for COVID-19</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4.67</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.33–9.69</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Oxygen use</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2.57</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.22–5.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.012<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Steroid use</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.93</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.41–6.08</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.004<sup>**</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Remdesivir use</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">4.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2.25–9.33</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>COVID-19 = coronavirus disease 2019, PASC = post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection, CI = confidence interval, COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, CKD = chronic kidney disease.</p><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Univariate and multivariate analysis of long COVID based on the NASEM criteria</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-i003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="1.9%" span="1"/><col width="23.3%" span="1"/><col width="13.15%" span="1"/><col width="13.15%" span="1"/><col width="12.04%" span="1"/><col width="14.9%" span="1"/><col width="9.51%" span="1"/><col width="12.04%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="2" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Variables</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Univariate analysis</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Multivariate analysis</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Odds ratio</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">95% CI</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Adjusted odds ratio</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">95% CI</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Age</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.03</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.01–1.05</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.004<sup>**</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.04</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.02–1.07</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Sex, male</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.04</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.57–1.90</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.898</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.52</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.23–1.13</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">No. of COVID-19 episodes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.20</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.11–4.58</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.028<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3.19</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.54–7.00</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.003<sup>**</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Vaccination status</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Unvaccinated</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.00</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Partially vaccinated</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.17</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.29–4.73</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.826</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Fully vaccinated or boosted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.03</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.33–3.34</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.959</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Charlson comorbidity index</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.25</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.11–1.43</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Body mass index</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.99</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.93–1.01</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.475</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.72</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.28–6.03</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.01<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">CKD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">3.87</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.61–10.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.004<sup>**</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">4.14</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.62–11.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.004<sup>**</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Solid organ transplant</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.94</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.29–7.19</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.013<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Immunosuppressant</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2.94</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.29–7.19</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.013<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Hospitalization for COVID-19</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.85</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.54–5.57</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Steroid use</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2.43</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.21–4.98</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.013<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Remdesivir use</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.70</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.47–5.05</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.002<sup>**</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>COVID = coronavirus disease, NASEM = National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, CI = confidence interval, COVID-19 = coronavirus disease 2019, CKD = chronic kidney disease.</p><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Using the NASEM criteria to define long COVID, significant risk factors for long COVID were identified as age (aOR, 1.04; 95% CI, 1.02–1.07; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), the number of COVID-19 episodes (aOR, 3.19; 95% CI, 1.55–7.00; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003), and chronic kidney disease (CKD; aOR, 4.14; 95% CI, 1.62–11.7; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004).</p></sec><sec><title>Long COVID-defined symptom frequency over time</title><p>A summary of symptom frequency at each time point, based on two definitions of long COVID, was presented (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Participants with the PASC index (≥ 12) most commonly reported brain fog, fatigue, and thirst, with frequency ranging from 16% to 30%. A similar pattern was observed in the non-PASC group. However, alterations in smell or taste and post-exertional malaise were observed in fewer than 2% of non-PASC participants. In the NASEM-defined group, brain fog, fatigue, and headache were the most frequent symptoms, with frequency ranging from 17% to 48% across the assessed time points.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Temporal symptom distributions by PASC index and NASEM criteria. Each cell in the heatmap represents the frequency (%) at the corresponding time point. The shading in each column reflects the frequency, ranging from 0% up to 50%.</title><p>PASC = post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection, GI = gastrointestinal, NASEM = National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sensitivity analysis</title><p>Among the 39 complete responders, 31 (79.5%) met the NASEM criteria and 14 (35.9%) met the PASC index. All participants classified as PASC-positive were also NASEM-positive, resulting in 17 participants (43.6%) classified exclusively by the NASEM criteria and none classified exclusively by the PASC index.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this prospective study, we enrolled patients and monitored their symptoms to compare two recently proposed definitions of long COVID. The findings demonstrated that nearly half of the participants were classified under the NASEM criteria, while around one quarter fell into the PASC index. Most individuals who met the PASC index also satisfied the NASEM criteria. Thus, although the NASEM criteria reflects a duration of at least three months, it remains broader and more inclusive in scope. Furthermore, Bello-Chavolla et al.<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> previously reported that the PASC index ≥ 12 represents a severe phenotype of long COVID. These findings suggest that patients presenting with multiple symptoms meeting the PASC index threshold after COVID-19 infection are likely to experience persistent and clinically significant manifestations. Therefore, a high PASC index score may serve as an early indicator of severe long COVID, warranting close clinical monitoring, particularly in the absence of long-term follow-up.</p><p>Previous studies have reported that the prevalence of long COVID among individuals diagnosed with COVID-19 varies considerably, ranging from approximately 7% to 50%.<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Such discrepancies are thought to stem from differing definitions of long COVID used across various investigations.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In the RECOVER cohort study, Thaweethai et al.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> described that 23% of COVID infected individuals met the PASC index, aligning with the present study.</p><p>In the present study, participants with a PASC index of 12 or higher exhibited a persistent prevalence of symptoms such as brain fog and fatigue over time (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Notably, these symptoms remained significantly higher in subjects not classified by the PASC index, which is the opposite of the NASEM classification. Given that these symptoms are a key feature of long COVID, this suggests that some patients below the PASC index threshold persist with symptoms that would be classified as long COVID and would be diagnosed with long COVID if the NASEM criteria were applied.<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> When the PASC index falls below a certain threshold but symptoms are present (PASC index 1-11), it does not adequately capture these persistent symptoms. This suggests that the NASEM criteria, which includes such cases, may provide a more inclusive and clinical framework for diagnosing long COVID. However, given that the PASC index ≥ 12 is predominantly incorporated into the NASEM criteria and the PASC index is a metric that limits the probability of exceeding the threshold to approximately 5% in uninfected individuals, it possesses the capacity to mitigate false positives in individuals who align with the NASEM definition.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Therefore, by providing an objective and granular set of criteria, the PASC index is expected to greatly facilitate future research on long COVID.</p><p>According to the multivariable regression analyses of long COVID risk factors, older age was identified as an independent risk factor in both models, and the number of COVID-19 episodes emerged as an independent risk factor based on the NASEM criteria of long COVID. Previous studies have consistently shown that older age and repeated COVID-19 infection increase the risk of long COVID, whereas the role of CKD remains controversial.<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> In the present cohort, 19 patients with CKD (66.7%) had undergone solid organ transplantation and were receiving immunosuppressive therapy (data not shown). Because previous research has suggested that immunosuppressed status is a risk factor for long COVID, we presume that this underlying immunosuppression may have contributed to CKD being identified as an independent risk factor in our study.<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Moreover, repeated COVID-19 infection was identified as a significant factor only according to the NASEM criteria of long COVID. This finding suggests that repeated infection may contribute to the persistence of long COVID, underscoring the importance of strategies aimed at preventing reinfection to reduce the burden of long COVID.</p><p>Our study has several limitations. First, although this study employed a prospective design, the sample size was relatively small and was not a multicenter study, and the response rate at the 1-month follow-up was especially low. Such limited data may restrict the validity of the findings. However, to address potential bias arising from incomplete follow-up, we conducted a sensitivity analysis restricted to participants who completed all four follow-up visits. The distribution of long COVID definitions in this complete-case cohort closely mirrored that observed in the full cohort, supporting the robustness of our findings despite the limited response rate at early follow-up. Second, because the study was performed in a single tertiary care center primarily treating patients with severe acute illness, the proportion of hospitalized cases was relatively high, potentially limiting the generalizability of our findings. Third, the study results were limited to assessments at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months, and the NASEM criteria of “symptom persistence for three months or more” was applied solely by checking whether the same symptom was present at two distinct time points. Potential fluctuations in symptoms between these intervals may not have been fully captured. Therefore, there is a risk that symptom severity and duration may have been either under- or overestimated. Fourth, for comparison with the PASC index, we excluded all diagnosable conditions based on the NASEM criteria and did not include individuals who were never diagnosed with COVID-19. To address these limitations, further large-scale prospective studies following both infected and uninfected populations are needed. Lastly, the PASC index was updated in 2024.<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Although the report indicated that the original index and its refined version are largely consistent, there may still be subtle differences that represent a potential limitation of this study.</p><p>In conclusion, this study compared two updated definitions of long COVID within a prospective cohort. According to the PASC index, 26% of participants were identified as having long COVID, whereas the NASEM criteria identified 48%. Notably, the NASEM criteria largely encompassed those classified by the PASC index. While the broader scope of the NASEM criteria may capture more individuals with long COVID, the PASC index offers a more specific metric that can provide researchers with clearer insights.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work is conducted as part of the Korea Health Technology Research and Development Project through the Korea Health Industry Development Institute (KHIDI), which is funded by the National Institute of Infectious Diseases, National Institute of Health, Republic of Korea (grant No. HD22C2045).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Disclosure:</bold> The authors have no potential conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Kim SH.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Kwon K, Jang CY, Kim W, Son J.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> .</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Kwon K Funding acquisition:</bold> Kim SH.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Kwon K, Jang CY, Kim W, Son J.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Kwon K, Kim SH.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Resources:</bold> Kim SH.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Kim SH, Chang E.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing - original draft:</bold> Kwon K.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing - review &amp; editing:</bold> Kwon K, Chang E, Kim SH.</p></list-item></list>
</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><source>WHO COVID-19 dashboard</source><date-in-citation content-type="updated">Updated 2025</date-in-citation><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed February 24, 2025</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alwan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luyckx</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID: long-term health outcomes and implications for policy and research</article-title><source>Nat Rev Nephrol</source><year>2023</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36319780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41581-022-00652-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9628426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>The long-term health outcomes, pathophysiological mechanisms and multidisciplinary management of long COVID</article-title><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>416</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37907497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41392-023-01640-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10618229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soh</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID-19 and health-related quality of life of mild cases in Korea: 3-months follow-up of a single community treatment center</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><issue>46</issue><elocation-id>e326</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36631024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3346/jkms.2022.37.e326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9705205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mateu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tebe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loste</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lladós</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>López</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Determinants of the onset and prognosis of the post-COVID-19 condition: a 2-year prospective observational cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Eur</source><year>2023</year><volume>33</volume><elocation-id>100724</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37954002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lanepe.2023.100724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10636281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wulf-Hanson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID science, research and policy</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>30</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2148</fpage><lpage>2164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39122965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-024-03173-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grafton</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kompas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Honeyman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Notaras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>The public health and economic burden of long COVID in Australia, 2022–24: a modelling study</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2024</year><volume>221</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39154292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5694/mja2.52400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Erlandson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaggi</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thaweethai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Differentiation of prior SARS-CoV-2 infection and postacute sequelae by standard clinical laboratory measurements in the RECOVER cohort</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>177</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1209</fpage><lpage>1221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39133923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M24-0737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11408082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Manachevakul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Biomarkers in long COVID-19: a systematic review</article-title><source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>1085988</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36744129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2023.1085988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9895110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Solving the puzzle of long covid</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2024</year><volume>383</volume><issue>6685</issue><fpage>830</fpage><lpage>832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38386747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.adl0867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abedian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Verzani</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karlson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Long-COVID incidence proportion in adults and children between 2020 and 2024</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2025</year><volume>80</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1247</fpage><lpage>1261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39907495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cid/ciaf046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12272849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Au</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Capotescu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eyal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Finestone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Long covid and medical gaslighting: dismissal, delayed diagnosis, and deferred treatment</article-title><source>SSM Qual Res Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>100167</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36092770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ssmqr.2022.100167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9448633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sivan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perlowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolich</surname><given-names>JŽ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID: a clinical update</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2024</year><volume>404</volume><issue>10453</issue><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39096925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01136-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamlin</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blish</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Challenges and opportunities in long COVID research</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2024</year><volume>57</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38865966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.immuni.2024.05.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11210969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The definition of long COVID used in interventional studies</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Invest</source><year>2023</year><volume>53</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e13989</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36964995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/eci.13989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of long COVID and the path toward therapeutics</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2024</year><volume>187</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>5500</fpage><lpage>5529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39326415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2024.07.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11455603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Selph</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID definitions and models of care</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>177</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38768458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M24-0677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ely</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fineberg</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name>
</person-group><collab>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine Committee on Examining the Working Definition for Long Covid</collab><article-title>Long covid defined</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>391</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>1746</fpage><lpage>1753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39083764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsb2408466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thaweethai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karlson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levitan</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McComsey</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Development of a definition of postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2023</year><volume>329</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>1934</fpage><lpage>1946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37278994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2023.8823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10214179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bishof</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dumes</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wesley Ely</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Troxel</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>The 2024 National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine long COVID definition: what clinicians need to know</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2025</year><volume>40</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2024</fpage><lpage>2027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40063321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-025-09415-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12325811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stave</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Long-term health effects of COVID-19 disability and function following SARS-CoV-2 infection and a long COVID definition: a chronic, systemic disease state with profound consequences</article-title><source>J Occup Environ Med</source><year>2025</year><volume>67</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e195</fpage><lpage>e196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39639510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/JOM.0000000000003288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bello-Chavolla</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fermín-Martínez</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ramírez-García</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vargas-Vázquez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Chirino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Basile-Alvarez</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence and determinants of post-acute sequelae after SARS-CoV-2 infection (long COVID) among adults in Mexico during 2022: a retrospective analysis of nationally representative data</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Am</source><year>2024</year><volume>30</volume><elocation-id>100688</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38327277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lana.2024.100688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10847769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pazukhina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spiridonova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bobkova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shikhaleva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>El-Taravi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of post-COVID-19 condition in adults and children at 6 and 12 months after hospital discharge: a prospective, cohort study in Moscow (StopCOVID)</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>244</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35794549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12916-022-02448-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9257572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perlis</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santillana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ognyanova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Safarpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lunz Trujillo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simonson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence and correlates of long COVID symptoms among US adults</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e2238804</fpage><lpage>e2238804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36301542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.38804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9614581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vahratian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saydah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bertolli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence of post-COVID-19 condition and activity-limiting post-COVID-19 condition among adults</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e2451151</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39671200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.51151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11645641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taquet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dercon</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luciano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geddes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Incidence, co-occurrence, and evolution of long-COVID features: a 6-month retrospective cohort study of 273,618 survivors of COVID-19</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e1003773</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34582441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8478214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrnsbrak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rekito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Evidence mounts that about 7% of US adults have had long COVID</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2024</year><volume>332</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38848092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2024.11370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sargent</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>ZUA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tharmaratnam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dunai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egbe</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Posthospitalization COVID-19 cognitive deficits at 1 year are global and associated with elevated brain injury markers and gray matter volume reduction</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2025</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39312956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-024-03309-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11750706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guttuso</surname><given-names>T</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilding</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Lithium aspartate for long COVID fatigue and cognitive dysfunction: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e2436874</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39356507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.36874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11447566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Babalola</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clouston</surname><given-names>SAP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sekendiz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soriolo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kawuki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>SARS-COV-2 re-infection and incidence of post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC) among essential workers in New York: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Am</source><year>2025</year><volume>42</volume><elocation-id>100984</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39866362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lana.2024.100984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11764319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bouwmans</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malahe</surname><given-names>SRK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Messchendorp</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Post COVID-19 condition imposes significant burden in patients with advanced chronic kidney disease: a nested case-control study</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>142</volume><elocation-id>106990</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38428480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijid.2024.106990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tsampasian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elghazaly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Debski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Naing</surname><given-names>TKP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with post-COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>183</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10037203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Erlandson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hornig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Letts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaggi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ashktorab</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>2024 update of the RECOVER-adult long COVID research index</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2025</year><volume>333</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39693079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2024.24184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11862971</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</title><supplementary-material id="S1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 1</title><p>The survey questions and a scoring system consisting of the post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection (PASC) index</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-s001.doc" id="d67e2367" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 2</title><p>The survey questions and common symptoms consisting of the NASEM criteria of long COVID</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-s002.doc" id="d67e2372" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 3</title><p>Baseline and clinical characteristics of participants according to NASEM criteria</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-s003.doc" id="d67e2377" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S4" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 4</title><p>Baseline and clinical characteristics of participants according to PASC index</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-s004.doc" id="d67e2382" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S5" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Fig. 1</title><p>Venn diagram illustrating overlap between the PASC index and NASEM criteria.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-41-e54-s005.doc" id="d67e2387" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>