<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Bioeng Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Bioeng Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2507</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontbb</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Bioengineering and Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-4185</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12256466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12256466.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12256466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12256466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40661336</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fbioe.2025.1604447</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1604447</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Bioengineering and Biotechnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Low-intensity ultrasound lysis of amyloid microclots in a lab-on-chip model</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Rasouli et al.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fbioe.2025.1604447" ext-link-type="uri">10.3389/fbioe.2025.1604447</ext-link>
</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasouli</surname><given-names initials="R">Reza</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/3022088/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names initials="B">Brad</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/3081677/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/Writing - review &amp; editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konecky</surname><given-names initials="SD">Soren D.</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2968702/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/Writing - review &amp; editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff>
<institution>Openwater</institution>, <addr-line>San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line>CA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>
<bold>Edited by:</bold>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/965903/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Pablo Taboada</ext-link>, University of Santiago de Compostela, Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>
<bold>Reviewed by:</bold>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1811804/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Feng Shen</ext-link>, Beijing University of Technology, China</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1991399/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Abraham Samuel Finny</ext-link>, Waters Corporation, United States</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2771546/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Antonio Topete</ext-link>, University of Guadalajara, Mexico</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Reza Rasouli, <email>reza@openwater.cc</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480748</issue-id><elocation-id>1604447</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-15 09:25:43.203"><day>15</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025 Rasouli, Hartl and Konecky.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Rasouli, Hartl and Konecky</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fbioe-13-1604447.pdf"/><abstract><p>Amyloid fibrin(ogen) microclots are misfolded protein aggregates with β-sheet structures that have been associated with Long COVID and numerous thrombo-inflammatory diseases. These microclots persist in circulation and obstruct microvasculature, impair oxygen transport and promote chronic inflammation. Conventional thrombolytic therapies such as recombinant tissue plasminogen activator (rtPA) show limited efficacy against these microclots due to their structure and composition. In this study, we assess the impact of low intensity focused ultrasound (LIFU) stimulation on amyloid microclot fragmentation, the role of cavitation in this process and investigate whether microbubble-assisted ultrasound can enhance their lysis. Amyloid microclot models were generated using freeze-thaw cycles followed by incubation. Microclots were exposed to ultrasound waves at 150, 300, 500 kHz, and 1 MHz under four conditions: ultrasound alone (US), ultrasound with microbubbles (MB + US), ultrasound with rtPA (rtPA + US), and ultrasound with both microbubbles and rtPA (MB + rtPA + US). Low-frequency ultrasound at 150 kHz resulted in a significant clot lysis with up to three-fold reduction in both clot size and the number of large clots. The addition of microbubbles enhanced clot lysis at 150, 300, and 500 kHz. These findings suggest that ultrasound, particularly at 150 kHz is a promising method for amyloid microclot lysis. The combination of ultrasound with microbubbles and rtPA further improved clot fragmentation, rendering it a potential therapeutic tool for conditions like Long COVID.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>microclots</kwd><kwd>ultrasound</kwd><kwd>fibrinolysis</kwd><kwd>long COVID</kwd><kwd>lab on a chip</kwd><kwd>LIFU</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Tissue Engineering and Regenerative Medicine</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>1 Introduction</title><p>Protein misfolding into abnormal amyloid microclots is a defining hallmark of a wide array of human disorders, known as amyloidoses (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Almeida and Brito, 2020</xref>). Over 50 diseases, including neurodegenerative conditions (e.g., Alzheimer’s, Parkinson’s, Huntington’s diseases), metabolic/endocrine diseases (e.g., Type II diabetes), and systemic amyloidoses (e.g., light-chain amyloidosis), are characterized by pathological amyloid accumulation (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Almeida and Brito, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Rambaran and Serpell, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Kell et al., 2025</xref>).</p><p>In these disorders, soluble proteins misfold and aggregate into insoluble fibrillar microclots where they lead to disruption of tissue architecture and function. These protein aggregates not only can interfere with cellular processes but also lead into disease progression through inducing chronic inflammation and oxidative stress (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Almeida and Brito, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Rambaran and Serpell, 2008</xref>). Although the composition of amyloid microclots varies in different biological conditions, their common structural feature is the formation of ordered β-across-β architecture (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2023a</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Mai et al., 2024</xref>). The cross-β core increases the stability of amyloid fibrils, rendering them insoluble and proteolysis-resistant (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Rambaran and Serpell, 2008</xref>).</p><p>Among amyloid-related pathologies, amyloid fibrin(ogen) microclots have recently gained attention due to their role in Long COVID (post-acute COVID-19 syndrome) and cardiovascular diseases. Recent studies have identified amyloid fibrin(ogen) microclots in the blood of patients with Long COVID (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2023a</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Kell et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Laubscher et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Kruger et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Pretorius et al., 2021</xref>). These amyloid microclots typically range in size from 1 to 200 μm, with a median diameter of approximately 15 µm (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Kell et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Sakharov et al., 2000</xref>). Due to their size, microclots can circulate within the bloodstream and obstruct the microvasculature, disrupting perfusion and impairing oxygen delivery to tissues. As a result, these microclots have been detected as a central pathological factor which are associated with persistent symptoms such as fatigue, breathlessness, and cognitive dysfunction. Further coagulation of such microclots can lead to hypoxia, chronic organ dysfunction and inflammation (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Pretorius et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2023b</xref>). Proteomic analyses showed that COVID-related microclots contain pro-inflammatory molecules and clotting factors that result in persistent inflammation and resistance to fibrinolysis (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Kruger et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>Current therapies for Long COVID focus primarily on enzymatic clot dissolution, where fibrinolytic enzymes such as rtPA act as a serine protease to convert plasminogen to plasmin and degrade fibrin networks. Although enzymatic therapies are effective against conventional thrombi, they struggle to address amyloid-rich microclots due to their structural resistance to enzymatic breakdown. This fibrinolysis resistance is further exacerbated in COVID-19 patients by upregulation of α-(2)-antiplasmin which inhibits plasmin activity and limits the effectiveness of rtPA (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Kell et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Sakharov et al., 2000</xref>). Clinical observations confirm this inefficiency, where COVID-19 patients often showed poor response to tPA-mediated thrombolysis (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Pretorius et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Another strategy to treat circulating microclots is filtration-based strategies to physically remove them from the bloodstream. Apheresis is reported for severe COVID patients (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Jaeger et al., 2022</xref>), in which blood is drawn from the patient, passes through an extracorporeal filter, and then returns to the body. However, extracorporeal methods are invasive, resource-intensive, and involve health risks such as bleeding and infection which limit their application to acute conditions or experimental settings. Given the pathological impact and therapy resistance of amyloid microclots, there is a clear need for innovative and non-invasive treatments that can effectively disrupt circulatory amyloid microclots in patients and restore microvascular function.</p><p>Ultrasound has a long and successful history of treating blood clots in clinical settings, both as a stand-alone therapy and in combination with fibrinolytic enzymes such as rtPA (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Školoudík et al., 2025</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Draxler et al., 2025</xref>). Addition of transcranial ultrasound exposure to IV tPA treatment significantly improved thrombolysis in a phase II trial for acute ischemic stroke, leading to early arterial recanalization and enhanced clinical recovery rates compared to tPA alone (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Tsivgoulis and Alexandrov, 2007</xref>). In deep vein thrombosis (DVT), ultrasound-assisted catheter thrombolysis outperformed enzymatic thrombolysis alone with high clot clearance and faster treatment (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Parikh et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>There is a strong theoretical and clinical basis for employing ultrasound to disrupt microclots (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Sakharov et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Rasouli et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Molina et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Ward et al., 2024</xref>). Ultrasound in the low-kilohertz to low-megahertz range can induce mechanical phenomena such as acoustic streaming, cavitation, shear forces, and radiation forces that can be used to promote clot fragmentation (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Rad et al., 2023</xref>). Acoustic streaming generates convective currents and shear stress around the thrombus, enhancing penetration and mixing of fibrinolytic agents into the clot (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Rasouli et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bader et al., 2014</xref>). Acoustic streaming and acoustic radiation force (ARF) can also physically erode clot structure by pushing fluid through the fibrin mesh, loosening pore spaces and increasing permeation of plasminogen activators into the thrombus (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Ward et al., 2024</xref>). This streaming action also exposes new fibrin binding sites to plasmin, enhancing enzymatic breakdown (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Ward et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p>Numerous <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, animal, and clinical studies report faster and more effective thrombolysis when ultrasound is applied alongside fibrinolytic drugs (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Ward et al., 2024</xref>). Unlike chemical thrombolysis which relies solely on biochemical mechanisms, ultrasound offers advantage by offering a mechanical mode of action that can help to overcome the fibrinolysis resistance of amyloid clots (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Ward et al., 2024</xref>). The combination of acoustic streaming and cavitation can physically disrupt and weaken the clot. Prior studies on clots have shown that ultrasound can significantly accelerate clot lysis by mechanical forces (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2022</xref>). For example, exposure to 1 MHz ultrasound at ∼2 W/cm<sup>2</sup> produced streaming with a shear rate on the order of 40 s<sup>−1</sup>, roughly doubling the enzymatic lysis rate <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Sakharov et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Acconcia et al., 2014</xref>). In microbubble-assisted sonothrombolysis, oscillating microbubbles create vigorous microstreaming and localized shear forces that significantly accelerate clot breakdown (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Molina et al., 2006</xref>). Experimental studies have visually confirmed these effects, showing that stable cavitation bubbles preferentially erode clots and correlate with faster lysis rates compared to enzymatic treatments (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Mai et al., 2024</xref>). Furthermore, microbubble-assisted sonothrombolysis facilitates cavitation to enhance clot lysis and significantly boost clot dissolution (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Molina et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>Despite significant progress in sonothrombolysis for large vascular clots, no reported studies have specifically explored ultrasound-mediated lysis of circulating amyloid microclots which are recognized as a key therapeutic target in Long COVID. Here, we hypothesize that applying ultrasound can effectively disrupt amyloid fibrin microclots <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> via acoustically induced streaming. To test this, we employed a LOC model that enables precise control over microclot exposure conditions, allowing systematic evaluation of the effects of frequency, shear stress, and microbubble presence on clot disruption. Our goal is to identify optimal ultrasound parameters for microclot fragmentation and lay the groundwork for noninvasive strategies to mitigate microvascular dysfunction and coagulopathies in amyloid-related pathologies such as Long COVID.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>2 Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>2.1 Materials</title><p>Porcine plasma was obtained from Innovative Research, Inc. (United States; No. IGPCPLANAC500ML) and stored at −20°C until use. Plasma aliquots (1 mL) were used for microclot formation. rtPA was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (MilliporeSigma, United States; No. T0831) and reconstituted according to the manufacturer’s protocol to achieve a final working concentration of 3 μg/mL. Thioflavin T (ThT) was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, United States; No. T3516). Vevo MicroMarker<sup>®</sup> contrast agents (FUJIFILM VisualSonics Corp., Japan; No. 11678) were used as exogenous microbubbles and were diluted in PBS buffer per manufacturer protocol.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>2.2 Amyloid microclot formation</title><p>Amyloid fibrin(ogen) microclots were generated by subjecting porcine plasma to repeated freeze-thaw cycles, followed by incubation at 37°C. Plasma aliquots (1 mL) underwent 12 freeze-thaw cycles, with each cycle consisting of freezing at −20°C and thawing at 37°C for 2 hours. The aliquots were diluted 1.5 x before the ultrasound treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>2.3 Lab on chip device fabrication</title><p>The LOC device was designed to replicate a 6 mm diameter popliteal vein, providing a controlled environment for targeted ultrasound exposure of amyloid microclots. The popliteal vein was selected due to its accessibility for transcutaneous ultrasound exposure rendering it a relevant site for potential clinical applications of ultrasound. The device molds were designed using Onshape (version 1.188, PTC Inc., United States) CAD software and fabricated via digital light processing (DLP) technology using a 285 D Printer (CADWorks3D, Canada). One side of the channel was made slightly flat (5.8 mm instead of a full 6 mm circle) to create a smooth surface for bonding the silicone layer. This made it easier to peel off the PDMS and allowed better imaging, while still keeping the overall shape close to that of a popliteal vein. After UV treatment, Momentive RTV615 silicone elastomer (RS Hughes, United States) was cast into the molds and cured following manufacturer-recommended conditions to form the microfluidic channels. The cured elastomer was then bonded onto a 20 µm silicone sheet (Gteek, United Kingdom) using plasma surface treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>2.4 Experimental setup</title><p>The schematic representation of the LOC platform, transducer arrangement, and acoustic bath setup is shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. The experimental setup consisted of a custom-designed and 3D printed acoustic water bath, which housed the LOC device, a piezoelectric transducer, and supporting components. The transducers were mounted at the bottom of the bath. The LOC chip was mounted on top of the water bath using a custom-designed holder, securing its position at the pre-measured focal plane of the ultrasound transducers to maintain consistent acoustic exposure across all experimental conditions.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>(A)</bold> Schematic of the experimental platform for ultrasound-mediated amyloid microclot lysis. The LOC platform is placed in an acoustic water bath and exposed to focused ultrasound at 150 kHz, 300, 500 kHz, and 1 MHz. A function generator controls the ultrasound frequency, and an amplifier amplifies the signal. <bold>(B)</bold> Zoomed-in view of the LOC channel, showing the interaction of ultrasound, microbubbles, and rtPA with microclots. Microbubbles undergo volumetric oscillations in response to acoustic pressure waves, generating streaming effect and shear stress to lyse microclots.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fbioe-13-1604447-g001.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Diagram illustrating the setup and process of microclot lysis using ultrasound (US) and microbubbles. Panel A shows equipment including a function generator, amplifier, water bath, and transducer targeting a chip with focal length. Panel B depicts the effects of US on amyloid microclots, microbubbles, and rtPA within a 6 mm PDMS chamber. With US off, components are static. With US on, microclots are disrupted. A graph represents microbubble oscillation under US, with pressure (p) against time (t).</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>A function generator (DG4162, Rigol Technologies Co., Ltd., China) controlled the ultrasound frequency generated continuous stepped pulse waveform, while an amplifier (Model 1040L, Electronics &amp; Innovation, Ltd., United States) regulated the voltage to the transducers. The bath was filled with degassed water as a coupling medium for ultrasound wave transmission while minimizing acoustic attenuation.</p><p>Experiments were conducted under static flow conditions in the LOC platform. Ultrasound was applied at four different frequencies: 150, 300, 500 kHz, 1 MHz. The mechanical index (MI) is defined as MI = <inline-formula id="inf1">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="m1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PNP</mml:mtext><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>√</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula> , where PNP is the measured peak negative pressure (MPa), and <italic toggle="yes">f</italic> is the ultrasound frequency (MHz). The MI was maintained at 0.3 for all the experiments by adjusting the ultrasound pressure accordingly for all frequencies which corresponds to PNP of 1 MHz = 0.30 MPa, 500 kHz = 0.21 MPa, 300 kHz = 0.16 MPa, and 150 kHz = 0.11 MPa. The thin silicone membrane at the base of the chip allows acoustic waves to enter the microfluidic chamber while minimizing attenuation. Inside the LOC channel, ultrasound waves interact with the plasma and amyloid microclots, generating acoustic streaming, cavitation, and shear forces. These interactions induce microstreaming and localized mechanical forces, which contribute to the mechanical fragmentation and potential enzymatic enhancement of clot lysis.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>2.5 Microscopy and image analysis</title><p>Thioflavin T was used as a fluorescent dye to stain amyloid fibrils. A stock solution of 30 mM Thioflavin T was prepared in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), pH 7.4. The solution was filtered using a 0.2 µm syringe filter to ensure clarity. Samples were incubated with Thioflavin T at final concentration of 30 μM room temperature for 30 min prior to imaging. Amyloid microclot lysis was evaluated based on clot count reduction and size reduction. The microclots morphology and count were monitored before and after ultrasound exposure, and changes in clot size were analyzed using fluorescence microscopy. This concentration was selected based on previously published studies demonstrating that 30 μM offers an optimal balance between signal intensity and minimal fluorescence quenching (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Mai et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Sakharov et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Xue et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Imaging was conducted using the Countstar BioTech Automated Cell Counter (Model IC1000), which uses epifluorescence microscopy with a fixed-focus optical system and a 5-megapixel CMOS camera. A ×10 objective lens was used to capture the fluorescent microclots, and a GFP filter was used for ThT-labeled samples. Image analysis was performed using segmentation and particle detection plugins in ImageJ software, which measured clot area and count. Equivalent circular diameter (D<sub>eq</sub>) was calculated from the measured area for each microclot and analyzed in a custom Python script.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>2.6 Statistical analysis</title><p>All statistical analyses were conducted using GraphPad Prism version 10.4.1. Group comparisons for clot count and average clot diameter were performed using one-way ANOVA. Sidak’s <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> multiple comparisons test was used to identify pairwise differences between groups. A p-value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p><p>Each experimental group included three biologically independent samples (n = 3), except for <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, where two replicates (n = 2) were analyzed. For each replicate, three non-overlapping microscopic fields of view were imaged. Every image contained thousands of individual microclots. Clot count and diameter were quantified using ImageJ version 2.16.0 with particle segmentation and custom Python scripts. Diameter was determined using effective diameter to estimate the equivalent size for irregular shapes. Data are reported as mean ± standard deviation (SD).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>(A)</bold> Schematic representation of amyloid microclot model formation using freeze-thaw cycles. <bold>(B)</bold> Fluorescence microscopy images of ThT-stained porcine plasma across freeze-thaw cycles. Scale bar is 200 µm. <bold>(C)</bold> Clot count quantification graph showing the increase in amyloid microclots over cycles.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fbioe-13-1604447-g002.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Diagram A illustrates a process involving 24-hour freezing at negative 20 degrees Celsius followed by 2-hour thawing at 37 degrees Celsius, with repetition. Panel B shows six images of clots under a microscope during cycles 7 to 12, each with increasing density. Graph C displays a line chart indicating a increase in clot counts from cycles 6 to 12.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results|discussion" id="s3"><title>3 Results and discussion</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>3.1 Amyloid microclot model formation</title><p>Development of a reproducible amyloid fibrin microclot model is essential for investigating their role in clinical disorders including Long COVID, Alzheimer’s, type 2 diabetes (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Kell et al., 2025</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2023a</xref>). Various <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> methods have been reported to produce amyloid microclots including drying, heating, exposure to acidic pH, hydrophobic surfaces, and organic solvents (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Mai et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we used the freeze-thaw method and incubation at biological temperature to induce amyloidogenesis. Freeze-thawing results in ice-water interfaces in plasma and introduces structural stress into proteins which could induce protein misfolding and aggregation (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bader et al., 2014</xref>). Moreover, the incubation at room temperature can promote amyloidogenesis through oxidative stress and spontaneous fibrinogen misfolding that ultimately enhances the formation of amyloid fibrin microclots. Freeze-thaw-based amyloid formation is a cell and enzyme-free approach. In this method, protein structural modification results from intrinsic protein dynamics rather than external biochemical interactions, offering reproducibility and control over aggregation conditions (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Graether et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Filippov et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>To verify amyloid formation by freeze-thawing, we employed the Thioflavin T (ThT) dye, which selectively binds to β-sheet-rich amyloid fibrils and enhances fluorescence upon interaction. Fluorescent ThT staining is widely used in amyloid research as a reliable marker for detecting the amyloid transition of fibrinogen, owing to its high specificity for cross-β structures (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2023a</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Kell et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Laubscher et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Pretorius et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>
<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref> shows the fluorescence microscopy images of freeze-thawed plasma samples stained with ThT. In the earlier cycles, there are no visible ThT-labeled amyloid structures. However, green, fluorescent ThT-labeled microclots emerge starting from cycles 7, indicating a gradual amyloid microclot formation. By cycle 8, a marked increase in ThT-tagged microclots can be observed which shows significant amyloid microclot formation and with each cycle more amyloid microclots appear in the sample. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref> shows the quantitative clot counts as a function of cycles, confirming a significant increase in amyloid microclots after cycle 7. This cycle-dependent increase in amyloid microclot counts confirms amyloidogenesis by repeated freeze-thaw cycles and incubation. The formation of microclots with repeated freeze–thaw cycles and incubation are previously reported, showing that freeze-thaw processes generate ice-water interfaces that impose structural stress on plasma proteins and lead to misfolding and aggregation. Fibrinogen, in particular, has been shown to adopt abnormal conformations under these conditions and covert into amyloid-like forms (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Graether et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Filippov et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2003</xref>). This experiment was repeated twice to ensure reproducibility. However, since plasma contains natural proteins, batch-to-batch variations are inherent. As a result, the data presented here is primarily aimed to show the trend of increasing clot formation with successive cycles rather than serving as an exact reference for clot numbers. Although we use a particle detection algorithm to identify discrete microclots, accumulation of submicron amyloid clots can lead to diffuse green fluorescence across the field. These clots are likely too small or diffuse to be detected as distinct particles but still bind Thioflavin T (ThT) and result in a uniform background signal. This background signal may reflect early-stage amyloid formation occurring before the assembly of detectable microclots.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>3.2 Effect of ultrasound on amyloid microclots across different frequencies</title><p>After amyloid microclot formation, we explore how different ultrasound frequencies impact both microclot morphology and count. The different mechanical interactions of ultrasound with microclots are frequency-dependent, as acoustic forces such as acoustic radiation force and acoustic streaming exhibit varying levels of dominance based on their inherent frequency ranges (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Rasouli et al., 2023</xref>). The balance between these forces dictates whether ultrasound leads to microclot fragmentation, which is our aim, or instead results in displacement or even aggregation of the microclots. Hence, identifying the optimal frequency and experimental conditions for effective clot disruption is crucial for the potential therapeutic applications of our ultrasound platform. To this end, we tested the effect of different ultrasound frequencies on the lysis of microclots by subjecting them to 150, 300, 500 kHz, and 1 MHz.</p><p>This experiment was also repeated in the presence of rtPA, a serine protease used as a thrombolytic agent to dissolve blood clots. rtPA works by binding to fibrin in microclots and then converting plasminogen into plasmin, which subsequently dissolves the clot through a process known as fibrinolysis. We sought to determine whether ultrasound increases the rate of clot dissolution when rtPA is used and whether a possible synergistic effect of the acoustic forces and pharmacological thrombolysis can be observed.</p><p>
<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A, B</xref> show fluorescence microscopy images of ThT-tagged microclots treated with different ultrasound (US) frequencies for US-only and US + rtPA groups. The control samples show a high density of large (over 30 microns) amyloid microclots, which are uniformly distributed across the image. Upon exposure to 150 kHz waves, the microclots exhibit a marked reduction in size. At higher frequencies, however, less fragmentation can be observed, and the clots remain intact.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Effect of ultrasound (US) and ultrasound combined with rtPA (US + rtPA) on microclot lysis at different frequencies. <bold>(A, B)</bold> Fluorescence microscopy images of microclots under <bold>(A)</bold> ultrasound alone and <bold>(B)</bold> ultrasound with rtPA at control, 150, 300, 500 kHz, and 1 MHz. <bold>(C, D)</bold> Bar graphs showing average clot diameter as a function of ultrasound frequency for <bold>(C)</bold> US-only and <bold>(D)</bold> US + rtPA conditions. Clot size is significantly reduced at 150 kHz, with a minor reduction at higher frequencies. <bold>(E, F)</bold> Clot counts for microclots larger than 30 µm across different conditions, demonstrating a frequency-dependent clot fragmentation. Error bars represent standard deviations. Scale bar is 200 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fbioe-13-1604447-g003.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Ultrasound images and bar graphs displaying the effect of various frequencies on clot size and count. Panels A and B show fluorescent images under different conditions: Control, 150 kHz, 300 kHz, 500 kHz, and 1 MHz. Panels C and D present bar graphs of average diameter for US and rtPA conditions. Panels E and F show bar graphs of clot counts over 30 micrometers for US and rtPA, with statistical significance indicated by asterisks.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>To quantify microclot lysis under US treatment, image analysis was performed, and the average clot diameter and count of clots above 30 μm at each testing condition were calculated for three samples to ensure statistical robustness. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3C, D</xref> show the average clot diameter and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3E, F</xref> show the number of clots over 30 μm as a function of ultrasound frequency for both US and US + rtPA samples. In agreement with the microscopy images, a significant reduction in clot size is observed at 150 kHz, while exposure to higher frequencies leads to less pronounced fragmentation. US + rtPA shows a similar trend of reduction in average diameter and large clot count at 150 kHz. For US + rTPA the mean clot diameter decreases from ∼20 µm in the control to ∼7 μm at 150 kHz, confirming significant fragmentation at this frequency. At 300 kHz and higher frequencies there is no statistically significant change in clot size for both US and US + rTPA.</p><p>The findings indicate that 150 kHz ultrasound is the most effective frequency for reducing both large clot count and size in both US-only and US + rtPA groups, whereas higher frequencies (300 kHz–1 MHz) result in less pronounced disruption. One potential explanation for clot lysis at 150 kHz is the formation of endogenous microbubbles, which can result in boundary-layer-driven acoustic microstreams (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Rasouli et al., 2023</xref>). During the 150 kHz experiment, bubbles became visibly present, whereas no such bubble formation was observed at higher frequencies. Plasma and most biological fluids naturally contain gas nuclei that act as precursors for bubble formation under ultrasound exposure. Upon formation, these bubbles oscillate in response to ultrasound actuation and create localized streaming which in turn can enhance clot lysis.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>3.3 The role of cavitation in ultrasound-induced clot fragmentation</title><p>To investigate whether the mechanism of fragmentation at 150 kHz was directly linked to cavitation and acoustic streaming, we compared the effect of ultrasound exposure on degassed and non-degassed plasma samples. Cavitation requires dissolved gas nuclei to form microbubbles and thus degassing the plasma minimizes endogenous cavitation and bubble formation.</p><p>
<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> shows the fluorescence microscopy results of microclots in degassed and non-degassed plasma. Clot lysis and reduced micro clot size was observed in the gassed plasma sample after treatment with 150 kHz acoustic waves as shown by the images in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>. The same ultrasound waves failed to lyse microclots in degassed plasma samples and they remained largely intact. The absence of visible bubble formation in the degassed sample during the test as compared to the non-degassed sample suggests that clot lysis at 150 kHz can be attributed to the formation of endogenous bubbles and their attendant acoustic streaming.</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Effect of degassing on ultrasound US-induced microclot lysis at 150 kHz. <bold>(A)</bold> Fluorescence microscopy images of microclots exposed to 150 kHz ultrasound in non-degassed (left) and degassed (right) conditions. Clot size remains larger in the degassed condition, indicating reduced lysis efficiency. Scale bars represent 100 µm. <bold>(B)</bold> Quantitative analysis of clot size and count. The left graph shows the average clot diameter across conditions.150 kHz stimulation of non-degassed sample significantly reduced clot size compared to the control, while the degassed condition retains larger clots. The right graph displays the number of clots over 30 μm, showing a significant reduction for non-degassed, whereas degassed conditions result in higher clot retention.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fbioe-13-1604447-g004.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Panel A shows two microscopic images of clots at 150 kHz and 150 kHz degassed, demonstrating a difference in density. Panel B presents bar charts comparing average clot diameter and clot counts over 30 micrometers among control, 150 kHz, and 150 kHz degassed samples. Statistical significance is indicated with asterisks, showing differences in measurements.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Quantitative data on microclot size after ultrasound exposure is depicted in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref> for both degassed and non-degassed samples. The left graph investigates microclot lysis in degassed vs. non degassed plasma where cavitation effects are inhibited. The y-axis is the mean clot diameter, and the x-axis is frequency. Although the degassed samples showed a minor decrease in clot size it is considered statistically nonsignificant with diameters ranging from ∼17 to ∼14 µm compared to ∼7 µm in non-degassed sample. Moreover, the number of large clots over 30 µm decreased for non-degassed sample to approximately a third of the control while in the degassed sample the variation was not statistically significant. This supports the hypothesis that clot lysis observed at 150 kHz is due to the cavitation, likely through cavitation-induced acoustic streams.</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>3.4 Effect of microbubbles and rtPA on clot lysis across frequencies</title><p>Previous results showed that cavitation is crucial for clot fragmentation at 150 kHz. In this section, we introduce exogenous microbubbles (MBs) into the plasma to promote stable cavitation. We use gas-filled microbubbles ∼1–2 µm in diameter which are coated with a phospholipid shell to render them more stable. In response to acoustic waves, these microbubbles undergo rapid compression and expansion cycles and generate localized fluid motion known as acoustic streams. Unlike endogenous cavitation, which relies on the presence of dissolved gas nuclei that varies between samples, contrast agents provide more consistent and controlled bubble dynamics and acoustic streaming. We hypothesize that the use of exogenous bubble can further increase lysis. In this section we also investigate the impact of MBs in combination with rtPA on clot lysis to assess whether this approach would further enhance enzymatic clot degradation.</p><p>
<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> shows the fluorescence microscopy images of ThT-stained plasma in the MB and MB + rtPA groups at the tested frequencies. In both groups, clot fragmentation is more pronounced at 150 kHz and 300 kHz, showing a significant reduction in clot size. Fragmentation is also observable with less impact at 500 kHz, while at 1 MHz, the effect diminishes significantly. Clot size analysis shown in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> further supports these observations and confirms a substantial decrease in clot size. The average clot diameter significantly decreases from ∼18 µm in the control group to ∼7 μm at 150 kHz, ∼8 μm at 300 kHz, and ∼10 μm at 500 kHz, while at 1 MHz, the clot size remained about 10 µm in the MB group. Additionally, the large clot count decreased from ∼450 in the control to ∼70 at 150 kHz, 90 at 300 kHz, 140 at 500 kHz, and 350 at 1 MHz. The results confirm the capability of the ultrasound system in combination with MBs for fragmentation and elimination of large microclots.</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Effect of acoustically stimulated microbubbles (MB) and microbubbles combined with rtPA (MB + rtPA) on microclot lysis at different frequencies. <bold>(A, B)</bold> Fluorescence microscopy images of microclots under <bold>(A)</bold> ultrasound and Microbubbles and <bold>(B)</bold> combination of ultrasound, microbubbles with rtPA at control, 150, 300, 500 kHz, and 1 MHz. <bold>(C, D)</bold> Bar graphs showing average clot diameter as a function of ultrasound frequency for <bold>(C)</bold> MB <bold>(D)</bold> and MB + rtPA conditions. <bold>(E, F)</bold> Clot counts for microclots larger than 30 µm across different conditions. Error bars represent standard deviations. Scale bar is 200 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fbioe-13-1604447-g005.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Two sets of fluorescent microscopy images show green tagged Microclots under different ultrasound frequencies for two conditions: A) microbubbles (MB) and B) microbubbles with rtPA. Below, bar graphs C and D illustrate the average diameters of clots, showing significant reductions with increasing frequency. Graphs E and F display clot counts over 30 micrometers, also decreasing with higher frequencies for both conditions. Statistical significance is indicated with asterisks in the graphs.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>A similar trend, with a slightly stronger effect, can be seen in the MB + rtPA conditions, where the average clot diameter decreases from 19 µm in the control to 7 μm at 150 kHz, and the large clot count declines from ∼500 to 50 at 150 kHz. The observed reduction in clot size and count suggests a potential synergistic interaction between ultrasound, microbubbles, and enzymatic lysis, warranting further investigation to optimize this effect. This is particularly relevant given that acoustic streaming is reported to be one of the strongest mechanisms to induce normal advection and enhancing mixing (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Rasouli and Tabrizian, 2019</xref>). Strong and rapid mixing can accelerate enzymatic clot degradation by facilitating the binding of rtPA to fibrin within the clot, thereby promoting the conversion of plasminogen to plasmin.</p><p>These results indicate that microbubble-assisted ultrasound stimulation is more effective for clot fragmentation at lower frequencies (150–500 kHz). The addition of exogenous contrast agents enhances cavitation and acoustic streaming, resulting in more effective clot disruption. Also, in MB added groups the clot fragmentation was observed across multiple frequencies, while in the US-only group, lysis was observed only at 150 kHz. The enhanced efficacy observed at 150–300 kHz aligns with prior studies showing that microbubble volumetric oscillation is markedly stronger in this range. Volumetric expansion ratios can exceed 30-fold at these frequencies, while at 1 MHz, expansion is typically below 2-fold under comparable pressure conditions (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Ilovitsh et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>The clot lysis in the presence of microbubbles can be attributed to boundary-layer-driven acoustic microstreaming generated by oscillating stable or semi-stable microbubbles which creates strong localized shear forces capable of breaking down the brittle amyloid fibrin(ogen) microclots. This also provides additional targeting specificity to the microclots, as they are more susceptible to fragmentation than other biological particles. Moreover, the streaming-induced mixing may improve enzymatic access by exposing binding sites and facilitating the interaction of rtPA with the microclots (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Školoudík et al., 2025</xref>). The absence of lysis in degassed conditions supports the role of cavitation-driven streaming in this process. These results emphasize the potential of MB-assisted ultrasound therapy for targeting persistent amyloid microclots in conditions such as Long COVID.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>4 Conclusion and future directions</title><p>In this study, we showed that ultrasound stimulation is an effective strategy for lysing amyloid fibrin(ogen) microclots, particularly at 150 kHz. Using a LOC model we observed a significant reduction in clot size and large clot count after ultrasound exposure. The lack of fragmentation in degassed plasma confirms that cavitation plays a key role in clot lysis by generating acoustic microstreaming that enhances fibrinolysis. Microbubble contrast agents further improved clot fragmentation through stable cavitation and generating acoustic streams. Our results suggest that the observed lysis effect is primarily governed by the oscillation of microbubbles, which are determined by their physical properties and the applied frequency. While vessel geometry may influence local acoustic conditions, the matching of applied frequency and the resonance characteristics of the microbubbles appears to play a dominant role and indicates that the effect is not critically dependent on the specific dimensions of the LOC model. The combination of ultrasound microbubbles and rtPA (MB + rtPA + US) resulted in the largest reduction in clot size. This suggests that mechanical disruption enhances enzymatic penetration and fibrinolysis. Further characterization methods such as electron microscopy and FTIR spectroscopy could provide deeper insight into fibrillar architecture, molecular conformation, and morphology changes induced by ultrasound. Nevertheless, our findings support the potential of ultrasound-enhanced therapy for amyloid-associated coagulopathies where persistent microclots impair vascular function and suggest ultrasound-based treatments could serve as a non-invasive tool to restore blood flow and improve oxygenation in affected patients.</p><p>Prior to advancing toward clinical application, further studies are required to bridge the gap between this proof-of-concept and physiological conditions. While the LOC platform enabled controlled testing of ultrasound-mediated lysis and helped isolate acoustic and biochemical effects, incorporating flow conditions and more anatomically representative vascular geometries will be essential to better simulate the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> microenvironment. In addition, quantitative mapping of acoustic streaming and shear forces using methods such as particle image velocimetry (PIV) can clarify the mechanical interactions responsible for clot disruption. Moreover, exploring more frequencies range including 100 kHz could uncover additional insights into threshold behavior and bubble dynamics. Future research should also refine ultrasound parameters for <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> use, assess safety and efficacy, and explore the synergy between ultrasound and thrombolytic agents in biological systems.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Dr. Muhammad Zubair for his contributions to the measurement and characterization of the focal length of the ultrasound transducers.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s6"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Ethical approval was not required for the studies on animals in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements because only commercially available biosamples established cell lines were used.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s7"><title>Author contributions</title><p>RR: Conceptualization, Investigation, Writing – original draft. BH: Conceptualization, Supervision, Writing – review and editing. SK: Conceptualization, Supervision, Writing – review and editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s9"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>Authors RR, BH, and SK were employed by Openwater.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="s10"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that Generative AI was used in the creation of this manuscript. Generative AI was used to help with copy editing, formatting, grammar correction, and improving the clarity of the text including the language of the abstract, introduction, and figure captions. All scientific content, data interpretation, and conclusions were developed and validated by the authors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s11"><title>Publisher’s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Acconcia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>B. Y. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manjunath</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goertz</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Interactions between individual ultrasound-stimulated microbubbles and fibrin clots</article-title>. <source>Ultrasound Med. Biol.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>2134</fpage>–<lpage>2150</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2014.03.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24882525</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>Z. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>R. M. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Structure and aggregation mechanisms in amyloids</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1195</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules25051195</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32155822</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7179426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Shaken and stirred: mechanisms of ultrasound-enhanced thrombolysis</article-title>. <source>Ultrasound Med. Biol.</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2014.08.018</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438846</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4258471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Effect of freezing and thawing rates on denaturation of proteins in aqueous solutions</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. Bioeng.</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>684</fpage>–<lpage>690</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.10612</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12673768</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Draxler</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalkou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turovskij</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keragala</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2025</year>). <article-title>The individual fibrinolytic capacity predicts the efficacy of ultrasound-assisted catheter-directed thrombolysis in patients with acute pulmonary embolism</article-title>. <source>J. Thrombosis Haemostasis</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1416</fpage>–<lpage>1427</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtha.2024.12.043</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39884395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Filippov</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suleimanova</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grobner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antsutkin</surname><given-names>O. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Effect of freezing on amyloid peptide aggregation and self-diffusion in an aqueous solution</article-title>. <source>Colloid J.</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1134/s1061933x08040157</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graether</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slupsky</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Freezing of a fish antifreeze protein results in amyloid fibril formation</article-title>. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0006-3495(03)74874-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12524307</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1302635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilovitsh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilovitsh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foiret</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caskey</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusunose</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fite</surname><given-names>B. Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Enhanced microbubble contrast agent oscillation following 250 kHz insonation</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>16347</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-34494-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30397280</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6218550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arron</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalka-Moll</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>The potential of heparin-induced extracorporeal LDL/fibrinogen precipitation (H.E.L.P.)-apheresis for patients with severe acute or chronic COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Front. Cardiovasc Med.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1007636</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2022.1007636</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36304538</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9592739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2025</year>). <article-title>A direct relationship between ‘blood stasis’ and fibrinaloid microclots in chronic, inflammatory, and vascular diseases, and some traditional natural products approaches to treatment</article-title>. <source>Pharm. (Basel)</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>712</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ph18050712</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12114700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40430532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laubscher</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>A central role for amyloid fibrin microclots in long COVID/PASC: origins and therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>479</volume>, <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bcj20220016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35195253</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8883497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlok</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laubscher</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Proteomics of fibrin amyloid microclots in long COVID/post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC) shows many entrapped pro-inflammatory molecules that may also contribute to a failed fibrinolytic system</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Diabetol.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>190</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12933-022-01623-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36131342</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9491257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laubscher</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lourens</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>TEG®, microclot and platelet mapping for guiding early management of severe COVID-19 coagulopathy</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Med.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>5381</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10225381</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34830660</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8621180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Self-assembly of human fibrinogen into microclot-mimicking antifibrinolytic amyloid fibrinogen particles</article-title>. <source>ACS Appl. Bio Mater</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>825</fpage>–<lpage>834</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsabm.4c01651</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39723824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubiera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montaner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santamarina</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado-Mederos</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Microbubble administration accelerates clot lysis during continuous 2-MHz ultrasound monitoring in stroke patients treated with intravenous tissue plasminogen activator</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.str.0000199064.94588.39</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16373632</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Motarjeme</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raabe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagspiel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benenati</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Ultrasound-accelerated thrombolysis for the treatment of deep vein thrombosis: initial clinical experience</article-title>. <source>J. Vasc. Interv. Radiol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvir.2007.11.023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18375296</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mbotwe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bester</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Acute induction of anomalous and amyloidogenic blood clotting by molecular amplification of highly substoichiometric levels of bacterial lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>J. R. Soc. Interface</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>20160539</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2016.0539</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27605168</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5046953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laubscher</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lourens</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of readily detected amyloid blood clots in ‘unclotted’ Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus and COVID-19 plasma: a preliminary report</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Diabetol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12933-020-01165-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33203441</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7670290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlok</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bezuidenhout</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laubscher</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Persistent clotting protein pathology in Long COVID/Post-Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC) is accompanied by increased levels of antiplasmin</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Diabetol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12933-021-01359-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34425843</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8381139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>I. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tupally</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veidt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Sadiq</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>A systematic review of ultrasound-mediated drug delivery to the eye and critical insights to facilitate a timely path to the clinic</article-title>. <source>Theranostics</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>3582</fpage>–<lpage>3638</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7150/thno.82884</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37441595</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10334839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaran</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serpell</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Amyloid fibrils: abnormal protein assembly</article-title>. <source>Prion</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/pri.2.3.7488</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19158505</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2634529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasouli</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabrizian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>An ultra-rapid acoustic micromixer for synthesis of organic nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>Lab. Chip</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>3316</fpage>–<lpage>3325</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c9lc00637k</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31495858</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasouli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villegas</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabrizian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Acoustofluidics – changing paradigm in tissue engineering, therapeutics development, and biosensing</article-title>. <source>Lab. Chip</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1300</fpage>–<lpage>1338</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d2lc00439a</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36806847</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakharov</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hekkenberg</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rijken</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Acceleration of fibrinolysis by high-frequency ultrasound: the contribution of acoustic streaming and temperature rise</article-title>. <source>Thromb. Res.</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0049-3848(00)00319-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11113277</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Školoudík</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hrbáč</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovář</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beneš</surname><given-names>V.</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Branca</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2025</year>). <article-title>Sonolysis during carotid endarterectomy: randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<volume>388</volume>, <fpage>e082750</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj-2024-082750</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40107675</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11921150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsivgoulis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Ultrasound-enhanced thrombolysis in acute ischemic stroke: potential, failures, and safety</article-title>. <source>Neurotherapeutics</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nurt.2007.05.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17599707</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7479735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Putrino</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodcock</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2023b</year>). <article-title>Long COVID: pathophysiological factors and abnormalities of coagulation</article-title>. <source>Trends Endocrinol. Metab.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tem.2023.03.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37080828</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10113134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laubscher</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2023a</year>). <article-title>Accelerating discovery: a novel flow cytometric method for detecting fibrin(ogen) amyloid microclots using long COVID as a model</article-title>. <source>Heliyon</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e19605</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e19605</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37809592</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10558872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Enhanced thrombolysis by endovascular low-frequency ultrasound with bifunctional microbubbles in venous thrombosis: <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> study</article-title>. <source>Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>965769</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fbioe.2022.965769</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35942007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9356075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Correa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tierradentro-García</surname><given-names>L. O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Sonothrombolysis: state-of-the-art and potential applications in children</article-title>. <source>Children</source>
<volume>11</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/children11010057</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10814591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38255371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Thioflavin T as an amyloid dye: fibril quantification, optimal concentration and effect on aggregation</article-title>. <source>R. Soc. Open Sci.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>160696</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.160696</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28280572</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5319338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>