<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">63</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcph</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12754863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12754863.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12754863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12754863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41272653</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-025-25704-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">25704</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact of COVID-19 lived experiences on future influenza pandemic worry: a cross-sectional survey in China</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="B">Baohua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaozhuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuchen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="L">Laiyou</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhenzhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname> Wang</surname><given-names initials="F">Feng </given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname> Jiang</surname><given-names initials="L">Lingli</given-names></name><address><email>jllgrace@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/041tqx430</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.496809.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 1080</institution-id><institution>School of Health Services and Wellness, Ningbo College of Health Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>51 Xuefu Road, Ningbo, Zhejiang China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478168</issue-id><elocation-id>4405</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-01 10:25:13.220"><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12889_2025_Article_25704.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="structured"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Against the backdrop of repeated warnings regarding the inevitability of future influenza pandemics and the critical importance of public preparedness, the aim of this study was to explore public worry about a future influenza pandemic and its influencing factors in the post-coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID−19) era, particularly focusing on the role of lived experiences during the COVID−19 pandemic.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">An online cross-sectional study was conducted between October and December 2024. Overall, 1254 valid samples were finally included. Descriptive analysis and hierarchical logistic regression were performed to examine the associations between potential influencing factors and public worry about a future influenza pandemic.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Approximately 48.49% of the participants reported being worried about a future influenza pandemic. The final model of hierarchical logistic regression revealed that sex, educational level, having one or more children in the family, lived experiences (repeated infections, long-COVID, medical resource shortages), and risk perceptions (perceived likelihood and severity) were associated with worry about a future influenza pandemic.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">This study reveals that lived experiences during the COVID−19 pandemic are associated with increased worry about a future influenza pandemic by the public. The factors identified can be used to guide the development of evidence-based risk communication and preparedness strategies to foster public participation. Crucial baseline data were also provided from a specific period to monitor changes in public perceptions of influenza pandemic threats over time.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12889-025-25704-7.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>COVID−19</kwd><kwd>Worry</kwd><kwd>Lived experiences</kwd><kwd>Influenza pandemic</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100010248</institution-id><institution>Zhejiang Province Public Welfare Technology Application Research Project</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>LGF22G030018</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Baohua</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Key Project of Ningbo Public Welfare Research Plan</institution></funding-source><award-id>2023S027</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Baohua</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par11">The influenza virus poses a worldwide threat to human health, triggering epidemics that are unpredictable yet occur repeatedly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Over the past century, five global viral pandemics have occurred—one caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2, responsible for coronavirus disease 2019 [COVID-19]) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], and the other four triggered by influenza A viruses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The pathogens of avian influenza are the subtypes of influenza A virus, and their adaptability to various animal hosts highlights the risk of transmission to humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. No sustained human-to-human transmission has occurred; however, human infection with avian influenza remains a very concerning issue, as all influenza pandemics in human history to date have virus genes derived from the avian influenza virus (AIV) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Several potential new candidate variants of AIV have raised alerts about an influenza pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. According to a study in <italic toggle="yes">The</italic><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Infectious Diseases</italic>, the next influenza pandemic virus is likely to originate from spillover events involving birds—recognised as the natural reservoir of all influenza viruses—or pigs, where avianand human influenza viruses can coexist, thereby facilitating viral recombination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Given that China is a high-risk region for avian influenza outbreaks and human infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], it is necessary to raise public vigilance regarding a potential pandemic risk of human avian influenza in China.</p><p id="Par12">During the COVID-19 pandemic, a series of non-pharmaceutical interventions to curb the spread of the disease was also effective in reducing the spread of the influenza virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. From 2020 to 2021, the prevalence of seasonal influenza remained extremely low in China and globally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This significant reduction in influenza activity resulted in a decline in population-level immunity to influenza viruses and a corresponding increase in susceptibility to infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In December 2022, China ended its Zero-COVID Policy (During the COVID-19 pandemic, China implemented a targeted "dynamic zero-COVID strategy" between early 2020 and late 2022. This approach included large-scale nucleic acid testing, large-scale quarantines, extensive lockdowns and the use of health QR codes for entry into public spaces. The central objectives were to minimise COVID-19 infections, reduce severe cases and fatalities, safeguard public health, and protect vulnerable groups amid the global pandemic) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Subsequently, the intensity of influenza activity rebounded, with the intensity in 2023 the influenza activity intensity was higher than that of the year before the COVID-19 pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This influenza resurgence overlapped with multiple other respiratory infectious diseases, causing a prolonged epidemic cycle that had serious impacts on public health, and revived concerns regarding a pandemic potential of influenza [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. </p><p id="Par13">Indeed, both before and after the COVID-19 pandemic, scientists have repeatedly emphasised the inevitability of a future influenza pandemic and underscored the crucial importance of public preparedness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. </p><p id="Par14">The COVID-19 pandemic represents as the most severe threat to global health in history. During the COVID-19 pandemic, people face uncertain opportunities for infections, recurrent infection, hospitalisation, and even death. Even if there was recovery from the SARS-CoV-2 infection, many people still experienced long-term clinical sequelae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Owing to the rapid increase in the number of patients with COVID-19 in a short time, difficulties such as a shortage of medical resources, a lack of epidemic prevention materials, insufficient treatment capacity, and inability to access medical consultation and hospital admission were encountered by many people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Beyond physical health impacts, the COVID-19 pandemic also exerted far-reaching impacts on the mental health of individuals; worry was prevalent among the public during this period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. </p><p id="Par15">Worry and risk perception are relevant psychological factors that influence preventive health behaviours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Worry, also known as affective risk perception[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], which is stimulated by the anticipating a negative outcome that is uncertain and may happen in the future [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Worry was an important predictor of more responsible behaviour during the COVID-19 pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. People may be aware of the risks they face, but if they are not worried about them, preventive measures may not be taken [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Risk perception can affect worry, and thus predict subsequent intentions and behaviors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], emphasising the role of emotions experienced during decision-making [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Studies indicate that factors such as age, gender, education level, income level, occupation, and health condition are associated with viral pandemic-related worry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">The world may witness another pandemic similar to COVID-19 in the coming decades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Yet despite lessons learned from COVID-19, global readiness for an influenza pandemic remains insufficient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], whether the COVID-19 pandemic has reshaped people's awareness and concerns about similar crises remains unclear. This underscores the need to thoroughly understand the factors driving public worry about the pandemic: historical records of pandemic-related losses highlight the value of identifying these factors to guide future public engagement in crisis prevention and risk communication. Notably, the World Health Organisation (WHO) has already designated public engagement and communication as a key priority for enhancing future pandemic responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">A number of theories have been developed to explain the relationship between risk perception, emotions such as worry, and behaviors. Protection Motivation Theory reveals that changes in behavior are driven by fear, which is regulated by the perception of threats or risks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. It is believed in the Prospect Theory that a person's judgment of events is not based on absolute results, but on reference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Those who had specific adverse lived experiences during the COVID-19 pandemic may fear facing similar experiences if they take normal life as a reference point, thus showing worry. While the impact of COVID-19 on people's psychology and emotional states has been extensively explored, only a few studies have focused on how individuals' unique experiences shape their worry about similar crises. To design targeted interventions that promote mental health and bolster future preparedness, identifying these influencing factors is essential. In this study, the Protection Motivation Theory and Prospect Theory were combined to explore the public worry about a future influenza pandemic and its influencing factors, particularly focusing on the role of lived experiences during the COVID-19 pandemic. The following hypotheses were tested:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par18">H1: Individuals who experienced specific negative events during the COVID-19 pandemic will have a higher likelihood of worrying about a future influenza pandemic.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">H2: Individuals with higher levels of risk perception will be more likely to worry about a future influenza pandemic.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par20">To comprehensively explore the factors influencing public worry about a future influenza pandemic, key sociodemographic characteristics, chronic non-communicable disease (CNCD) status, and specific career and family-related factors were also included as variables in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par21">The study did not involve clinical data, human specimens, or animal experiments, nor was personal information collected; hence, ethical review was waived by the Ningbo College of Health Sciences. All participants were informed of the objectives of the study. Data were anonymously collected, and all methods were conducted, following relevant ethical guidelines and regulations.</p><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study design and data Collection</title><p id="Par22">This study is a sub-investigation derived from a larger study titled “Research on the Mechanism of Vulnerability Formation and Governance Strategies of Human Avian Influenza Risk Response System - Taking Zhejiang Province as an Example”, funded by the Zhejiang Province Public Welfare Technology Application Research Project. A cross-sectional, questionnaire-based study was conducted between October and December 2024, using two channels in China: WenJuanXing (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.wjx.cn/">https://www.wjx.cn/</ext-link>), a professional platform for electronic questionnaire design and data collection widely used in academic research, and WeChat, a mainstream social networking application.</p><p id="Par23">A convenience sampling method was adopted. Specifically, including three community physicians from health service centres (one each from Ningbo, Wenzhou, and Quzhou) and three physicians from village health clinics (one each from the aforementioned three cities) in Zhejiang Province. These recruited physicians were subsequently requested to distribute the electronic link to the questionnaire to their community WeChat groups, which included their respective community residents and typically used for issuing community notices. In the introduction section of the online questionnaire (located between the title and the questionnaire body), we explained the purpose of the survey, the inclusion criteria, and instructions for completing the questionnaire. We reminded the participants that completing and submitting the questionnaire would be considered informed consent. People in the WeChat group could voluntarily decide whether or not to respond. The inclusion criteria were (1) ≥ 18 years, (2) residing in the selected community for at least 1 year, and (3) voluntary participation and the ability to complete the entire questionnaire.</p><p id="Par24">The respondents’ identifiers were not collected to ensure confidentiality throughout the study. Only completed questionnaires could be uploaded to the survey platform. The questionnaire could only be filled out once using each IP address. Logically incorrect responses were considered invalid and excluded. In total, 1254 valid questionnaires were finally collected.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Variables</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>Outcome variable</title><p id="Par25">The dependent variable in this study was respondents’ self-assessed worry about a future influenza pandemic. “Worry” was measured using a single adapted item from the Brief Illness Perception Questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], which has been widely used in risk perception studies, including those focusing on the COVID−19 pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Participants were asked: “How worried are you about a possible future influenza pandemic?” Responses were recorded on a 5-point Likert scale (1–5), where 1 represented “very worried”, and 5 represented “not worried at all”. For the purposes of modelling, this variable was dichotomised to distinguish between worried and non-worried respondents: those who scored 1 or 2 on the Likert scale were classified as “worried”, while those with scores of 3, 4, or 5 were classified as “not worried”.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Sociodemographic factors</title><p id="Par26">The following sociodemographic data were collected: sex, age, educational background, marital status, residential area, monthly income, and employment status.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Career and family-related factors</title><p id="Par27">Given the potential influence of specific occupational roles or routine contact with vulnerable populations on on worry by individuals, participants were asked to respond to four binary (“yes/no”) questions: whether they (1) worked as healthcare workers; (2) were employed in elderly care or long-term care institutions; (3) held positions in childcare institutions; and (4) had children under 3 years in their household.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Chronic non-communicable diseases</title><p id="Par28">Building on previous research, which has shown that individuals with chronic non-communicable diseases (CNCDs) were disproportionately impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], we also assessed the status of CNCDs. Participants were asked to self-report their history of CNCDs, including hypertension, diabetes, coronary heart disease, malignant tumours, stroke, asthma, chronic pulmonary obstruction, kidney disease, autoimmune diseases (e.g., lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis), or other CNCDs reported by themselves. Participants who reported having at least one of the above CNCDs were classified as “individuals with CNCDs”.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Risk perceptions</title><p id="Par29">Risk perceptions were assessed using two indicators adapted from previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]: (i) perceived probability and (ii) perceived severity. Perceived probability was measured by asking the following questions: “Do you think an influenza pandemic is likely to occur in the next few decades?“. Responses were recorded on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (“very high probability”) to 5 (“very low probability”). Perceived severity was assessed with a single item: “What do you think the severity of the illness would be if humans were infected with a new type of influenza virus?“. Responses were collected on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (“Very severe”) to 5 (“Not severe at all”). For analytical purposes, both variables were dichotomised into “high” (combining categories 1 and 2) and “not high” (categories 3, 4, and 5).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Lived experiences during the COVID-19 pandemic</title><p id="Par30">The measure of lived experiences during the COVID−19 pandemic comprises three dimensions that were highly prevalent and significantly impacted individuals’ physical and mental health: repeated infections, medical resource shortages, and long-COVID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Repeated infection was assessed by asking participants the number of times they had confirmed SARS-CoV−2 infections throughout the pandemic. Those reporting two or more infections were classified into the repeated infection group. Medical resource shortage experiences were assessed using the following question: “Have you ever experienced the hospital capacity crisis caused by COVID−19, which has brought difficulties for you or your family to see a doctor or be hospitalised?“. Participants responded to this item using a binary “yes/no” answer. Long-COVID was measured from participants’ reported symptoms of COVID−19 infection and the duration of these symptoms. We adopt the definition endorsed by the WHO: long-COVID is a condition occurring in patients with a history of probable or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, which typically develops 3 months from the onset of symptoms, persists for at least 2 months, and cannot be explained by alternative diagnoses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Long-COVID primarily includes the presence of at least one symptom, such as fatigue, dyspnoea, cognitive impairment/brain fog, postexertional malaise, memory issues, musculoskeletal pain/spasms, cough, sleep disturbances, tachycardia/palpitations, altered smell/taste perception, headache, chest pain, and depression.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par31">Descriptive statistics were analysed using frequencies and percentages for variables. Chi-square test was performed to assess statistical significance of independent variables. Variables with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.20 were included in the multivariate analysis.</p><p id="Par32">Hierarchical logistic regression models were used to test the impact of COVID−19 lived experiences variables on influenza pandemic worry. Hierarchical logistic regression was conducted with four models. Model 1 incorporatesed demographic variables and established a baseline; Model 2 added occupational and family related factors, as well as chronic non communicable diseases, to control for their confounding effects; Model 3 added lived experiences during the COVID−19 pandemic to observe whether these experiences contributeed significantly to the model; Model 4 further added risk perceptions to observe whether the effect of COVID−19 experiences were still statistically significant. Odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) for OR were calculated. Statistical analyses were performed with SPSS version 24.0, and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was defined as significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><p id="Par33">The characteristics of the respondents are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Of the respondents, approximately 48.49% expressed feeling worry about a future influenza pandemic. Most respondents were women (65.87%), married (80.38%), had a high school or above education level (76.56%), reported a monthly income of 3000–5999 yuan (28.47%), and lived in urban areas (51.67%). Most respondents believed that the possibility of an influenza pandemic occurring in the next few decades was high (62.92%) and that human infection with the novel influenza virus was severe (59.25%). Regarding experiences during COVID−19 pandemic, 38.76%, 18.50%, and 36.84% of the respondents reported having been infected with COVID−19 twice or more, experiencing long COVID, and having experienced a hospital capacity shortages, respectively.</p><p id="Par34">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of respondents (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1254)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Worried about the influenza pandemic</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not worried<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 646)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Worried<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 608)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.224</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">826(65.87%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">251(38.85)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">431(70.89)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">428(34.13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">395(61.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177(29.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.144</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
<sup>**</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">535(42.66%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">251(38.85)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">282(46.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 40 ~ 59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">589(46.97%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">309(47.83)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">280(46.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130(10.37%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85(13.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46(7.57)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marital status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.033</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.856</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unmarried/Divorced/Widowed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">246(19.62%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128(19.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 118(19.41)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Married</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1008(80.38%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 518(80.19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 490(80.59)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Living area</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">()</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.594</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.441</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Rural area</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">606(48.33%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">319(49.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">287(47.20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Urban area</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">648(51.67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">327(50.62)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">321(52.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monthly income</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.424</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.024</bold>
<sup><bold>*</bold></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3000 yuan below</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">355(28.31%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">201(31.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154(25.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3000 to 5999 yuan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">357(28.47%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163(25.23)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">194(31.91)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 6000 to 9999 yuan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">298(23.76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150(23.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148(24.34)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 10,000 yuan or above</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">244(19.46%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132(20.43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112(18.42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Education background</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.576</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.019</bold>
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Undergraduate or above</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">960(76.56%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">477(73.84)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">483(79.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> High school or below</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">294(23.44%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">169(26.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">125(20.56)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Employment status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.825</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.050</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Not employed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">322(25.68%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">181(28.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">141(23.19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Employed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">932(74.32%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">465(71.98)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">467(76.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Having one or more children under 3 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.597</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.003</bold>
<sup><bold>**</bold></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1228(97.93%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">640(99.07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">588(96.71)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26(2.07%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6(0.93)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20(3.29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical staff</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.154</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.695</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1053(83.97%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">545(84.37)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">508(83.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">201(16.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101(15.63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100(16.45)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Staff of elderly care institutions, long-term care institutions, or welfare homes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.838</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.175</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1217(97.05%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">631(97.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">586(96.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37(2.95%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15(2.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22(3.62)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Childcare institutions or primary school staff</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.028</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.867</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1224(97.61%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">631(97.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">593(97.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30(2.39%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15(2.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15(2.47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Individuals with CNCDs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.456</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.228</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">941(75.04%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">494(76.47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">447(73.52)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">313(24.96%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152(23.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161(26.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Perceived probability of influenza pandemic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">262.362</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Not high probability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">465(37.08%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">378(58.51)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87(14.31)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> High probability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">789(62.92%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">268(41.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">521(85.69)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Perceived consequences of the influenza pandemic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">358.953</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
<sup>**</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Not severe</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">511(40.75%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">428(66.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83(13.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Severe</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">743(59.25%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">218(33.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">525(86.35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of infections with COVID-19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.305</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 2 times</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">768(61.24%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">449(69.50)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">319(52.47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 2 times</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">486(38.76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">197(30.50)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">289(47.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Long-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.031</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1022(72.57%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">554(85.76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">468(76.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232(18.50%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92(14.24)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140(23.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Experience of medical resource shortages</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.543</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
<sup><bold>***</bold></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">792(63.16%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">461(71.36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">331(54.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">462(36.84%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185(28.64)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">277(45.56)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; 0.01; <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.001; Bold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par35">Bivariate analysis results are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The results showed that gender, age, monthly income, educational background, having one or more children under 3 years old, long-COVID, repeated infection, experience of medical resource shortages, perceived probability, and perceived severity reflected statistical differences in different groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><p id="Par36">Variables with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.20 in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> were included in the hierarchical logistic regression. Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the results of factors related to influenza pandemic worry. All four logistic regression models are significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0. 001), and the ‘−2 Log likelihood’ of each model are given (model 1: 1700.209, model 2: 1692.765, model 3:1621.395, and model 4: 1203.500). The optimal model (Model 4) results show that compared to men, women (OR = 0.669; CI = 0.493–0.909) were more likely to report worry about an influenza pandemic. Worry was also associated with educational level: among participants, those with an educational level of undergraduate or above (OR = 0.619; CI = 0.402–0.954) were more likely to report influenza pandemic worry. During the COVID−19 pandemic, participants who had a history of repeated infection (OR = 3.623; CI = 1.099–11.949), long-COVID (OR = 1.527; CI = 1.135–2.054), or experienced medical resource shortages (OR = 1.469; CI = 1.022–2.110) were more likely to report worry; thus, Hypothesis 1 was supported. Perceived likelihood (OR = 4.593; 95% CI = 3.309–6.376) and perceived severity (OR = 8.239; 95% CI = 6.000–11.314) had been identified as the two factors strongest associated with influenza pandemic worry; therefore, Hypothesis 2 was supported.</p><p id="Par37">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Logistic regression analysis of factors associated with influenza pandemic worry</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 2</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 3</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 4</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR<break/>(95 CI%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR<break/>(95 CI%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR<break/>(95 CI%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR<break/>(95 CI%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"> Female</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.654(0.513–0.834)</bold>
<sup>**</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.669(0.524–0.853)</bold>
<sup>**</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.667(0.518–0.859)</bold>
<sup>**</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.669(0.493–0.909)</bold>
<sup><bold>**</bold></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"> &lt; 40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 40 ~ 59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0.885(0.687–1.141)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0.928(0.717–1.201)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0.836(0.639–1.092)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1.006(0.729–1.389)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0.568(0.351–0.916)<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0.601(0.371–0.974)<sup>**</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0.712(0.432–1.172)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1.083(0.581–2.019)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Monthly income</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"> 3000 yuan below</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3000 to 5999 yuan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.422(0.999–2.023)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.409(0.987–2.011)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.368(0.950–1.9702.950.9702)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.413(0.898–2.224)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 6000 to 9999 yuan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.171(0.796–1.723)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.178(0.799–1.735)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.027(0.689–1.532)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.844(0.520–1.370)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 10,000 yuan or above</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.997(0.661–1.503)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.992(0.657–1.497)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.892(0.583–1.364)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.847(0.507–1.414)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Education background</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"> Undergraduate or above</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> High school or below</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.136(0.820–1.574)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.142(0.823–1.5849)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.013(0.722–1.421)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.619(0.402–0.954)</bold>
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Employment status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"> Not employed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Employed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1.004(0.704–1.432)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1.006(0.705–1.436)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1.057(0.733–1.524)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0.839(0.532–1.322)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Staff of elderly care institutions, long-term care institutions, or welfare homes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.225(0.618–2.429)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.153(0.570–2.332)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.051(0.448–2.463)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Having one or more children under 3 years</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>3.012(1.184–7.659)</bold>
<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>2.928(1.134–7.558)</bold>
<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>3.623(1.099–11.949)</bold>
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Number of infections with COVID-19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 2 times</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 2 times</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.748(1.368–2.235)</bold>
<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.527(1.135–2.054)</bold>
<sup>**</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Long-COVID</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.641(1.209–2.228)</bold>
<sup>**</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.469(1.022–2.110)</bold>
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Experience of medical resource shortages</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>2.033(1.591–2.598)</bold>
<sup>***</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.444(1.075–1.940)</bold>
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Perceived probability of influenza pandemic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Not high probability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> High probability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>4.593(3.309–6.376)</bold>
<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Perceived consequences of the influenza pandemic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Not severe</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Severe</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>8.239(6.000–11.314.000.314)</bold>
<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2 Log likelihood</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1700.209</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1692.765</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1621.395</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1203.500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagelkerke R2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.035</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.041</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.114</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.460</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001; Bold,<italic toggle="yes"> p</italic>&lt;0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par38">It is worth noting that COVID−19 lived experiences remained statistically significant across different model specifications, independent of other covariates included. This indicates that the association between COVID−19 lived experiences and influenza pandemic worry is not substantially confounded by other factors included in the models, confirming these COVID−19 experiences are independent influencing factors on influenza pandemic worry.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par39">Viral outbreaks are increasing rapidly owing to climate change, anthropogenic environmental changes, and frequent contact between humans and disease-carrying animals. The possibility of extreme epidemics similar to that of COVID−19, such as the influenza pandemic, is increasing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The survey was conducted more than a year after the WHO announced that the COVID−19 epidemic was no longer a “public health emergency of international concern”. In this study, COVID−19 lived experiences, risk perceptions, having one or more children under 3 years of age in the family, being a woman, and a higher education level are associated with influenza pandemic worry.</p><p id="Par40">Approximately half of the participants reported worry about a future influenza pandemic in this study. A review of global research on public concern about the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic revealed that, with the exception of Saudi Arabia, where the proportion of individuals expressing concern reached 54.3%, the corresponding figure across other regions ranged from 2 to 36%. Additionally, the findings revealed that public concern about the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic declined as the pandemic progressed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. A comparison of data from before and after the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic revealed a decline in public influenza pandemic worry, from 45.5% in 2007 to 32.5% in 2009–2010 (3 months after the peak of the H1N1 2009 pandemic and 1 month after the pattern of cases had declined to normal seasonal levels) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The reasonable explanation for the decrease in the level of worry is that the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic did not meet people’s expectations of a severe, terrifying, and widespread influenza outbreak. Some studies suggest that the 2009 H1N1 influenza was a false pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Therefore, the level of worry about a future influenza pandemic in this study was higher than that in previous studies, which may be related to the timing of the investigation—the survey took place less than 2 years after the end of the COVID−19 pandemic, and there was also a rebound of seasonal influenza during this period. Continuous attention should be paid to whether the worry about future similar crises will change over time in the public. This study provides a benchmark for comparing future research on worry about an influenza pandemic and risk perception.</p><sec id="Sec15"><title>Lived experiences during the COVID−19 pandemic</title><p id="Par41">An important finding of this study is that certain lived experiences during the COVID-19 pandemic significantly influenced worry about a future influenza pandemic in the public and exerted an independent impact on these public concerns. In this study, 38.76% of the participants reported having contracted COVID-19 twice or more. COVID-19 reinfection is associated with an increased risk of all-cause mortality and adverse health outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. According to a global analysis, the cumulative prevalence of long-COVID ranges from 9 to 63% and is about 6-fold higher than that of similar post-viral infection conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In this study, long-COVID prevalence was 18.50%. Long-COVID is a debilitating post-infection multisystem condition, impairing one’s ability to perform daily activities and potentially causing lifelong consequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Therefore, those who have experienced COVID−19 reinfection or long-COVID may have a deeper concern about a future influenza pandemic in which they may face similar health damage. In addition, during the COVID−19 pandemic, there were instances where a sharp surge in infections over a short period overwhelmed and even paralysed healthcare systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Personal or familial experiences of being unable to access medical resources because of such circumstances have further amplified the worry about potential similar crises in the future. These lived experiences once again emphasise the necessity of preparing for future influenza pandemics and enhancing healthcare resilience.</p><p id="Par42">It was confirmed in this study that worry about a future influenza pandemic is partly driven by personal lived experiences during previous pandemics. History shows that the high level of attention garnered during the COVID−19 pandemic will soon fade; however, this study indicates that the potential impact of the pandemic may persist. In the field of natural hazards, experience is recognised as a key factor influencing risk preparedness, with direct and indirect experiences playing roles in shaping future preparation decisions and actions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Thus, the scope of research on the impact of lived experiences was expanded in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Risk Perceptions</title><p id="Par43">The relationship between risk perceptions and worry is usually highly correlated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. In this study, perceived probability and perceived severity were identified as the two important factors influencing influenza pandemic worry. This correlation underscores a critical opportunity to proactively address future pandemic threats—one that hinges on understanding public responses to such risks, as risk perceptions is a core component of how communities engage with preparedness efforts. To drive meaningful public participation, conveying the genuine risk and severity of a influenza pandemic is essential. For policymakers, this offers a clear roadmap: pairing transparent risk communication with demonstrations of a robust, well-prepared public health system can channel public worry into a catalyst for constructive preparedness rather than anxiety.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Sociodemographic factors</title><p id="Par44">Women were more likely to report worry about a future influenza pandemic in this study. The sex differences in stress responses may be a reason, as women have lower tolerance for negative stress than men [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Reportedly, women are more likely to express concerns about COVID−19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The inconsistency in previous research is the relationship between education level and worry. It has been previously suggested that individuals with higher levels of education may have more resources to cope with COVID-19 and are less concerned about it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. However, in this study, the opposite result was found: participants with a higher level of education were more likely to be worried. A possible explanation is that limited understanding of the complex biological mechanisms underlying the occurrence of influenza pandemics, combined with its seasonality and confusion with the common cold, may lead individuals with lower levels of education to underestimate its severity, while those with higher education levels may be more likely to be aware of its severe implications. Another finding of this study is that participants with children under 3 years at home were more likely to be worried. Reports show that families with young children have increased concerns about the pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Concerns about family members were also a studied topic about the virus pandemic, especially vulnerable groups who are considered more susceptible to infections or complications. However, an Australian survey found no significant differences in risk perception of a future influenza pandemic between men and women, nor between individuals with children and those without [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The background and stage of the pandemic in these studies differ, so people adapt their worry to fit the changing context [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par45">This study has some limitations that need to be mentioned. First, the use of a cross-sectional survey does not establish causality and only shows a snapshot of influenza pandemicrelated worry at a particular time. Second, the survey was conducted online, although considerable efforts were made to reduce bias in online surveys by obtaining a larger sample size (over 1000) and balancing the sample size between urban and rural areas; nonetheless, some sample biases (a larger proportion of higher education and female respondents) still existed. Our non-random sample is not representative of the general public in China, which limits its generalisability. Third, the concerns of the public about the influenza pandemic may be influenced by many other complex factors not identified in this study. These factors may include public trust in medicine development capabilities and the government’s ability to respond to public health crises. Fourth, self-reported COVID−19 experience data may have memory bias. These factors also limit the generalisability of the study findings, which should be interpreted with caution. In the future, large-scale longitudinal studies should be conducted to determine whether the impact of the COVID−19 pandemic experience on similar pandemic identification and judgment changes over time.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par46">This study highlights that lived experiences during the COVID−19 pandemic are associated with increased worry about future influenza pandemics among the public. Given the inherent unpredictability of the influenza virus, effective pandemic management will depend on proactive public planning and preparedness. Therefore, the factors identified in this research can be used to guide the development of evidence-based risk communication and preparedness strategies to foster public participation. Furthermore, future measures should specifically address the needs of vulnerable populations to enhance the overall effectiveness of these policies. Finally, this study also provides crucial baseline data from a specific period for monitoring changes in public perceptions of influenza pandemic threats over time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12889_2025_25704_MOESM1_ESM.doc" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AIV</term><def><p id="Par5">Avian influenza virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par6">Coronavirus disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par7">Confidence intervals</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNCDs</term><def><p id="Par8">Chronic non-communicable diseases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p id="Par9">Odds ratios </p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p id="Par10">World health organization </p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Baohua Liu, Xiaozhuo Zhu and Yuchen Ying contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to convey our sincere appreciation to the individuals who have aided us during the process of data collection and analysis.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>Baohua Liu, Lingli Jiang, and Xiaozhuo Zhu planned the study. Baohua Liu, Hongguo Zhou, Yuchen Ying and Zhenzhen Xu were responsible for the data collections in Study. Baohua Liu had the main responsibility for writing the main manuscript text. Baohua Liu, Laiyou Li, Feng Wang ran the statistical analyses. All authors commented on and revised the text. The author(s) read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This project received funding from Zhejiang Province Public Welfare Technology Application Research Project (LGF22G030018) and Key Project of Ningbo Public Welfare Research Plan (2023S027).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par47">This study was conducted according to the guidelines laid down in the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Ethics Committee of Ningbo College of Health Sciences. Informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par48">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par49">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Feng Zijian</collab></person-group><article-title>Seasonal, avian and pandemic influenza: are we prepared?</article-title><source>Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi</source><year>2018</year><volume>39</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30180420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3760/cma.j.issn.0254-6450.2018.08.001</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Feng Zijian. Seasonal, avian and pandemic influenza: are we prepared? Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi. 2018;39(8):1017–20. in Chinese.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30180420</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3760/cma.j.issn.0254-6450.2018.08.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Epidemiology, Virology, and pathogenicity of human infections with avian influenza viruses</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>a038620</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a038620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31964651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8015695</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Wang D, Zhu W, Yang L, et al. The Epidemiology, Virology, and pathogenicity of human infections with avian influenza viruses. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med. 2021;11(4):a038620.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31964651</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/cshperspect.a038620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8015695</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dzau</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influenza imperative: we must prepare now for seasonal and pandemic influenza</article-title><source>Lancet Microbe</source><year>2023</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e203</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(23)00013-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36738755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9891732</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Dzau V, Yadav P. The influenza imperative: we must prepare now for seasonal and pandemic influenza. Lancet Microbe. 2023;4(4):e203–5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36738755</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2666-5247(23)00013-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9891732</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>On the centenary of the Spanish flu: being prepared for the next pandemic</article-title><source>Virol Sin</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12250-018-0079-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30570715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6335225</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Liu WJ, Bi Y, Wang D, et al. On the centenary of the Spanish flu: being prepared for the next pandemic. Virol Sin. 2018;33(6):463–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30570715</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12250-018-0079-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6335225</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucinotta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic</article-title><source>Acta Biomed</source><year>2020</year><volume>91</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7569573</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Cucinotta D, Vanelli M. WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic. Acta Biomed. 2020;91(1):157–60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191675</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7569573</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunning</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thwaites</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Openshaw</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal and pandemic influenza: 100 years of progress, still much to learn</article-title><source>Mucosal Immunol</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41385-020-0287-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32317736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7223327</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Dunning J, Thwaites RS, Openshaw P. Seasonal and pandemic influenza: 100 years of progress, still much to learn. Mucosal Immunol. 2020;13(4):566–73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32317736</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41385-020-0287-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7223327</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haerheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zoonotic infections by avian influenza virus: changing global epidemiology, investigation, and control</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e522</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(24)00234-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38878787</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Kang M, Wang LF, Sun BW, Wan WB, Ji X, Baele G, Bi YH, Suchard MA, Lai A, Zhang M, Wang L, Zhu YH, Ma L, Li HP, Haerheng A, Qi YR, Wang RL, He N, Su S. Zoonotic infections by avian influenza virus: changing global epidemiology, investigation, and control. Lancet Infect Dis. 2024;24(8):e522–31.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38878787</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(24)00234-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cargnin Faccin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pandemic preparedness through vaccine development for avian influenza viruses</article-title><source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source><year>2024</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2347019</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21645515.2024.2347019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38807261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11141480</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Cargnin Faccin F, Perez DR. Pandemic preparedness through vaccine development for avian influenza viruses. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2024;20(1):2347019.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38807261</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/21645515.2024.2347019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11141480</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Lancet Infectious Diseases</collab></person-group><article-title>How to be ready for the next influenza pandemic</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>697</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30364-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29976515</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">The Lancet Infectious Diseases. How to be ready for the next influenza pandemic. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018;18(7):697.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29976515</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30364-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huang QS, Wood T, Jelley L et al. Impact of the COVID-19 nonpharmaceutical interventions on influenza and other respiratory viral infections in new Zealand.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-021-21157-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7881137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33579926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rockman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Which influenza viruses will emerge following the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic?</article-title><source>Influenza Other Respir Viruses</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/irv.12866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33955176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8242426</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Laurie KL, Rockman S. Which influenza viruses will emerge following the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic? Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2021;15(5):573–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33955176</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/irv.12866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8242426</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Influenza</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Preparing amidst a pandemic</article-title><source>J Vasc Nurs</source><year>2021</year><volume>39</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvn.2021.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34507699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8422853</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Bennett J, Influenza. Preparing amidst a pandemic. J Vasc Nurs. 2021;39(3):49.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34507699</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvn.2021.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8422853</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemic trends and prevention and control of seasonal influenza in China after the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Zhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi</source><year>2024</year><volume>104</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38389234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3760/cma.j.cn112137-20231220-01430</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Wang MH, Hu ZX, Feng LZ, et al. Epidemic trends and prevention and control of seasonal influenza in China after the COVID-19 pandemic. Zhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi. 2024;104(8):559–65. Chinese.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38389234</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3760/cma.j.cn112137-20231220-01430</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The outbreak of seasonal influenza after the COVID-19 pandemic in china: unraveling the immunity debt</article-title><source>Infect Dis now</source><year>2024</year><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>104834</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idnow.2023.104834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37972819</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Pan Q, Chen X, Yu Y, et al. The outbreak of seasonal influenza after the COVID-19 pandemic in china: unraveling the immunity debt. Infect Dis now. 2024;54(1):104834.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37972819</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.idnow.2023.104834</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimizing the dynamic zero-COVID policy in China</article-title><source>Int J Biol Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>18</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>5314</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7150/ijbs.75699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36147473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9461673</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Bai W, Sha S, Cheung T, Su Z, Jackson T, Xiang YT. Optimizing the dynamic zero-COVID policy in China. Int J Biol Sci. 2022;18(14):5314–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36147473</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7150/ijbs.75699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9461673</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchis-Gomar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and its long-term sequelae: what do we know in 2023?</article-title><source>Pol Arch Intern Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>133</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>16402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36626183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.20452/pamw.16402</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Lippi G, Sanchis-Gomar F, Henry BM. COVID-19 and its long-term sequelae: what do we know in 2023? Pol Arch Intern Med. 2023;133(4):16402.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36626183</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.20452/pamw.16402</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xin Zhang N et al. ning, Yingxue Su,. Research on public medical service satisfaction and influencing factors under the background of medical resources run crisis[J].Chin. J of PHM. 2022,38(01):29–33. in chinese.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blix</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birkeland</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thoresen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Worry and mental health in the Covid-19 pandemic: vulnerability factors in the general Norwegian population</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>928</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-021-10927-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34001071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8127278</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Blix I, Birkeland MS, Thoresen S. Worry and mental health in the Covid-19 pandemic: vulnerability factors in the general Norwegian population. BMC Public Health. 2021;21(1):928.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34001071</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-021-10927-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8127278</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social factors and worry associated with COVID-19: evidence from a large survey in China</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>113934</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.113934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33878665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9756108</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Zhou M, Guo W. Social factors and worry associated with COVID-19: evidence from a large survey in China. Soc Sci Med. 2021;277:113934.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33878665</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.113934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9756108</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinkel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiele</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahnen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radtke</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuczyk</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harke</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Debus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schimmöller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krilaviciute</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seibold</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arsov</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadaschik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaaks</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gschwend</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herkommer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Worry about prostate cancer and risk perception among middle-aged men: results from the PROBASE trial</article-title><source>J Behav Med</source><year>2025</year><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10865-025-00559-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40042752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12078363</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Meissner VH, Dinkel A, Kron M, Schiele S, Jahnen M, Lakes J, Radtke JP, Kuczyk MA, Harke NN, Debus J, Fink CA, Antoch G, Schimmöller L, Kristiansen G, Krilaviciute A, Seibold P, Behrens S, Benner A, Arsov C, Hadaschik B, Becker N, Kaaks R, Albers P, Gschwend JE, Herkommer K. Worry about prostate cancer and risk perception among middle-aged men: results from the PROBASE trial. J Behav Med. 2025;48(3):464–77.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40042752</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10865-025-00559-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12078363</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilverda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vollmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of risk perception in students’ COVID-19 vaccine uptake: A longitudinal study</article-title><source>Vaccines (Basel)</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines10010022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35062683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8777829</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Hilverda F, Vollmann M. The role of risk perception in students’ COVID-19 vaccine uptake: A longitudinal study. Vaccines (Basel). 2021;10(1):22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35062683</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vaccines10010022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8777829</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kummeneje</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rundmo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk perception, worry, and pedestrian behaviour in the Norwegian population</article-title><source>Accid Anal Prev</source><year>2019</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>105294</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2019.105294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31586825</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Kummeneje AM, Rundmo T. Risk perception, worry, and pedestrian behaviour in the Norwegian population. Accid Anal Prev. 2019;133:105294.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31586825</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.aap.2019.105294</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erceg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruzojcic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Misbehaving in the Corona crisis: the role of anxiety and unfounded beliefs</article-title><source>Curr Psychol</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>5621</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12144-020-01040-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34305363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280379</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Erceg N, Ruzojcic M, Galic Z. Misbehaving in the Corona crisis: the role of anxiety and unfounded beliefs. Curr Psychol. 2022;41(8):5621–30.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34305363</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12144-020-01040-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280379</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Neill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brereton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahumyan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clinch</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of perceived flood exposure on flood-Risk perception: the role of distance</article-title><source>Risk Anal</source><year>2016</year><volume>36</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2158</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/risa.12597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043331</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">O’Neill E, Brereton F, Shahumyan H, Clinch JP. The impact of perceived flood exposure on flood-Risk perception: the role of distance. Risk Anal. 2016;36(11):2158–86.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043331</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/risa.12597</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting vaccination using numerical and affective risk perceptions: the case of A/H1N1 influenza</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2012</year><volume>30</volume><issue>49</issue><fpage>7019</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2012.09.064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23046542</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Renner B, Reuter T. Predicting vaccination using numerical and affective risk perceptions: the case of A/H1N1 influenza. Vaccine. 2012;30(49):7019–26.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23046542</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vaccine.2012.09.064</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>EU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk as feelings</article-title><source>Psychol Bull</source><year>2001</year><volume>127</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.127.2.267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11316014</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Loewenstein GF, Weber EU, Hsee CK, Welch N. Risk as feelings. Psychol Bull. 2001;127(2):267–86.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11316014</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037/0033-2909.127.2.267</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raphael</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giffin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lujic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pandemic influenza in australia: using telephone surveys to measure perceptions of threat and willingness to comply</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>117</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-8-117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18793441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2556339</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Barr M, Raphael B, Taylor M, Stevens G, Jorm L, Giffin M, Lujic S. Pandemic influenza in australia: using telephone surveys to measure perceptions of threat and willingness to comply. BMC Infect Dis. 2008;8:117.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18793441</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2334-8-117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2556339</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tappin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using survey experiment pretesting to support future pandemic response</article-title><source>PNAS Nexus</source><year>2024</year><volume>3</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>pgae469</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39484044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11523628</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Tappin BM, Hewitt LB. Using survey experiment pretesting to support future pandemic response. PNAS Nexus. 2024;3(11):pgae469.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39484044</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11523628</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katul</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intensity and frequency of extreme novel epidemics</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2021</year><volume>118</volume><issue>35</issue><fpage>e2105482118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2105482118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34426498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8536331</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Marani M, Katul GG, Pan WK, et al. Intensity and frequency of extreme novel epidemics. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2021;118(35):e2105482118.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34426498</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.2105482118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8536331</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. 2022. How global research can end this pandemic and tackle future ones. [accessed 2025 May 28].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rogers RW Cognitive and physiological processes of fear appeals and attitude change: A revised theory of protection motivation. Social Psychophysiology., Caciopppo J, Petty R. New York: Gilford Press, 1983.153-176.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broadbent</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrie</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Main</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The brief illness perception questionnaire</article-title><source>J Psychosom Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>60</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2005.10.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731240</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Broadbent E, Petrie KJ, Main J, Weinman J. The brief illness perception questionnaire. J Psychosom Res. 2006;60(6):631–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731240</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2005.10.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dillard</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holyfield</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations between COVID-19 risk perceptions, behavior intentions and worry</article-title><source>Health Psychol Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/hpr.2022.114477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38084329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10681832</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Dillard AJ, Lester J, Holyfield H. Associations between COVID-19 risk perceptions, behavior intentions and worry. Health Psychol Rep. 2022;10(2):139–48.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38084329</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5114/hpr.2022.114477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10681832</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deslauriers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gosselin-Boucher</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Léger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of COVID-19 on the lives of Canadians with and without non-communicable chronic diseases: results from the iCARE study</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-023-15658-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37884921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10604733</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Deslauriers F, Gosselin-Boucher V, Léger C, Vieira AM, Bacon SL, Lavoie KL. The impact of COVID-19 on the lives of Canadians with and without non-communicable chronic diseases: results from the iCARE study. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):2106.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37884921</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-023-15658-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10604733</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unraveling the fear of COVID-19 reinfection: insights from frontline Doctors in China</article-title><source>Psychol Health Med</source><year>2025</year><volume>30</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13548506.2024.2442110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39699075</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Zhang B, Xiong S, Sun Y, et al. Unraveling the fear of COVID-19 reinfection: insights from frontline Doctors in China. Psychol Health Med. 2025;30(4):723–36.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39699075</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/13548506.2024.2442110</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garry</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>I am not the same as I was before: A qualitative analysis of COVID-19 survivors</article-title><source>Int J Behav Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12529-022-10129-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36227557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9559269</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Duan E, Garry K, Horwitz LI, et al. I am not the same as I was before: A qualitative analysis of COVID-19 survivors. Int J Behav Med. 2023;30(5):663–72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36227557</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12529-022-10129-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9559269</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Supady</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allocating scarce intensive care resources during the COVID-19 pandemic: practical challenges to theoretical frameworks</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30580-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33450202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7837018</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Supady A, Curtis JR, Abrams D, et al. Allocating scarce intensive care resources during the COVID-19 pandemic: practical challenges to theoretical frameworks. Lancet Respir Med. 2021;9(4):430–4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33450202</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30580-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7837018</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. 2023. Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): Post COVID-19 condition. [accessed 2025 July 1]. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/zh/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-post-covid-19-condition">https://www.who.int/zh/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-post-covid-19-condition</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tooher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Street</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braunack-Mayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Community knowledge, behaviours and attitudes about the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic: a systematic review</article-title><source>Influenza Other Respir Viruses</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1316</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/irv.12103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23560537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4634241</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Tooher R, Collins JE, Street JM, Braunack-Mayer A, Marshall H. Community knowledge, behaviours and attitudes about the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic: a systematic review. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2013;7(6):1316–27.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23560537</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/irv.12103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4634241</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agho</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kable</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raphael</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crying wolf? Impact of the H1N1 2009 influenza pandemic on anticipated public response to a future pandemic</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2012</year><volume>197</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/mja11.11623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23163686</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Taylor MR, Stevens GJ, Agho KE, Kable SA, Raphael B. Crying wolf? Impact of the H1N1 2009 influenza pandemic on anticipated public response to a future pandemic. Med J Aust. 2012;197(10):561–4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23163686</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5694/mja11.11623</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allam</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza A (H1N1) pandemic: true or false alarm</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>2009</year><volume>63</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>862</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.2009.094581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19749128</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Allam MF. Influenza A (H1N1) pandemic: true or false alarm. J Epidemiol Community Health. 2009;63(10):862.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19749128</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jech.2009.094581</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and postacute sequelae associated with SARS-CoV-2 reinfection</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2398</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02051-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9671810</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Bowe B, Xie Y, Al-Aly Z. Acute and postacute sequelae associated with SARS-CoV-2 reinfection. Nat Med. 2022;28(11):2398–405.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357676</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-022-02051-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9671810</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Lancet</collab><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>COVID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3 years in</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2023</year><volume>401</volume><issue>10379</issue><fpage>795</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00493-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36906338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9998094</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">The Lancet, Long COVID. 3 years in. Lancet. 2023;401(10379):795.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36906338</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00493-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9998094</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyrrell</surname><given-names>CSB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mytton</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Managing intensive care admissions when there are not enough beds during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2021</year><volume>76</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-215518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33334908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7892390</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Tyrrell CSB, Mytton OT, Gentry SV, et al. Managing intensive care admissions when there are not enough beds during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review. Thorax. 2021;76(3):302–12.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33334908</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-215518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7892390</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneiderbauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontanella Pisa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delves</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk perception of climate change and natural hazards in global mountain regions: A critical review</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2021</year><volume>784</volume><fpage>146957</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33895507</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Schneiderbauer S, Fontanella Pisa P, Delves JL, et al. Risk perception of climate change and natural hazards in global mountain regions: A critical review. Sci Total Environ. 2021;784:146957.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33895507</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146957</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cisternas</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cifuentes</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronfman</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The influence of risk awareness and government trust on risk perception and preparedness for natural hazards</article-title><source>Risk Anal</source><year>2024</year><volume>44</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/risa.14151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37094814</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Cisternas PC, Cifuentes LA, Bronfman NC, et al. The influence of risk awareness and government trust on risk perception and preparedness for natural hazards. Risk Anal. 2024;44(2):333–48.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37094814</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/risa.14151</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kam</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insights from avian influenza: A review of its multifaceted nature and future pandemic preparedness</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>458</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v16030458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38543823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10975894</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">He J, Kam YW. Insights from avian influenza: A review of its multifaceted nature and future pandemic preparedness. Viruses. 2024;16(3):458.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38543823</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/v16030458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10975894</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tingvold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subjective age, worry and risk-related perceptions in older adults in times of a pandemic</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e0274293</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0274293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36174067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9522013</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Tingvold M, Albert I, Hoffmann M, et al. Subjective age, worry and risk-related perceptions in older adults in times of a pandemic. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(9):e0274293.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36174067</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0274293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9522013</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krayem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Understanding health anxiety in the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Int J Soc Psychiatry</source><year>2022</year><volume>68</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1756</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00207640211057794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34823387</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Heinen A, Varghese S, Krayem A, et al. Understanding health anxiety in the COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Soc Psychiatry. 2022;68(8):1756–63.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34823387</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/00207640211057794</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>