<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="review-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Health Serv Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Health Serv Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">34</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmchsr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Health Services Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6963</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12577318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12577318.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12577318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12577318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41168795</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-025-13631-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13631</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Systematic Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physiotherapy interventions in post- and long-COVID-19: a scoping review of the literature up to February 2023</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0001-0494-9542</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Gartmann</surname><given-names initials="J">Judith</given-names></name><address><email>gartmann.judith@mh-hannover.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0251-2782</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names initials="C">Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1485-2151</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Bökel</surname><given-names initials="A">Andrea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00f2yqf98</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10423.34</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2342 8921</institution-id><institution>Department of Rehabilitation und Sports Medicine, </institution><institution>Hannover Medical School, </institution></institution-wrap>Carl-Neuberg-Straße 1, 30625 Hannover, OE 4250 Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478160</issue-id><elocation-id>1425</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-01 10:25:41.547"><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12913_2025_Article_13631.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="structured"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Physiotherapy is an accepted and recommended treatment for post- and long-COVID-19 condition. It is assumed that physiotherapists reported a lack of information on physiotherapy interventions and treatment parameters. This scoping review provides an overview of the evidence on physiotherapy interventions published in the scientific literature.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The scoping review includes studies analysing physiotherapy treatment parameters and interventions in post- and long-COVID patients. Studies focusing on telemedicine or exclusively home-based workouts are excluded. A systematic literature search was conducted by two independent researchers in the databases PubMed, EBSCO, SCOPUS, Web of Science, EMBASE, PEDro, Cochrane, and WISO. Following the abstract screening process, data extraction and critical assessment were performed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">In this scoping review, 6 studies were included, providing information physiotherapy management of post- and long-COVID-19. The research identified respiratory therapy, aerobic training or strength training as key areas of focus.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">This scoping review highlights the need for further studies on physiotherapy treatment in post- and long-COVID condition.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial registration</title><p id="Par5">Open Science Framework (Registry number osf.io/5k3tA).</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12913-025-13631-7.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Physical therapy modalities</kwd><kwd>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</kwd><kwd>Scoping review</kwd><kwd>Treatment parameter</kwd><kwd>Treatment outcome</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Medizinische Hochschule Hannover (MHH) (3118)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par6">The prevalence of long-COVID varies across different studies, ranging from 12.7 and 43% depending on the source [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Various systematic reviews and meta-analyses have concluded that long-COVID is more prevalent in hospitalised adults with severe cases of COVID-19 than in those with milder cases that do not require hospitalisation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Patients with long-COVID can exhibit a wide range of symptoms. The most common symptoms are fatigue (47%), dyspnoea (32%), myalgia (25%), joint pain (20%), headache (18%), cough (18%), and chest pain (15%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Due to this wide variety of symptoms and the numerous potential comorbidities, many authors recommend a multimodal, multidisciplinary and individually tailored rehabilitation approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] which also includes physiotherapy and symptom self-management. Treatment is symptom-oriented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. As physiotherapy interventions show positive effects in the treatment of symptoms of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], fibromyalgia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] or HIV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] it is a worldwide accepted and recommended treatment in rehabilitation.</p><p id="Par7">Physiotherapists working in outpatient practices are uncertain about how to treat the long-term effects of the COVID-19 virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">A preliminary search on physiotherapy interventions was conducted in 2021 using the following databases: PubMed, Pedro, Embase and Cochrane Database. The search revealed no current or ongoing systematic or scoping reviews on the topic of physiotherapy treatment parameters. Nevertheless, the preliminary search demonstrated that multidisciplinary rehabilitation in infectious diseases and physiotherapy is a recommended treatment for post- and long-COVID symptoms, including pulmonary symptoms and pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">Systematic reviews conclude that rehabilitation using an exercise programme could improve both physical and psychological outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] as well as quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. However, the relevant training guidelines regarding the frequency, intensity, timing and type of exercise for long-term rehabilitation are not yet fully clear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Therefore, high-quality clinical studies need to be developed and implemented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Due to the lack of studies to date, rehabilitation is partly based on expert opinion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and on research into rehabilitation methods proven to be effective in treating similar symptoms in different contexts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">This scoping review aimed to summarise the available evidence on physiotherapy interventions and treatment parameters for managing patients with post- and long-COVID conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par11">This scoping review was registered in on Open Science Framework (Registry number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://osf.io/5k3tA">http://osf.io/5k3tA</ext-link>). As no patients and public were involved a positive vote of an ethical committee was not necessary.</p><p id="Par12">The proposed scoping review was conducted in accordance with the Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) methodology for scoping reviews [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) checklist extension for scoping reviews was used for reporting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">The methodological framework provided by the JBI was used. This methodological framework includes several steps from defining the research question and the eligibility criteria, conducting the literature research, study selection and data extraction. Additionally, a critical appraisal was conducted using the JBI critical appraisal tools. The quality of the methodology of the selected studies was evaluated with regard to the extracted data.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Review question</title><p id="Par14">The primary question guiding this scoping review is ‘What kind of physiotherapeutic interventions are used in both outpatient and inpatient settings for post- and long-COVID-19 patients?’ This question is divided into subquestions, as illustrated in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. <table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sub-questions of the scoping review</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Perspective</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Research questions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(1) Descriptive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">a) How many studies were published between January 2020 and February 2023 on physiotherapy interventions in patients with post- or long-COVID-Syndrome?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(2) Methods</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>a) Which research methods were used in the published literature?</p><p>b) What population characteristics were described in the published literature?</p><p>c) What definitions of post- and long-COVID-19 were used in the published literature?</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(3) Physiotherapy interventions</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>a) What types of physiotherapy interventions were reported in the published literature?</p><p>b) What was the reported frequency of the physiotherapeutic interventions?</p><p>c) What was the reported intensity of the physiotherapeutic interventions?</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(4) Physiotherapy and Post-/Long-COVID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>a) What was the impact of physiotherapy on post- or long-COVID-19 symptoms?</p><p>b) Were adverse events reported for physiotherapeutic interventions in patients with post- or long- COVID syndrome?</p><p>c) Were negative influences reported for parallel, applied physiotherapeutic interventions in patients with post- or long-COVID syndrome?</p><p>d) Were differences reported in- and outpatient interventions?</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p id="Par15">The decision to include only German and English language studies in this study was based on the authors’ proficiency in both, thus allowing for a more accurate analysis and interpretation of the data. Studies addressing post-COVID, post-acute COVID and long- COVID were included. Studies that also examined acute COVID-19 or COVID-19 in general were only considered eligible if the results pertaining to post- COVID, post-acute COVID or long- COVID were reported separately and in a comprehensible format. Randomised controlled trials, observational studies, case reports, umbrella reviews, rapid reviews focusing on post- and long-COVID-19 in adults were considered for inclusion in this scoping review, when published between January 2020 and February 2023. Qualitative studies were excluded due to the quantitative nature of the analysis in this study, which focuses on treatment details. Grey literature, text and opinion papers were not considered for inclusion in this scoping review.</p><p id="Par16">Studies analysing telemedicine and solely home-based workouts were not included in this study because the telemedicine approach has not yet been widely established in German physiotherapy care.</p><p id="Par17">Eligibility criteria are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. <table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Eligibility criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inclusion criteria</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Exclusion criteria</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Long-COVID-19</p><p>Post-COVID-19</p><p>Post-acute COVID</p><p>Adult patients aged above 18 years</p><p>Physiotherapy interventions</p><p>Physiotherapy interventions with additional home exercise workout</p><p>Randomised controlled trials, observational studies, case reports, umbrella reviews, rapid reviews</p><p>German or English language</p><p>Publication date between January 2020 and February 2023</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Acute COVID-19</p><p>Non-COVID-19</p><p>Other infectious diseases</p><p>Other respiratory disorders</p><p>Non-systematic reviews</p><p>Study protocols</p><p>Editorials, letters</p><p>Narrative reviews</p><p>Qualitative studies</p><p>Grey literature</p><p>Children and adolescent patients aged under 18 years</p><p>Telemedicine</p><p>Solely home-based workouts</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sources</title><p id="Par18">Databases PubMed, EBSCO, Scopus, Web of Science, Embase, PEDRO, Cochrane and WISO were searched by two independent researchers. A professional librarian was not involved.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Search strategy</title><p id="Par19">The search strategy is focused on published studies. The primary search strategy is based on the 4 domains of population, physiotherapy intervention, outcome, study design shown in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. The secondary search strategy involves the combination of these domains: ‘population AND physiotherapy intervention’, ‘population AND physiotherapy intervention AND outcome’, and ‘population AND physiotherapy intervention AND outcome AND study design’. <table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Search terms and MeSH</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Domain</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Search terms</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MeSH terms</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Population</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Long-COVID, post-COVID-19,</p><p>Post-acute COVID</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">”Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome”</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physiotherapy intervention</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physiotherapy, aerobic exercise, physical activity, resistance training, passive mobilisation, active mobilization, manual therapy, massage therapy, lymphatic drainage, electrotherapy, ultrasound, respiratory therapy, proprioceptive neuromuscular facilitation (PNF), Vojta, Bobath, pressure ulcer management, prevention</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">“Physical therapy modalities“OR “Physical therapy specialty“OR”Exercise therapy” OR “Exercise movement techniques” OR “Physical fitness“OR “Musculoskeletal manipulation” OR “Relaxation” OR “Stress, physiological” OR “Immobilisation” OR “Prevention &amp; control” OR “Manual lymphatic drainage“OR “Electric stimulation therapy“OR “Ultrasonic therapy“OR “Respiratory therapy“OR “Breathing exercises“</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcome</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical fitness, fatigue, general health, pain, return to work, physical health, mental health, mobility, vital capacity, dyspnoea, myalgia, arthralgia, functional capacity, health-related quality of life, stress, range of movement, patient-reported outcome measures</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">“Physical fitness“OR “Fatigue“OR “Mental health” OR “Return to work“OR “Pain management” OR “Vital capacity“OR “Myalgia“OR “Arthralgia” OR “Quality of life“OR “Patient-reported outcome measures“OR “Health” OR “Health status”</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study design</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Randomised control trial</p><p>Observational studies</p><p>Case reports</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">“Randomised controlled trial” OR “Observational study” OR “Case reports”</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par20">The search terms and relevant keywords were identified and deposited with medical subject headings (MeSH) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The strategies for the literature search are listed in the Appendix <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">I</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Screening process</title><p id="Par21">Two independent researchers collected the identified literature in separate Excel sheets and removed duplicates. Titles and abstracts were then screened by two independent reviewers to ascertain whether they met the inclusion criteria for the scoping review. Thereafter, the full-text articles that met the inclusion criteria in the title and abstract screening process were screened independently by the two researchers with the aim of identifying the inclusion criteria. The reasons for the exclusion of sources of evidence at full-text that do not meet the inclusion criteria were recorded and reported in the scoping review. In the next step both independent researchers compared their search results. Any disagreement was resolved through discussion or consulting with a third independent researcher.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Critical appraisal</title><p id="Par22">Additionally, a critical appraisal of each included article was conducted by the two independent researchers using the JBI critical appraisal tools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The quality assessment evaluated the methodological quality with regard to the extracted data on physiotherapy interventions and treatment parameters. Thereafter, both researchers compared the results of the critical appraisal. In the event of differences in the quality report the results were discussed or a third independent researcher was involved for reaching a consensus.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Data extraction</title><p id="Par23">Data was extracted from the included papers by two reviewers independently using a data extraction tool that has been developed by the reviewers. The data extraction tool was created in MS Word providing specific details on the study design, research method, population characteristics, definition of post- and long- COVID-19, intervention and key findings relevant to the review question/s, e. g. these included frequency and intensity of the intervention, the outcome of the study and adverse events.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><p id="Par24">The literature search was conducted in March 2023.</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Descriptive</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>How many studies were published between January 2020 and February 2023 on physiotherapy interventions in patients with post- or long-COVID syndrome?</title><p id="Par25">45.801 articles were screened on the inclusion criteria. 19 papers remained. After reduction of duplets 15 articles remained for the title and abstract screening process after which 9 studies were excluded. Finally, 6 studies were included in the scoping review (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). A flow diagram can be found in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analysis (PRISMA) flow diagram [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12913_2025_13631_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Illustration of the included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Author</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Country</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study design</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Objective</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Post-COVID-19</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</p><p>DOI: 10.47750/pnr.2023.14.S02.87.</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2023</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Egypt</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Randomized controlled trial,</p><p>prospective, single-blinded, two groups, before and post-test analysis,</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">’to determine how active cycle breathing affects specific pulmonary outcomes in patients having post-COVID syndrome.’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</p><p>DOI: 10.2340/jrm.v54.3972.</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Egypt</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Randomized controlled trial,</p><p>Study group and control group</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">’to evaluate the combined effect of manual DR and IMT compared with IMT alone on selected parameters (blood pressure, dyspnoea, high serum lactate, and fatigue levels) in men with post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 syndrome.’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</p><p>DOI: 10.1177/026921552110369</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Saudi Arabia,</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Randomized, single-blinded,</p><p>Low intensity aerobic training group (LAT) versus high intensity aerobic training group (HAT)</p><p>prospective, clinical study</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">’to find and compare the clinical and psychological effects of low and high-intensity aerobic training combined with resistance training in community-dwelling older men with post-COVID-19 sarcopenia symptoms.’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rutkowski S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</p><p>DOI: 10.3389/fpubh.2023.1121554.</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2023</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poland, United States of America</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Randomized controlled trial;</p><p>VR group versus control group both with 4 pulmonary rehabilitation models</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">’to propose an innovative comprehensive intervention based on a pulmonary rehabilitation programme for patients with post-acute sequelae of COVID-19.’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</p><p>DOI: 10.1093/ptj/pzab098.</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">United States of America</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case Report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">’to present the clinical presentation and physical therapist management for a patient with post–COVID syndrome.’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>SARS-CoV-2: post-COVID-19</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</p><p>DOI: 10.1002/pri.1938.</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peru</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case Report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">describe ‘an intervention based on musculoskeletal physiotherapy in a post-COVID-19 adult woman with physical sequelae’. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Which research methods were used in the published literature?</title><p id="Par26">The majority of the studies were published in 2022 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5) concentrating on ‘post-COVID-19’. No published study focusing on ‘long-COVID-19’was identified. One study used ‘SARS-CoV-2’ and defined the subtype of ‘post-COVID-19’ in the abstracts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Two-thirds of the 6 included studies were randomized controlled trials (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>What population characteristics were described in the published literature?</title><p id="Par27">The published population characteristics are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. <table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Population characteristics of the included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Author</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Population</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Healthcare delivery setting</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Post-COVID-19</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>60 patients both sexes (31 female, 29 male), with difficulty in breathing during activities of daily living (dyspnoea, cough and sputum production)</p><p>Age in years: 45.62 ± 2.47 versus 45.7 ± 2.33</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>52 men with post-COVID-19 syndrome,</p><p>Age in years: 40.00 ± 3.36 versus 39.70 ± 3.55</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outpatient</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>65 men, post COVID 19 sarcopenia</p><p>Age in years: 63.2 ± 3.1 versus 64.1 ± 3.2</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>32 patients (20 female, 12 male) with a confirmation from a primary care physician of having had COVID-19 infection,</p><p>Age in years: 57,8 ± 4,92</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inpatient</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Woman 37 years old, day 62 after initial infection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outpatient</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>SARS-CoV-2: post-COVID-19</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Woman, 60 years old, 28 days after initial infection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outpatient (home visit)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>What definitions of post- and long-COVID-19 were used in the published literature?</title><p id="Par28">Hardly any definitions for post- and long-COVID-19 were identified. The authors of the included literature referred to other authors and described the possible symptoms of this post infectious condition (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). <table-wrap id="Tab6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Definitions of post- and long-COVID-19 used in the included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Author</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Definition post- and long-COVID-19</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Post-COVID-19</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">’ … PCS is a condition in which signs and symptoms persist for more than 4 weeks following an acute infection.’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No definition identified</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No definition identified</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No definition identified</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">’two definitions of post-acute COVID-19 are given: (1) ongoing symptomatic COVID-19 for people who still have symptoms between 4 and 12 weeks after the start of acute symptoms; and (2) post-COVID-19 syndrome for people who still have symptoms for more than 12 weeks after the start of acute symptoms.’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>SARS-CoV-2: post-COVID-19</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No definition identified</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Physiotherapy interventions</title><sec id="Sec18"><title>What types of physiotherapy interventions were reported in the published literature?</title><p id="Par29">The research of physiotherapy management of post- and long-COVID-19 identified on the following key areas of focus: respiratory therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], aerobic training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] or strength training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. One study reported ‘hands-on’ physiotherapy interventions like manual therapy and TENS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The interventions are reported in Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>. <table-wrap id="Tab7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Reported physiotherapy interventions and treatment parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Category</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interventions</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Frequency and duration in therapy</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intensity</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Frequency in general</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Respiratory therapy</td><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Post-COVID-19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- Respiratory exercise with active cycle of breathing technique, controlled breathing,</p><p>- thoracic expansion exercises, forced expiration technique,</p><p>- active diaphragma release techniques,</p><p>- pursed-lip abdominal breathing exercise</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- 2-3 times: 20–30 seconds controlled breathing, Thoracic expansion exercises 3–4 times, normal breath 20–30 seconds or 6 breaths</p><p>- daily 3–4 times maximum of 3 min, 10 breaths, 20 seconds rest</p><p>- 4-6 seconds</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1-3 sessions per week for 12 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- Diaphragm release</p><p>- Inspiration muscle Training with tool</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2x 10 breaths, 1 minute rest</p><p>4 min, twice a day 30 breaths, 2 min rest</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 sessions per week for 6 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- High-intensity pulmonary programme with breathing exercise</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 sessions per week for 3 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diaphragm breathing techniques</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 sessions in 8 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Aerobic training</td><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Post-COVID-19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- Treadmill</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 min</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Increased each day regarding to patients’ tolerability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 sessions per week for 12 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- Treadmill</p><p>- Cycle ergometer</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>20 min</p><p>10 min</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low-intensity aerobic training (40-60% of maximum heart rate) or high-intensity aerobic training (60-80% of maximum heart peak)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 sessions per week for 8 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- Cycle ergometer with or without Virtual Reality</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Twice a day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Heart rate increase of 90%/80%/70%/20-30%</p><p>50-70 RPM</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 sessions per week for 3 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- Crosstrainer, treadmill, jogging, upper extremity bicycle ergometer</p><p>- Dancing</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15-45 min</p><p>3-6 min</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- Initial level 60-80% Heart rate max,</p><p>Increased to mRPE scale 4/10 (somewhat hard) to 6/10 (hard)</p><p>- cadence 80 bpm</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 sessions in 8 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Strength training</td><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Post-COVID-19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- Active limb exercises with weight machines, free weights, elastic bands</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10 - 45 min</p><p>3 sets of 8–12 repetition with progression to 15 repetitions, with 1 min rest</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1-3 sessions per week for 12 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- With weights</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 times 10 repetitions, 1 min rest</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 sessions per week for 8 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- General fitness exercises, resistance training and relaxation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 sessions per week for 3 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- Weight machines, dumbbells, ankle weights, Core stability</p><p>- Home workout with elastic bands</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10-20 min</p><p>3 times per week 3x15 repetitions</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 sessions in 8 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="8" colspan="1">‘Hands-on’ physiotherapy</td><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Post-COVID-19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- Stretching for warm- up and cool-down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">SARS-CoV-2: post-acute COVID-19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- Stretching</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">From 4<sup>th</sup> session on</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 sessions in 5 weeks; 1:15 h - 1:50 h</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- Transcutaneous electric nerve stimulation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Analgesic type, tetrapolar, 20 min</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60-100Hz</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 sessions in 5 weeks; 1:15 h - 1:50 h</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- Cyriax Deep Transverse Friction Massage bilateral brachial biceps and supraspinosus muscle</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 sessions in 5 weeks; 1:15 h - 1:50 h</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- kinesitherapy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4<sup>th</sup> to 5<sup>th</sup></p><p>6<sup>th</sup> to 10<sup>th</sup></p><p>11<sup>th</sup> to 15th</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Passive</p><p>Active</p><p>body segment weight, increasing with 1/2 kg, 1 kg and up to 2 Kg</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 sessions in 5 weeks; 1:15 h - 1:50 h</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- Maitlands’ manual therapy spine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6<sup>th</sup> to 10<sup>th</sup> session</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 sessions in 5 weeks; 1:15 h - 1:50 h</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>What was the reported frequency of the physiotherapeutic interventions?</title><p id="Par30">The frequency varied from 3 to 12 weeks, with 1 to 5 sessions weekly, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. It is shown in Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>What was the reported intensity of the physiotherapeutic interventions?</title><p id="Par31">The intensity was not reported in every intervention. The intensity practiced found in the included literature is shown in Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Physiotherapy and post- and/or long-COVID-19</title><sec id="Sec22"><title>What was the impact of physiotherapy on post- or long-COVID symptoms?</title><p id="Par32">Overall physiotherapy resulted in a change in health status parameters, including a reduction in fatigue levels, an improvement in respiratory function, and an enhancement in physical capacity. Arterial oxygen saturation and partial pressure of oxygen increased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. However, muscle mass remained unaltered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The results are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab8" ref-type="table">8</xref>. <table-wrap id="Tab8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Impact of physiotherapy on health status parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Health status parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcome</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcome scores or scales</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Statistics</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue Assessment Scale</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (% of change); p-value</p><p>Group A 14.03 (35.92); 0.001</p><p>Group B 23.6 (61.05); 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue Severity Scale</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (SD); p-value</p><p>Study group from 43.36 (±5.25) to 28.68 (±6.01); &lt; 0.001</p><p>control group from 42.47 (±5.18) to 39.77 (±5.89); 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Borg scale while 6-minute walk test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean (median); p-value</p><p>VR group from 3.0 (1.0) to 2.0 (1.0); 0.055</p><p>Control group from 3.0 (1.0) to 2.0 (1.0); 0.010</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subjective description</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Walking distance</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">6-minute walk test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (% of change); p-value</p><p>Group A − 53.03 (11.09); 0.001</p><p>Group B − 105.27 (21.61); 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (SD); p-value</p><p>Study group 56.50 m 13.53%; &lt; 0.001</p><p>Control group from 16.50 m 3.92%; &lt; 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean ± SD in m; p-value</p><p>VR group from 502 ± 48.8 to 558 ± 76; 0.010</p><p>Control group from 512 ± 54.3 to 552 ± 49.1; &lt; 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Difference: from 312 m to 511 m (+199 m)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arterial oxygen saturation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arterial blood gas analysis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (% of change); p-value</p><p>Group A − 2.4 (2.70); 0.001</p><p>Group B − 5.7 (6.43); 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">partial pressure of oxygen</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arterial blood gas analysis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (% of change); p-value</p><p>Group A − 2.62 (3.50); 0.001</p><p>Group B − 9.25 (12.41); 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">partial pressure of carbon dioxide</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arterial blood gas analysis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (% of change); p-value</p><p>Group A 1.64 (4.35); 0.001</p><p>Group B 3.95 (10.75); 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arterial blood pressure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sphygmomanometer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (% of change); p-value</p><p>Study group</p><p>Systolic blood pressure −25.00 mmHg (16.67); &lt; 0.001</p><p>Diastolic blood pressure −17.10 mmHg (18.08); &lt; 0.001</p><p>Control group</p><p>Systolic blood pressure −3.73 mmHg (2.48); 0.032</p><p>Diastolic blood pressure −0.90 mmHg (0.95); 0.01</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Serum lactate level</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Veinous blood sample</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference (% of change); p-value</p><p>Study group −0.82 mmol/L (51.57); &lt; 0.001</p><p>control group −0.27 mmol/L (17.65); &lt; 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Muscle mass</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">↔</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Magnetic resonance imaging</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>MRI – mid arm in cm<sup>2</sup></p><p>Group Mean ± SD in kg; p-value</p><p>Baseline LAT 55.9 ± 1.7, HAT 56.3 ± 1.; 0.227</p><p>4 weeks LAT 57.5 ± 1.0, HAT 57.9 ± 0.9; 0.070</p><p>8 weeks LAT 58.9 ± 0.6, HAT 59.0 ± 0.5; 0.432</p><p>6 months LAT 61.4 ± 0.5, HAT 61.5 ± 0.2; 0.256</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>MRI – mid thigh in cm<sup>2</sup></p><p>Group Mean ± SD in kg; p-value</p><p>Baseline LAT 63.4 ± 0.8, HAT 63.5 ± 0.8; 0.587</p><p>4 weeks LAT 65.3 ± 0.6, HAT 65.5 ± 0.6; 0.150</p><p>8 weeks LAT 68.4 ± 0.6, HAT 68.5 ± 0.6; 0.469</p><p>6 months LAT 72.5 ± 0.8, HAT 72.6 ± 0.8; 0.587</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>MRI - mid calf in cm<sup>2</sup></p><p>Group Mean ± SD in kg; p-value</p><p>Baseline LAT 60.2 ± 1.1, HAT 60.2 ± 1.1; 1.000</p><p>4 weeks LAT 65.2 ± 0.6, HAT 65.2 ± 0.6; 1.000</p><p>8 weeks LAT 66.3 ± 0.5, HAT 66.4 ± 0.5; 0.386</p><p>6 months LAT 68.7 ± 0.5, HAT 68.7 ± 0.5; 1.000</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kinesiophobia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tampa scale of kinesiophobia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean ± SD; p-value</p><p>Baseline LAT 32.1 ± 1.0, HAT 32.3 ± 0.9; 0.362</p><p>4 weeks LAT 23.5 ± 0.9, HAT 29.9 ± 0.9; 0.001</p><p>8 weeks LAT 18.0 ± 0.9, HAT 24.5 ± 1.4; 0.001</p><p>6 months LAT 13.5 ± 1.0, HAT 18.2 ± 1.0; 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risk of falls</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Timed-Up and Go Test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">From 9.0 s to 7.3 s</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Functional status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Short Performance Physical Battery</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total from 11 to 12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quality of life</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sarcopenia and Quality of Life questionnaire</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean ± SD; p-value</p><p>Baseline LAT 57.3 ± 1.0, HAT 57.7 ± 1.0; 0.085</p><p>4 weeks LAT 63.0 ± 0.7, HAT 58.8 ± 0.9; 0.001</p><p>8 weeks LAT 69.0 ± 1.0, HAT 60.5 ± 0.8; 0.001</p><p>6 months LAT 72.6 ± 1.0, HAT 62.2 ± 0.8; 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Health-related Quality of Life Questionnaire (Eq-5D-5 L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Eq-5D-5 L (VAS 0–100): 50 to 40</p><p>Eq-5D-5 L (mean): 2.6 to 2.8</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cognitive function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Montreal Cognitive Assessment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 to 28 (out of 30)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↔</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time-up and Go Test with cognitive component</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">From −34% to − 21% difference</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Distress</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Impact of Events Scale-Revised</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total: from 36 to 46</p><p>Mean response: from 1.6 to 2.1</p><p>Intrusion mean: from 1.6 to 1.9</p><p>Avoidance mean: from 0.75 to 1.25</p><p>Hyperarousal mean: from 2.8 to 3.5</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Perceived Stress Scale</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean ± SD; p-value</p><p>VR group from 23.1 ± 4.2 to 20.7 ± 3.5; 0.015</p><p>Control group from 23.8 ± 3.1. to 22.2 ± 3.8; 0.004</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Lung function</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">↔</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Spirometry</p><p>(expiratory volume for 1 s (FEV<sub>1</sub>); forced vital capacity (FVC); forced expiratory volume in one second of vital capacity (FEV<sub>1</sub>/VC))</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean ± SD (mean); p-value</p><p>FEV<sub>1</sub> in l</p><p>VR group from 2.8 ± 0.66 to 2.77 ± 0.68; 0.708</p><p>Control group from 2.72 ± 0.60 to 2.76 ± 0.61; 0.879</p><p>FVC in l</p><p>VR group from 3.46 ± 0.78 to 3.56 ± 0.8; 0.087</p><p>Control group from 3.49 ± 0.86 to 3.5 ± 0.85; 0.168</p><p>FEV<sub>1</sub>/VC in %</p><p>VR group from 84.3 (6.89) to 81.4 (7.77); 0.028</p><p>Control group from 82.4 (5.32) to 83.2 (10.1); 0.130</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Plethysmography</p><p>(total lung capacity (TLC))</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean ± SD in l; p-value</p><p>VR group from 5.18 ± 1.2 to 5.39 ± 1.1; 0.288</p><p>Control group from 4.9 ± 1.2 to 5.27 ± 1.0; 0.070</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Dyspnoea</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Modified Medical Research Council</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean difference; p-value</p><p>Study group 48.89%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001</p><p>control group 12.81%; 0.001</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">From 2 to 1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Borg scale while 6-minute walk test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean (median); p-value</p><p>VR group from 2.0 (3.0) to 0.0 (2.0); 0.033</p><p>Control group from 2.0 (2.75) to 0.5 (2.0); 0.004</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Muscle strength</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical Research Council sum score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">From 55 to 59</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lower extremity unilateral leg press</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2-lb resistance (Watts): from 14.3 to 17.7</p><p>10% of body weight resistance (Watts): from 88 to 134</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑↓</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Handgrip dynamometer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Right: from 24 kg to 33 kg</p><p>Left: from 36 kg to 34 kg</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Group Mean ± SD in kg; p-value</p><p>Baseline LAT 28.4 ± 0.7, HAT 28.5 ± 0.6; 0.505</p><p>4 weeks LAT 29.4 ± 0.5, HAT 29.2 ± 0.6; 0.118</p><p>8 weeks LAT 31.5 ± 0.6, HAT 29.8 ± 0.5; 0.001</p><p>6 months LAT 34.3 ± 0.8, HAT 30.4 ± 0.8; 0.003</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muscle strength</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Daniels Scale</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">From 2 to 4 out of 5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pain reduction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↓</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Numeric Pain Scale</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">From 10 to 3 out of 10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range of motion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Goniometer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Shoulder movements in ° Right pre/post physiotherapy; Left pre/post physiotherapy</p><p>Flexion 100/160; 120/160</p><p>Extension 20/40; 30/40</p><p>Abduction 90/150; 120/160</p><p>Adduction 10/20; 30/30</p><p>External rotation 60/80; 80/80</p><p>Internal rotation 50/55; 60/60</p><p>Elbow movements in ° Right pre/post physiotherapy; Left pre/post physiotherapy</p><p>Flexion 120/130; 130/140</p><p>Extension 0/0; 0/0</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Balance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unipodal Station Test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">From 3 s to 8 s</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Basic activities of daily living</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Instrumental activities of daily living</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">↑</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N. a.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Santos S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Legend</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><p>↑ increasing</p><p>↔ unchanged</p><p>↓ decreased</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Were adverse events reported for physiotherapeutic interventions in patients with post- or long- COVID syndrome?</title><p id="Par33">In one case report the quality of life decreased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. But in most cases patients felt better regarding the quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec2953"><title>Were negative influences reported for parallel, applied physiotherapeutic interventions in patients with post- or long-COVID syndrome?</title><p id="Par34">Due to a lack of information, it is not possible to make a statement on this issue.</p></sec><sec id="Sec295153"><title>Were differences reported inpatient and out patient interventions?</title><p id="Par35">Table <xref rid="Tab9" ref-type="table">9</xref> summarizes the identified practiced interventions and treatment parameters as the general frequency in mean. Only the 6 studies focusing on the subtype post-COVID-19 were considered because they provided enough information. <table-wrap id="Tab9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Summarization on identified practised therapy interventions, their parameters and general frequency in mean for post-COVID-19</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Healthcare delivery setting</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Therapy category</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intervention</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">General frequency<break/>(in mean)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Inpatient and</p><p>Outpatient</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Respiratory therapy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Diaphragma release</p><p>Breathing exercises</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3 sessions per week</p><p>for 7 weeks</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</p><p>Nagy EN et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</p><p>Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</p><p>Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Inpatient and</p><p>Outpatient</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aerobic training</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Treadmill;</p><p>Cycle ergometer</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3–20 minutes</p><p>40–60% of maximum heart rate</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 sessions per week for 9 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</p><p>Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</p><p>Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Inpatient and</p><p>Outpatient</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Strength training</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Free exercises, weights or weight machines</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 sets of 8–20 repititions, 1 minute rest</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 sessions per week for 9 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ali AA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</p><p>Nambi G et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</p><p>Mayer KP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Critical appraisal</title><p id="Par36">The studies selected for inclusion were subjected to critical appraisal by two independent researchers with extensive experience in the field of rehabilitation research, utilizing the JBI critical appraisal tools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The quality assessment was conducted to evaluate the methodological quality of the data to be extracted from the included articles. No manuscript was excluded during the critical appraisal process. The overall quality of the included literature was determined to be moderate. An overview of the critical appraisal is provided in Table <xref rid="Tab11" ref-type="table">10</xref>. <table-wrap id="Tab10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label> Table 11</label><caption><p>Overview on critical appraisal of the case reports following JBI critical appraisal tools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mayer et al.</bold> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Santos et al.</bold> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient characteristics clearly described</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient history clearly described</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current clinical condition clearly described</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diagnostic tests/assessment methods clearly described</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intervention clearly described</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-interventional clinical condition clearly described</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adverse/unanticipated events identified and described</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Take-away lessons provided</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Legend</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>y = yes</p><p>n = no</p><p>uc = unclear</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab11" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 10</label><caption><p>Overview on critical appraisal of the randomized controlled trials following JBI critical appraisal tools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Domain</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Selection and allocation</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Administration of intervention/exposure</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Assessment, detection, and measurement of the outcome</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participant retention</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Statistical conclusion validity</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Author</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Question no.</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Nagy et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnoea: Modified Medical Research Council</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue: Fatigue Severity Scale</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Walking distance: 6-minute walk test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arterial blood pressure Sphygmomanometer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Serum lactate level: Veinous blood sample</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Nambi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kinesiophobie: Tampa scale of kinesiophobia</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muscle mass: Magnetic resonance imaging</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muscle strength: Handgrip dynamometer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quality of life: Sarcopenia and Quality of Life questionnaire</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Rutkowski et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue: Borg scale while 6-minute walk test</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">uc</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Walking distance: 6-minute walk test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Distress: Perceived Stress Scale</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lung function:</p><p>a) Spirometry</p><p>b) Plethysmography</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>a) y</p><p>b) y</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>a) y</p><p>b) y</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>a) y</p><p>b) y</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dyspnoe: Borg scale while 6-minute walk test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Ali et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fatigue: Fatigue Assessment Scale</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">uc</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">uc</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">uc</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">uc</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Walking Distance: 6-minute walk test</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arterial oxygen saturation: Arterial blood gas analysis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Partial pressure of oxygen: Arterial blood gas analysis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Partial pressure of carbon dioxide: Arterial blood gas analysis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">y</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Legend</td><td align="left" colspan="14" rowspan="1"><p>y = yes</p><p>n = no</p><p>uc = unclear</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par37">This scoping review aimed to give an overview on physiotherapeutic interventions and treatment parameters published in the scientific literature. The number of identified studies shows a gap in research on the topic which is contradictory to the recommendations of physiotherapy in the treatment of post- and long-COVID condition and the high number of prescribed physiotherapeutic remedies in the treatment of post- and long-COVID-19.</p><p id="Par38">The included literature referring to physiotherapy interventions focus on respiratory therapy, aerobic and strength training. This scoping review reveals that the different interventions and techniques of respiratory therapy, aerobic and strength training were combined in each separate session. The majority of studies employed a set of three, with 10 to 15 repetitions and a one-minute rest interval between sets.</p><p id="Par39">Only one of the included studies documented the practice of traditional physiotherapy techniques, including transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation, friction massage and manual therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. This finding points out a research gap concerning the diversity of physiotherapeutic interventions in the treatment of patients with post-and long-COVID-19.</p><p id="Par40">The assessments used in the studies were standardized assessments. Some of them do not meet the profile of physiotherapy, like spirometry or blood serum analysis. Others are highly practicable in the setting of outpatient physiotherapy, like the Borg scale or the 6-minute walk test. The included studies indicate reduction in fatigue, enhancements in respiratory function, and improvements in physical function. The quality of life increased in most cases, with the exception of one patient in one case report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Pain is only assessed in one case report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. This finding raises the question whether pain reduction is a relevant outcome for post- and long-COVID-19 patients.</p><p id="Par41">Medical guidelines and recommendations emphasize the treatment of physiotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Several studies and reviews have demonstrated the positive impact of multidisciplinary rehabilitation programmes, even in infectious diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The post- and long-COVID-19 physiotherapy is based on the treatment of symptoms associated with certain diseases such as pain in fibromyalgia, cancer related fatigue or dyspnea in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Exercise programmes have been evaluated in post- and long-COVID research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Commonly exercise programmes are carried out by sports and physiotherapists. A ‘slow progressive approach’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] or ‘pacing’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] is required in the treatment implying that therapeutic interventions must be introduced gradually and cautiously to promote adaption and minimize the risk of adverse reaction or symptom exacerbation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. This therapeutic approach is demonstrated in the included case reports as they provide concrete insights to the physiotherapy treatment in time course [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Further studies focusing on gradual adaption of therapeutic interventions are needed as they are recommended for practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par42">The definitions of post- and long-COVID syndrome vary slightly with respect to the onset of symptoms following an acute infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Authors refer to the work of other authors or focus on describing the complex symptoms of this condition. This circumstance appears to influence the synthesis of physiotherapeutic interventions as the treatments provided were not aligned with the ICD-10 diagnosis.</p><p id="Par43">Study limitations can be identified on the search strategy as no professional librarian supported the literature search. The involvement of a librarian could have improved the methodological quality of the literature search. as the literature research was limited to studies German and English published studies it may have led to the exclusion of relevant studies in other languages. Furthermore, grey literature was not considered, as it is only partially accessible and not published in a standardized manner. To ensure transparency and reproducibility the literature search was limited to peer-reviewed sources from established academic databases.</p><p id="Par44">The number of identified studies publish until February 2023 addressing physiotherapy in post- and long-COVID-19 is very limited which also influences the statistical reporting. Study designs, outcomes and involved patient characteristics are very heterogenous making a direct comparison and quantitative synthesis difficult. The data was summarized descriptively which inhibits to draw conclusions about effectiveness of physiotherapy treatment in post- and long-COVID patients. Furthermore, treatment interventions were not described adequately detailed. For those reasons case reports were also included in the search beneath the low level of evidence, as they provide detailed insights on common therapeutic interventions applied from session to session.</p><p id="Par45">However, from the findings of this scoping review objectives for further research can be derived as the gap in research is evident. Physiotherapy interventions addressing symptoms need to be evaluated with a higher methodological design and a higher sample size. A concrete definition of the included post- or long-COVID-19 diagnosis to specify the indication of physiotherapy is mandatory. Therefore, the ICD-10 codes could be useful. Nevertheless, influencing characteristics, especially in case reports, should be considered in health research as they provide a holistic picture of the participants. Therefore, the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) contextual factors are appropriate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Collecting these variables allows a more comprehensive understanding of participant profiles and the differentiation of treatment effects. These findings may contribute the development of clinical prediction rules by generating relevant predictors associated with treatment response within the specific clinical context.</p><p id="Par46">Only a limited number of the identified publications provide detailed information regarding the specific treatment modalities practiced. The treatment methods and parameters vary across studies. For reproducibility, further research and translation into the health system it is necessary to provide detailed descriptions of the processes and the applied interventions. For example, there is a need to distinguish between a passive mobilization of the spine in general or a mobilization of a specific vertebral segment or a manipulation of a specific vertebral segment. Functional exercises need to be described more detailed additionally with pictures or videos. Standardized assessments need to be validated in the context of post- and long-COVID-19.</p><p id="Par47">As physiotherapy comprises a broader spectrum of interventions beyond respiratory therapy, aerobic exercise, and strength training there are further physiotherapeutic approaches that need to be evaluated in pilot studies and randomized controlled trials. Future research should examine the efficacy of interventions such as manual therapy, passive mobilization, massage techniques, lymphatic drainage, relaxation therapies and neuromuscular treatment strategies in the context of different COVID-19 subtypes. Educational material used for training the therapists and assessors in the study also need to be provided in the publications for reproducibility and in particular to ensure the translation into practice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par48">This scoping review highlights a high demand for research in the treatment of post- and long-COVID patients for the in-person physiotherapy setting. To ensure reproducibility and clinical applicability, a detailed description of all practiced physiotherapy techniques is essential. However, the results of this scoping review provide physiotherapists treatment options for patients with post- and long-COVID-19 as physiotherapy demonstrated to have positive trends in supporting health outcomes among patients with post- and long-COVID condition.</p></sec><sec id="Sec524" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12913_2025_13631_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank the ZVK-Stiftung e. V. and colleagues from the Department of Rehabilitation and Sports Medicine, Physical and Rehabilitative Medicine, Hannover Medical School, for their support and advice.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JG and AB were involved in conceptualising, drafting and revising the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript. JG planned the project. JG and AB were actively developing the scoping review protocol. CS was involved in writing the manuscript and contributed to the linguistic improvement. The funders were not involved in the study design or writing the manuscript. JG was major contributor in writing the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL. Funding was provided by the ZVK-Stiftung e. V. (award/grant number: N/A). The funder was not involved in the study design, review process or writing the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on the reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par49">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par50">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par51">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballering</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Zo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosmalen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistence of somatic symptoms after COVID-19 in the Netherlands an observational cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2022</year><volume>400</volume><issue>10350</issue><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01214-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35934007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9352274</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Ballering AV, van Zo S, Hartman TC, Rosmalen J. Persistence of somatic symptoms after COVID-19 in the Netherlands an observational cohort study. Lancet. 2022;400(10350):452–61. 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01214-4<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35934007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01214-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9352274</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Logue</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franko</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magedson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequelae in adults at 6 months after COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open Open</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e210830</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.0830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7896197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33606031</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Logue JK, Franko NM, McCulloch DJ, McDonald D, Magedson A, Wolf CR, et al. Sequelae in adults at 6 months after COVID-19 infection. JAMA Netw Open. 2011;4:e210830. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.0830<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.0830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7896197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33606031</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haupert</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global prevalence of post-coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) condition or long COVID: a meta-analysis and systematic review</article-title><source>The J Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>226</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiac136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35429399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047189</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Chen C, Haupert SR, Zimmermann L, Shi X, Fritsche LG, Mukherjee B. Global prevalence of post-coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) condition or long COVID: a meta-analysis and systematic review. The J Infect Dis. 2022;226(9):1593–607. 10.1093/infdis/jiac136<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35429399</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/infdis/jiac136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047189</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Mahoney</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Routen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekezie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The prevalence and long-term health effects of long covid among hospitalised and non-hospitalised populations: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2023</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>101762</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36474804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9714474</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">O’Mahoney LL, Routen A, Gillies C, Ekezie W, Welford A, Zhang A, et al. The prevalence and long-term health effects of long covid among hospitalised and non-hospitalised populations: a systematic review and meta-analysis. EClinicalMedicine. 2023;55:101762. 10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101762<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36474804</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9714474</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiyegbusi</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMullan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symptoms, complications and management of long COVID: a review</article-title><source>J R Soc Of Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>114</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01410768211032850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8450986</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Aiyegbusi OL, Hughes SE, Turner G, Rivera SC, McMullan C, Chandan JS, et al. Symptoms, complications and management of long COVID: a review. J R Soc of Med. 2021;114(9):428–42. 10.1177/01410768211032850<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265229</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/01410768211032850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8450986</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Limbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merkl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakab</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of a three-week inpatient pulmonary rehabilitation program for patients after COVID-19: a prospective observational study</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Pub Health And Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>1</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>9001</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18179001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8430843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34501596</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Hayden MC, Limbach M, Schuler M, Merkl S, Schwarzl G, Jakab K, et al. Effectiveness of a three-week inpatient pulmonary rehabilitation program for patients after COVID-19: a prospective observational study. Int J Environ Res Pub Health. 2021;1(17):9001. 10.3390/ijerph18179001<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph18179001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8430843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34501596</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nopp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klok</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gattinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonbank</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Outpatient pulmonary rehabilitation in patients with long COVID improves exercise capacity, functional status, Dyspnea, fatigue, and quality of life</article-title><source>Respiration</source><year>2022</year><volume>101</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000522118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35203084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9059007</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Nopp S, Moik F, Klok FA, Gattinger D, Petrovic M, Vonbank K, et al. Outpatient pulmonary rehabilitation in patients with long COVID improves exercise capacity, functional status, Dyspnea, fatigue, and quality of life. Respiration. 2022;101(6):593–601. 10.1159/000522118<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35203084</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000522118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9059007</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker-Davies</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Sullivan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senaratne</surname><given-names>KPP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cranley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dharm-Datta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Stanford Hall consensus statement for post-COVID-19 rehabilitation</article-title><source>Br J Sports Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>54</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2020-102596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32475821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7418628</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Barker-Davies RM, O’Sullivan O, Senaratne KPP, Baker P, Cranley M, Dharm-Datta S, et al. The Stanford Hall consensus statement for post-COVID-19 rehabilitation. Br J Sports Med. 2020;54(16):949–59. 10.1136/bjsports-2020-102596<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32475821</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bjsports-2020-102596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7418628</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE). COVID-19 rapid guideline: managing the long-term effects of COVID-19. 2020, 2025. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng188">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng188</ext-link>. Accessed 4. June 2025.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33555768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gloeckl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarosch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary rehabilitation and exercise training in chronic obstructive pumonary disease</article-title><source>Dtsch Arztebl Int</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3238/arztebl.2018.0117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29526182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5852307</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Gloeckl R, Schneeberger T, Jarosch I, Kenn K. Pulmonary rehabilitation and exercise training in chronic obstructive pumonary disease. Dtsch Arztebl Int. 2018, Feb, 23;115(8):117–23. 10.3238/arztebl.2018.0117<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29526182</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3238/arztebl.2018.0117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5852307</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kuz U, Maliuvanchuk S, Herych R, Herych P. Efficacy and safety of physical therapy in patients with stage III COPD during ambulatory rehabilitation. J Med Life. 2023, Dec;16(12):1769–75. 10.25122/jml-2023-0237<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.25122/jml-2023-0237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10994626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38585540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Troosters</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demeyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabinovich</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary rehabilitation and physical interventions</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2023</year><volume>32</volume><issue>168</issue><fpage>220222</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0222-2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37286219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10245142</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Troosters T, Janssens W, Demeyer H, Rabinovich RA. Pulmonary rehabilitation and physical interventions. Eur Respir Rev. 2023;32(168):220222. 10.1183/16000617.0222-2022. 2023 Jun 7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37286219</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/16000617.0222-2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10245142</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Araújo</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeSantana</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Physical therapy modalities for treating fibromyalgia</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12688/f1000research.17176.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6979469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32047594</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="book">Araújo FM, DeSantana JM. Physical therapy modalities for treating fibromyalgia. F1000Research 2019, 8(F1000 Faculty Rev):2030. 2019. 10.12688/f1000research.17176.1<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12688/f1000research.17176.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6979469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32047594</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banda</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mwale</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chimwala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malimus</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chisati</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Common impairments and functional limitations of HIV sequelae that require physiotherapy rehabilitation in the medical wards at Queen Elizabeth central hospital, Malawi: a cross sectional study</article-title><source>Malawi Med J</source><year>2019</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/mmj.v31i3.2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31839885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6895382</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Banda GT, Mwale G, Chimwala M, Malimus L, Chisati E. Common impairments and functional limitations of HIV sequelae that require physiotherapy rehabilitation in the medical wards at Queen Elizabeth Central Hospital, Malawi: a cross sectional study. Malawi Med J. 2019;31(3):171–76. 10.4314/mmj.v31i3.2<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31839885</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4314/mmj.v31i3.2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6895382</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Izquierdo-Alventosa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inglés</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cortés-Amador</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gimeno-Mallench</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chirivella-Garrido</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kropotov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P</surname><given-names>S-A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-intensity physical exercise improves pain catastrophizing and other psychological and physical aspects in women with fibromyalgia: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3634</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17103634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32455853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7277480</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Izquierdo-Alventosa R, Inglés, Cortés-Amador, Gimeno-Mallench L, Chirivella-Garrido J, Kropotov J, P S-A. Low-intensity physical exercise improves pain catastrophizing and other psychological and physical aspects in women with fibromyalgia: a randomized controlled trial. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:3634. 10.3390/ijerph17103634<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32455853</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph17103634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7277480</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheiber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiederin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schifferegger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiefermeier-Mach</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 rehabilitation: perception and experience of Austrian physiotherapists and physiotherapy students</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>8730</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18168730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34444477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8394152</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Scheiber B, Spiegl C, Wiederin C, Schifferegger E, Schiefermeier-Mach N. Post-COVID-19 rehabilitation: perception and experience of Austrian physiotherapists and physiotherapy students. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(16):8730. 10.3390/ijerph18168730<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34444477</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph18168730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8394152</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theodoridou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maltezou</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID syndrome: incidence, clinical spectrum, and challenges for primary healthcare professional</article-title><source>Arch Med Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>52</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arcmed.2021.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33962805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8093949</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Pavli A, Theodoridou M, Maltezou HC. Post-COVID syndrome: incidence, clinical spectrum, and challenges for primary healthcare professional. Arch Med Res. 2021;52(6):575–81. 10.1016/j.arcmed.2021.03.010<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33962805</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arcmed.2021.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8093949</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>König</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise training in non-hospitalized patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome: a narrative review</article-title><source>Healthcare (basel)</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>2277</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/healthcare11162277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37628475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10454172</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Sick J, König D. Exercise training in non-hospitalized patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome: a narrative review. Healthcare (Basel). 2023;11(16):2277. 10.3390/healthcare11162277<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37628475</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/healthcare11162277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10454172</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nambi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelbasset</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alrawaili</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative effectiveness study of low versus high-intensity aerobic training with resistance training in community-dwelling older men with post-COVID 19 sarcopenia: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Clin Rehabil</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/026921552110369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34344230</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Nambi G, Abdelbasset WK, Alrawaili SM, et al. Comparative effectiveness study of low versus high-intensity aerobic training with resistance training in community-dwelling older men with post-COVID 19 sarcopenia: a randomized controlled trial. Clin Rehabil. 2022;36(1):59–68. 10.1177/026921552110369<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34344230</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/02692155211036956</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elnahas</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Algazzar</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of active cycle of breathing technique on selected pulmonary outcomes in post-COVID syndrome patients</article-title><source>J Pharm Negat Results</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>710</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.47750/pnr.2023.14.S02.87</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Ali AA, Elnahas NG, Algazzar SA, et al. Impact of active cycle of breathing technique on selected pulmonary outcomes in post-COVID syndrome patients. J Pharm Negat Results. 2023;14:710–17. 10.47750/pnr.2023.14.S02.87</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soper</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Physical therapy management of an individual with post-COVID syndrome: a case report</source><year>2021</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ptj/pzab098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7989151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33735380</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="book">Mayer KP, Steele AK, Soper MK, et al. Physical therapy management of an individual with post-COVID syndrome: a case report. Oxford University Press; 2021. 10.1093/ptj/pzab098<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ptj/pzab098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7989151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33735380</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary rehabilitation in SARS-CoV-2: a systematic review and meta-analysis of post-acute patients</article-title><source>Diagnostics</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3032</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diagnostics12123032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36553039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9776761</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Reinert G, Müller D, Wagner P, et al. Pulmonary rehabilitation in SARS-CoV-2: a systematic review and meta-analysis of post-acute patients. Diagnostics. 2022;12:3032. 10.3390/diagnostics12123032<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36553039</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/diagnostics12123032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9776761</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi Hekmatikar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira Júnior</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahrbanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional and psychological changes after exercise training in post-COVID-19 patients discharged from the hospital: a PRISMA-Compliant systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Pub Health And Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2290</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19042290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8871540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35206483</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Ahmadi Hekmatikar AH, Ferreira Júnior, Shahrbanian S, Suzuki K. Functional and psychological changes after exercise training in post-COVID-19 patients discharged from the hospital: a PRISMA-Compliant systematic review. Int J Environ Res Pub Health. 2022;19(4):2290. 10.3390/ijerph19042290<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph19042290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8871540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35206483</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Musculoskeletal physiotherapy in physical sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection: a case report</article-title><source>Physiother Res Intl</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e1938</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pri.1938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35044028</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Santos S, Flores JA. Musculoskeletal physiotherapy in physical sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection: a case report. Physiother Res Intl. 2022;27(2):e1938. 10.1002/pri.1938<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pri.1938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35044028</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halabchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selk-Ghaffari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tazesh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahdaviani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of exercise rehabilitation on COVID-19 outcomes: a systematic review of observational and intervention studies</article-title><source>Sport Sci Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11332-022-00966-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35789736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9244056</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Halabchi F, Selk-Ghaffari M, Tazesh B, Mahdaviani B. The effect of exercise rehabilitation on COVID-19 outcomes: a systematic review of observational and intervention studies. Sport Sci Health. 2022;18(4):1201–19. 10.1007/s11332-022-00966-5<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35789736</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11332-022-00966-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9244056</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meléndez-Oliva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Pozas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuenca-Zaldívar</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villafañe</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiménez-Ortega</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez-Romero</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of pulmonary rehabilitation in post-COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2213</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines11082213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37626710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10452542</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Meléndez-Oliva E, Martínez-Pozas O, Cuenca-Zaldívar JN, Villafañe JH, Jiménez-Ortega L, Sánchez-Romero EA. Efficacy of pulmonary rehabilitation in post-COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Biomedicines. 2023;11(8):2213. 10.3390/biomedicines11082213<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37626710</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines11082213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10452542</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pouliopoulou</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macdermid</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rehabilitation interventions for physical capacity and quality of life in adults with post-COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e2333838</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37725376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10509723</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Pouliopoulou DV, Macdermid JC, Saunders E, Peters S, Brunton L, Miller E, et al. Rehabilitation interventions for physical capacity and quality of life in adults with post-COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(9):e2333838. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33838<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37725376</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10509723</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization (WHO). Clinical management of COVID-19: living guideline. 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-clinical-2023.2">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-clinical-2023.2</ext-link>. Accessed 15 March 2025, 7th.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35917394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>ATP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ski</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventions for mental health, cognition, and psychological wellbeing in long COVID: a systematic review of registered trials</article-title><source>Psychol Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>52</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>2426</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291722002203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35768406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9300978</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Hawke L, Nguyen ATP, Ski CF, Thompson DR, Ma C, Castle D. Interventions for mental health, cognition, and psychological wellbeing in long COVID: a systematic review of registered trials. Psychol Med. 2022;52(13):2426–40. 10.1017/S0033291722002203<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35768406</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0033291722002203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9300978</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dillen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bekkering</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gijsbers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vande Weygaerde</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Herck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haesevoets</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical effectiveness of rehabilitation in ambulatory care for patients with persisting symptoms after COVID-19: a systematic review</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>419</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-023-08374-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37344767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10283248</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Dillen H, Bekkering G, Gijsbers S, Vande Weygaerde Y, Van Herck M, Haesevoets S, et al. Clinical effectiveness of rehabilitation in ambulatory care for patients with persisting symptoms after COVID-19: a systematic review. BMC Infect Dis. 2023;23(1):419. 10.1186/s12879-023-08374-x<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37344767</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-023-08374-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10283248</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Covid</surname><given-names>TEL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Covid TEL. Major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023;21(3):133–46. 10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Décary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Groote</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arienti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiekens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boldrini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazzarini</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Scoping review of rehabilitation care models for post COVID-19 condition</article-title><source>Bull. World Health Organ</source><year>2022</year><volume>100</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2471/BLT.22.288105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36324552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9589389</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Décary S, De Groote W, Arienti C, Kiekens C, Boldrini P, Lazzarini SG, et al. Scoping review of rehabilitation care models for post COVID-19 condition. Bull. World Health Organ. 2022;100(11):676–88. 10.2471/BLT.22.288105<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36324552</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2471/BLT.22.288105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9589389</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Negrini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiekens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arienti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groote</surname><given-names>WWDE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cochrane “evidence relevant to” rehabilitation of people with post COVID-19 condition. What it is and how it has been mapped to inform the development of the World Health Organization recommendations</article-title><source>Eur J Phys Rehabil Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>58</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23736/S1973-9087.22.07793-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36468825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10077960</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Negrini S, Kiekens C, Cordani C, Arienti C, Groote WWDE. Cochrane “evidence relevant to” rehabilitation of people with post COVID-19 condition. What it is and how it has been mapped to inform the development of the World Health Organization recommendations. Eur J Phys Rehabil Med. 2022;58(6):853–56. 10.23736/S1973-9087.22.07793-0<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36468825</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.23736/S1973-9087.22.07793-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10077960</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Joana Briggs Institute (JBI). JBI manual for evidence synthesis. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jbi-global-wiki.refined.site/space/MANUAL/355862497/10.+Scoping+reviews">https://jbi-global-wiki.refined.site/space/MANUAL/355862497/10.+Scoping+reviews</ext-link>. Accessed 1 Nov 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gartmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bökel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiotherapy interventions in post- and long-COVID -19: a scoping review protocol</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e0777420</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11367397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39209506</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Gartmann J, Sturm C, Bökel A. Physiotherapy interventions in post- and long-COVID -19: a scoping review protocol. BMJ Open. 2024;14:e0777420. 10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077420<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11367397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39209506</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levac</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PRISMA extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>169</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M18-0850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178033</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Tricco AC, Lillie E, Zarin W, O’Brien KK, Colquhoun H, Levac D, et al. PRISMA extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation. Ann Intern Med. 2018;169(7):467–73. 10.7326/M18-0850<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178033</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M18-0850</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Joana Briggs Institute (JBI). JBI critical appraisal tools. https://jbi.global/critical-appraisal-tools. Accessed 7 Nov 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulrow</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The PRISMA, 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2021</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>n71</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33782057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8005924</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, Boutron I, Hoffmann TC, Mulrow CD, et al. The PRISMA, 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ. 2021;372:n71. 10.1136/bmj.n71<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33782057</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.n71</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8005924</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elimy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influence of manual diaphragm release technique combined with inspiratory muscle training on selected persistent symptoms in men with post-covid-19 syndrome: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>J Rehabil Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>jrm00330</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2340/jrm.v54.3972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36121338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9608026</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Nagy EN, Elimy DA, Ali AY, et al. Influence of manual diaphragm release technique combined with inspiratory muscle training on selected persistent symptoms in men with post-COVID-19 syndrome: a randomized controlled trial. J Rehabil Med. 2022;54:jrm00330. 10.2340/jrm.v54.3972<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36121338</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2340/jrm.v54.3972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9608026</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rutkowski S, Bogacz K, Rutkowska A, Szczegielniak JCR, Casaburi R. Inpatient post-COVID rehabilitation program featuring virtual reality-preliminary results of randomized controlled trial. Front Public Health. 2023;11:1121554. 10.3389/fpubh.2023.1121554<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1121554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9939639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36815161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrigues</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janvier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kherabi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gouze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-discharge persistent symptoms and health-related quality of life after hospitalization for COVID-19</article-title><source>The J Infect</source><year>2020</year><volume>81</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e4</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7445491</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Garrigues E, Janvier P, Kherabi Y, Le Bot A, Hamon A, Gouze H, et al. Post-discharge persistent symptoms and health-related quality of life after hospitalization for COVID-19. The J Infect. 2020;81(6):e4–6. 10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.029<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853602</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7445491</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatesan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NICE guideline on long COVID</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00031-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33453162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7832375</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Venkatesan P. NICE guideline on long COVID. Lancet Respir Med. 2021;9(2):129. 10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00031-X<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33453162</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00031-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7832375</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klugar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tufanaru</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonardi-Bee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aromataris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munn</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The revised JBI critical appraisal tool for the assessment of risk of bias for randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>JBI Evidence Synth</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11124/JBIES-22-00430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36727247</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Barker TH, Stone JC, Sears K, Klugar M, Tufanaru C, Leonardi-Bee J, et al. The revised JBI critical appraisal tool for the assessment of risk of bias for randomized controlled trials. JBI Evidence Synth. 2023;21(3):494–506. 10.11124/JBIES-22-00430<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.11124/JBIES-22-00430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36727247</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arbeitsgemeinschaft der Wissenschaftlichen Medizinischen Fachgesellschaften e.V. (AWMF). S1-Leitlinie Long/Post-COVID (Stand 30.05. 2024) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://register.awmf.org/assets/guidelines/020-027l_S1_Long-Post-Covid_2024-06_1.pdf">https://register.awmf.org/assets/guidelines/020-027l_S1_Long-Post-Covid_2024-06_1.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 8. July 2025.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Koninklijk Nederlands Genootschap voor Fysiotherapie (KNGF). Position statement on physical therapy during COVID-19. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.kngf.nl/binaries/content/assets/kennisplatform/onbeveiligd/guidelines/kngf-position-statement-on-physical-therapy-during-covid-19.pdf">https://www.kngf.nl/binaries/content/assets/kennisplatform/onbeveiligd/guidelines/kngf-position-statement-on-physical-therapy-during-covid-19.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 28 June 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Funke-Chambour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bridevaux</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarenbach</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Swiss recommendations for the follow-up and treatment of pulmonary long COVID</article-title><source>Respiration</source><year>2021</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>826</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000517255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34091456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8339046</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Funke-Chambour M, Bridevaux PO, Clarenbach CF, et al. Swiss recommendations for the follow-up and treatment of pulmonary long COVID. Respiration. 2021;100:826–41.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34091456</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000517255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8339046</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chiaramonte R, D’amico S, Marletta C, Grasso G, Pirrone S, Bonfiglio M. Impact of clostridium difficile infection on stroke patients in rehabilitation wards. Infect Dis Now. 2023;53(5). 10.1016/j.idnow.2023.104685<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.idnow.2023.104685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36841431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeBoer H</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cudd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Where and how does physical therapy fit? Integrating physical therapy into interprofessional HIV care</article-title><source>Disabil Rehabil</source><year>2019</year><volume>41</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>1768</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09638288.2018.1448469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29529881</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">DeBoer H, Andrews M, Cudd S, et al. Where and how does physical therapy fit? Integrating physical therapy into interprofessional HIV care. Disabil Rehabil. 2019;41(15):1768–77. 10.1080/09638288.2018.1448469<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29529881</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09638288.2018.1448469</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sivan M, Taylor S. NICE guideline on long COVID. BMJ. 2020;371. 10.1136/bmj.m4938<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.m4938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33361141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grotkamp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>w</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüggemann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coenen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gmünder</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nüchtern</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwegler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>w</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Staubli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Raison</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weißmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahemann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Personal factors classification revisited: a proposal in the light of the biopsychosocial model of the world health organization (WHO)</article-title><source>Aust J Marit Ocean Aff J Rehabil Counselling</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/jrc.2020.14</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Grotkamp S, Cicis W, Brüggemann S, Coenen M, Gmünder HP, Keller K, et al. Personal factors classification revisited: a proposal in the light of the biopsychosocial model of the World Health Organization (WHO). Aust J Marit Ocean Aff J Rehabil Counselling. 2020;26(2):73–91. 10.1017/jrc.2020.14</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>