<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="letter" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infection</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infection</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">springeropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0300-8126</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1439-0973</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12675724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12675724.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12675724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12675724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40690153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s15010-025-02612-x</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2612</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Possible long COVID biomarker: identification of SARS-CoV-2 related protein(s) in Serum Extracellular Vesicles</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3034-0068</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names initials="A">Asghar</given-names></name><address><email>asghar.abbasi@lundquist.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names initials="R">Ritin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names initials="N">Nathaniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirrotte</surname><given-names initials="P">Patrick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names initials="WW">William W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05h4zj272</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239844.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0157 6501</institution-id><institution>The Lundquist Institute for Biomedical Innovation, </institution><institution>Harbor-UCLA Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Torrance, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02hfpnk21</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.250942.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0507 3225</institution-id><institution>Early Detection and Prevention Division, </institution><institution>Translational Genomics Research Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Phoenix, AZ USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00w6g5w60</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410425.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0421 8357</institution-id><institution>Integrated Mass Spectrometry Shared Resource, </institution><institution>City of Hope Comprehensive Cancer Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Duarte, CA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>53</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">501816</issue-id><fpage>2909</fpage><lpage>2912</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>21</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-12-05 00:25:12.533"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="15010_2025_Article_2612.pdf"/><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>UCLA David Geffen School of Medicine (DGSoM)-Ventura County Community Foundation (VCCF) Long COVID 19 Research Award</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1">Clinical trial registration number/other number: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT05398692">NCT05398692</ext-link>.</p><p id="Par2">Clinical trial date of registration: 2022-05-10.</p><p id="Par3">Emerging evidence suggests that SARS-CoV-2 RNA and viral antigens can persist in diverse tissues- (lung, brain, muscles, lymph nodes, and plasma)- for months to years after acute infection, and may be pathogenic for common long COVID symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Extracellular vesicles (EVs)- nanosized vesicles (30–1000 nm) which facilitate intracellular communication of bioactive molecules such as proteins, lipids, nucleic acids, and metabolites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]- have been found to harbor other viral RNA and proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], and may potentiate viral replication, immune activation and inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. We propose that EVs with viral contents may serve as a potential biomarker in long COVID.</p><p id="Par4">Blood samples were collected from 14 adults (aged ≥ 18 years) with a documented history of SARS-CoV-2 infection (confirmed via PCR or patient report) and persistent long COVID symptoms proposed by CDC and WHO (&gt; 12 weeks since initial SARS-CoV-2 infection) including fatigue, dyspnea, exercise intolerance, or post-exertional malaise (PEM). The cohort was demographically and clinically diverse, including 43% women and 43% Hispanic/Latino participants. The majority (79%) were not hospitalized during their initial infection, and only one participant was unvaccinated at the time of study entry. Obesity was common (mean BMI 32.5 ± 8.4), and baseline physical activity levels were predominantly sedentary or limited to walking. The mean duration between initial SARS-CoV-2 infection and study enrollment was 17 ± 10 months. For further details about methods, see our previous publication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Samples were obtained in response to acute incremental exercise (at rest and peak exercise), both before and after completion of the exercise training program. EVs were isolated from serum using precipitation kits (EQULTRA-20A-1, SBI Inc.) and analyzed by mass spectrometry-based proteomics. To assess whether any of the detected peptides were associated with SARS-CoV-2, the SARS-CoV-2 proteome (17 reviewed entries) was obtained from UniProt (UP000464024). EV samples were queried against a predicted SARS-CoV-2 spectral library in Spectronaut using default parameters (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Detection of SARS-CoV-2 peptides in serum EVs from individuals with long COVID. <bold>A</bold> Study design and analytical workflow. Blood samples were collected from individuals with long COVID in response to an acute exercise test (both at rest and peak exercise), before (visit 2) and after (visit 24) completing an exercise training program. Serum EVs were isolated from 56 samples, and proteins were analyzed using mass spectrometry to search for viral peptides. Samples were analyzed by data-independent acquisition mass spectrometry (DIA-MS) with a library-free search against the predicted SARS-CoV-2 proteome. Five EV samples with positive identification of the SARS-CoV-2 polyprotein 1ab (Pp1ab) were further validated using targeted MS2 with a spiked-in stable isotope-labeled synthetic (SIS) peptide standard (“GSLPINVIVFDGK”) (Supplementary Fig. 1). Subsequently, all 56 EV samples were analyzed by targeted MS2 on the Thermo Stellar mass spectrometer for enhanced sensitivity using the same SIS peptide standard. For comparison, 20 control EV samples- collected prior to the COVID-19 pandemic- were processed and analyzed identically using the targeted MS2 workflow with spiked-in SIS peptides. <bold>B</bold> Heatmap showing EV samples from each long COVID patient with detected SARS-CoV-2 Pp1ab peptides. Color intensity (blue to red) reflects peptide abundance, and the numbers in parentheses indicate how many distinct Pp1ab peptides were found in each sample. The data table is available in Supplementary Table 1. In total, Pp1ab peptides were detected in 22 of the 56 EV samples, with each subject exhibited at least one peptide in their EV cargo. The peptide “GSLPINVIVFDGK,” highlighted in red, was selected for further validation by targeted MS2 analysis. <bold>C</bold> Overlay of extracted ion chromatograms (EICs) illustrating the SARS-CoV-2 peptide “GSLPINVIVFDGK” detected in EV samples from long COVID patients (endogenous), alongside the matching synthetic reference peptide (spike-in-standard). The matching chromatographic patterns between the endogenous and synthetic peptides confirmed the presence of “GSLPINVIVFDGK” in 12 out of 14 patients with a positive signal. Full chromatogram profiles and related data are provided in Supplementary Table 2. <italic toggle="yes">EVs</italic> extracellular vesicles, <italic toggle="yes">Pt</italic> patient, <italic toggle="yes">visit 2</italic> pre-training, <italic toggle="yes">visit 24</italic> post-training</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="15010_2025_2612_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par5">Despite inter-individual variability, we detected 65 unique SARS-CoV-2 peptides mapping to the replicase polyprotein 1ab (Pp1ab; UniProt ID:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0DTD1">P0DTD1</ext-link>, R1AB_SARS2), in 22 of the 56 serum EV samples (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). Sequence analysis (pBLAST) confirmed that these peptides were specific to SARS-CoV-2 and did not overlap with human proteins. Importantly, each subject exhibited one or more SARS-CoV-2 peptides in their EV cargo, suggesting the persistence of viral components over time (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). Pp1ab is encoded by the ORF1ab gene and plays a crucial role in viral RNA transcription and replication. To validate these findings, we applied a targeted mass spectrometry approach, using stable isotope-labelled synthetic (SIS) peptides (reference peptides) and high-resolution parallel reaction monitoring (PRM), to confirm the presence of Pp1ab-derived peptides in five randomly selected EV samples (Supplementary Fig. 1). We further verified the presence of a specific Pp1ab peptide (“GSLPINVIVFDGK”) in serum EVs in 12 out of 14 long COVID subjects across multiple time points (20 out of 56 samples in total) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C). This peptide sequence (GSLPINVIVFDGK) corresponds specifically to non-structural protein 3 (nsp3) and is conserved across major SARS-CoV-2 variants, including Alpha, Delta, and Omicron, suggesting it is not variant-dependent.</p><p id="Par6">To assess whether the peptides identified in long COVID EVs were also present in individuals without COVID-19 exposure (control group), we analyzed 20 serum EV samples collected prior to the COVID-19 pandemic (before 2019). These EV samples, obtained at rest and at peak incremental exercise from ex-smokers, showed no detectable viral peptide in any of the pre-pandemic specimens.</p><p id="Par7">Overall, our targeted analysis confirmed the presence of the Pp1ab peptide in at least one sample in all long COVID subjects, while absent in controls. This finding will require confirmation in other long COVID studies with appropriate controls to establish the durability and sensitivity/specificity of this peptide biomarker. The detection of Pp1ab-laden EVs highlights the potential role of EVs in transporting viral material and suggests that these Pp1ab-laden EVs could serve as a potential biomarker for ongoing viral activity in the host, offering new avenues for diagnosis and therapeutic development in long COVID.</p><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="15010_2025_2612_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (DOCX 161 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="15010_2025_2612_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary file2 (XLSX 32 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="15010_2025_2612_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary file3 (XLSX 297 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Patrick Pirrotte and William W. Stringer are co-senior authors.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to express their gratitude to Melissa Martinez for her assistance with sample collection and handling in this study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>A.Abbasi contributed to conceptualization, methodology, validation, investigation, resources, data curation, writing original draft, writing—review and editing, visualization, supervision, project administration and funding acquisition. R.Sharma was involved in methodology, validation, formal analysis, investigation, writing—review and editing and visualization. N.Hansen was involved in formal analysis, data curation, writing—review and editing and visualization of this manuscript. P.Pirrotte was involved in methodology, writing—review and editing, visualization, supervision of this manuscript. W.W.Stringer contributed to conceptualization, methodology, validation, investigation, data curation, writing original draft, writing—review and editing, visualization, supervision of the study and this manuscript, project administration and funding acquisition.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by the Pulmonary Education and Research Foundation (PERF) and the UCLA David Geffen School of Medicine (DGSoM)-Ventura County Community Foundation (VCCF) Long COVID 19 Research Award.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data are available with appropriate requests to the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par8">Asghar Abbasi is supported by TRDRP (28FT-0017), NIH (R43HL167289, 2R44HL167289-02), and the Johnny Carson Foundation. William Stringer receives research foundation support from the Pulmonary Education and Research Foundation and the UCLA David Geffen School of Medicine (DGSoM)-Ventura County Community Foundation (VCCF) Long COVID 19 Research Award. He reports consulting fees from Verona, Genetech, and Vyaire. He is the co-author of a clinical exercise testing physiology textbook for Lippincott.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamoulle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carletto</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyts</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Blood transcriptomic analyses reveal persistent SARS-CoV-2 RNA and candidate biomarkers in post-COVID-19 condition</article-title><source>Lancet Microbe</source><year>2024</year><volume>5</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>100849</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(24)00055-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38677304</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Menezes SM, Jamoulle M, Carletto MP, Moens L, Meyts I, Maes P, et al. Blood transcriptomic analyses reveal persistent SARS-CoV-2 RNA and candidate biomarkers in post-COVID-19 condition. Lancet Microbe. 2024;5(8): 100849.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38677304</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2666-5247(24)00055-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swank</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalhuisen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plasma-based antigen persistence in the post-acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>medRxiv</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.10.24.23297114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38604216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11650779</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Peluso MJ, Swank ZN, Goldberg SA, Lu S, Dalhuisen T, Borberg E, et al. Plasma-based antigen persistence in the post-acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection. medRxiv. 2023. 10.1101/2023.10.24.23297114.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37961239</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/2023.10.24.23297114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10635183</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buzas</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The roles of extracellular vesicles in the immune system</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-022-00763-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35927511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9361922</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Buzas EI. The roles of extracellular vesicles in the immune system. Nat Rev Immunol. 2022. 10.1038/s41577-022-00763-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35927511</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41577-022-00763-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9361922</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Londono-Renteria</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colpitts</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arthropod EVs mediate dengue virus transmission through interaction with a tetraspanin domain containing glycoprotein Tsp29Fb</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><issue>28</issue><fpage>E6604</fpage><lpage>E6613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1720125115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29946031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6048473</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Vora A, Zhou W, Londono-Renteria B, Woodson M, Sherman MB, Colpitts TM, et al. Arthropod EVs mediate dengue virus transmission through interaction with a tetraspanin domain containing glycoprotein Tsp29Fb. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2018;115(28):E6604–13.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29946031</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1720125115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6048473</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The extracellular vesicles in HIV infection and progression: mechanisms, and theranostic implications</article-title><source>Front Bioeng Biotechnol</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1376455</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fbioe.2024.1376455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38655385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11035885</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Tang Z, Lu Y, Dong JL, Wu W, Li J. The extracellular vesicles in HIV infection and progression: mechanisms, and theranostic implications. Front Bioeng Biotechnol. 2024;12:1376455.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38655385</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fbioe.2024.1376455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11035885</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breyne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ughetto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breakefield</surname><given-names>XO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA delivery by extracellular vesicles in mammalian cells and its applications</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-020-0251-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32457507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7249041</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">O’Brien K, Breyne K, Ughetto S, Laurent LC, Breakefield XO. RNA delivery by extracellular vesicles in mammalian cells and its applications. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2020;21(10):585–606.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32457507</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41580-020-0251-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7249041</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gattoni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iacovino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tosolini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A pilot study on the effects of exercise training on cardiorespiratory performance, quality of life, and immunologic variables in long COVID</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>5590</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm13185590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39337079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11433403</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Abbasi A, Gattoni C, Iacovino M, Ferguson C, Tosolini J, Singh A, et al. A pilot study on the effects of exercise training on cardiorespiratory performance, quality of life, and immunologic variables in long COVID. J Clin Med. 2024;13(18):5590.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39337079</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm13185590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11433403</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>