<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Complement Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Complement Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2985</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">kargersd</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CMR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Complementary Medicine Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2504-2092</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2504-2106</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Karger Author's Choice</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12826761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12826761.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12826761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12826761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41362171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000549822</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">549822</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Traditional Medicine, Complementary and Integrative Medicine</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Utilizing the DMN and DAN to Study the Effects of Acupuncture on Patients with Cognitive Impairment in Long COVID: A Pragmatic Randomized Controlled Trial Protocol</article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="de"><trans-title>Nutzung des DMN und DAN zur Untersuchung der Effekte von Akupunktur bei Patientinnen und Patienten mit kognitiven Beeinträchtigungen nach Long COVID: Protokoll einer pragmatischen, randomisierten kontrollierten Studie</trans-title></trans-title-group><trans-title-group xml:lang="fr"><trans-title>Utilisation du DMN et du DAN pour étudier les effets de l’acupuncture chez les patients présentant des troubles cognitifs liés au long COVID : protocole d’un essai contrôlé randomisé pragmatique</trans-title></trans-title-group><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Acupuncture Therapy for Cognitive Impairment in Long COVID</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809659</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="J">Jing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809660</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yanyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809661</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Ziang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809662</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names initials="M">Mengru</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809663</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809664</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="H">Han</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809665</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zesen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809666</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="S">Shiqi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809667</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="D">Dan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809668</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="L">Lei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809669</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yingqi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="relnr" authenticated="false">2809670</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="S">Shangjie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">
<label>a</label>First Affiliated Hospital of Bengbu Medical College, <city>Bengbu</city>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>b</label>Department of Rehabilitation, The People’s Hospital of Baoan Shenzhen, Bengbu Medical College, <city>Shenzhen</city>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>c</label>Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine, <city>Guangzhou</city>, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to: Lei Xu, <email>xuleibyfy@163.com</email> or Yingqi Lu, <email>lyq01232023@163.com</email> or Shangjie Chen, <email>csjmesz@sina.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Jing Chen and Yanyu Wu contributed equally to this work and should be regarded as equivalent first authors.</p><p>Trial registration: Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.chictr.org.cn" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.chictr.org.cn</ext-link>), Registration number: ChiCTR2400092961, date of registration: 2024-11-26. For the SPIRIT-Outcomes 2022 Checklist, see online supplementary material at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1159/000549822" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1159/000549822</ext-link>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">505869</issue-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-23 16:25:14.407"><day>23</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Author(s). Published by S. Karger AG, Basel</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://karger.com/Services/OpenAccessLicense">https://karger.com/Services/OpenAccessLicense</ext-link>). Usage and distribution for commercial purposes requires written permission.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cmr-2025-0000-0000-549822.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>Cognitive impairment is one of the long COVID symptoms that many people experience after Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19). Many individuals report a decline in cognitive functions, such as reduced memory and brain fog. These symptoms not only directly affect the cognitive functions of the brain but also hinder daily living activities, thereby reducing the quality of life. Moreover, these symptoms are significant risk factors for long-term cognitive decline in the elderly and can have both short-term and long-term effects on brain function. Clinically, acupuncture is widely used to improve cognitive impairment in the elderly. Elucidating the brain network mechanisms underlying acupuncture therapy for long COVID-related cognitive impairment represents an urgently needed research focus. In this study, we employed acupuncture as an intervention to mitigate cognitive decline in long COVID patients and investigate the potential mechanisms by which acupuncture alleviates cognitive impairment.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>In this randomized controlled trial, 60 eligible participants are planned to be recruited and randomly assigned in a 1:1 ratio to the acupuncture group and the health education group, which will then receive acupuncture treatment and health education. The acupuncture group will participate in treatment three times per week for a total of 8 weeks. The health education group will receive health education once per week for a total of 8 weeks. The primary assessment index was the Montreal Cognitive Assessment Scale (MoCA), and the secondary assessment indexes included Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR), Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), Activity of Daily Living Scale (ADL), Auditory Verbal Learning Test-Huashan Version (AVLT-H), and resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging data. These assessment indicators were all tested in 1 week each before and after the intervention was implemented.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>This trial aims to investigate the therapeutic effects of acupuncture on cognitive impairment in patients with long COVID and to further explore the imaging mechanisms by which acupuncture alleviates cognitive dysfunction in these patients.</p></sec></abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="de"><title>Zusammenfassung</title><sec><title>Hintergrund</title><p>Kognitive Beeinträchtigungen zählen zu den häufigen Symptomen von Long COVID, die viele Menschen nach einer Infektion mit dem Coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) erleben. Zahlreiche Betroffene berichten „über nachlassende Gedächtnisleistungen und Konzentrationsstörungen“ („brain fog“). Diese Symptome beeinträchtigen nicht nur direkt die kognitiven Funktionen des Gehirns, sondern erschweren auch alltägliche Aktivitäten und führen zu einer verminderten Lebensqualität. Darüber hinaus stellen sie bedeutende Risikofaktoren für einen langfristigen kognitiven Abbau im höheren Lebensalter dar und können sowohl kurz-als auch langfristige Auswirkungen auf die Hirnfunktion haben. In der klinischen Praxis wird Akupunktur häufig zur Verbesserung kognitiver Beeinträchtigungen bei älteren Menschen eingesetzt. Die Aufklärung der zugrunde liegenden Mechanismen auf Ebene der Hirnnetzwerke bei der Akupunkturtherapie Long COVID-assoziierter kognitiver Störungen stellt ein dringendes Forschungsanliegen dar. In der vorliegenden Studie wird Akupunktur als Intervention eingesetzt, um den kognitiven Abbau bei Long COVID-Patientinnen und -Patienten zu mildern und die potenziellen Mechanismen der Akupunktur zur Linderung kognitiver Beeinträchtigungen zu untersuchen.</p></sec><sec><title>Methoden</title><p>In dieser randomisierten kontrollierten Studie sollen 60 geeignete Teilnehmende rekrutiert und im Verhältnis 1:1 randomisiert der Akupunkturgruppe bzw. der Gesundheitsbildungsgruppe zugeteilt werden. Die Akupunkturgruppe erhält dreimal wöchentlich über insgesamt acht Wochen eine Akupunkturbehandlung. Die Kontrollgruppe erhält einmal wöchentlich über acht Wochen eine Gesundheitsbildung. Der primäre Endpunkt ist die Montreal Cognitive Assessment Scale (MoCA). Sekundäre Endpunkte umfassen die Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR), den Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), die Skala für Aktivitäten des täglichen Lebens (ADL), den Auditory Verbal Learning Test – Huashan Version (AVLT-H) sowie Daten der funktionellen Magnetresonanztomographie im Ruhezustand (rs-fMRT). Alle Messungen erfolgen jeweils eine Woche vor und nach der Intervention.</p></sec><sec><title>Diskussion</title><p>Diese Studie zielt darauf ab, die therapeutischen Effekte der Akupunktur auf kognitive Beeinträchtigungen bei Patientinnen und Patienten mit Long COVID zu untersuchen und die bildgebenden Mechanismen zu erforschen, durch die Akupunktur kognitive Dysfunktionen in dieser Patientengruppe lindert.</p></sec></trans-abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="fr"><title>Résumé</title><sec><title>Contexte </title><p>Le trouble cognitif constitue l’un des symptômes du long COVID que de nombreuses personnes présentent après une infection par le SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19). De nombreux individus rapportent une diminution des fonctions cognitives, telle qu’une mémoire réduite ou un « brouillard cérébral ». Ces symptômes affectent non seulement directement les fonctions cognitives du cerveau, mais entravent également les activités de la vie quotidienne, réduisant ainsi la qualité de vie. Par ailleurs, ces manifestations représentent des facteurs de risque majeurs pour un déclin cognitif à long terme chez les personnes âgées et peuvent avoir des répercussions tant à court qu’à long terme sur la fonction cérébrale. En pratique clinique, l’acupuncture est largement utilisée pour améliorer les troubles cognitifs chez les sujets âgés. L’élucidation des mécanismes des réseaux cérébraux sous-jacents à la thérapie par acupuncture dans le cadre des troubles cognitifs associés au long COVID représente un axe de recherche prioritaire. Dans cette étude, nous avons utilisé l’acupuncture comme intervention afin d’atténuer le déclin cognitif chez les patients atteints de long COVID et d’explorer les mécanismes potentiels par lesquels l’acupuncture pourrait soulager les troubles cognitifs.</p></sec><sec><title>Méthodes </title><p>Dans cet essai contrôlé randomisé, il est prévu de recruter soixante participants éligibles, répartis de façon aléatoire selon un ratio 1 : 1 entre un groupe acupuncture et un groupe éducation à la santé, lesquels recevront respectivement un traitement par acupuncture ou une éducation à la santé. Le groupe acupuncture bénéficiera de trois séances hebdomadaires pendant huit semaines. Le groupe éducation à la santé recevra une séance hebdomadaire sur la même période. Le critère d’évaluation principal est l’échelle d’évaluation cognitive de Montréal (MoCA) ; les critères secondaires comprennent la Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR), le Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), l’échelle des activités de la vie quotidienne (ADL), l’Auditory Verbal Learning Test – version Huashan (AVLT-H) ainsi que les données d’imagerie par résonance magnétique fonctionnelle au repos (rs-IRMf). Tous ces critères ont été évalués une semaine avant et une semaine après l’intervention.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion </title><p>Cet essai vise à évaluer les effets thérapeutiques de l’acupuncture sur les troubles cognitifs chez les patients atteints de long COVID et à approfondir l’exploration des mécanismes d’imagerie par lesquels l’acupuncture pourrait atténuer la dysfonction cognitive dans cette population.</p></sec></trans-abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Brain network</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Acupuncture</kwd><kwd>Cognitive impairment</kwd><kwd>Functional magnetic resonance imaging</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group xml:lang="de"><title>Schlüsselwörter</title><kwd>Hirnnetzwerk</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Akupunktur</kwd><kwd>Kognitive Beeinträchtigung</kwd><kwd>Funktionelle Magnetresonanztomographie</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group xml:lang="fr"><title>Mots-clés</title><kwd>Réseau cérébral</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Acupuncture</kwd><kwd>Trouble cognitif</kwd><kwd>Imagerie par résonance magnétique fonctionnelle</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>Funding sources were as follows: National Natural Science Foundation of China (81973922); Shenzhen Bao'an District Medical Association (BAYXH2023011); Shenzhen Bao’an District Traditional Chinese Medicine Development Foundation (2022KJCX-ZJZL-14); and Shenzhen Sanming Project (2022).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><ref-count count="33"/><page-count count="11"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>accessibilitySummary</meta-name><meta-value>WCAG 2.1 Level AA</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>accessibility-pdf-ua-compliance</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The infection caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has led to a sharp increase in cases of COVID-19, placing a heavy burden on global healthcare systems [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Although many infected individuals have recovered, a significant number of people continue to experience symptoms and complications after the acute phase [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Many patients are currently suffering or have previously suffered from long COVID syndrome [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This public health crisis has severely threatened people’s mental health and quality of life and has imposed an inexpressible burden on society and the nation.</p><p>Within the 12 months following discharge from COVID-19, approximately 3.3% of COVID-19 survivors were diagnosed with dementia, while 9.1% of patients experienced mild cognitive impairment (MCI). Particularly in severe cases, the incidence rates of dementia and MCI were as high as 15.00% and 26.15%, respectively [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Three months following the onset of possible or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, with symptoms persisting for at least 2 months, patients exhibited overall cognitive impairment and episodic memory deficits, particularly in attention, working memory, and processing speed [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Additionally, neuroimaging of the brain revealed lower fractional anisotropy and higher radial diffusivity in white matter regions [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Following severe SARS-CoV-2 infection, patients may develop chronic systemic inflammation, which can exacerbate neurodegeneration [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The resulting cognitive impairment is comparable to the natural cognitive decline that occurs between the ages of 50 and 70, and this impact can still be detected 6 months later [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Whether individuals are symptomatic or asymptomatic, COVID-19 may have both short-term and long-term effects on the brain function of patients [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In imaging studies, it has been observed that, compared to healthy individuals, patients with long COVID exhibit reduced connectivity between the left and right par hippocampal gyri, as well as decreased functional brain connections between the bilateral orbitofrontal regions and the cerebellum [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In addition, there is a more pronounced reduction in gray matter thickness of the orbitofrontal cortex and the par hippocampal gyrus, a decrease in overall brain volume, and more significant changes in tissue damage markers in areas related to the function of the primary olfactory cortex [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. There is further evidence to suggest that the impact of SARS-CoV-2 on the central nervous system may be a key factor in the risk of cognitive decline in later life, Alzheimer’s disease, and other forms of dementia [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>Acupuncture, as a common and green intervention method, has extensive regulatory effects on the human body. Based on bioinformatics research, it has been found that acupuncture can treat COVID-19 by inhibiting inflammatory stress, enhancing immunity, and regulating nervous system function through the activation of neuroactive ligand-receptor interactions, calcium signaling pathways, and cancer pathways, among others. This research has, for the first time, elucidated the multiple synergistic mechanisms of acupuncture in treating COVID-19, indicating that acupuncture may play a positive role in the treatment of COVID-19 [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In addition, a systematic review that included several randomized controlled trials also showed that acupuncture can improve symptoms such as fatigue, cognitive impairment, depression, and anxiety and may be applicable to patients with long COVID [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In order to further investigate the efficacy of acupuncture in treating cognitive impairment in long COVID patients, we proposed this randomized controlled trial. In this study, we provided acupuncture treatment for patients with MCI due to long COVID, aiming to alleviate cognitive impairment in these patients. At the same time, we utilized functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) technology to explore the potential mechanisms of acupuncture in treating MCI in long COVID patients from the perspective of brain networks.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods and analysis" id="s2"><title>Methods and Analysis</title><sec id="s2-1-1"><title>Study Design</title><p>This study employed a randomized controlled trial, including allocation concealment and assessor blinding, and recruited 60 eligible patients who met the diagnostic criteria for MCI due to long COVID from the local area, in accordance with the inclusion criteria. These patients were randomly allocated to two groups using the random number table method: acupuncture group and health education group, with 30 participants each. Sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes were created to ensure allocation concealment. During the trial, the experimenters, recorders, and assessors were independent of each other, and researchers responsible for experimental operations, data collection, and data statistics were not allowed to exchange their respective work content. The control group only received routine health education and did not undergo any other form of intervention. The acupuncture group received acupuncture treatment in addition to routine health education. At the beginning and end of the study, all participants who met the inclusion criteria underwent a comprehensive cognitive assessment. For a comprehensive understanding of the study design and the timetable for outcome assessment, please refer to <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1</xref> and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the trial.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cmr-2025-0000-0000-549822_F01.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Schedule of enrollment, assessments, and interventions.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cmr-2025-0000-0000-549822_F02.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Inclusion Criteria</title><p>Patients with MCI due to long COVID should meet the following criteria: (1) Older adults with MCI following SARS-CoV-2 infection at 3 months; (2) aged between 60 and 75 years; (3) educational level above middle school; (4) health checkup in a tertiary hospital or above within the past 6 months proving good health; (5) body mass index within the range of 20–24; (6) right handed; (7) signed an informed consent form.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Long COVID Diagnostic Criteria</title><p>Symptoms of long COVID typically occur in individuals with a history of SARS-CoV-2 infection, whether suspected or confirmed. These symptoms generally manifest 3 months after the onset of COVID-19 and persist for at least 2 months, with no other diagnosis able to explain them. Common symptoms include fatigue, shortness of breath, and cognitive impairment, which often interfere with daily activities. These symptoms may either newly emerge during the initial recovery period following acute COVID-19 or persist from the initial illness. Additionally, the symptoms may fluctuate over time or relapse [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>The diagnostic criteria for MCI refer to the criteria proposed by the International Working Group in 2003, as recommended in the 2018 Chinese Guidelines for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Dementia and Cognitive Impairment [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]: (1) Memory impairment is the chief complaint, and it is confirmed by an informant. (2) There is an objective decline in memory that is not consistent with age. (3) There is impairment in one or more cognitive domains (memory, language, visuospatial abilities, or executive function). (4) Daily living abilities are essentially normal. (5) The degree of cognitive impairment is not sufficient to diagnose dementia.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Exclusion Criteria</title><p>Exclusion criteria were as follows: (1) Individuals with metal residues in the body or tattoos, as well as those with other conditions that make them unsuitable for magnetic resonance imaging; (2) individuals who have a fear of fMRI, or who are unable to complete the fMRI scan for other reasons; (3) individuals in whom brain examinations reveal significant or suspicious lesions; (4) individuals with a history of heavy alcohol use or drug abuse; (5) individuals with a history of mental illness or congenital mental retardation, including those who have taken or are currently taking psychotropic medications such as anti-anxiety or antidepressant drugs within the past 3 months, patients undergoing psychotherapy, and individuals using medications and treatments that may significantly affect cognition; (6) individuals suffering from severe cardiac, hepatic, or renal diseases, or other neurological disorders that may cause cognitive impairment, such as brain tumors, encephalitis, epilepsy, Parkinson’s disease, etc.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Termination Criteria</title><p>Treatment criteria were as follows: (1) Participants who withdraw from the study for any reason midway; (2) participants with poor compliance who are unable to complete the treatment; (3) participants who are lost to follow-up; (4) participants with incomplete data. Any participant who meets any of the above criteria will be terminated from the study or excluded from this research.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Rationale for the Pragmatic Design</title><p>Our previous investigations and numerous similar studies [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] have consistently revealed that, within the realm of neurocognitive research, sham acupuncture groups – specifically those incorporating appropriate “penetrative” or “non-meridian, non-acupoint” designs – fail to demonstrate any clinically meaningful or sustained therapeutic effects. These effects are assessed through objective cognitive measures like ADAS-Cog and MoCA scores, along with neuroimaging connectivity features, as well as patient-reported improvements in cognitive function, with no significant impacts observed beyond baseline levels. Such evidence strongly implies that the placebo effect of sham acupuncture may be weak and unstable when targeting complex neurocognitive enhancements, differing fundamentally from true acupuncture in its mechanisms, which involve specific neurological pathway integration. In actual clinical settings, patients grappling with long COVID-related cognitive impairment typically face a core choice: opting for acupuncture treatment or foregoing it altogether, rather than selecting between genuine and sham approaches. Factors such as time constraints, preconceived notions about acupuncture, procedural apprehensions, and transportation accessibility directly shape their willingness to engage with the therapy. We fully recognize the value of placebo controls in randomized controlled trials, particularly their importance for verifying specific therapeutic mechanisms. However, in this study where the primary objective is to evaluate the clinical utility of acupuncture in managing Long COVID-related cognitive impairment, we implemented a pragmatic randomized controlled trial design comparing an acupuncture group versus a health education group.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6-1"><title>Recruitment</title><p>To attract eligible participants, researchers employed a variety of strategies, including organizing free clinics, posting recruitment information on WeChat Moments, putting up promotional posters, distributing flyers in the community, and conducting on-site presentations. These recruitment activities were primarily conducted at The Second Affiliated Hospital of Shenzhen University and its affiliated Xin'an Street Community Health Service Center. During the recruitment process, staff members who had undergone professional training would provide potential participants with a detailed introduction to the specific content of the study. They would also ensure that these individuals signed an informed consent form before agreeing to participate, confirming that they had fully understood the relevant information about the study and were participating voluntarily.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6-2"><title>Randomization, Allocation Concealment, and Blinding</title><p>In this study, we generated a random allocation sequence using the random number table method to assign participants to different groups. The researcher managing this randomization sequence did not participate in the recruitment, assessment, or intervention processes and was independently responsible for the entire sequence management, informing participants of their group assignments. Given the nature of acupuncture treatment, it was not feasible to achieve complete double blinding for all participants and the medical staff administering acupuncture during the treatment phase of this study; however, the assessors and statisticians responsible for data analysis remained unaware of the participants’ group assignments. After the statistical analysis was completed, the treatment group information of the participants was revealed for analysis and summary.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Sample Size</title><p>The MoCA score served as the primary outcome measure for evaluating participants’ cognitive function. Based on existing literature, the MoCA is reported to have a large Cohen’s effect size [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Using G*Power 3.1 software, a sample size calculation was performed with a two-sided α of 0.05 and a power of 0.8, yielding a required sample size of 52 participants. Accounting for a 10–20% attrition rate, the total sample size for this study was set at 60 participants. Furthermore, according to a study by Desmond et al. [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], for fMRI experiments with multiple comparisons corrected at a two-tailed α of 0.05, a minimum of 24 subjects is required to achieve an 80% activation detection rate at the individual level. After considering a potential dropout rate, the adjusted sample size was 29 participants. To ensure higher validity and robustness of the findings, the final sample size selected for this study was 60 participants.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Intervention</title><sec id="s2-8-1"><title>Acupuncture Group</title><p>Acupuncture treatment was conducted in the acupuncture clinic of The Second Affiliated Hospital of Shenzhen University, once on each Monday, Wednesday, and Friday, that is, every other day, for a total of three sessions per week. The entire treatment process consisted of four courses, each lasting 2 weeks. During the treatment process, the number of treatments for participants is recorded by research assistants, who also promptly remind the participants to attend the sessions. The treatment was performed by a licensed traditional Chinese medicine practitioner with over 15 years of acupuncture experience, using disposable Hua Tuo brand acupuncture needles (specifications of 0.25 × 25 mm or 0.30 × 40 mm). Do not engage in other treatments. The selected acupoints included EX-HN1, EX-HN3, bilateral PC6, bilateral ST40, bilateral SP6, bilateral KI3, and bilateral LR3. The specific locations of the acupuncture points can be found in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. Participants were positioned supine, and the skin was routinely disinfected before needling. After needle insertion, the corresponding acupuncture technique is applied based on ensuring that the participant experiences the sensation of deqi. The specific procedures are as follows: for the EX-HN3 points, insert the needle horizontally 0.5 transverse finger width toward the GV20 point along the scalp, using the twisting and rotating reducing method. The procedure for the EX-HN3 point is as follows: first, insert the needle vertically and shallowly into the subcutaneous layer, using the sparrow pecking reducing method until the eyes become moist. Then, pinch the skin and insert the needle horizontally 0.5 transverse finger width toward the tip of the nose. The PC6 point is needled vertically to a depth of 0.5–1.0 transverse finger width, using the twisting and rotating reducing method. The ST40 point is needled vertically to a depth of 1–1.5 transverse finger widths, employing the combined twisting, lifting, and inserting reducing method. For the SP6 point, insert the needle along the posterior edge of the medial side of the tibia at a 45°angle to the skin and needle obliquely backward to a depth of 1.0–1.5 transverse finger widths, using the lifting and inserting tonifying method. The KI3 point is needled vertically to a depth of 0.5 transverse finger width, using the twisting and rotating tonifying method. The LR3 point is needled vertically to a depth of 0.5 transverse finger width, using the twisting and rotating reducing method. During each treatment session, each acupoint is needed for 1 min, followed by a 30-min retention period. The needles are removed after the retention period. During the retention period, the needles are manipulated every 10 min.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Green circular markers indicate the acupoint locations for the acupuncture group: EX-HN1, EX-HN3, PC6, ST40, SP6, KI3, and LR3.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cmr-2025-0000-0000-549822_F03.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>Health Education Group</title><p>The control group received only conventional health education without any additional special interventions. The education was conducted once a week for a total of 8 weeks. The content of the health education covered the symptoms that COVID-19 may cause, how to maintain a healthy lifestyle in the face of subhealth conditions, and the importance of early prevention of Alzheimer’s disease.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2-10"><title>Assessment of Results</title><p>The variables considered in this trial include the participants’ basic information, primary outcomes, and secondary outcomes. Baseline characteristics will be assessed within 1 week prior to randomization. Primary and secondary outcomes will be evaluated within 1 week before and after the participants receive acupuncture treatment. All these assessments will be conducted by multiple members of the research team with extensive experience, reducing the subjectivity of the assessment indicators. These assessors will remain blinded to the group assignments of all participants to ensure the integrity and objectivity of the study.</p></sec><sec id="s2-11"><title>Outcome Indicators</title><p>This study utilized the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) as the primary outcome measurement tool. Designed for rapid assessment within 10 min, this scale provides a standardized evaluation of overall cognitive function in MCI patients, covering seven domains: visuospatial/executive function, naming, verbal memory, attention, abstract thinking, delayed recall, and orientation. Scoring from 0 to 30 (with one point added for individuals with ≤12 years of education), the MoCA yields lower scores correlating with more severe cognitive impairment [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Secondary outcomes employed a multidimensional assessment system. Quantifying dementia severity, the Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR) assesses six domains spanning memory, orientation, judgment and problem-solving, community affairs, home and hobbies, and personal care, producing a total score (0–3) corresponding to the spectrum from normal to severe dementia [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. For initial screening, the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) screens for cognitive deficits using a 0–30 scale (scores &lt;27 suggestive of impairment), offering a rapid and effective diagnostic reference [<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Evaluating independence and rehabilitation needs, the Activities of Daily Living Scale (ADL) [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] measures both basic (BADL) and instrumental (IADL) activities, with higher total scores reflecting greater functional impairment. Focusing on sensitive indicators like long-delay recall (20 min) and recognition, the Huashan version Auditory Verbal Learning Test (AVLT-H) precisely assesses episodic memory function through the memory quotient (MQ), thereby providing specific evidence for identifying MCI [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><sec id="s2-11-1"><title>Resting-State fMRI Data</title><p>After head fixation, resting-state functional brain imaging was initiated using a gradient echo-planar imaging sequence for axial anatomical imaging. The data acquisition slices were parallel to the line connecting the anterior and posterior commissures, ensuring full coverage of the entire brain region. All participants were instructed to remain relaxed and motionless during the scanning process. The specific scanning parameters were set as follows: repetition time = 2 s, echo time = 30 ms, field of view = 220 mm × 220 mm, flip angle = 77°, matrix size = 64 × 64, slice thickness = 4 mm, slice gap = 1 mm, with a total of 30 slices. For anatomical imaging, a T1-weighted gradient echo sequence was used. The acquisition direction of the functional images was consistent with that of the anatomical images, with the following parameters: repetition time = 2.1 s, echo time = 4.6 ms, matrix size = 256 × 256, field of view = 230 mm × 230 mm, flip angle = 8°, slice thickness = 1 mm.</p></sec><sec id="s2-11-2"><title>fMRI Data Analysis Preprocessing</title><p>Using the GRETNA toolbox (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.nitrc.org/projects/gretna/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.nitrc.org/projects/gretna/</ext-link>) on the MATLAB 2013b platform (The MathWorks, Inc., Natick, MA, USA), the initial resting-state fMRI data were converted from the “dicom” format to the “*.nii” format. To eliminate the effects of initial signal instability and the participants’ adaptation to the environment, the first 10 resting-state images were discarded. Subsequently, each image underwent slice timing correction, and the corrected data were realigned to correct for head motion. Data with head motion exceeding 1.5 degrees of rotation or 3 mm of translation were excluded. The data were then normalized, spatially standardized, smoothed, detrended to remove linear drift, and filtered using a band-pass filter for further preprocessing. Finally, time points with excessive head motion were removed through scrubbing to further minimize the impact of head motion.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2-12"><title>Functional Connectivity Matrix</title><p>The GRETNA toolbox was used to perform correlation analysis on the time series between each pair of brain nodes. Common correlation coefficients include Pearson, Spearman, and Kendall. Since Spearman and Kendall correlation coefficients typically measure the monotonic relationship between two variables, this study used the Pearson correlation coefficient to measure the correlation between any two brain regions. Based on the anatomical automatic labeling template, the entire brain was abstracted into a brain network containing 90 nodes. The functional connections between the 90 brain regions were defined as the edges of the brain network. The blood oxygen level-dependent time series of all voxels within each node were extracted, and the pairwise correlations of the time series were used to construct the functional connectivity matrix.</p></sec><sec id="s2-12-1"><title>Risks of Acupuncture</title><p>Acupuncture may cause adverse reactions such as mental fatigue, dizziness, pale complexion, decreased blood pressure, and excessive sweating or subcutaneous bleeding at the acupuncture site leading to swelling, pain, and bruising. Additionally, excessive needle manipulation by the practitioner may cause fainting. The operator will assess these situations and provide appropriate treatment and documentation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-12-2"><title>Safety Monitoring</title><p>During the study, close attention was paid to the frequency and severity of adverse events experienced by patients. Any adverse events that occurred were meticulously recorded in the “Adverse Event Record Form” and addressed accordingly.</p></sec><sec id="s2-13"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data analysis was conducted using SPSS (IBM SPSS Statistics 26.0 for Windows) software by research data processors who were blinded to the group assignments, ensuring the implementation of the blinding method. Initially, summary statistics for all variables were cleaned and processed, checking for missing values and supplementing and perfecting the original data as necessary. The normality of the data was assessed by calculating the deviation of sample data from the theoretical values of a normal distribution, and the Shapiro-Wilk test was used to determine if the data followed a normal distribution. For data that met the normal distribution, the mean ± standard deviation (X ± S) was used for description; for data that did not meet the normal distribution, the Wilcoxon rank-sum test was used, and the median (M) and interquartile range (lower quartile P25, upper quartile P75) were used for description. For the comparison of count data, the chi-square test was used, and the sample size (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>) was used for description. All <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values calculated during the data analysis process were corrected for multiple comparisons. All statistical tests were two tailed, with a significance level α set at 0.05; a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. Analysis of covariance was employed, controlling for covariates such as gender, age, and education level, to accurately assess the independent effect of the intervention. Intergroup comparisons were conducted using an independent-samples <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. Multiple imputation will be utilized to handle missing data, thereby reducing potential bias and ensuring dataset completeness.</p></sec><sec id="s2-14"><title>Data Collection and Data Management</title><p>In this study, data collection will be conducted by data evaluators using the Case Report Form tool. Subsequently, research assistants will enter these data into the data collection system provided by the Clinical Research Electronic Management Public Platform (ResMan) of the Chinese Clinical Trial Registration Center (URL: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.medresman.org.cn" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.medresman.org.cn</ext-link>). After the study is completed, all data generated during this study will be publicly released through this platform for further analysis and validation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-15"><title>Dissemination</title><p>The findings of this study will be published in journals and conference proceedings related to cognitive rehabilitation. The results will be shared with the public through various online and offline methods, including but not limited to academic conferences, online courses, video conferences, and health education sessions. The study protocol has been registered and can be accessed through the Chinese Clinical Trial Registration Center Website (registered at: ChiCTR.org.cn, Registration Number: ChiCTR2400092961).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>In our preliminary studies, resting-state fMRI and cognitive assessments have demonstrated that acupuncture can activate brain regions associated with cognition. The changes in brain networks following acupuncture are characterized by increased connectivity between multiple brain regions. The application of acupuncture can modulate brain networks by enhancing the connectivity between cognition-related brain regions, thereby improving cognitive impairments in patients [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Acupuncture has been found to have a positive effect on cognitive impairments in the elderly. However, research on acupuncture treatment for long COVID syndrome is currently in its preliminary stages. In this study, we designed an acupuncture intervention for patients with MCIs due to long COVID, aiming to investigate the role of acupuncture in alleviating cognitive impairments in patients with long COVID. Additionally, we employed fMRI technology to explore the mechanisms of this intervention from the perspectives of the default mode network and the dorsal attention networks associated with episodic memory in patients with MCIs.</p><p>During the trial, the blinding rule will be strictly followed. The specific grouping details of the trial will be concealed from the study evaluators and data analysts to reduce subjective bias and enhance the reliability and scientific validity of the research results. During the treatment process, the acupuncturist is a licensed traditional Chinese medicine practitioner with over 15 years of acupuncture experience. Patients receive acupuncture treatment three times a week on Mondays, Wednesdays, and Fridays for a total of 8 weeks. Compared to pharmacological treatments, acupuncture has a lower likelihood of causing adverse reactions such as gastrointestinal disturbances and hepatic or renal dysfunction, making it a relatively safe treatment option. This is particularly beneficial for patients with long COVID, especially the elderly and those with chronic underlying conditions, as acupuncture is highly safe with minimal side effects. Moreover, the cost of acupuncture treatment is relatively low. When compared to expensive pharmacological treatments or high-tech medical equipment therapies, acupuncture offers a significant economic advantage. For patients with long COVID who require long-term treatment, this can greatly reduce their financial burden.</p><p>Therefore, this study will yield direct neuroimaging evidence demonstrating that acupuncture improves cognitive function via neuroplastic pathways. It is expected to identify key impaired brain networks associated with cognitive impairment in post-COVID-19 condition and further elucidate acupuncture’s modulatory effects on the functional activity and connectivity strength of these specific networks. The findings may reveal distinct brain network features correlated with the severity of cognitive deficits or treatment response, which could serve as potential objective biomarkers for future auxiliary diagnosis or outcome prediction. This research will provide outcomes with practical value for guiding clinical practice.</p></sec><sec sec-type="acknowledgments" id="s4"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors sincerely thank the staff of the community service centers who participated in this study. We are grateful for the support provided by the clinical trial team at The Second Affiliated Hospital of Shenzhen University.</p></sec><sec sec-type="statement of ethics" id="s5"><title>Statement of Ethics</title><p>This study protocol complies with the Declaration of Helsinki. It has been approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of The Second Affiliated Hospital of Shenzhen University (Approval No. BYL20230815). All participants will provide written consent after being fully informed (trial registration: Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.chictr.org.cn" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.chictr.org.cn</ext-link>), Registration Number: ChiCTR2400092961, Date of Registration: 2024-11-26).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s6"><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding sources" id="s7"><title>Funding Sources</title><p>Funding sources were as follows: National Natural Science Foundation of China (81973922); Shenzhen Bao'an District Medical Association (BAYXH2023011); Shenzhen Bao’an District Traditional Chinese Medicine Development Foundation (2022KJCX-ZJZL-14); and Shenzhen Sanming Project (2022).</p></sec><sec sec-type="author contributions" id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Shangjie Chen and Lei Xu designed the study protocol and conceived the research. Jing Chen wrote the manuscript and participated in the study’s implementation. Dan Wang assisted with the data processing section of the manuscript. Ziang Zhang and Mengru Shen handled participant recruitment. Yingqi Lu contributed to revising the study protocol. All authors participated in drafting the manuscript and read and approved the final version.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s26"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The corresponding author will provide research datasets underlying this work to qualified investigators following reasonable validation of intended usage.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s41"><label>Supplementary Material</label><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Supplementary_material-Suppl.1-s1.pdf" id="d67e584" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>JFW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>To</surname><given-names>KKW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A familial cluster of pneumonia associated with the 2019 novel coronavirus indicating person-to-person transmission: a study of a family cluster</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>395</volume>(<issue>10223</issue>):<fpage>514</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31986261</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30154-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7159286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Horby</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A novel coronavirus outbreak of global health concern</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>395</volume>(<issue>10223</issue>):<fpage>470</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31986257</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30185-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7135038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Serrano Del Pueblo</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano-Heras</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Romero Sánchez</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Landete</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas-Bartolome</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feria</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Brain and cognitive changes in patients with long COVID compared with infection-recovered control subjects</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>147</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3611</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38562097</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/brain/awae101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Taquet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Geddes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luciano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>6-month neurological and psychiatric outcomes in 236 379 survivors of COVID-19: a retrospective cohort study using electronic health records</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33836148</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2215-0366(21)00084-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8023694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haupert</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Global prevalence of post-coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) condition or long COVID: a meta-analysis and systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>226</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1593</fpage>–<lpage>607</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35429399</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/infdis/jiac136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Sk Abd Razak</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul Aziz</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suddin</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Azzeri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sha’ari</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Post-COVID syndrome prevalence: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1785</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38965510</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-024-19264-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11223303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>One-year trajectory of cognitive changes in older survivors of COVID-19 in wuhan, China: a longitudinal cohort study</article-title>. <source>JAMA Neurol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35258587</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaneurol.2022.0461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8905512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tavares-Júnior</surname>
<given-names>JWL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>ACC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>JWP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siqueira-Neto</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sobreira-Neto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>COVID-19 associated cognitive impairment: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35537236</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cortex.2022.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9014565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Panagea</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Messinis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liampas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anyfantis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nasios</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neurocognitive impairment in long COVID: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Arch Clin Neuropsychol</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38850628</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/arclin/acae042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11754669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farah</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sossi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Differences in brain structure and cognitive performance between patients with long-COVID and those with normal recovery</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>300</volume>:<fpage>120859</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39317274</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2024.120859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Díez-Cirarda</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Ruiz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Polidura</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gil-Martínez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado-Alonso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multimodal neuroimaging in post-COVID syndrome and correlation with cognition</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>2142</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36288544</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/brain/awac384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9620345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Merkler</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kamel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of ischemic stroke in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vs patients with influenza</article-title>. <source>JAMA Neurol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32614385</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaneurol.2020.2730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7333175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Hampshire</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chatfield</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>MPhil</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Trender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hellyer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multivariate profile and acute-phase correlates of cognitive deficits in a COVID-19 hospitalised cohort</article-title>. <source>eClinicalMedicine</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>101417</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35505938</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9048584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Damiano</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Rocca</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Pádua Serafim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>LHM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Munhoz</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive decline following acute viral infections: literature review and projections for post-COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>272</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34173049</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00406-021-01286-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8231753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Douaud</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro-Almagro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arthofer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 is associated with changes in brain structure in UK biobank</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>604</volume>(<issue>7907</issue>):<fpage>697</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35255491</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41586-022-04569-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9046077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>de Erausquin</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brugha</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The chronic neuropsychiatric sequelae of COVID-19: the need for a prospective study of viral impact on brain functioning</article-title>. <source>Alzheimers Dement</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1056</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33399270</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/alz.12255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10431934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>de Erausquin</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brugha</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sagar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic neuropsychiatric sequelae of SARS-CoV-2: protocol and methods from the Alzheimer’s association global consortium</article-title>. <source>Alzheimer Dement</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e12348</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/trc2.12348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9494609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36185993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leverenz</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kallianpur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mehra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Network medicine links SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 infection to brain microvascular injury and neuroinflammation in dementia-like cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source>Alzheimers Res Ther</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34108016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13195-021-00850-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8189279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Is acupuncture effective in the treatment of COVID-19 related symptoms? Based on bioinformatics/network topology strategy</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>bbab110</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33866350</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bib/bbab110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8083275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>MXY</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The use of acupuncture for addressing neurological and neuropsychiatric symptoms in patients with long COVID: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Neurol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1406475</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39099786</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fneur.2024.1406475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11294104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Soriano</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Relan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></string-name>; <collab>WHO Clinical Case Definition Working Group on Post-COVID-19 Condition</collab></person-group>. <article-title>A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e102</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Petersen</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mild cognitive impairment as a diagnostic entity</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>256</volume>(<issue>3</issue>) <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15324362</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2796.2004.01388.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Acupuncture on mild cognitive impairment: a systematic review of neuroimaging studies</article-title>. <source>Front Aging Neurosci</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1007436</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36875696</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnagi.2023.1007436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9975578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Puetz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of electroacupuncture vs sham treatment on change in pain severity among adults with chronic low back pain: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e2022787</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33107921</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.22787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7592030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tu</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of intensive acupuncture versus sham acupuncture in knee osteoarthritis: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheumatol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>448</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33174383</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/art.41584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Larner</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect size (cohen’s d) of cognitive screening instruments examined in pragmatic diagnostic accuracy studies</article-title>. <source>Dement Geriatr Cogn Dis Extra</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25177332</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000363735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4132220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Desmond</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating sample size in functional MRI (fMRI) neuroimaging studies: statistical power analyses</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Methods</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12204303</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0165-0270(02)00121-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Nasreddine</surname>
<given-names>ZS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bédirian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Charbonneau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The Montreal cognitive assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817019</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Morris</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical dementia rating: a reliable and valid diagnostic and staging measure for dementia of the Alzheimer type</article-title>. <source>Int Psychogeriatr</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>; discussion 177-178.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9447441</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/s1041610297004870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tombaugh</surname>
<given-names>TN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The mini-mental state examination: a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>922</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1512391</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1532-5415.1992.tb01992.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Pashmdarfard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Azad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment tools to evaluate Activities of Daily Living (ADL) and Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (IADL) in older adults: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Med J Islam Repub Iran</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32617272</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.34171/mjiri.34.33</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7320974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Short-term delayed recall of auditory verbal learning test is equivalent to long-term delayed recall for identifying amnestic mild cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e51157</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23236445</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0051157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3517417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>TT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Modulatory effects of acupuncture on brain networks in mild cognitive impairment patients</article-title>. <source>Neural Regen Res</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28400807</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/1673-5374.200808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5361509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>