<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="other" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Lifestyle Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Lifestyle Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2667</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jlifemed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Lifestyle Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2234-8549</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2288-1557</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Yonsei University Wonju College of Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12405982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12405982.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12405982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12405982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40909985</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15280/jlm.2025.15.2.87</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jlm-15-2-87</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Opinion</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>My Long COVID Journey – How To Slay Dragons Using Neuroplasticity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-5513-6588</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Salker</surname><given-names initials="P">Poonam</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Fernlea Surgery, London, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Poonam Salker, Fernlea Surgery, 114 High Road, London N15 6JR, United Kingdom, Tel: +44-20-8809-6445, E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="p.salker@nhs.net">p.salker@nhs.net</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">496123</issue-id><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-09-05 09:25:55.133"><day>05</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 Journal of Lifestyle Medicine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jlm-15-2-87.pdf"/><abstract><p>Framed through the long COVID experience of a United Kingdom physician, this narrative delineates the neurobiological consequences of chronic stress and highlights the role of neuroplastic interventions in facilitating physiological and cognitive recovery.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Neuronal plasticity</kwd><kwd>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</kwd><kwd>Stress</kwd><kwd>Psychological</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>• <bold>Funding:</bold> None.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Hello All. I’m a general practitioner based in London. I wanted to share with you how I learned to tame my Long COVID. It worked for me and I hope it could work for some of you.</p><p>Prior to the pandemic I was working full-time as an National Health Service doctor and Lifestyle Medicine doctor. I exercised regularly. I was eating healthy unprocessed homecooked food most of the week. I didn’t drink alcohol or smoke. I meditated most days. I mean seriously…!... I was the epitome of ‘health’. Or so I thought.</p><p>After recovering from COVID in March 2020 I was left with a lingering fatigue which I spuriously ignored. I mean don’t we all snub the little parrot that sits on our shoulder squawking “I’m so tired.”? I found myself exhausted and needing sleep after a run as opposed to feeling rejuvenated. Reflecting on it now, these were glimpses of Long COVID.</p><p>By March 2021 I continued to deteriorate and had to stop working. The following months were a blur. I slept for an entire month, waking only to eat, shower and use the bathroom. My thoughts felt slow, my muscles ached, I developed palpitations. I had lost my sparkle. I was just an existence. I remember feeling that if this was going to be my new life, then I didn’t want to be alive. But I never gave up hope.</p><p>My work in lifestyle medicine meant that I knew of people and patients who had overcome conditions such as chronic fatigue syndrome (CFS). Although not so well understood in conventional medicine, in lifestyle medicine it is much better understood and that is where I turned to find my road to recovery.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other"><title>CHRONIC STRESS</title><p>CFS (like Long COVID) does not just develop overnight. It usually develops insidiously after a series of ‘insults’ to our body and mind. Insults can vary from mild or severe illnesses, to micro-stressors, major stressors or poor diet etc. It could simply be a full-time working parent navigating through life. Interestingly most people will have a clear recollection of the final ‘event’ that triggered CFS. For me, acute COVID was the straw that broke the camels’ back. Looking back, I realize that I had huge personal stressors and I didn’t allow myself to process them. In fact I distracted myself by becoming busier than ever to avoid thinking about those ‘dragons’. Do you agree that our world favors those that just power through?</p><p>Insults cause stress on our body via cortisol. Cortisol creates an immune reaction to allow our body to deal with that stress. Even when we exercise there is an immune reaction—this is good stress—i.e. hormetic stress. Consider this day: morning alarm, traffic to work, long list of patients with extra emergencies, dash to pick up kids from school, fix up a quick dinner etc. It’s not particularly odd but with constant exposure to micro-stress we remain in a constant low-level of distress. We were only ever designed to have episodic periods of ‘real’ stress – like running away from a Sabre-tooth tiger.</p><p>Chronic stress in caveman terms suggests poor survival (cannot outrun the Sabre-tooth tiger) and our innate body will do anything consciously or subconsciously to keep us alive. For example our modern-day body could form a risk-averse personality; or be tired all the time to ‘avoid outside danger’; or to not sleep well so we can stay awake in case something tries to ‘kill us’. Of course in reality we aren’t actually going to die.</p><p>I believe we have forgotten how to listen to our body. It is constantly sending us signals. Imagine walking on a dark street alone hearing footsteps behind you – it would be alarming right? But we don’t listen to other alarm bells such as “I’m so tired today, I really can’t get out of bed”. This is not laziness, this is a red flag.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other"><title>ENTER NEUROPLASTICITY TRAINING</title><p>Neuroplasticity is the remarkable ability humans have to make and remake connections in our brain. It was previously thought that brain development ceased during early adulthood. But researchers have shown that our brain networks change constantly throughout our life adjusting to our environment.</p><p>One aspect of neuroplasticity involves experience-dependant plasticity. Whether you are a child, adolescent or older adult, repetitive actions and thoughts (both positive and negative) form neural pathways. That means if you practice something consistently such as meditating, exercising or even things like worrying, those pathways become strengthened.</p><p>Our ancestral bodies are unable to tell the difference between a physical threat (Sabre-tooth tiger/infection) or a psychological threat (pile of deadlines to meet). Our body produces the same immunological response. Our bodies should be fighting off an infection or trigger e.g. stressful day at work and then go back into immunological balance. But with chronic stress, our bodies remain immunologically vulnerable. If we are constantly running from a Sabre-tooth tiger our bodies then worry about what is it taking so long to recover and it goes into overdrive i.e. it overstimulates the neuro-immune system to fight off the threat.</p><p>A perpetuating survival mode primes our bodies—always ready to fight—as it has learnt that its environment is a constant threat to its existence. And so a vicious subconscious/unconscious loop is formed between the amygdala (fear center) and the insula (danger radar). The insula takes signals from the body and feeds it to the brain to allow for the appropriate autonomic and immunological response in order to maintain survival. If everything is perceived as a threat, then the loop is always ‘on’. The conditioned response gets stronger and stronger with an incessant supply of triggers. This persistently ‘on’ alarm bell can eventually give rise to a myriad of symptoms – not just fatigue – it can trigger autoimmune conditions such as Crohn’s or other conditions such as migraines, postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS), food intolerances and allergies. It can literally affect any body system or organ. This could explain the wide variety of Long COVID symptoms.</p><p>We can switch the ‘on’ alarm bell ‘off’ by learning how to stop overresponding to signals. This is the crux of neuroplasticity training. Specific psychological techniques are employed to retrain the conditioned somatic signalling in the brain which locks the neuro-immune system in its state of heightened arousal. Retraining techniques involve repeatedly interrupting signals from the amygdala and insula using a variety of generative practices tailored to the individual patient [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The patient is taught to become aware of the internal signals of the symptoms, and then to act on these signals in a specific way that drastically interrupts the signaling [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. For example, mindfulness training has been shown to reduce amygdala reactivity, and to increase grey matter volume in the prefrontal cortex and the insula [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] which relates to improved symptoms of stress. In a similar vein, mindfulness based interventions have literally shown the ability to reduce inflammatory markers in those with fibromyalgia [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="other"><title>WHO IS IT FOR?</title><p>It has the potential to work for anyone but it is not a panacea; interrupting brain signals are obviously not going to remove a blood clot. If you have POTS then you may need medication to help. That is to say neuroplasticity training has its place.</p><p>I would strongly recommend taking the time to understand how it could work for you before taking a leap of faith.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other"><title>FINAL WORDS</title><p>If you take nothing else from this, please just be open. You could get your life back. I did.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Thank you to my clinical appraiser Mimi Bhattacharya for encouraging me to do this to help others.</p></ack><fn-group><title>NOTES</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>• <bold>Conflicts of Interest:</bold> No conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sanabria-Mazo</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Montero-Marin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feliu-Soler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gasión</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro-Gil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morillo-Sarto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2020</year><article-title>Mindfulness-based program plus amygdala and insula retraining (MAIR) for the treatment of women with fibromyalgia: A pilot randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3246</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9103246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33050630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7599726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gotink</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meijboom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vernooij</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hunink</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>8-week mindfulness based stress reduction induces brain changes similar to traditional long-term meditation practice - A systematic review</article-title><source>Brain Cogn</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bandc.2016.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27429096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2020</year><article-title>New study indicates: Neuroplasticity 'brain retraining' program is a promising treatment for fibromyalgia</article-title><source>J Aust Tradit Med Soc</source><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>