<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Prev Med Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2904</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">pmedr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Preventive Medicine Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2211-3355</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12432515</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12432515.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12432515</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12432515</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40948805</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2025.103188</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2211-3355(25)00227-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103188</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Regular article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association of COVID vaccinations and treatments with long COVID beyond 6 months: a case-control study on the adult population in a large integrated healthcare system in the United States from 2020 to 2023</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="C">Curtis</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="C">Celina</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="R">Rui</given-names></name><email>rui.x.yan@kp.org</email><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names initials="D">Davida</given-names></name><email>davida.becker@kp.org</email><xref rid="af0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names initials="JX">Jia Xiao</given-names></name><email>jiaxiao.m.shi@kp.org</email><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slezak</surname><given-names initials="J">Jeffrey</given-names></name><email>jeff.m.slezak@kp.org</email><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jerng</surname><given-names initials="D">Diane</given-names></name><email>diane.y.jerng@kp.org</email><xref rid="af0025" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>University of Texas Southwestern Medical School, Dallas, TX, United States</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Washington University in St. Louis, St. Louis, MO, United States</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>Department of Research and Evaluation, Kaiser Permanente Southern California Permanente Medical Group, Pasadena, CA, United States</aff><aff id="af0020"><label>d</label>Graduate Medical Education Administration &amp; Research, Kaiser Permanente Southern California Permanente Medical Group, Pasadena, CA, United States</aff><aff id="af0025"><label>e</label>Department of Family Medicine, Kaiser Permanente Southern California Permanente Medical Group, Santa Ana, CA, United States</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: 1900 4<sup>th</sup> Street, Santa Ana, CA 92705, United States. <email>diane.y.jerng@kp.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>57</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">493461</issue-id><elocation-id>103188</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-09-15 15:25:19.733"><day>15</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="ab0005"><sec><title>Objective</title><p>Long coronavirus disease (Long COVID) is a chronic condition causing significant long-term disability and economic burden. This study aims to measure the association between COVID vaccinations and treatment at the time of acute infection with Long COVID outcomes beyond six months post-infection, controlling for demographic and medical variables.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This retrospective case-control study used electronic medical records from Kaiser Permanente Southern California to evaluate Long COVID outcomes from January 2022 to June 2023 with vaccination doses and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir, and from October 2020 to June 2023 with remdesivir and other treatments. Statistical analysis used univariate chi-square and Kruskal-Wallis tests and conditional logistic regression.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Our study had 840 (January 2022 analysis) and 2632 (October 2020 analysis) Long COVID patients diagnosed by International Classification of Diseases-10 code at least 6 months after acute COVID infection with 1:5 matched controls by age, sex, race/ethnicity, Body Mass Index, and date of acute COVID infection. Long COVID outcome was inversely associated with the number of COVID vaccination doses (one dose odds ratio (OR) 0.77; 95 % CI 0.63–0.96, two doses OR 0.73; 95 % CI 0.59–0.92, three doses OR 0.64; 95 % CI 0.44–1.00, four doses OR 0.29; 95 % CI 0.06–1.49) and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir (OR 0.05; 95 % CI 0.04–0.07) or remdesivir (OR 0.31; 95 % CI 0.19–0.49) treatment with no interaction between three vaccinations with nirmatrelvir/ritonavir and four vaccinations with remdesivir treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These findings may influence existing clinical practices for vaccination and antiviral treatment strategies to decrease Long COVID consequences.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab0010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="li0005"><label>•</label><p id="p0005">Addresses vaccination and treatment impact on Long COVID outcome beyond six months.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0010"><label>•</label><p id="p0010">Increasing number of vaccinations further decreases Long COVID 23–36 %.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0015"><label>•</label><p id="p0015">Remdesivir reduced Long COVID by 69 %.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0020"><label>•</label><p id="p0020">Remdesivir effect was independent of up to four vaccination doses.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0025"><label>•</label><p id="p0025">Nirmatrelvir/ritonavir reduced Long COVID by 95 %.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0030"><label>•</label><p id="p0030">Nirmatrelvir/ritonavir effect was independent of up to three vaccination doses.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</kwd><kwd>Antiviral agents</kwd><kwd>Severe acute respiratory syndrome-coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2)</kwd><kwd>Vaccination</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term id="kw0030">BMI</term><def><p>Body Mass Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0040">CDC</term><def><p>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0050">CI</term><def><p>Confidence Interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0060">COPD</term><def><p>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0070">COVID</term><def><p>Coronavirus Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0080">COVID-19</term><def><p>Coronavirus Disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0090">HTN</term><def><p>Hypertension</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0100">ICD-10</term><def><p>International Classification of Diseases 10</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0110">KPSC</term><def><p>Kaiser Permanente Southern California</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0120">Long COVID</term><def><p>Long coronavirus disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0130">ME/CFS</term><def><p>Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0140">OR</term><def><p>Odds Ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0150">PASC</term><def><p>Post-acute Sequelae of COVID-19 infection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0160">RRC</term><def><p>Regional Research Committee</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0170">SARS-CoV-2</term><def><p>Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome-Coronavirus 2</p></def></def-item></def-list></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><sec id="s0010"><label>1.1</label><title>Background</title><p id="p0040">Long coronavirus disease (Long COVID) is “an infection-associated chronic condition that occurs after severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection and is present for at least 3 months as a continuous, relapsing and remitting, or progressive disease state that affects one or more organ systems.” (<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr"><italic toggle="yes">Examining the Working Definition for Long COVID | National Academies</italic>, 2024</xref>) An estimated 6 % of the global population infected with coronavirus disease (COVID) suffer with Long COVID (<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Global Burden of Disease Long COVID Collaborators, Sarah Wulf Hanson, Cristiana Abbafati, Joachim G. Aerts, Ziyad Al-Aly, Charlie Ashbaugh, Tala Ballouz, 2022</xref>). Studies have found increased risk of Long COVID with repeated COVID infections, potentially increasing Long COVID incidence over time (<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Bowe et al., 2022</xref>). Health care costs and reduction or loss of employment costs range up to $3.7 trillion in the United States alone (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Cutler, 2022</xref>). Thus, there is a desperate need to understand preventive measures for Long COVID.</p></sec><sec id="s0015"><label>1.2</label><title>Rationale</title><p id="p0045">COVID vaccinations and treatments are modifiable factors, which makes them useful preventive measures. COVID vaccination has been associated with a reduced risk of Long COVID; however, vaccination benefit spans a wide range from 4 to 84 % risk reduction (<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Al-Aly et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Arjun et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Byambasuren et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Kuodi et al., 2022</xref>). In addition, although anti-viral results varied widely (<xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Ioannou et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Durstenfeld et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., n.d.</xref>; <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Fernández-de-las-Peñas et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Boglione et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2025</xref>), a meta-analysis of all anti-viral treatments also concluded that Long COVID was on average 27.5 % lower in the antiviral treatment group, including remdesivir, nirmaltrelvir-ritonavir (Paxlovid), and molnupiravir (<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2023</xref>). However, most of the existing studies evaluated Long COVID at or less than 6 months, a time period that some patients are still naturally recovering from their symptoms to complete resolution (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Montoy, 2023</xref>). This self-recovery process can skew the existing research results on vaccine and treatment efficacy for the group of Long COVID patients who continue to suffer more than 6 months after their acute COVID infection. Because Long COVID has been demonstrated to extend months and years beyond the initial 3-to-6-month period, it is important to differentiate the impact of vaccination and treatments on Long COVID risk for this group of Long COVID people who suffer this prolonged disability (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Montoy, 2023</xref>).</p><p id="p0050">Moreover, no publications to our knowledge to date directly address the interaction of vaccinations and antiviral medications. To address these issues and further clarify the utility of vaccinations and treatments for risk reduction of Long COVID, we employ a case-control design within a large integrated healthcare electronic database, accounting for known confounding factors cited in the literature, and using physician/clinician diagnosis by International Classification of Diseases 10 (ICD-10) codes of Long COVID 6 months and beyond after acute COVID infection (<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Duerlund et al., 2022</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0020"><title>Objectives</title><p id="p0055">To test whether the number of COVID vaccinations received (zero to five doses) prior to acute COVID infection and the receipt of COVID treatment at the time of acute COVID infection is associated with Long COVID outcomes 6 months and beyond post-infection.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0030"><label>2.1</label><title>Study design and setting and study population</title><p id="p0060">This case-control study was conducted within the Kaiser Permanente Southern California (KPSC) integrated healthcare system in the United States and approved by the Institutional Review Board of Kaiser Permanente Southern California. Patient records link patient data over time and through enrollment and non-enrollment periods. We included patients with data at the time of acute COVID infection and Long COVID diagnosis coded 6 months until the end of the study period.</p><p id="p0065">Our electronic medical record database tracks COVID infections by SARS-CoV-2 positive lab results, ICD-10 codes for COVID infection, patient reported positive home test kits, patient request for acute COVID treatment and work notes, chart review search words for COVID/SARS-CoV-2 infection, and reported care received outside of our healthcare system.</p><p id="p0070">Cases were patients diagnosed with Long COVID whose symptoms persisted for greater than 6 months after an acute COVID infection. In cases with multiple COVID infection, the index COVID infection was the most recent COVID infection that was at least 6 months prior to the first ICD coding for Long COVID. Controls without Long COVID have a corresponding positive COVID test result on the exact date of case infection.</p><p id="p0075">A chart review was performed to validate the ICD codes used to distinguish between cases and controls. 125 case patients and 75 control patients were randomly selected for a physician manual chart review to verify physician/clinician accuracy of Long COVID diagnosis (Appendix A). Some patients were assigned a Long COVID ICD code that subsequent visits did not substantiate. Therefore, patients were defined as Long COVID cases only if they had two or more ICD-10 coded Long COVID diagnosis 6 months and beyond an acute COVID infection and/or Long COVID diagnosis coded as an ongoing chronic medical condition in the Problem List. This adjustment helped to avoid inaccurate diagnosis or self-resolving symptoms that may have been mis-attributed to Long COVID. The Long COVID patients who continued to have ongoing Long COVID symptoms 6 months and beyond from their acute COVID infection were selected as cases with this ICD criteria adjustment. Patients who only had an ICD code for Long COVID within 6 months of their index COVID infection were excluded from the Long COVID case cohort. All 75 controls in the chart review did not have any Long COVID diagnostic codes or associated symptoms by chart review word search.</p><p id="p0080">KPSC patients from 18 years old and older with a COVID positive result or documented COVID infection from January 1, 2022 to November 30, 2022 were included to evaluate the effect of vaccinations and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir treatment on Long COVID outcomes. This study period spans the time after primary COVID vaccination series with booster was available and use of nirmatrelvir/ritonavir began in our organization. The Long COVID diagnostic codes for Post-Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC) (U09.9/B94.8, G93.31/R53.82, U09.9/B94.8, U09.9/B94.8, U09.9/B94.8, U09.9/B94.8, U09.9/B94.8, U09.9/B94.8) were abstracted from June 1, 2022 to June 30, 2023 to capture Long COVID diagnostic codes 6 months to 1 year from the acute COVID infection.</p><p id="p0085">Since nirmatrelvir/ritonavir treatment during the January 1, 2022 to November 30, 2022 study period was being used in place of remdesivir and other COVID treatments when criteria were met (Appendix B), a second analysis was performed when these other treatments were available. KPSC patients from 18 years old and older with a COVID positive result or documented COVID infection from October 1, 2020 to November 30, 2022 were included to evaluate the effect of remdesivir and other available treatments on Long COVID outcomes. Long COVID diagnostic codes were abstracted from April 1, 2021 to June 30, 2023 to capture Long COVID diagnostic codes 6 months to 2.16 years from the acute COVID infection.</p><p id="p0090">A sensitivity analysis was conducted with KPSC patients from 18 years old and older with a COVID positive result or documented COVID infection from March 1, 2020 to November 30, 2022 when COVID testing became widely available.</p><p id="p0095">Patients with a history of myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome (ME/CFS) (ICD-10 code R53.82) or fibromyalgia (ICD-10 code M79.7) fulfilling ME/CFS criteria were excluded. We did not include pediatric patients in this study as the number of Long COVID patients less than 18 years old was small and anti-viral treatment usage was rare.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.2</label><title>Case-control matching</title><p id="p0100">This study used matched cohorts (1:5 case: control) to age, sex, ethnicity, and body mass index (BMI), as well as the exact date of acute COVID infection to account for different SARS-CoV-2 variant periods (Appendix B). For categorical age groups, we used 18 to less than 45, 45 to 55, and greater than 55 years old. Sex was female or male. Ethnicity was grouped into Asian, Black, LatinX, White, and Other. BMI was grouped categorically as normal (less than 25), overweight (25 to 30), and obese (greater than 30). These demographic factors have been implicated to have impact on risks for Long COVID (<xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Vimercati et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Tsampasian et al., 2023</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.3</label><title>Variables</title><p id="p0105">The primary exposure variable was number of vaccination doses at the time of index COVID infection. Completion of three vaccination doses was available at the initiation of our January 2022 study period, with the primary series beginning December 2020 and the third booster dose available October 2021. The fourth vaccination dose was available April 2022, within six months after the third dose. The fifth vaccination dose was available September 2022, within six months after the fourth dose. We did not include vaccination categories defined as Full, Partial, or None (Appendix B), because our sample size for fully vaccinated Long COVID patients was small. Only patients with Pfizer and Moderna mRNA vaccinations were used in our study because of its wide availability in our healthcare system.</p><p id="p0110">A secondary exposure variable was the dispensed use of inpatient and outpatient treatment of acute COVID infection with remdesivir, monoclonal antibodies, convalescent plasma, or nirmatrelvir/ritonavir, which were the most used treatments at the time (Appendix B). Our pharmacy database tracks dates of inpatient or home infusion initiation and dispensed outpatient medications within our pharmacy and outside KPSC-affiliated pharmacies. Monoclonal antibody and convalescent plasma treatment was variable in availability and efficacy through this study period, and use was discontinued December 1, 2022 in our healthcare system.</p><p id="p0115">Other covariates included hospitalization at the time of the index COVID infection, number of COVID infections, comorbid asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), diabetes, hypertension (HTN), depression, anxiety, and smoking.</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0120">Continuous variables were compared using Kruskal-Wallis test. Categorical variables were analyzed using chi-square test. A conditional logistic regression analysis examined the association between exposures to COVID vaccinations and treatments at the time of the index COVID infection and Long COVID outcome. Based on significant variables and adequate sample size, the following variables were included along with number of COVID vaccination and acute COVID treatment with nirmatrelvir/ritonavir and remdesivir: hospitalization, number of COVID infections, and comorbidities (asthma, COPD, smoking status, diabetes, hypertension, depression). Odds ratios (OR) are reported with 95 % confidence intervals.</p><p id="p0125">An interaction study to analyze the maximum likelihood estimates was also conducted to evaluate any interaction between vaccination doses and treatment effect for nirmatrelvir/ritonavir from January 2022 to June 2023 and remdesivir from October 2020 to June 2023.</p><p id="p0130">Age groups 18–49, 50–64, and 65+ were used in the conditional logistic regression model to correspond to updated Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) guidelines for vaccination and anti-viral treatment.</p><p id="p0135">All statistical analysis was performed using statistical software SAS 9.4.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0055"><label>3.1</label><title>Study size</title><p id="p0140">The total population in our database included 1,118,736 controls and 6546 cases that met our definition of Long COVID with symptoms beyond 6 months (Appendix C). 15,553 patients were excluded from our unmatched total population due to ME/CFS or fibromyalgia diagnosis. After matching demographic factors (age, sex, ethnicity, BMI, and date of acute COVID infection), we studied 840 cases and 4200 controls for the January 2022 to June 2023 analysis (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1a</xref>), and 2632 cases and 13,160 controls for the October 2020 to June 2023 analysis (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 1b</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1a</label><caption><p>Demographic information, treatment, and comorbidities split between Long COVID (coronavirus) cases and COVID positive controls for matched adult population in Kaiser Permanente Southern California from January 2022 to November 2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Table 1a</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">1</xref><hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">1</xref><hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 4200)<break/>n (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 840)<break/>n (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 5040)<break/>n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age Group at Diagnosis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18–45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1280 (30.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256 (30.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1536 (30.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45–55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">950 (22.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">190 (22.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1140 (22.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1970 (46.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">394 (46.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2364 (46.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2815 (67.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">563 (67.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3378 (67.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1385 (33.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">277 (33.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1662 (33.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race/Ethnicity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">355 (8.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (8.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">426 (8.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">230 (5.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (5.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">276 (5.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1955 (46.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">391 (46.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2346 (46.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (3.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (3.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">156 (3.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1530 (36.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">306 (36.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1836 (36.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Body Mass Index</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal (&lt;25)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">835 (19.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">167 (19.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1002 (19.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overweight (25–30)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1105 (26.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">221 (26.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1326 (26.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obese (&gt;30)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2260 (53.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">452 (53.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2712 (53.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">COVID Variant</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1255 (29.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">251 (29.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1506 (29.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1050 (25.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">210 (25.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1260 (25.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">385 (9.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (9.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">462 (9.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1510 (36.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">302 (36.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1812 (36.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatments</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaccinations</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1104 (26.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">272 (32.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1376 (27.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1334 (31.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">250 (29.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1584 (31.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1439 (34.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">266 (31.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1705 (33.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">304 (7.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (6.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">354 (7.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (0.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remdesivir Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4131 (98.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">833 (99.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4964 (98.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (1.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monoclonal Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4193 (99.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">840 (100.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5033 (99.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nirmatrelvir/<break/>ritonavir Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2317 (55.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">757 (90.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3074 (61.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1883 (44.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83 (9.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1966 (39.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Convalescent Plasma Transfusion</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4200 (100.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">840 (100.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5040 (100.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical History</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4191 (99.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">836 (99.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5027 (99.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (0.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Acute Covid Infections</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1383 (32.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">388 (46.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1771 (35.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2535 (60.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">383 (45.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2918 (57.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">261 (6.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (7.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">322 (6.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (0.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (0.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asthma prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3861 (91.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">751 (89.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4612 (91.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">339 (8.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89 (10.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">428 (8.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3962 (94.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">779 (92.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4741 (94.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">238 (5.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (7.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">299 (5.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Depression prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3883 (92.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">752 (89.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4635 (92.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">317 (7.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (10.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">405 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2725 (64.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">529 (63.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3254 (64.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1475 (35.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">311 (37.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1786 (35.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension<break/>prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3419 (81.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">719 (85.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4138 (82.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">781 (18.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">121 (14.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">902 (17.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3704 (88.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">761 (90.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4465 (88.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">496 (11.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (9.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">575 (11.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking Status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">387 (9.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70 (8.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">457 (9.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">407 (9.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (11.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">506 (10.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2911 (69.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">600 (71.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3511 (69.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">495 (11.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (8.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">566 (11.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0005"><label>1</label><p id="np0005">Controls defined as no Long COVID diagnosis by International Classification of Diseases (ICD). Cases defined as Long COVID diagnosis by ICD code 6 months and beyond acute COVID infection.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0010"><label>2</label><p id="np0010">Chi-Square test and matched by age, sex, race/ethnicity, Body Mass Index (BMI), acute coronavirus (COVID) infection variant date.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1b</label><caption><p>Demographic information, treatment, and comorbidities split between Long COVID (coronavirus) cases and COVID positive controls for matched adult population in Kaiser Permanente Southern California from October 2020 to November 2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Table 1b</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control<xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">1</xref><hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case<xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">1</xref><hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 13,160)<break/>n (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 2632)<break/>n (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 15,792)<break/>n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age at Diagnosis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0020" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18–45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4565 (34.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">913 (34.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5478 (34.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45–55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3040 (23.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">608 (23.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3648 (23.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5555 (42.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1111 (42.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6666 (42.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0020" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8400 (63.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1680 (63.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,080 (63.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4760 (36.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">952 (36.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5712 (36.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race/Ethnicity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0020" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">915 (7.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">183 (7.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1098 (7.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">750 (5.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">150 (5.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">900 (5.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7095 (53.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1419 (53.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8514 (53.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">360 (2.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 (2.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">432 (2.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4040 (30.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">808 (30.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4848 (30.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Body Mass Index</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0020" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal (&lt;25)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2275 (17.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">455 (17.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2730 (17.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overweight (25–30)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3875 (29.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">775 (29.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4650 (29.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obese (&gt;30)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7010 (53.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1402 (53.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8412 (53.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">COVID Variant</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.99<xref rid="tf0020" ref-type="table-fn">2</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alpha</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">155 (1.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (1.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">186 (1.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6635 (50.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1327 (50.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7962 (50.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delta</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1720 (13.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">344 (13.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2064 (13.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1705 (13.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">341 (13.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2046 (13.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1050 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">210 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1260 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">385 (2.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (2.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">462 (2.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1510 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">302 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1812 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatments</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaccinations</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8961 (68.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1875 (71.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,836 (68.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2351 (17.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">426 (16.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2777 (17.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1524 (11.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">278 (10.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1802 (11.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">305 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (1.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">356 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remdesivir Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,845 (97.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2611 (99.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,456 (97.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">315 (2.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">336 (2.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monoclonal Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,144 (99.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2632 (100.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,776 (99.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nirmatrelvir/<break/>ritonavir Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7653 (58.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2340 (88.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9993 (63.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5507 (41.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">292 (11.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5799 (36.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Convalescent Plasma Transfusion</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.37</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,115 (99.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2620 (99.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,735 (99.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (0.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (0.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical History</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,954 (98.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2573 (97.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,527 (98.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">206 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (2.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">265 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Acute Covid Infections</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4553 (34.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">979 (37.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5532 (35.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7845 (59.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1368 (52.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9213 (58.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">711 (5.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">260 (9.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">971 (6.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asthma prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,199 (92.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2411 (91.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,610 (92.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">961 (7.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">221 (8.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1182 (7.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,456 (94.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2455 (93.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,911 (94.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">704 (5.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">177 (6.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">881 (5.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Depression prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,271 (93.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2383 (90.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,654 (92.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">889 (6.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">249 (9.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1138 (7.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8729 (66.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1700 (64.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,429 (66.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4431 (33.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">932 (35.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5363 (34.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension<break/>prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,792 (82.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2254 (85.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,046 (82.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2368 (18.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">378 (14.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2746 (17.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,538 (87.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2361 (89.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,899 (88.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1622 (12.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">271 (10.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1893 (12.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking Status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1152 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">218 (8.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1370 (8.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1180 (9.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">278 (10.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1458 (9.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9192 (69.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1906 (72.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,098 (70.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1636 (12.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">230 (8.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1866 (11.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0015"><label>1</label><p id="np0015">Controls defined as no Long COVID diagnosis by International Classification of Diseases (ICD). Cases defined as Long COVID diagnosis by ICD code 6 months and beyond acute COVID infection.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0020"><label>2</label><p id="np0020">Chi-Square test and matched by age, sex, race/ethnicity, Body Mass Index (BMI), acute coronavirus (COVID) infection variant date.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>3.2</label><title>Descriptive statistics</title><p id="p0145">Participants with Long COVID were less likely to be treated with nirmatrelvir/ritonavir (9.9 % vs 44.8 %; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0 0.001) (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1a</xref>) and remdesivir (0.8 % vs 2.4 %; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0 0.001). Convalescent plasma (0.5 % vs 0.3 %, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.37) and monoclonal antibody (0 % vs 0.1 %, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.07) treatment were not significantly different between groups (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 1b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>3.3</label><title>Conditional logistical regression analysis</title><p id="p0150">The number of COVID vaccinations was inversely associated with Long COVID outcome compared to those who had no COVID vaccinations; odds ratios for Long COVID were reduced among those with one dose (OR 0.77; 95 % CI 0.63–0.96), two doses (OR 0.73; 95 % CI 0.59–0.92), and three doses (OR 0.66; 95 % CI 0.44–1.00). Patients with four doses showed a trend only for reduced odds of Long COVID compared to those who had no vaccination (OR 0.29; 95 % CI 0.06–1.49) (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 2a</xref>). There were no patients with five vaccination doses in our Long COVID cases. Treatment with nirmatrelvir/ritonavir (OR 0.05; 95 % CI 0.04–0.07) at the time of the index COVID infection was associated with decreased Long COVID outcome (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 2a</xref>). Treatment with remdesivir (OR 0.31; 95 % CI 0.19–0.49) at the time of the index COVID infection was associated with decreased Long COVID outcome (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 2b</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2a</label><caption><p>Adjusted odds ratios from conditional logistic regression with 95 % confidence intervals for vaccination and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir effect on Long COVID (coronavirus) outcome from matched adult population in Kaiser Permanente Southern California with acute COVID infection January 2022 to November 2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Table 2a</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 % CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18–49 years old</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50–64 years old</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54–1.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65+ years old</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31–0.75</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Treatments</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Vaccination Doses</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.77</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63–0.96</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59–0.92</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44–1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06–1.49</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remdesivir Given<xref rid="tf0025" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20–1.18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nirmatrelvir/<break/>ritonavir Given<xref rid="tf0025" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04–0.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Medical History</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization<xref rid="tf0025" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22–4.58</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of COVID-19 Infections</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07–1.42</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Asthma<xref rid="tf0025" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05–1.85</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease<xref rid="tf0025" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92–1.81</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Depression<xref rid="tf0025" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06–1.90</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Hypertension<xref rid="tf0025" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.65–1.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Diabetes<xref rid="tf0025" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62–1.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Smoking Status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95–2.04</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83–1.51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49–1.08</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0025"><label>⁎</label><p id="np0025">Compared to patients without the variable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t0020" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2b</label><caption><p>Adjusted odds ratios from conditional logistic regression with 95 % confidence intervals for remdesivir effect on Long COVID (coronavirus) outcome from matched adult population in Kaiser Permanente Southern California with acute COVID infection October 2020 to November 2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0020">Table 2b</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 % CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18–49 years old</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50–64 years old</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75–1.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65+ years old</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46–0.76</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Treatments</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Vaccination Doses</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73–0.97</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.65–0.96</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46–1.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06–1.58</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remdesivir Given<xref rid="tf0030" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.19–0.49</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nirmatrelvir/<break/>ritonavir Given<xref rid="tf0030" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05–0.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Medical History</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization<xref rid="tf0030" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00–1.98</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of COVID-19 Infections</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68–1.96</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Asthma<xref rid="tf0030" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98–1.38</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease<xref rid="tf0030" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05–1.55</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Depression<xref rid="tf0030" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22–1.70</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Hypertension<xref rid="tf0030" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72–0.97</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Diabetes<xref rid="tf0030" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74–1.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Smoking Status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14–1.77</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95–1.32</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59–0.91</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0030"><label>⁎</label><p id="np0030">Compared to patients without the variable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0155">Our sensitivity analysis for KPSC patients from 18 years old and older with a COVID positive result or documented COVID infection from March 1, 2020 to November 30, 2022 when COVID testing became available revealed comparable results (<xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0025" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Adjusted odds ratios from conditional logistic regression with 95 % Wald confidence intervals for sensitivity analysis for Long COVID (coronavirus) outcome from matched adult population in Kaiser Permanente Southern California with acute COVID infection from March 2020 to November 2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0025">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 % CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18–49 years old<break/>50–64 years old</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00<break/>0.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><break/>0.77–1.10</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65+ years old</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48–0.77</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Treatments</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Vaccination Doses</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71–0.95</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64–0.95</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45–0.99</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06–1.56</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remdesivir Given<xref rid="tf0035" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20–0.50</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nirmatrelvir/ritonavir Given<xref rid="tf0035" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05–0.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Medical History</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization<xref rid="tf0035" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12–2.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of COVID-19 Infections</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.89</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.75–2.03</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Asthma<xref rid="tf0035" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03–1.43</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior COPD<xref rid="tf0035" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07–1.55</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Depression<xref rid="tf0035" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21–1.66</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Hypertension<xref rid="tf0035" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73–0.96</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prior Diabetes<xref rid="tf0035" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.77–1.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Smoking Status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18–1.78</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98–1.34</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0035"><label>⁎</label><p id="np0035">Compared to patients without the variable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0160">There was no interaction found between nirmatrelvir/ritonavir and three vaccination doses (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.38 for one vaccination, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.24 for two vaccinations, and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.08 for three vaccinations). For four vaccination doses, there was an interaction found, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002. There was no interaction found between remdesivir for four vaccination doses (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.74 for one vaccination, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.92 for two vaccinations, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.96 for three vaccinations, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.98 for four vaccinations).</p><p id="p0165">When using the 18–49 age group as a reference in the January 2022 to June 2023 analysis, the 65 and older age group had a reduced odds of Long COVID (OR 0.48; 95 % CI 0.31–0.75) and the 50–64 age group had a nonsignificant result (OR 0.76; 95 % CI 0.54–1.07). When using the 18–49 age group as a reference in the October 2020 to June 2023 analysis, the 65 and older age group had a reduced odds of Long COVID (OR 0.59; 95 % CI 0.46–0.78 and the 50–64 age group had a nonsignificant result (OR 0.90; 95 % CI 0.75–1.09).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0070"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0170">Our case-control study using an electronic database adjusted for demographic and other confounding variables was consistent with other studies finding a reduced risk of Long COVID after vaccination, nirmatrelvir-ritonavir, and remdesivir treatment.</p><p id="p0175">Since a universally accepted definition of Long COVID is still controversial and being established, different definitions of Long COVID used across studies may affect data outcomes (Appendix A). Our study differed from most studies in that we assessed Long COVID conditions after 6 months, a distinction that has been supported by more recent studies (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Montoy, 2023</xref>; <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Thaweethai et al., 2023</xref>). Significant natural reduction and resolution of symptoms can occur up to 6 months at which point Long COVID symptoms seem to stabilize (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Montoy, 2023</xref>). Interestingly, Long COVID with post-viral chronic fatigue and ME/CFS share similar features and the Institute of Medicine of the National Academies recommends 6 months of symptoms before the diagnosis of ME/CFS is made (<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Komaroff and Lipkin, 2023</xref>; <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Wong and Weitzer, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">IOM, 2015</xref>). Using at least 6 months of Long COVID symptoms in our study clarifies the impact of intervention and limits confounding scenarios that include individuals whose symptoms continue to decrease and resolve naturally 4 weeks to 6 months from their acute COVID infection.</p><sec id="s0075"><label>4.1</label><title>Vaccinations</title><p id="p0180">Our findings support other studies in that one vaccination dose decreases Long COVID, but an increasing number of vaccine doses further reduce Long COVID outcomes (<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Byambasuren et al., 2023</xref>). Patients with four vaccination doses showed no statistical significance, likely due to inadequate power in this Long COVID cohort. The small number of Long COVID cases in our data of four or more vaccination doses as well as in our fully vaccinated cohort may also reflect a vaccination protective factor which could not be addressed in our case-control design. In our total population of over one million patients prior to matched data, there were only 3 patients in our Long COVID cohort with 4 vaccinations and no Long COVID patients in our cohort who had 5 vaccinations, the maximum number of vaccinations recommended by CDC at the time of our study period (Appendix C).</p></sec><sec id="s0080"><label>4.2</label><title>Treatments</title><p id="p0185">For the impact of nirmatrelvir-ritonavir on Long COVID outcomes, there was a significant decrease in Long COVID at a greater impact than other studies examining Long COVID at or less than 6 months (<xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Fernández-de-las-Peñas et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Boglione et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2023</xref>). In our January 2022 to June 2023 analysis, remdesivir effect on Long COVID outcomes was not statistically significant, likely from the small number of patients treated with remdesivir during this time period. When we analyzed the impact of remdesivir on Long COVID outcome in our October 2020 to June 2023 analysis, the results were similar to a study on Long COVID risk at a mean of 18 months post-acute COVID infection with a risk reduction of 60 % on Long COVID (OR 0.40; 95 % CI 0.26–0.63) (<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Fernández-de-las-Peñas et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p id="p0190">Moreover, this study provides new evidence that there was no significant interaction between the effect of vaccination up to three doses and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir treatment and up to four vaccination doses with remdesivir treatment. This result supports strong protection against persistent Long COVID symptoms with anti-viral treatment for all adults who continue to decline COVID vaccination due to adverse side effects, allergic reactions, or vaccine hesitancy. Moreover, these findings not only support the importance of vaccinating widely but also providing antivirals for vaccinated individuals to significantly reduce Long COVID outcomes. These results are consistent with findings by Xie, Choi, and Al-Aly (2023b) who examined the effect of nirmatrelvir/ritonavir treatment and also found a 26 % reduction of Long COVID in patients with at least one risk factor for progression to severe COVID-19 illness at 6 months follow-up in “unvaccinated, vaccinated, and boosted, and in people with primary SARS-CoV-2 infection and reinfection” (<xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p id="p0195">In contrast to antivirals showing a greater reduction in Long COVID outcomes, our study was inconclusive for plasma transfusion and monoclonal antibody treatment on Long COVID. Since plasma transfusion and monoclonal antibody treatment were not consistently available or widely used in our organization, our sample size was small. In contrast, a prospective study in a randomized treatment trial demonstrated early COVID convalescent plasma (CCP) treatment less than 5 days after symptom onset compared to late CCP treatment had statistically significant lower odds of Post COVID Conditions at 90 days post-infection (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Gebo et al., 2023</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>4.3</label><title>Limitations and next steps</title><p id="p0200">This research study used a case-control design, which has inherent limitations because causality cannot be established. In addition, our sample may not be representative of all patients who were undiagnosed, misdiagnosed, died, or left our organization through the COVID pandemic. In addition, patients may have filled nirmatrelvir/ritonavir prescriptions but may not have subsequently taken the medication.</p><p id="p0205">Because we designated the index COVID infection as the most recent COVID infection documented at least 6 months prior to the first ICD coding for Long COVID, it is possible that a second infection occurring within the 6 months of the Long COVID diagnosis was the infection that caused the Long COVID diagnosis. The incorrect COVID infection may have been attributed to the Long COVID diagnosis in our data for these instances.</p><p id="p0210">This design also could not address incidence or prevalence, so we could not evaluate the decreased risk of Long COVID that vaccinations may affect by preventing or mitigating COVID infection. Vaccination and treatment recommendations as well as different times of availability varied throughout the course of the COVID pandemic, which may have limited sample size and power for direct comparison. It may be important in future studies to investigate whether four or more doses of vaccination or vaccination status with booster dose within 6 months of acute COVID infection provides significant risk reduction of Long COVID. It would also be important to further study the pediatric population on vaccination and treatment impact for Long COVID beyond 6 months.</p><p id="p0215">There were a few patients (2 %) in our chart review study who had Long COVID symptoms for more than 6 months but recovered after a year, having received several vaccinations within the first 6-month period after acute infection. We did not analyze the impact of COVID vaccination after acute COVID infection or other factors on resolution of Long COVID symptoms beyond 6 months since this was out of the scope of our study. However, our observation is supported by studies showing that an initial early vaccination after acute COVID infection may decrease the risk of ongoing Long COVID symptoms (<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Al-Aly et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Kuodi et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Herman et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Malden et al., 2024</xref>). However, results from other studies on vaccination after Long-COVID diagnosis to improve Long COVID symptoms revealed conflicting outcomes of improvement, same, or worsening status (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Scherlinger et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Wanga, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Tran et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Arnold et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Strain et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Massey et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Ceban et al., 2023</xref>). Further studies exploring the effects of vaccination after acute COVID infection could clarify outcomes of Long COVID and provide another strategy in controlling the incidence rate of Long COVID.</p><p id="p0220">Our findings may support more widespread use of antiviral treatment to reduce the risk of Long COVID than current clinical practice. Future study to explore the patient characteristics in each of the vaccination and treatment exposure and non-exposure groups would further enlighten our understanding of Long COVID risk factors to guide future clinical practice guidelines.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0090"><label>5</label><title>Summary</title><p id="p0225">Our case-control study of adults in a large electronic healthcare database, accounting for existing known confounding factors and using physician/clinician diagnosed Long COVID by ICD-10 code, advances previous studies that vaccination, remdesivir, and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir show significant associations with decreased Long COVID outcomes at 6 months and beyond after acute COVID infection. Moreover, our interaction study findings suggest that broader use of anti-viral treatment may greatly decrease the risk of future Long COVID disability with its associated personal, societal, and economic suffering.</p></sec><sec id="s0105"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0240"><bold>Curtis Liu:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Writing – original draft, Visualization, Formal analysis. <bold>Celina Liu:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Writing – original draft, Visualization, Formal analysis. <bold>Rui Yan:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Visualization, Software, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation. <bold>Davida Becker:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Supervision, Methodology, Formal analysis, Conceptualization. <bold>Jia Xiao Shi:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Supervision, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Jeffrey Slezak:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Methodology, Formal analysis, Conceptualization. <bold>Diane Jerng:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Writing – original draft, Supervision, Methodology, Investigation, Funding acquisition, Formal analysis, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec id="s0095"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="p0230">The Institutional Review Board of Kaiser Permanente Southern California reviewed and approved the protocol on 4/13/2022 #13206. Patient consent was not deemed necessary.</p></sec><sec id="s0100"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0235">This research was supported by the Regional Research Committee of <funding-source id="gts0005"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100005977</institution-id><institution>Kaiser Permanente</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Southern California [grant # <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gts0005">KP-RRC-20230502</award-id>] from July 1, 2023 to June 30, 2024.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0005"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0250">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID after breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1461</fpage><lpage>1467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01840-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35614233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9307472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arjun</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and predictors of long COVID among diagnosed cases of COVID-19</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>17</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0278825</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0278825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9767341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36538532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samms</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maskell</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>F.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Symptoms after COVID-19 vaccination in patients with persistent symptoms after acute infection: a case series</article-title><source>Ann. Intern. Med.</source><volume>174</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M21-1976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34029484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8252827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boglione</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poletti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors and incidence of long-COVID syndrome in hospitalized patients: does remdesivir have a protective effect?</article-title><source>QJM Mon J Assoc Physicians.</source><volume>114</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>871</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qjmed/hcab297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8690187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34850210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and postacute sequelae associated with SARS-CoV-2 reinfection</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>2398</fpage><lpage>2405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02051-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9671810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byambasuren</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stehlik</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcorn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of covid-19 vaccination on long covid: systematic review</article-title><source>BMJ Med.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e000385</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjmed-2022-000385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9978692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36936268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceban</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulzhabayeva</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 vaccination for the prevention and treatment of long COVID: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Brain Behav. Immun.</source><volume>111</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2023.03.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36990297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10067136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Y.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of antiviral therapy on long COVID: a systematic review and Meta-analysis</article-title><source>J. Clin. Med.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>7375</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12237375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38068427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10707593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The costs of long COVID</article-title><source>JAMA Health Forum.</source><volume>3</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e221809</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2022.1809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36219031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duerlund</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shakar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodilsen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Positive predictive value of the ICD-10 diagnosis code for long-COVID</article-title><source>Clin. Epidemiol.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CLEP.S344515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35177935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8843419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Durstenfeld</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of nirmatrelvir for acute SARS-CoV-2 infection with subsequent long COVID symptoms in an observational cohort study</article-title><source>J. Med. Virol.</source><volume>96</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e29333</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.29333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10786003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38175151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="rf0060"><article-title>Examining the Working Definition for Long COVID | National Academies</article-title><comment>Accessed March 31</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/our-work/examining-the-working-definition-for-long-covid#sectionProjectScope" id="ir0005">https://www.nationalacademies.org/our-work/examining-the-working-definition-for-long-covid#sectionProjectScope</ext-link><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-de-las-Peñas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franco-Moreno</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Ruigómez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Is antiviral treatment with Remdesivir at the acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection effective for decreasing the risk of long-lasting post-COVID symptoms?</article-title><source>Viruses</source><volume>16</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>947</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v16060947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38932239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11209434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebo</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuta</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early antibody treatment, inflammation, and risk of post-COVID conditions</article-title><source>mBio</source><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>e00618</fpage><lpage>e00623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mbio.00618-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37724870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10653913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>Sarah Wulf</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbafati</surname><given-names>Cristiana</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aerts</surname><given-names>Joachim G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Ziyad</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashbaugh</surname><given-names>Charlie</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballouz</surname><given-names>Tala</given-names></name><etal/><collab>Global Burden of Disease Long COVID Collaborators</collab></person-group><article-title>Estimated global proportions of individuals with persistent fatigue, cognitive, and respiratory symptom clusters following symptomatic COVID-19 in 2020 and 2021</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>328</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1604</fpage><lpage>1615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.18931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36215063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9552043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viwattanakulvanid</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dzulhadj</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oo</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patricia</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pongpanich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Effect of full vaccination and post-covid olfactory dysfunction in recovered covid-19 patient. A retrospective longitudinal study with propensity matching</part-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.01.10.22269007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>G.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajeevan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of Nirmatrelvir-ritonavir against the development of post-COVID-19 conditions among U.S. veterans : a target trial emulation</article-title><source>Ann. Intern. Med.</source><volume>176</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1486</fpage><lpage>1497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M23-1394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37903369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10620954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>IOM</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic criteria | diagnosis | healthcare providers | Myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome (ME/CFS) | CDC</article-title><source>April</source><volume>27</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>2021</fpage><comment>Accessed March 15, 2024</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/me-cfs/healthcare-providers/diagnosis/iom-2015-diagnostic-criteria.html" id="ir0010">https://www.cdc.gov/me-cfs/healthcare-providers/diagnosis/iom-2015-diagnostic-criteria.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komaroff</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipkin</surname><given-names>W.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ME/CFS and long COVID share similar symptoms and biological abnormalities: road map to the literature</article-title><source>Front. Med.</source><year>2023</year><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2023.1187163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10278546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37342500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuodi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorelik</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zayyad</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between BNT162b2 vaccination and reported incidence of post-COVID-19 symptoms: cross-sectional study 2020-21, Israel</article-title><source>NPJ Vaccines.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41541-022-00526-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36028498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9411827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The effect of nirmatrelvir-ritonavir on the long-term risk of neuropsychiatric sequelae following COVID-19</part-title><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.28951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37436873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malden</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>I.L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-COVID conditions following COVID-19 vaccination: a retrospective matched cohort study of patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>4101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-48022-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38778026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11111703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massey</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berrent</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akrami</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><part-title>Change in Symptoms and Immune Response in People with Post-Acute Sequelae of SARS-Cov-2 Infection (PASC) After SARS-Cov-2 Vaccination. Published online July 28</part-title><year>2021</year><fpage>21260391</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.07.21.21260391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montoy</surname><given-names>J.C.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of symptoms ≤12 months after acute illness, by COVID-19 testing status among adults — United States, December 2020–march 2023</article-title><source>MMWR Morb. Mortal Wkly. Rep.</source><year>2023</year><fpage>72</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7232a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10415002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37561663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherlinger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pijnenburg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatelus</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination on symptoms from post-acute sequelae of COVID-19: results from the Nationwide VAXILONG study</article-title><source>Vaccines</source><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>46</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines10010046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35062706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8781023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Togt</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hishmeh</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of COVID vaccination on symptoms of long COVID: an international survey of people with lived experience of long COVID</article-title><source>Vaccines</source><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>652</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines10050652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35632408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9146071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thaweethai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlson</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of a definition of Postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>329</volume><issue>22</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1934</fpage><lpage>1946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2023.8823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37278994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10214179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>V.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrodeau</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pane</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravaud</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of COVID-19 vaccination on the symptoms of patients with long COVID: a target trial emulation using data from the ComPaRe e-cohort in France</article-title><source>Published online September</source><volume>29</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3932953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsampasian</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elghazaly</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with post−COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and Meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Intern. Med.</source><volume>183</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10037203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vimercati</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Maria</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quarato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between long COVID and overweight/obesity</article-title><source>J. Clin. Med.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>18</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>4143</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10184143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34575251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8469321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Real-world effectiveness of Nirmatrelvir in protecting long COVID for outpatient adult patients – a large-scale observational cohort study from the RECOVER initiative</article-title><source>Res Sq</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-4536807/v1</pub-id><comment>Published online June 20. rs.3.rs</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanga</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-Term Symptoms Among Adults Tested for SARS-CoV-2 — United States, January 2020–April 2021</article-title><source>MMWR Morb. Mortal Wkly. Rep.</source><volume>70</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7036a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8437054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34499626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weitzer</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID and Myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome (ME/CFS)-a systemic review and comparison of clinical presentation and symptomatology</article-title><source>Med Kaunas Lith.</source><volume>57</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>418</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/medicina57050418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8145228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33925784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of Treatment with Nirmatrelvir and the risk of post-COVID-19 condition. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></article-title><source>Intern. Med.</source><volume>183</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10037200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0175"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Nirmatrelvir and the Risk of Post-Acute Sequelae of COVID-19. Published online November 5, 2022</part-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.11.03.22281783</pub-id><comment>11.03.22281783</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="s0115"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Long coronavirus (COVID) clinical criteria</title><sec id="s0120"><label>A.1</label><title>Criteria for long COVID with chronic fatigue symptoms</title><p id="p0260"><bold>Post-Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 with Chronic Fatigue</bold> (U09.9).</p><p id="p0265"><bold>Post-Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 with Post-viral Fatigue Syndrome</bold> (G93.31)<list list-type="simple" id="l0010"><list-item id="li0035"><label>•</label><p id="p0270">Symptoms persisting past 6 months after acute COVID infection, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0040"><label>•</label><p id="p0275">Decreased level of functioning (occupational, educational, social, or personal activities) compared to prior to COVID infection, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0045"><label>•</label><p id="p0280">Symptoms of post-exertional malaise/fatigue (PEM): not completely relieved with sleep, exacerbated by physical or mental exertion, requiring a recovery time, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0050"><label>•</label><p id="p0285">At least one of the following persistent or recurring neuroimmune symptoms:<list list-type="simple" id="l0015"><list-item id="li0055"><label>o</label><p id="p0290">cognitive (i.e., brain fog, attention, concentration, memory, receptive and expressive communication)</p></list-item><list-item id="li0060"><label>o</label><p id="p0295">exertional pain (i.e., headache, myalgias, arthralgias, chest pain, abdominal pain)</p></list-item><list-item id="li0065"><label>o</label><p id="p0300">sleep disturbances (i.e., insomnia, falling/staying asleep, naps)</p></list-item><list-item id="li0070"><label>o</label><p id="p0305">vestibular (i.e., balance, tinnitus, vertigo, hearing)</p></list-item><list-item id="li0075"><label>o</label><p id="p0310">mood changes (i.e., depression, anxiety)</p></list-item><list-item id="li0080"><label>o</label><p id="p0315">sensory processing (i.e., photophobia, phonophobia, odor/texture sensitivity, taste changes)</p></list-item><list-item id="li0085"><label>o</label><p id="p0320">dysautonomia (i.e., breathing, palpitations, dizziness, temperature/sweat dysregulation, thirst, swallowing, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, pupillary, urinary, sexual, neuropathy, tremors, abnormal movements)</p></list-item><list-item id="li0090"><label>o</label><p id="p0325">immune activation (i.e., rash, swelling, sore throat, lymphadenopathy, environmental sensitivities), AND</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item id="li0095"><label>•</label><p id="p0330">At least one of the following persistent or recurring COVID infection system symptoms:<list list-type="simple" id="l0020"><list-item id="li0100"><label>o</label><p id="p0335">pulmonary, cardiac, neurologic, dermatologic, endocrine, gastrointestinal, genitourinary, ocular, olfactory/gustatory, renal, vascular/hematologic, immunologic, or psychiatric symptoms AND</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item id="li0105"><label>•</label><p id="p0340">No other condition causing symptoms.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="s0125"><label>A.2</label><title>Criteria for long covid with organ/system symptoms</title><p id="p0345"><bold>Post Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 with Respiratory Symptoms</bold> (U09.9).</p><p id="p0350"><bold>Post Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 with Heart Symptoms</bold> (U09.9).</p><p id="p0355"><bold>Post Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 with Neurological Symptoms</bold> (U09.9).</p><p id="p0360"><bold>Post Acute Sequelae of COVID-19 with other symptoms</bold> (U09.9)<list list-type="simple" id="l0025"><list-item id="li0110"><label>•</label><p id="p0365">Symptoms persisting past 6 months after acute COVID infection, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0115"><label>•</label><p id="p0370">Decreased level of functioning (occupational, educational, social, or personal activities) compared to prior to COVID infection, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0120"><label>•</label><p id="p0375">At least one of the following persistent or recurrent COVID infection system symptoms:<list list-type="simple" id="l0030"><list-item id="li0125"><label>o</label><p id="p0380">pulmonary symptoms (<bold>PASC with Respiratory)</bold></p></list-item><list-item id="li0130"><label>o</label><p id="p0385">cardiac symptoms (<bold>PASC with Heart)</bold></p></list-item><list-item id="li0135"><label>o</label><p id="p0390">neurologic symptoms (<bold>PASC with Neurological)</bold></p></list-item><list-item id="li0140"><label>o</label><p id="p0395">dermatologic, endocrine, gastrointestinal, genitourinary, ocular, olfactory/gustatory, renal, vascular/hematologic, immunologic, or psychiatric symptoms (<bold>PASC with Other symptoms</bold>), AND</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item id="li0145"><label>•</label><p id="p0400">No evidence of end-organ/system pathology/inflammation from COVID infection</p></list-item><list-item id="li0150"><label>•</label><p id="p0405">No other condition causing symptoms.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="s0130"><label>A.3</label><title>Criteria for long COVID with end-organ/system sequelae.</title><p id="p0410"><bold>Late Sequelae of COVID infection</bold> (U09.9)<list list-type="simple" id="l0035"><list-item id="li0155"><label>•</label><p id="p0415">Symptoms persisting past 6 months after acute COVID infection, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0160"><label>•</label><p id="p0420">Decreased level of functioning (occupational, educational, social, or personal activities) compared to prior to COVID infection, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0165"><label>•</label><p id="p0425">At least one of the following persistent or recurrent COVID infection system symptoms:<list list-type="simple" id="l0040"><list-item id="li0170"><label>o</label><p id="p0430">pulmonary, cardiac, neurologic, dermatologic, endocrine, gastrointestinal, genitourinary, ocular, olfactory/gustatory, renal, vascular/hematologic, immunologic, or psychiatric symptoms, AND</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item id="li0175"><label>•</label><p id="p0435">Evidence of end-organ/system pathology/inflammation from COVID infection:<list list-type="simple" id="l0045"><list-item id="li0180"><label>o</label><p id="p0440">pulmonary, cardiac, neurologic, dermatologic, endocrine, gastrointestinal, genitourinary, ocular, olfactory/gustatory, renal, vascular/hematologic, immunologic, or psychiatric symptoms, AND</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item id="li0185"><label>•</label><p id="p0445">No other condition causing symptoms.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="s0135"><label>A.4</label><title>Criteria for post COVID recovery</title><p id="p0450"><bold>Post COVID-19 Condition</bold> (U09.9)<list list-type="simple" id="l0050"><list-item id="li0190"><label>•</label><p id="p0455">Symptoms persisting past 4 weeks after acute COVID infection, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0195"><label>•</label><p id="p0460">Complete resolution of COVID infection system symptoms, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0200"><label>•</label><p id="p0465">Complete recovery to normal level of functioning (occupational, educational, social, or personal activities), AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0205"><label>•</label><p id="p0470">No evidence of end-organ/system pathology/inflammation from COVID infection, AND</p></list-item><list-item id="li0210"><label>•</label><p id="p0475">No other condition causing symptoms.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0480">*Patients may have Long COVID prior to 6 months but meet the clinical criteria at 6 months since there is higher rate of full recovery from ongoing symptoms prior to 6 months.</p><p id="p0485">**Patients may have multiple or concurrent Long COVID diagnosis at different periods of time.</p><p id="p0490">***Criteria may be used in conjunction with the U.S. National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine definition of Long COVID.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0140"><label>Appendix B</label><title>Variable definitions</title><sec id="s0145"><label>B.1</label><title>COVID variant periods</title><p id="p0495">
<list list-type="simple" id="l0055"><list-item id="li0215"><label>•</label><p id="p0500">Alpha 12/29/2019–10/25/2020</p></list-item><list-item id="li0220"><label>•</label><p id="p0505">Beta 10/26/2020–6/21/21</p></list-item><list-item id="li0225"><label>•</label><p id="p0510">Delta 6/22/21–11/22/21</p></list-item><list-item id="li0230"><label>•</label><p id="p0515">Omicron BA1 11/23/21–1/19/22</p></list-item><list-item id="li0235"><label>•</label><p id="p0520">Omicron BA2 1/20/22–3/29/22</p></list-item><list-item id="li0240"><label>•</label><p id="p0525">Omicron BA4 3/30/22–5/31/22</p></list-item><list-item id="li0245"><label>•</label><p id="p0530">Omicron BA5 6/1/22–11/30/22</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0150"><label>B.2</label><title>Antiviral inclusion criteria</title><p id="p0535">Remdesivir inclusion criteria included COVID symptoms within 7 days, with priority given to patients with presence of risk factors, including unvaccinated individuals, older age, and risk factors for severe disease progression. Risk factors may include asthma, cancer, cerebrovascular disease, children with underlying conditions, chronic kidney disease, chronic lung disease, chronic liver disease, cystic fibrosis, diabetes, Down's syndrome, coronary artery disease, congestive heart failure, cardiomyopathy, HIV, hypertension, immune deficiencies, immunosuppressive medications including steroids, mood disorders including depression, neurologic conditions including dementia, schizophrenia, current or former smoking, BMI greater or equal to 25, pregnancy and recent pregnancy, sickle cell disease, solid organ or blood stem cell transplantation, substance use disorders, thalassemia, tuberculosis.</p><p id="p0540">*Remdesivir was not used for age less than 28 days old and weight less than or equal to 3 kg.</p><p id="p0545">*Although current guidelines cite 7 days within symptom onset, remdesivir was often used past 7 days for hospitalized patients during the inception of the pandemic.</p><p id="p0550">Nirmatrelvir/ritonavir (Paxlovid) inclusion criteria included symptoms within 5 days, with priority given to patients with presence of risk factors (stated above in remdesivir inclusion criteria).</p><p id="p0555">*Nirmatrelvir/ritonavir was not used for age less than 12 years old, weight less than 88 pounds, persons with certain solid organ transplants or bone marrow transplants or other immunosuppressed state, and circumstances where remdesivir treatment is recommended.</p></sec><sec id="s0155"><label>B.3</label><title>Vaccination status</title><p id="p0560">We define full vaccination as 2 weeks after complete primary vaccination series doses (Moderna or Pfizer, 3 doses) AND within 4 months of vaccination OR completed the most recently available booster vaccination. Partial vaccination was defined as any number of vaccinations not fulfilling full vaccination criteria or no vaccination criteria. No vaccination included patients with no COVID vaccinations.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0160"><label>Appendix C</label><title>Demographic statistics, treatment, and comorbidities comparing Long COVID (coronavirus) cases and COVID positive controls for unmatched total adult population in Kaiser Permanente Southern California from March 2020 to June 2023</title><p id="p0565">
<table-wrap position="anchor" id="t0030" orientation="portrait"><alt-text id="al0030">Unlabelled Table</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1,118,736)<break/>n (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 6546)<break/>n (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">(N = 1,125,282)<break/>n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age at Diagnosis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01<xref rid="tf0040" ref-type="table-fn">1</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.8 (17.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.5 (14.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.9 (17.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median (IQR)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.0 (32.0, 58.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.0 (41.0, 61.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.0 (32.0, 58.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age Group at Diagnosis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18–45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">567,274 (50.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2175 (33.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">569,449 (50.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45–55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">206,225 (18.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1634 (25.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">207,859 (18.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">345,237 (30.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2737 (41.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">347,974 (30.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9395 (63.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1879 (63.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,274 (63.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5380 (36.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1076 (36.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6456 (36.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Binary</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unspecified</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race/Ethnicity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">114,001 (10.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">501 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">114,502 (10.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82,040 (7.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">513 (7.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82,553 (7.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">567,291 (50.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3605 (55.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">570,896 (50.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70,620 (6.3 %)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">226 (3.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70,846 (6.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">284,784 (25.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1701 (26.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">286,485 (25.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Body Mass Index</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal &lt;25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">274,349 (24.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1076 (16.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">275,425 (24.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overweight 25–30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">354,266 (31.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1952 (29.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">356,218 (31.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obese &gt;30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">490,121 (43.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3518 (53.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">493,639 (43.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variant</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alpha</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88,188 (7.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">938 (14.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89,126 (7.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">299,579 (26.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3075 (47.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">302,654 (26.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delta</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89,070 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">765 (11.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89,835 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">252,622 (22.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">742 (11.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">253,364 (22.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84,944 (7.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">415 (6.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">85,359 (7.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">48,448 (4.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">150 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">48,598 (4.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Omicron BA5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">255,885 (22.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">461 (7.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256,346 (22.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatments</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaccinations</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">629,299 (56.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5046 (77.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">634,345 (56.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">252,316 (22.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">923 (14.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">253,239 (22.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">198,738 (17.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">503 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">199,241 (17.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35,598 (3.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (1.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35,669 (3.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2754 (0.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2757 (0.)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remdesivir Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,111,431 (99.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6503 (99.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,117,934 (99.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7305 (0.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (0.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7348 (0.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monoclonal Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,118,147 (99.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6546 (100.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,124,693 (99.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">589 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">589 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nirmatrelvir/ritonavir Treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,043,738 (93.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5933 (90.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,049,671 (93.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74,998 (6.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">613 (9.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">75,611 (6.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Convalescent Plasma Transfusion</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,115,723 (99.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6465 (98.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,122,188 (99.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3013 (0.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (1.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3094 (0.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical History</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,101,882 (98.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6236 (95.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,108,118 (98.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,854 (1.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">310 (4.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,164 (1.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Acute COVID Infections</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">871,597 (77.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2521 (38.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">874,118 (77.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">228,936 (20.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3234 (49.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">232,170 (20.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,480 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">710 (10.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18,190 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">692 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (1.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">765 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asthma Prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,053,741 (94.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6021 (92.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,059,762 (94.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64,995 (5.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">525 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65,520 (5.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,075,321 (96.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6145 (93.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,081,466 (96.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43,415 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">401 (6.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43,816 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Depression prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,048,176 (93.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5997 (91.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,054,173 (93.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70,560 (6.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">549 (8.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">71,109 (6.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anxiety prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">710,537 (63.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4278 (65.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">714,815 (63.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">408,199 (36.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2268 (34.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">410,467 (36.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">973,710 (87.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5561 (85.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">979,271 (87.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">145,026 (13.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">985 (15.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">146,011 (13.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes prior to COVID</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,025,832 (91.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5769 (88.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,031,601 (91.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">92,904 (8.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">777 (11.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">93,681 (8.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking Status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">98,924 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">522 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99,446 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">98,352 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">707 (10.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99,059 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">813,214 (72.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4767 (72.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">817,981 (72.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">108,246 (9.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">550 (8.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">108,796 (9.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0040"><label>1</label><p id="np0040">Kruskal-Wallis <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value; all other <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values used Chi-Square.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0005"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0035">No data was used for the research described in the article.</p></sec><ack id="ac0005"><title>Acknowledgment</title><p id="p0255">Stephanie Tovar, MS, Manager, Program Management, Clinician Research Division, Department of Research &amp; Evaluation, Kaiser Permanente Southern California Permanente Medical Group.</p></ack></back></article></pmc-articleset>