<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Chin Med Assoc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Chin Med Assoc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4801</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jcma</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CA9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of the Chinese Medical Association : JCMA</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1726-4901</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1728-7731</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12718764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12718764.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12718764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12718764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39350480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JCMA.0000000000001175</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JCMA-D-24-00346</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The neuropsychological impacts of coronavirus disease 2019 in nonhospitalized patients with long coronavirus disease and brain fog</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names initials="YC">Yu-Chen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names initials="YH">Yu-Hsiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names initials="MJ">Meng-Ju</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="YJ">Yi-Jiun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuh</surname><given-names initials="JL">Jong-Ling</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of General Neurology, Department of Neurology, Neurological Institute, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan, ROC</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Neurological Institute, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan, ROC</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>School of Medicine, College of Medicine, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan, ROC</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Brain Research Center, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan, ROC</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>*</label>Address correspondence. Dr. Jong-Ling Fuh, Division of General Neurology, Department of Neurology, Neurological Institute, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, 201, Section 2, Shi-Pai Road, Taipei 112, Taiwan, ROC. E-mail address: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jlfuh@vghtpe.gov.tw">jlfuh@vghtpe.gov.tw</email> (J.-L. Fuh).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>88</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">502848</issue-id><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-06 00:25:12.393"><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2024, the Chinese Medical Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ca9-88-58.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ca9-88-58.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) causes persistent symptoms, including brain fog. Based on limited research on the long-term consequences of mild COVID-19, which has yielded inconsistent results, we investigated which cognitive functions were most affected by COVID-19 in nonhospitalized Asian patients with long-term COVID and subjective cognitive complaints.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Fifty-five nonhospitalized patients with subjective cognitive complaints after COVID infection (24 males and 31 females, mean age: 45.6 ± 14.6 years, mean duration of education: 14.4 ± 3.0 years) finished the study. Neuropsychological assessments included screening tests for overall cognition, and comprehensive tests for memory, executive function, processing speed, and subjective emotional and disease symptoms. Cognitive test scores were converted into <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-scores. Moreover, principal component analysis (PCA) was used to define cognitive domains across subtest scores.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Comprehensive assessments revealed cognitive impairment in 69.1% of patients (&lt;1.5 SD in at least one test). The processing speed (27.3%), memory recall (21.8%), memory learning (20.0%), and inhibitory control (18.2%) were the most affected areas. Self-reported anxiety and depression were observed in 35% and 33% of patients, respectively. Furthermore, the degree of anxiety was predictive of learning performance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Nearly 70% of patients with subjective cognitive complaints and long COVID had objective cognitive impairments. A comprehensive evaluation is essential for these patients, even when they present with mild symptoms.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Brain fog</kwd><kwd>Cognitive function</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Neuropsychology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. INTRODUCTION</title><p>According to the World Health Organization (WHO), “long COVID” (post-coronavirus disease 2019 [COVID-19] condition) refers to symptoms emerging within 3 months post-initial severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection that persist for at least 2 months without other explanation. These include physiological symptoms, including chronic cough, difficulty breathing, palpitations, chest tightness, joint soreness, and fatigue,<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> as well as cognitive and emotional problems, such as impaired concentration, memory loss, insomnia, mental slowness, depression, and anxiety.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> “Brain fog” entails a sensation of sluggishness, concentration difficulties, and mental haziness, although it lacks a precise definition.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Generally, patients with subjective cognitive complaints are considered to have brain fog.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p><p>Not all patients with long COVID and cognitive complaints have measurable impairments.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> However, impaired performance may indicate neurological damage, potentially increasing the risk of neurodegenerative diseases.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Identifying whether these patients demonstrate objective cognitive deficits using neuropsychological tests is crucial for managing long COVID and preventing further cognitive decline or dementia. Although studies have demonstrated cognitive impairment in patients with a long COVID, their findings have been inconsistent. Some studies have identified deficits in executive function,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> processing speed,<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> and attention,<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> whereas others have reported memory deficits,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> including immediate and delayed memory. These discrepancies may be due to two factors: the use of assessment tools with limited sensitivity in previous studies, such as the Montreal Cognitive Assessment or Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), and the varying tests across studies, which complicates the identification of specific cognitive functions, such as executive function or memory, affected by COVID-19.</p><p>To date, most studies have focused on patients with long COVID who were either hospitalized or had a history of hospitalization. Few studies have investigated those with mild disease who did not require hospitalization.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Crivelli et al<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> identified that patients with mild COVID-19 exhibited impairments in memory, attention, and executive functions at 5 months postinfection. Kirchberger et al<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> observed that 41% and 12% of patients exhibited mild changes in memory and verbal fluency, respectively, 9 months after infection. Additionally, Schild et al’s<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> study revealed that 60% of patients met the criteria for minor neurocognitive disorder (&lt;1 SD in two tests) according to the DSM-5, 3 months following COVID-19. Given the limited and inconsistent results of the aforementioned studies, in which most infections were mild or asymptomatic, our research aimed to shed light on the cognitive performance of Asian individuals with mild COVID-19.</p><p>This study selected a series of comprehensive tests to assess cognitive function extensively. We aimed to examine the cognitive performance of nonhospitalized patients with long COVID and brain fog and to identify the primary cognitive functions affected by COVID-19 in this cohort using comprehensive neuropsychological assessments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>2. METHODS</title><sec><title>2.1. Participants</title><p>In contrast to many European and American countries that experienced large numbers of infections in the early stages of the pandemic in 2020, Taiwan did not experience a peak until 2022, according to the Ministry of Health and Welfare (Taiwan) (2021).<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> The participants in our study were diagnosed with COVID-19 for the first time during the study period. They were not hospitalized and were referred from the Taipei Veterans General Hospital’s neurology outpatient clinic to undergo comprehensive assessments when they met specific criteria, including: (1) being confirmed positive for SARS-CoV-2; (2) subjective cognitive complaints referred to patients who reported a positive answer to any of the two questions: “do you feel like your memory or other mental functions is becoming worse” or “do you have problems with your memory or other mental functions”<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>; (3) the complaints appeared within 3 months after diagnosis that persisted for at least 2 months. Patients with any neurological, psychiatric, or systemic disorders or medication use that could potentially affect cognitive function were excluded. This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the Taipei Veterans General Hospital.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Neuropsychological assessment</title><p>Upon enrollment, the history of each participant was evaluated, including the severity and duration of infection, subjective disease symptoms of the acute COVID-19 episode, and premorbid medical data. They underwent an objective neurological examination and completed a series of neuropsychological tests administered by clinical neuropsychologists in a controlled environment. The Cognitive Abilities Screening Instrument (CASI) and MMSE were used for general cognitive screening.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Verbal episodic memory was tested using the Word Sequence Learning Test (WSLT),<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> while the WAIS-IV Digit Span subtest evaluated working memory and verbal attention.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Executive function was assessed using the Modified Card Sorting Test (MCST) and the Stroop test.<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Processing speed was measured using the WAIS-IV Coding and Symbol Search subtests, and the Stroop test. Anxiety and depression were assessed using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS).<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Disease severity</title><p>The severity of illness was classified according to the WHO Clinical Progression Scale, which offers a measure of illness severity ranging from 0 (not infected) to 10 (dead), using data obtained from clinical records.<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.4. Statistical analysis</title><p>For each neuropsychological test, <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-scores were computed using normative data adjusted for age and education from various Taiwanese populations, as described in the test manuals.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Cognitive impairment was identified by a <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-score of –1.5 SD below the mean of the normative group in at least one cognitive domain. This criterion is widely accepted for diagnosing mild cognitive impairment in both research and clinical settings.<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> After standardizing the cognitive measures into <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-scores, principal component analysis (PCA) was used to identify variables measuring similar components of cognition, with a factor loading of &gt;0.40 considered significant. To correct for the common covariance of variables, rotation with the direct oblimin method was applied to the factor matrix.</p><p>Descriptive and Pearson correlation analyses were conducted. Statistical significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. Linear regression models were used to examine the associations between emotional complaints and cognitive performance. IBM SPSS Statistics 26.0 (IBM, Inc., Armonk, NY) was used for the statistical analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>3. RESULTS</title><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>3.1. Patient characteristics</title><p>Fifty-eight participants completed the assessment. Three participants were excluded as they had conditions that might influence their cognitive performance. The final cohort comprised of 55 (24 males and 31 females) participants, with a mean age of 45.6 ± 14.6 (range: 18-74) years and a mean duration of education of 14.4 ± 3.0 (range: 6-8) years. In line with the WHO definition of long COVID, the average time between COVID-19 diagnosis and neuropsychological assessment was 118 ± 69 (range, 60-335 days) days. All participants were classified as having mild ambulatory COVID-19, according to the WHO Clinical Progression Scale.<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>3.2. Neuropsychological performance</title><p>All the patients scored above the cutoff values of the CASI (&lt;79) and MMSE (&lt;24),<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> with a mean CASI score of 95.9 ± 4.0 (range: 84-100) and a mean MMSE score of 28.9 ± 1.2 (range: 26-30). In terms of comprehensive cognitive performance, 17 (30.9%) patients demonstrated performance within the normal range, whereas 38 (69.1%) patients exhibited impaired performance in at least one cognitive domain (<italic toggle="yes">Z</italic> &lt; 1.5 SD based on norms). Significant differences were noted between patients who had complaints without objective impairment and those with both complaints and impaired performance on comprehensive assessments, as evidenced by the position scores on the WSLT (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.040) and anxiety scores on the HADS (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004). Anxiety scores could predict performance on position scores in the WSLT (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = –0.051, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.045) in linear regression models.</p><p>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents the results of the comprehensive neuropsychological tests. Impairments in processing speed were more prevalent in the Stroop test than those in the WAIS-IV. Free and cued recall demonstrated more impairment than recognition in memory-recall tasks. Memory learning demonstrated similar levels of impairment across subtests. For inhibitory control, the Stroop color-word and interference tasks indicated impairments, while in problem solving, non-perseveration impairments exceeded those in the category and perseveration tasks.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Results of comprehensive neuropsychological tests</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N below –1.5 SD, %</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-score mean (SD)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Processing speed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stroop test: word reading</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (20%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.40 (0.98)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stroop test: color reading</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (11%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.43 (1.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WAIS-IV: symbol search</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.07 (0.90)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WAIS-IV: coding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (1.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Memory recall</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WSLT: free recall</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (16%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.17 (1.28)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WSLT: cued recall</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (11%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.06 (1.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WSLT: recognition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 (0.93)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Memory learning</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WSLT: correct</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (11%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.25 (0.96)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WSLT: position</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (13%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.26 (1.01)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WSLT: learning</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (11%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.24 (1.03)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Inhibitory control</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stroop test: color-word</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (18%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.45 (1.07)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stroop test: interference</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (13%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.13 (1.09)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Problem solving</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MCST: category</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 (0.85)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MCST: perseveration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.62)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MCST: non-perseveration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (11%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>–</bold>0.17 (0.90)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Working memory</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Digit span backward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (1.05)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Attention</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Digit span forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 (0.82)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>MCST ＝ Modified Card Sorting Test; WAIS-IV ＝ Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale-Fourth Edition; WSLT ＝ Word Sequence Learning Test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>3.3. Distribution of test scores</title><p>We excluded the CASI and MMSE scores as these two tests were performed to measure simple global cognitive function. After rotation, the PCA results suggested that the best factorial solution was saturated with five main factors explaining 79.6% of the variance. The five factors were evaluated, and their corresponding scores were as follows (Supplementary Table 1, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JCMA/A286" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JCMA/A286</ext-link>):</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Learning memory included the correct (0.88), position (0.93), and learning (0.95) components of the WSLT.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Memory recall included the scores of the free recall (0.74), cued recall (0.92), and recognition (0.90) components of the WSLT.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Problem-solving ability included the scores of categories completed (0.87) and the errors of perseveration (0.83) and non-perseveration (0.90) in the MCST.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Inhibitory control ability included scores for color words (0.81) and interference (0.97) in the Stroop test.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Processing speed, including the scores of coding (0.78), symbol search (0.60) in the WAIS-IV, word reading (0.81), and color reading (0.88) in the Stroop test.</p></list-item></list><p>Forward and backward digit span scores had low loadings and were not significantly associated with any of the five factors. Thus, we treated them independently, categorizing forward digit span scores as “attention” and backward digit span scores as “working memory,” based on test attributes.</p></sec><sec><title>3.4. Cognitive composite measures</title><p>Considering the frequency of the cognitive domains affected, the proportions of impairment were as follows: 27.3% for processing speed, 21.8% for memory recall, 20.0% for memory learning, 18.2% for inhibitory control ability, 12.7% for problem solving, 5.5% for working memory, and 3.6% for attention. Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> presents that single-domain impairment was more prevalent than multiple-domain impairment (38.2% vs 30.9%, χ<sup>2</sup> = 38.00, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.000).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of deficits in single- and multidomain cognitive impairments</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No domain affected</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">One domain affected</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Memory learning</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Memory recall</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Working memory</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Problem solving</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Inhibitory control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Processing speed</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.2%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Two domains affected</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Memory learning + inhibitory control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Memory learning + processing speed</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Memory recall + inhibitory control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Memory recall + working memory</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Memory recall + processing speed</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Processing speed + inhibitory control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Processing speed + working memory</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Problem solving + inhibitory control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Three domains affected</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Processing speed + problem solving + memory learning</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Processing speed + problem solving + memory recall</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Problem solving + inhibitory control + memory recall</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Impairment was defined as a <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-score &lt;1.5 SD based on norms.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>COVID ＝ coronavirus disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To investigate whether cognitive performance was influenced by overlapping deficits, correlation analyses of the seven domains based on PCA were conducted. The results revealed that processing speed was positively correlated with memory learning (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.177, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.023) and inhibitory control (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.226, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.018). Additionally, memory learning was positively correlated with the attention domain (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.386, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004) and negatively correlated with memory recall (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = –0.189, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.015).</p></sec><sec><title>3.5. Disease symptoms and emotional disturbances</title><p>Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents a comprehensive list of self-reported neurological and emotional symptoms. The most frequent symptoms included fatigue, cough, nasal congestion or runny nose, sore throat, headache or dizziness, and wheezing. Additionally, 33% of the patients reported feelings of depression, while 35% experienced feelings of anxiety.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Neurologic symptoms self-reported by patients with long COVID</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y<break/>Median (SD)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (male), n, %</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All participants</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.6 (14.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (43.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Self-reported neurologic symptoms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fatigue</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (76.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (50.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cough</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (74.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (43.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nasal congestion or runny nose</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (70.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (41.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sore throat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (63.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (42.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Headache or dizziness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (63.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (40.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Feeling wheezing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (60.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (36.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Muscle weakness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (56.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (38.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fever</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (56.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (41.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chest tightness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (49.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (37.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Loss of appetite</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (40.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (40.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Dyspnea</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (40.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (31.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Insomnia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (40.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (31.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (34.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (26.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Depression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (32.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (33.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gastrointestinal discomfort</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (29.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (43.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anosmia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (25.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (35.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diarrhea or abdominal pain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (20.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (36.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nausea or vomiting</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (18.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>COVID ＝ coronavirus disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>4. DISCUSSION</title><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>4.1. Cognitive performance of nonhospitalized patients with long COVID and brain fog</title><p>In this study, nearly 70% of patients with long COVID and cognitive complaints demonstrated impairments in comprehensive assessments. Screening tools are inadequate for detecting these dysfunctions, particularly in terms of processing speed, memory recall, learning, and inhibition control.</p><p>Consistent with previous research, screening measures were insufficient to detect cognitive dysfunction in patients with long COVID, including younger and older individuals.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Comprehensive evaluations revealed impairments in 69.1% of patients. Earlier studies have identified cognitive impairments in 21% to 65% of patients with long COVID,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> while García-Sánchez et al<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> reported that all patients with memory complaints had at least one cognitive deficit. Further research is needed to confirm these proportions and examine the changes over time.</p><p>Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref> highlights the large extent of cognitive impairments among patients with long COVID. Crivelli et al<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> identified significant deficits in memory, attention, executive functions, and language abilities. Similarly, Miskowiak et al and García-Sánchez et al<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> observed deficits, especially in memory, executive functions, and attention, noting significantly severe outcomes in patients who had been hospitalized. The studies emphasize the need for thorough cognitive assessments, given the significant effects of long COVID on processing speed, memory, and executive functions.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Summary of articles on cognitive assessment in long COVID-19 and brain fog</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Authors, y</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluation duration</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size type</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The cognitive assessment tool used</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenced cognitive domains (based on norms or group comparison)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chuang et al (current article)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60-335 (mean: 118) d after disease onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 nonhospitalized patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSLT, Stroop test, Coding, Digit Span Forward and Backward, Symbol Search, MCST</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on norm: processing speed (27.3%), memory recall (21.8%), memory learning (20.0%), inhibitory control (18.2%), problem solving (12.7%), working memory (5.5%), and attention (3.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miskowiak et al<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-4 mo after discharge</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 hospitalized patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screen for Cognitive Impairment in Psychiatry Danish Version (SCIP-D), Trail Making Test Part B (TMT-B)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on norm: verbal learning, executive function</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">García-Sánchez et al<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187 d after diagnosis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 hospitalized patients, 30 nonhospitalized patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA, CPT-II, RAVLR, ROCFT, Digit Span Forward and Backward, BNT, Block Design, Symbol Search, TMT, Stroop, verbal fluency tasks, and the 15-Objects Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group comparison: attention (61.9%), executive function (43%), learning, long-term memory, processing speed (lower performance in hospitalized patients)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crivelli et al<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 d after disease onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 nonhospitalized patients, 45 normal controls</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA, Trail Making A and B, Digit Span Forwards, Digit-Symbol Coding, Craft Story, RAVLT, Delayed Recall from the Benson Figure Test, Wisconsin Card Sorting Test, Stroop Test, phonological fluency. Benson Figure and Clock Drawing Test, Multilingual Naming Test, and semantic fluency</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group comparison: memory (RAVLT total and delayed recall), attention (digit span forward and backward, TMT-A, Coding), executive function (TMT-B, WCST car and pers), language (semantic and phonemic fluency)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kirchberger et al<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 mo after disease onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372 nonhospitalized patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The WAIS-IV digit span, SCWT, RWT, and subjective ratings of memory and concentration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on norm: memory (41.1% mild alterations, 6.2% distinct impairments) and verbal fluency (12.4% mild alterations, 5.4% distinct impairments)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Del Brutto et al<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 mo after disease onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 mild patients, 41 normal controls</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on norm: 21% decline in patients</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Becker et al<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 mo from disease onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379 nonhospitalized patients, 165 emergency patients, 196 hospitalized patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number Span forward (attention) and backward (working memory), Trail Making Test Part A and Part B (processing speed and executive functioning, respectively), phonemic and category fluency (language), and the Hopkins Verbal Learning Test-Revised (memory encoding, recall, and recognition)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group comparison: hospitalized patients were more likely to have impairments in attention, executive functioning, category fluency, memory encoding, and memory recall than those in the nonhospitalized group</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferrucci et al<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-5 mo after disease onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 hospitalized patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brief Repeatable Battery of Neuropsychological Tests</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on the norm: 42% had processing speed deficits, 26.3% demonstrated delayed verbal recall deficits</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hampshire et al<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 wk after disease onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 964 community sample</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eight computerized online tasks from the Cognition battery</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on the norm: memory (immediate and delayed recall), verbal analogical reasoning, and executive function</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mazza et al<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 mo after discharge</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226 discharged patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brief Assessment of Cognition in Schizophrenia, a broad battery evaluating verbal memory, verbal fluency, working memory (digit sequencing), selective attention and processing speed (symbol coding), psychomotor coordination (token motor task), and executive functions (Tower of London)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on the norm: executive functions (50%), psychomotor coordination (57%), information processing (30%), verbal fluency (30%), and working memory (30%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Méndez et al<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-3 mo from onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 discharged patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verbal learning, immediate and delayed memory subtests from the Subtest SCIP, animal naming test from the Controlled Oral Word Association Test for semantic verbal fluency, and the subtest Digit Span backward from the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale, Third Edition for working memory (tests were administered by telephone)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on the norm: immediate verbal memory and learning (38%), delayed verbal memory (11.8%), verbal fluency (34.6%), and working memory (executive function) (6.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schild et al<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 mo after disease onset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 nonhospitalized patients</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMSE, MoCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on norm: learning/memory, executive functions (60.7%), complex attention (51.6%), language (35.5%), and perceptual-motor function (29.0%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>BNT ＝ Boston Naming Test; CPT-II ＝ Continuous Performance Test; DST ＝ Digital Span Test; MCST = Modified Card Sorting Test; MMSE ＝ Mini-Mental State Examination; MoCA ＝ Montreal Cognitive Assessment; RAVLT ＝ Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test; ROCFT ＝ Reye Osterrieth Complex Figure Test; RWT = Regensburger Verbal Fluency Test; SCIP ＝ Subtest Screen for Cognitive Impairment in Psychiatry; SCIP-D ＝ Screen for Cognitive Impairment in Psychiatry Danish Version; SCWT = Stroop Color and Word Test; TMT ＝ Trail Making Test; WAIS = Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale; WSLT ＝ Word Sequence Learning Test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Research on the specific memory processes (encoding, storage, and retrieval) affected by long COVID has been limited. Our research revealed deficits in memory recall and learning among the patients. We observed delayed recall deficits consistent with those documented in prior studies.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Additionally, we identified immediate verbal learning deficits that aligned with the findings of earlier studies.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> More pronounced impairments were observed in free recall and cued recall than in recognition within the recall domain, suggesting that retrieval difficulties are the primary contributors to memory issues in patients with long COVID. The results imply that individuals with brain fog need additional information to aid recall (recognition) rather than just the initial word as a cue.</p><p>The specificity of the WSLT likely explains the inverse correlation between learning and recall in our study. High scores indicate less frequent achievement of the termination condition.<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Patients with low learning scores who needed additional time to learn words performed better in the recall, suggesting that those with long COVID and subjective complaints may benefit from practice to consolidate memory. Thus, an optimal number of practice sessions is crucial to prevent retrieval deficits during recall.</p><p>The patients exhibited impairments in inhibitory control (ie, Stroop test) and problem solving (ie, MCST) in executive functions, consistent with Kirchberger findings in the Stroop test<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> and Crivelli findings of differences in categorization in the MCST between healthy controls and post-COVID patients.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> However, unlike Crivelli et al,<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> we discovered no impairment in perseveration. “Categories completed” and “non-perseverative errors” in the MCST serve as primary indicators of categorization ability, while “perseverations” reflect the ability to shift sets.<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Consequently, low MCST scores in our patients were indicative of challenges in categorization. However, set-shifting appears to be relatively preserved in nonhospitalized patients with long COVID. Further research is imperative, given that the majority of studies have concentrated on hospitalized patients.</p><p>Processing speed was the most frequently impaired domain, with more impairments in Stroop test words and color reading than in WAIS-IV coding and symbol search, which is consistent with the observations of the previous studies.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> We hypothesize that this may be due to the additional cognitive demands of reading in the Stroop test, which involves semantic processing and visuomotor tasks.</p><p>These results differ from those of previous studies. Studies in the long COVID population with subjective cognitive complaints reported impaired attention and working memory,<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> whereas these two cognitive functions appeared unaffected in our cohort. This discrepancy may be attributed to two factors. First, we used a different test (WAIS-IV forward digit span), which measures verbal short-term memory rather than sustained attention and was mostly examined using the Continuous Performance Test.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Second, the patients included in our study were all nonhospitalized, which differs from the participants included in most previous studies.<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> This suggests that attention and working memory may not be significantly affected in this specific group; however, further research is needed to confirm this.</p></sec><sec><title>4.2. Potential neuropathological mechanisms of cognitive impairments</title><p>Despite extensive studies on the impact of SARS-CoV-2 infection on the central nervous system, controversy persists.<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Our study suggests that cognitive deficits in patients with long COVID, especially in reading speed, memory recall, and inhibitory control, are linked to frontal circuits, affecting the ventral prefrontal cortex more than the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex. Connectivity of the ventral prefrontal cortex with the hippocampus<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> may increase the risk of future degenerative diseases, particularly in older adults.<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> However, the small sample size and lack of brain imaging data necessitate cautious interpretation.</p></sec><sec><title>4.3. Emotional disturbances and cognitive impairments</title><p>Our study revealed moderate correlations between depression and processing speed, anxiety and memory learning, and depression and memory recall. Anxiety predicted the WSLT position scores, indicating that emotional disturbances affect cognitive performance. This connection also noted in Kirchberger study linking depression to impaired Stroop test performance,<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> warrants further exploration in nonhospitalized patients with long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>4.4. Strengths and weaknesses</title><p>Although not obligatory, our study comprehensively detailed the assessment tools selected for patients with long COVID. Memory tests included free recall, delayed recall, and recognition elements. Executive functions included problem-solving related to the dorsal pathway and inhibition and set-shifting associated with the ventral pathway. Language-related processing speed seems susceptible and tests for attention and working memory warrant further investigation. The study presented several limitations: the absence of a healthy control group posed challenges for cognitive comparisons, despite the use of tests with education- and age-adjusted norms. These findings, derived from nonhospitalized Asian patients with mild COVID-19 at a single tertiary hospital, may not be widely applicable because of the exposure to particular SARS-CoV-2 variants between 2022 and 2023. The lack of brain imaging has limited our understanding of the brain pathology. Additionally, the small sample size was restricted to Asian cohorts, and the potential for bias in self-reported symptoms stemming from perception, response, and cultural and linguistic biases were noted. Future studies should use a comprehensive battery of large, diverse populations to corroborate these findings.</p><p>In conclusion, in this study of nonhospitalized Asian patients with mild COVID-19 experiencing brain fog within 3 months postinfection, 70% demonstrated cognitive impairment regardless of illness severity. Studies have indicated that COVID-19 may have long-term impacts on cognitive functions by harming key brain areas, such as the hippocampus and anterior cingulate cortex.<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Furthermore, as these regions are closely linked to the progression of degenerative diseases, including extensive patient cohorts and prolonged follow-up periods to confirm the association between cognitive function and underlying brain pathology is imperative.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>This study was supported by grants from the Taipei Veterans General Hospital (V113A-015 and V113C-047), National Science and Technology Council, Taiwan (NSTC 112-2314-B-075-036-MY2, 113-2321-B-001-011, and 113-2321-B-A49-027), and the Brain Research Center, National Yang-Ming University, from the Featured Areas Research Center Program within the framework of the Higher Education Sprout Project of the Ministry of Education (MOE) in Taiwan. The interpretations and conclusions contained herein do not represent those of funding agencies.</p><p>We thank the patients who participated in this study.</p></sec><sec><title>APPENDIX A. SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JCMA/A286" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JCMA/A286</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="s1" content-type="document" xlink:href="ca9-88-58-s001.pdf" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflicts of interest: Dr. Jong-Ling Fuh, an editorial board member at <italic toggle="yes">Journal of the Chinese Medical Association</italic>, had no role in the peer review process of or decision to publish this article. The other authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest related to the subject matter or materials discussed in this article.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarantino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carducci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giampaolo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi Capitello</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive difficulties, psychological symptoms, and long-lasting somatic complaints in adolescents with previous SARS-CoV-2 infection: a telehealth cross-sectional pilot study.</article-title>
<source>Brain Sci</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>969</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35892410</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/brainsci12080969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9332506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asadi-Pooya</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotfi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rostamihosseinkhani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemati</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long COVID syndrome-associated brain fog.</article-title>
<source>J Med Virol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34672377</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jmv.27404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8662118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ocon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Caught in the thickness of brain fog: exploring the cognitive symptoms of chronic fatigue syndrome.</article-title>
<source>Front Physiol</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23576989</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphys.2013.00063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3617392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miskowiak</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sattler</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunalan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rungby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive impairment four months after COVID-19 hospital discharge: pattern, severity, and association with illness variables.</article-title>
<source>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33823427</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2021.03.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8006192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>García-Sánchez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calabria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grunden</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arroyo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Anson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neuropsychological deficits in patients with cognitive complaints after COVID‐19.</article-title>
<source>Brain Behav</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e2508</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35137561</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/brb3.2508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8933779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crivelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calandri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guekht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beghi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in cognitive functioning after COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
<source>Alzheimers Dement</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35297561</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/alz.12644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9073922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchberger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peilstöcker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warm</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linseisen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyhlik-Dürr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meisinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goßlau</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Subjective and objective cognitive impairments in non-hospitalized persons 9 months after SARS-CoV-2 infection.</article-title>
<source>Viruses</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36680296</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/v15010256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9865483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Brutto</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mera</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Recalde</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Issa</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive decline among individuals with a history of mild symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection: a longitudinal prospective study nested in a population cohort.</article-title>
<source>Eur J Neurol</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>3245</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33576150</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ene.14775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8014083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Twumasi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carnavali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of coronavirus disease-19 with cognitive impairment: a prospective cohort study.</article-title> Available at SSRN 4404856.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrucci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groppo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reitano</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term cognitive abnormalities following COVID-19.</article-title>
<source>Brain Sci</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33668456</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/brainsci11020235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7917789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hampshire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atchison</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellyer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giunchiglia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cognition and memory after COVID-19 in a large community sample.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>390</volume>:<fpage>806</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38416429</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa2311330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7615803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Méndez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balanzá-Martínez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luperdi</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estrada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>González-Jiménez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Short-term neuropsychiatric outcomes and QoL in COVID-19 survivors.</article-title>
<source>J Intern Med</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>290</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33533521</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/joim.13262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8013333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schild</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goereci</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scharfenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lülling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meiberth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multidomain cognitive impairment in non-hospitalized patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome: results from a prospective monocentric cohort.</article-title>
<source>J Neurol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>270</volume>:<fpage>1215</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36422669</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00415-022-11444-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9686246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>ESilva</surname><given-names>NML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros-Aragão</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felice</surname><given-names>FGD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammation at the crossroads of COVID-19, cognitive deficits, and depression.</article-title>
<source>Neuropharmacol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>209</volume>:<fpage>109023</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2022.109023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8894741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35257690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Ministry of Health and Welfare (Taiwan)</collab>. <article-title>Timeline COVID-19.</article-title>
<year>2024</year>. <comment>Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://covid19.mohw.gov.tw/en/sp-timeline0-206.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://covid19.mohw.gov.tw/en/sp-timeline0-206.html</ext-link>. Accessed May 15, 2024</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Rijsbergen</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Kort</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitskoorn</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Subjective cognitive complaints after stroke: a systematic review.</article-title>
<source>J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23800498</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2013.05.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Folstein</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helzer</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mini-mental state examination.</article-title>
<source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
<year>1983</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>812</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6860082</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archpsyc.1983.01790060110016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive Abilities Screening Instrument, Chinese version 2.0 (CASI C-2.0): administration and clinical application.</article-title>
<source>Acta Neurol Taiwan</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329550</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A normative study of Word Sequence Learning Tests in healthy Taiwanese individuals [Master’s thesis, National Taiwan University].</article-title> Airiti Library <year>2014</year>. <comment>Available at </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6342/NTU.2014.01265</pub-id><comment>. Accessed June 24, 2024</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale–Fourth Edition (WAIS–IV): Manual for Taiwan</source>. <publisher-loc>Taipei, Taiwan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chinese Behavioral Science Corporation</publisher-name>, <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A normative study of Nelson’s modified card-sorting test in healthy middle-aged and elderly individuals in Taiwan. [Unpublished master’s thesis, National Taiwan University].</article-title>
<comment>Airiti Library 2009. Available at </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6342/NTU.2009.10431</pub-id><comment>. Accessed June 24, 2024</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Normative Study of the Stroop Color and Word Test in Healthy Individuals in Taiwan [Master’s thesis, National Taiwan University].</article-title>
<comment>Airiti Library 2013. Available at </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6342/NTU.2013.10581</pub-id><comment>. Accessed June 24, 2024</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zigmond</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snaith</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hospital anxiety and depression scale.</article-title>
<source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source>
<year>1983</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6880820</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1600-0447.1983.tb09716.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angus</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arabi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A minimal common outcome measure for COVID-19 clinical research.</article-title>
<source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>e192</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32539990</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30483-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7292605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amariglio</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudel</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Isla</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blacker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Subjective cognitive concerns and neuropsychiatric predictors of progression to the early clinical stages of Alzheimer’s disease.</article-title>
<source>Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1642</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24698445</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jagp.2014.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4145054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceban</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>LMW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teopiz</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fatigue and cognitive impairment in post-COVID-19 syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
<source>Brain Behav Immun</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34973396</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbi.2021.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8715665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palladini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnaghi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poletti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Persistent psychopathology and neurocognitive impairment in COVID-19 survivors: effect of inflammatory biomarkers at three-month follow-up.</article-title>
<source>Brain Behav Immun</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33639239</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbi.2021.02.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7903920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schinka</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenberg</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banko</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Defining mild cognitive impairment: impact of varying decision criteria on neuropsychological diagnostic frequencies and correlates.</article-title>
<source>Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>684</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21399729</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/JGP.0b013e3181e56d5a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3052876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cianchetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foscoliano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scalas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sannio-Fancello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modified Wisconsin Card Sorting Test: proposal of a supplementary scoring method.</article-title>
<source>Arch Clin Neuropsychol</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15896568</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.acn.2004.12.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toniolo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Lorenzo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scarioni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nobili</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Is the frontal lobe the primary target of SARS-CoV-2?</article-title>
<source>J Alzheimer's Dis</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33720900</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3233/JAD-210008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive impairment after long COVID-19: current evidence and perspectives.</article-title>
<source>Front Neurol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1239182</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37583958</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fneur.2023.1239182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10423939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>