<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Health Serv Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Health Serv Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">34</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmchsr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Health Services Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6963</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12509383</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12509383.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12509383</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12509383</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41068758</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-025-13469-z</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13469</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Individuals’ perceptions of Long Covid: a phenomenological approach to an online health community narratives</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rochette</surname><given-names initials="C">Corinne</given-names></name><address><email>Corinne.Rochette@uca.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pontevia</surname><given-names initials="AFA">Anne Françoise Audrain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francois</surname><given-names initials="J">Julien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01a8ajp46</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.494717.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2173 2882</institution-id><institution>IAE Clermont Auvergne School of Management, CleRMa, Université Clermont Auvergne, </institution></institution-wrap>11 avenue Charles de Gaulle, Clermont-Ferrand, F-63000 France </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/002rjbv21</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.38678.32</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2181 0211</institution-id><institution>École Supérieure des Sciences de la Gestion, </institution><institution>Université du Québec à Montréal, </institution></institution-wrap>315 rue Sainte-Catherine Est, Montréal, QC H2X 3X2 Canada </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01a8ajp46</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.494717.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2173 2882</institution-id><institution>Research Chair Health and Territories, </institution><institution>University Clermont Auvergne, </institution></institution-wrap>Clermont–Ferrand, France </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478160</issue-id><elocation-id>1336</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-11 12:25:42.827"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12913_2025_Article_13469.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="structured"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">In 2023, it was estimated that at least 65 million individuals had Long Covid (LC). Yet the literature reveals a lack of knowledge on how individuals perceive and experience LC symptoms. This study aims to explore how individuals with Long Covid describe their symptoms across physical, cognitive, emotional, social, and behavioural dimensions, and to analyse these experiences through the lens of the Symptom Management Theory (SMT) using a phenomenological and netnographic approach to spontaneous patient narratives.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A netnographic study was conducted on 63 selected participants in France from 19 April 2020 to 31 December 2022. Narratives were first analysed phenomenologically using TROPES software. Verbatims were then coded through content analysis with NVivo12Pro and organised according to the SMT dimensions of symptom experience.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The study revealed that the testimonies of Long Covid patients are characterized by an argumentative, personal, and chronological discourse, highlighting the intensity of persistent symptoms and their significant impact on daily life. The most frequent symptoms identified include bodily pain, respiratory issues, chronic fatigue, as well as sensory and cognitive disturbances, along with significant emotional and social challenges.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Our study demonstrates the profound and multidimensional impact of Long Covid on patients’ daily lives, highlighting the need for a holistic, integrated approach to its management, considering affective, cognitive, behavioural, physical, and social dimensions to improve patients’ quality of life.</p></sec><sec><title>Practical implications</title><p id="Par5">Understanding the lived experiences of LC patients can guide healthcare services in providing more targeted, empathetic, and effective support.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12913-025-13469-z.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Long Covid</kwd><kwd>Symptoms experience</kwd><kwd>Phenomenological approach</kwd><kwd>Netnography</kwd><kwd>Online support community</kwd><kwd>France</kwd><kwd>Symptom management theory</kwd><kwd>Narrative medicine</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>research chair “Health and territories”of the Foundation of University Clermont Auvergne</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par6">The symptoms associated with the Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) infection were initially thought to be acute and transitory. However, it is estimated that one in ten patients has reported persistent symptoms for more than three weeks (post-acute symptoms) and sometimes for more than 12 weeks (chronic symptoms). In 2023, about 100 million people have suffered from Long Covid, which accounts for a total economic burden between 2.6 and 3.7 trillion US dollars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Post-acute and chronic symptoms have been coined under the term Long Covid (LC used further in this text) by the patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] to label the altered state of health they experienced. As described by Fernandez-de-la-Penas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], the term LC is generally used to describe the presence of symptoms lasting longer than would be expected.</p><p id="Par7">Though millions of people suffer from the persistence of Covid-19 symptoms or from the emergence of new symptoms, the patient’s experience of LC symptoms is still little documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Recent studies have explored lived experiences of COVID-19 patients, highlighting emotional distress, social isolation, and disruption to daily life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. However, these studies have often relied on structured interviews or surveys, limiting the capture of spontaneous narratives. In the specific context of Long Covid, patient-led accounts have emerged as a fundamental source of knowledge to document complex, fluctuating, and sometimes invisible symptoms. This research aims to fill this gap and examines how individuals voiced their symptoms and what are the related associated consequences. To do so, we analysed through a phenomenological lens, the narratives of individuals who participated in an online support community. In October 2020, to be heard and to benefit from the attention and the care needed, some LC patients in France acted through social networks, through Twitter first and then on a dedicated online support community named <italic toggle="yes">#ApresJ20</italic>. In a collective effort, these individuals and relatives managed in record time to bring the LC pathology into existence, whereas other patient associations took years to have their situations recognized and made legible (HIV-positive patients, parents of people with autistic disorders, etc.).</p><p id="Par8">Over time, the contributions of patients and lay people have often been ignored or misunderstood by conventional players, intensifying patient suffering and societal inequalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In 2023, scholars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] have underlined the denial and stigmatization faced by LC patients and called for more inclusion of the patient experience [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. To date, most research on LC has focused on clinical aspects and investigated the persistent symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Gathering and understanding the perceived experience of LC would help to improve LC treatment and to enrich scientific knowledge. Hence, research relying on patient experience is of utmost importance.</p><p id="Par9">Indeed, the experience of mild to acute symptoms pushes millions of patients to consult health care providers each year, but providers have difficulty developing applicable symptom management strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The Symptom Management Theory (SMT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] offers a robust conceptual framework for addressing this challenge. SMT conceptualizes symptom management as a dynamic process involving three interrelated components: (1) <italic toggle="yes">symptom experience</italic> (how individuals perceive, evaluate, and respond to symptoms); (2) <italic toggle="yes">management strategies (</italic>actions taken by patients or providers to prevent, alleviate, or adapt to symptoms); and (3) <italic toggle="yes">outcomes</italic> (the resulting effects on functional status, emotional well-being, and quality of life). This model has been applied to various chronic conditions, including chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), chronic heart failure (CHF), and end-stage renal disease (ESRD), where recent cross-sectional studies have assessed symptoms’ prevalence, severity, distress, and management using the SMT framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Emerging research on Long Covid has also begun to adopt this model to elucidate symptom variability, patient self-management efficacy, and the role of contextual influences such as social support and healthcare access. For instance, distinct Long Covid symptom burden profiles have been linked to differences in patients’ selfefficacy for symptom management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Additionally, the development of the Memorial Symptom Assessment Scale-Long Covid (MSAS-LC), which evaluates symptom frequency, severity, and distress in Long Covid, showcases the growing integration of symptom management frameworks in this context [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In the context of Long Covid, SMT is particularly relevant for capturing the interplay between physical manifestations, cognitive disruptions, emotional responses, and social consequences.</p><p id="Par10">Importantly, in contrast with previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] this research inferred the symptoms from individual narratives spontaneously posted on the online support community in France, <italic toggle="yes">#ApresJ20</italic> which was structured around the association after 20 days. Long covid is, among other things, identified from the persistence of symptoms beyond 20 days after infection. This naturalistic data source allows for capturing authentic, unprompted accounts of symptom evolution, including sensory and emotional dimensions that may be underreported in structured research settings. Contrarily to the growing body of qualitative research on the lived experience of LC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], we did not rely on any a priori interview or topic guide to elicit LC individuals’ perceived symptoms, but on pre-existing narratives. To our knowledge, this study on LC patients is the first to examine individuals’ symptoms experienced within a phenomenological approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] using netnography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">In contrast to the seminal research on LC symptoms, our approach aimed at bringing to the surface the perceived symptoms emerging from the individuals’ testimonials. Its purpose was to provide a naturalistic picture of the LC perceived symptoms and manifestations. Then, to compare our findings to the existing knowledge, we carried out a second analysis and classified the symptoms we obtained as well as the consequences of LC symptoms within well-known dimensions of individuals’ experience [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In the academic literature, two approaches to the patient experience are identifiable: the first focuses on the patient orientation of care providers, on the interactions between the patient and the human and non-human constituents of the care system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. A second less developed approach considers the patient experience in a more clinical-oriented approach by examining the way in which the patient’s experience the disease physically, psychologically and socially. This second approach has given rise to the concept of narrative medicine, which is still underdeveloped. A systematic review by Fioretti et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] provides evidence that narrative medicine is a useful tool to assess the patients’ experience of illness and to enrich general clinical information focused on the needs and the critical aspects of patients’ lives. Spontaneous patient testimonies are part of this perspective. This second approach echoes work that considers the patient experience as a multidimensional construct with cognitive, emotional, sensory, social and behavioural aspects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">This second approach of patient experience is particularly relevant for new diseases that are poorly documented in their emergence phase, such as LC. By situating our work within both the SMT and this multidimensional perspective, we address not only the clinical but also the experiential and social dimensions of Long Covid, thereby providing actionable insights for healthcare practice. The aim of this study is to explore how individuals with Long Covid experience and describe their symptoms across physical, cognitive, emotional, social, and behavioural dimensions, and to analyse these experiences through the lens of the Symptom Management Theory (SMT) using a phenomenological and netnographic approach to spontaneous patient narratives. Altogether, this research responds to the two following research questions: (RQ1) How do individuals experience LC symptoms, across physical, cognitive, affective, social, and behavioural dimensions? (RQ2) What are the manifestations and consequences of LC symptoms, and how can the SMT framework help in interpreting these lived experiences? To answer these two questions, we draw on work on the symptom management theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] and on the customer experience approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par13">This study consisted of a netnography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Precisely, it relied on a two-step approach: (i) a phenomenological approach to analyse the narratives of individuals reporting suffering from LC and (ii) a content analysis to classify the perceived symptoms and manifestations along the experiential dimensions using the multidimensional approach of people experience. The phenomenological approach is particularly suited here to understand the perception of the participants within an inductive perspective. This emic positioning of the research aims to reflect the inner perceptions and emotions associated with LC without considering any a priori framework. We inferred from testimonials how LC is experienced by individuals who participated in the <italic toggle="yes">#ApresJ20</italic> online community to make LC be recognized as a pathology.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Netnographic methods</title><p id="Par14">Netnography can be seen as a new qualitative research methodology that enables a more comprehensive view of a particular phenomenon or research questions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. It is an emerging method of obtaining qualitative data, which enables scholars to gain a naturalistic and immersive insight into information from online sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. In line with the phenomenological posture, netnography is a naturalistic, non-obtrusive approach which focuses on group or personal interviews [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Studies examining LC perceived symptoms mostly relied on qualitative methods such as focus groups or semi-structured interviews which are guided by a topic guide based on expert advice and / or a literature review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Although of interest, these approaches fail to provide a phenomenological approache to individuals’ perception. The netnographic approach we carried out relied on spontaneous and genuine testimonials posted on the <italic toggle="yes">#ApresJ20</italic> online support community. No a priori classification was mobilized. Further, the choice of netnography was motivated because we expected LC experience to be associated with emotions, which are difficult to capture and measure. Lastly, the netnographic approach proved to be a promising method to analyze patient perceptions, contribute to healthcare knowledge (e.g [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]). and to analyze narratives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par15">We focused on the individuals who claimed to have Long Covid on the <italic toggle="yes">#ApresJ20</italic> online community. The <italic toggle="yes">#ApresJ20</italic> association was created the 6th October 2020 by individuals who voiced their distress on Twitter, undergoing unusual, persistent, multi-systemic and invalidating LC symptoms. Because they felt unheard by the French authorities and practitioners, these patients created an online association that enabled them to centralize testimonials and provide information on Long Covid. In return, the nonprofit association aimed at providing social support to patients, family members and friends, and most importantly to make the LC disease recognized as a pathology in France. Hence, this association collected on a voluntary basis, on the <italic toggle="yes">#ApresJ20</italic> Website, testimonials which are published anonymously and without any modifications or corrections on the association website. The individuals defined as LC patients were individuals who reported persistent symptoms beyond three weeks or even beyond 12 weeks. The choice of a <italic toggle="yes">#ApresJ20</italic> online support community was motivated by the fact that this community provided individuals the opportunity to describe their symptoms with no specific guidelines or topic guide. This approach is consistent with the phenomenological perspective of this research which focuses on bringing out the LC symptoms and manifestations perceived by individuals without restraining itself to a specific analytical framework. Besides, the anonymity guaranteed by the website made it possible to provide comfort and confidentiality to patients without the interference of biases related to a third person.</p><p id="Par16">All the individual testimonials were collected for an initial screening. Out of the 76 testimonials (53, 745 words), 63 testimonials (43, 219 words) were selected. The inclusion criteria was the following: the individuals who wrote the testimonial had to be the person undergoing LC. Hence, we excluded parents or other family members / friends who wrote on behalf of someone else. Among these testimonials, 40 were from patients who reported their experiences of LC in the manner of a diary, adding specific dates for each phase of the experience. The remaining 23 testimonials were general reports of experiences with LC, with no temporal dimensions. The testimonials ranged from 126 to 5,600 words, with an average length of 686 words, and were published between 19 April 2020 and 31 December 2022.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par17">To uncover people’s experience, main thematic, effects, cognitions and manifestations concerning LC, we first carried out a semantic analysis which allowed a propositional and cognitive discursive analysis of the discourse. This, combined with no a priori approach, searching at eliciting the individuals’ thoughts in an organized and holistic view, was done using TROPES software. TROPES software is a linguistic software which allows the chronological analysis of the content, the terminological extraction as well as the categorization of words. It relies on a morphosyntactic analysis, a lexicon and a semantic network to categorize the texts and proposes hypertext graphical representations of the discourse. Thus, this first exploratory analysis of the 63 testimonials provided a first analysis of the main themes, styles and vocabulary associated with Long Covid without a priori knowledge. We then relied on NVivo R 1.7.1 software to organize the collected verbatims around themes and proceed to the content analysis along the experiential dimensions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. This double analysis makes it possible to compare a spontaneous analysis (TROPES) with an analysis controlled by the researcher (NVIVO R 1.7.1). the study is similar to a double coding, enabling the reinforcement of the internal reliability of the analysis.</p><p id="Par18">The experiential dimensions included affective (moods, feelings and emotions), cognitive (conscious thought and mental processes), behavioral (actions expressed by a specific behavior in a particular environment), physical (the manifestations of symptoms) and social (relationships, which occur during shared experience themes). Content analysis is a method of analyzing semi-structured interviews that can be applied in many disciplinary fields, including marketing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] and health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. This approach consists of a systematic examination and interpretation of the testimonials in an effort to identify themes and meanings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. It comprises a coding scheme based on specific research questions determined from a review of the relevant literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Hence, content analysis allows for the identification of data units, which are categorized into themes to reach a conclusion about the content of the material under study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. We have chosen content analysis as opposed to thematic analysis because it enables us to quantify and contrast the involved categories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Considering our research questions, we began by identifying the key dimensions of the patients’ experience as initial analytic categories: affective (emotional), cognitive, behavioral, physical (sensory) and social Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par19">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Qualitative analysis procedure</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e454" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12913_2025_13469_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results</title><p id="Par20">Our study aims to answer two questions: How do individuals experience LC symptoms? What are the manifestations of LC symptoms? Our results present a combined analysis of morphosyntactic analysis using TROPES and thematic content analysis conducted with NVIVO.</p><sec id="Sec7"><title>An embodied and factual discourse</title><p id="Par21">The analysis of testimonies using TROPES allows us to qualify the style of discourse. It is rather argumentative, indicating that people discuss, compare, and critique. They express facts and actions. The discourses are in the first person singular, denoting very personal testimonies. The importance of temporal modulizations shows that the testimonies situate facts and actions in time. Furthermore, negative modalisations dramatise the discourse and attest to its intensity.</p><p id="Par22">One contribution of the TROPES analysis compared to NVIVO coding is the emphasis on the importance of temporality. There are 545 occurrences related to the month, 503 to time fractions (morning, afternoon, evening, weekend), and 371 to the day or a specific day of the week. This denotes a testimony anchored in space-time and chronologically articulated around facts and feelings. This temporal anchoring not only reflects the chronic nature of LC symptoms but also suggests that patients construct their illness narrative through recurring temporal markers, highlighting a “before” and “after” illness rupture. Additionally, COVID-19 infection with persistent symptoms marks a significant rupture in the lives of these patients, with a “before” and “after” and a difficulty in projecting themselves into the future.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>The experience of symptoms (manifestations of physical and sensory symptoms)</title><p id="Par23">Patients described a broad and heterogeneous set of LC symptoms, whose intensity, duration, and combinations varied considerably between individuals - from brief, transient episodes to manifestations persisting for months. Some experienced only a few flu-like symptoms (e.g., headache, sore throat, fatigue, muscle pain), while others reported several dozen, with extreme cases reaching over 50 distinct symptoms during the illness trajectory. This variability suggests the possible existence of multiple LC phenotypes, shaped by individual susceptibility, comorbidities, viral variants, and environmental conditions. The following sub-sections synthesise these experiences along six dimensions, supported by the most frequent manifestations listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and their associated antecedents and consequences (Appendix <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par24">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The experienced symptoms</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Category of symptoms</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptoms</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Verbatim</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="16" colspan="1">Physical</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bodily pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Muscular pains like aches at night I am awakened by the pain of my muscles that tense up.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Chest pain became respiratory discomfort and my breath dried up.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Respiratory issues</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“breathing difficulties appeared a week later”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“After 3 days she started to feel weak and her oxygen level was dropping.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chronic fatigue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“10 days of fatigue where it is literally impossible for me to get out of bed.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Fatigue often takes me by surprise: either in the morning or in the afternoon or even all day long.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Headaches</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“My headache was still there and still as intense as ever.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Phase covid active: severe headaches.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sore throats</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“A few days ago and for a week I had pain in my throat and difficulty swallowing my saliva.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Sore throat and well-developed lymph nodes.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Fever</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Sensation of burning fever without fever.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I had a high fever.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Digestive disorders</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“And then my stomach hurts. Excruciating unbearable pain… I ‘burn’ from the inside.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Digestive problems since December accompanied by pain in the left hypochondrium.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dermatological problems</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I had dermatological symptoms and haematomas came out all over my body.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“During March April and May 2020 I experienced impressive hair loss which stopped today.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="10" colspan="1">Sensory</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Eye problems</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Intense eye pain. Strange visions and black or blue walls.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I’ve lost a great deal of visual acuity.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Loss of taste</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I haven’t recovered the taste either: I taste a green-red berry tea for a vanilla tea.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Today it’s been 6 months and I still haven’t recovered my taste.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Loss of smell</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I haven’t recovered my sense of smell: one day the meal was burning on the gas.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I still haven’t recovered my sense of smell. I sorely miss the smell of my daughter.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tinnitus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I have tinnitus in the evening mainly at bedtime: it crackles or whistles in my ear.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“The ones that bother me the most are: tinnitus which is sometimes deafening.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dizziness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I feel dizzy"</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Intense dizziness (I have to lean against walls to walk).”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Cognitive</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Brain fog</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I experience a cognitive fog that complicates my professional tasks.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I’m often asked what brain fog is. It’s not being able to think straight even about simple things.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Concentration and memory problems</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“This time I had memory lapses</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I couldn’t find my words”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“I have a lot of trouble concentrating</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and high-pitched noises attack me”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="14" colspan="1">Affective</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Hope</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Hope can be reborn when two nights follow each other more or less normally without the painful bite of a cruel vice gripping the rib cage.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“I’m happy because I’m alive</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> my husband and children are well.”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Relief</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“My GP was completely at a loss</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> so he prescribed home oxygen. When they came to install this device</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it was a relief””</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“I was relieved to have a diagnosis</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> because I’d been suffering since March 25”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Recognition of the disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“This is one of the most difficult questions: will I go back to the way I was? Will my brain regain its liveliness”?</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“I still feel lucky not to have had a stay in intensive care</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> because I know I was close”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Fear</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“What scares me is that it affects my memory and sociability”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I’m always afraid I’ll contract it again or that a new episode will prevent me from going to work”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Stress and anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Stress of not feeling in shape and of not having caught up with everything of not being up to date stress of the context in general.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Right now I feel quite alone and abandoned by everyone.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Anger</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I’m angry because they won’t give me the pass without giving me a vaccine”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“Sometimes I get angry at the situation because it’s not easy to be understood when no one can really understand what’s going on”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sadness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“I cried for 5 days</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> no one could tell me if I was better or not”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“I cried</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I longed for just one thing: to get back to my usual liveliness”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Social</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Role of Family</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“When I woke up in the morning my husband would take me out onto the terrace in the fresh air to help me breathe easier.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“My relatives are far from understanding</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and I try not to complain”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Role of Healthcare Professionals</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I’m lucky to have a great GP who has supported me from day one”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">“How can you cope</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> when you have doctors who are against you and do nothing to help you get better?”</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Behavioural</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Self-management of symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I treated myself with the medicines I had at home. I took a medicine that I only take when I have a cold. I increased the doses.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I protect myself: ventilation/ventilation as much as possible. Hydroalcoholic gel masks (when possible).”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Physical Activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“In order not to lose out physically I bought an electric bike and with my husband we’ve been quietly criss-crossing our region.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I’m trying to get back into running which can only help me feel better.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Rehabilitation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“For the past 3 weeks I’ve been following a sports rehabilitation program at Hôtel Dieu.”</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">“I started physiotherapy sessions in March 2021. We work on breathing and also do sports rehabilitation.”</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>The physical experience of symptoms</title><p id="Par25">Two distinct patterns of physical symptoms emerged. The first, common to most patients, included bodily pain, respiratory difficulties, and chronic fatigue. Fatigue, often qualified as <italic toggle="yes">“extreme”</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">“crushing”</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">“disabling”</italic>, severely compromised basic activities of daily living: <italic toggle="yes">“Standing up was a struggle</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> taking a shower was a challenge.”</italic> Many patients described post-exertional malaise, where even minor physical or mental effort triggered a disproportionate worsening of symptoms, an observation consistent with other chronic post-viral syndromes.</p><p id="Par26">Bodily pain ranged from diffuse muscle aches to localised joint stiffness, sometimes described as cyclical or migrating across body regions, making movement and exercise difficult. Respiratory manifestations -shortness of breath, chest pressure, or episodes of “air hunger”- frequently co-occurred with fatigue, amplifying functional limitations: <italic toggle="yes">“Chest pain became respiratory discomfort</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> my breath dried up.”</italic></p><p id="Par27">In addition to this first category of physical symptoms, there is a second pattern that encompassed symptoms present in only a subset of patients: digestive disorders (e.g., abdominal pain, nausea, gastric reflux), dermatological problems (e.g., rashes, urticaria, hair loss), sore throats, headaches, and fever sensations without hyperthermia. Some of these, such as dermatological issues, were described as sudden and visually alarming, impacting body image, self-esteem, and social comfort. Their heterogeneous distribution reinforces the hypothesis of immune-mediated and multi-systemic mechanisms in LC.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>The sensory experience of symptoms</title><p id="Par28">Sensory disturbances were diverse and included alterations in taste, smell, vision, hearing, and balance, often producing cascading effects on nutrition, emotional well-being, and occupational performance.</p><p id="Par29"><bold>Loss of taste</bold> (ageusia) and <bold>smell</bold> (anosmia) -hallmark LC symptoms- could persist for weeks or months. Qualitative distortions were also reported: metallic taste, phantom odours (e.g., burning, smoke) or parosmia, where pleasant smells became unpleasant or nauseating. These changes reduced appetite, disrupted eating patterns, and in some cases led to weight loss or nutritional imbalance. <italic toggle="yes">“Today</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it’s been six months</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and I still haven’t regained my sense of taste”.</italic></p><p id="Par30"><bold>Eye problems</bold> (reduced visual acuity, colour distortion, ocular pain, photophobia) limited daily activities, increased visual fatigue, and impaired reading or screen use: <italic toggle="yes">“I have lost a significant portion of my visual acuity […] and sometimes my eyes start to move like nystagmus</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I have flashes of light</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and my eyes itch to the point of wanting to scratch them.”</italic></p><p id="Par31"><bold>Tinnitus</bold>, characterized by ringing or buzzing in the ears, was also common among patients. These sounds were often more intense in quiet settings and at night, interfering with sleep onset and continuity: <italic toggle="yes">“It wakes me up in the middle of the night.”</italic></p><p id="Par32">Finally, <bold>dizziness</bold> was another sensory symptom. varied from mild disequilibrium to severe vertigo requiring support while walking. For some, these episodes were sudden and unpredictable, reinforcing fear of falls and loss of independence.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>The cognitive experience of symptoms</title><p id="Par33">The cognitive experience of LC was characterised by persistent disturbances in mental abilities, with brain fog, concentration difficulties, and memory lapses being among the most disabling. These impairments often remained even after other symptoms had subsided, profoundly affecting daily functioning.</p><p id="Par34"><bold>Brain fog</bold> was described as a as <italic toggle="yes">“mental cloudiness”</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">“slowness”</italic>, compromising the ability to focus, plan, and make decisions. Patients reported impaired executive functions: reduced working memory, difficulty sequencing tasks, and slower information processing. <italic toggle="yes">“It’s as if my brain doesn’t respond when I call on it for routine tasks.”</italic></p><p id="Par35">Brain fog, concentration issues, and memory problems appeared almost inseparable, frequently occurring together. As one patient explained: <italic toggle="yes">“I feel a sort of cognitive fog that complicates my professional tasks. Concentration</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> synthesis</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and verbalisation (less fluent speech</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> hesitant expression</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> stuttering</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> difficulty finding words) are now complicated for me.”</italic> This multifaceted cognitive decline affected not only professional performance but also personal life, leading to frustration, loss of self-confidence, and a diminished sense of control. These difficulties often forced patients to rethink their daily routines, as they felt incapable of organising thoughts, planning activities, or solving everyday problems. Such limitations prompted uncertainty about the future and raised concerns about long-term mental health. One patient shared: <italic toggle="yes">“Many questions ran through my mind. Would I have enough energy to get through the day? Would I suffer too much at work? How would I react to stressful situations?”</italic></p><p id="Par36">This constant cognitive strain, combined with the unpredictability of symptoms, amplified psychological distress and could contribute to heightened anxiety or even depression. As a result, cognitive symptoms in LC must be considered not only as isolated neurological manifestations but also as key drivers of emotional and social challenges in the patient’s overall experience.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>The affective experience of symptoms</title><p id="Par37">Living with Long Covid provoked wide range of emotions, with testimonies revealing a coexistence of negative states (stress, anxiety, anger, abandonment, fear, sadness) and positive feelings (hope, relief, gratitude).</p><p id="Par38"><bold>Hope</bold> was most often expressed when patients noticed improvement or perceived themselves as moving toward recovery: <italic toggle="yes">“Hope can be reborn when two nights follow each other more or less normally without the painful grip of a cruel vice squeezing the chest.”</italic> Such hope was described as a resource that helped maintain morale and navigate setbacks. <bold>Relief</bold> frequently followed a formal LC diagnosis or effective medical intervention. For example: <italic toggle="yes">“I had an appointment with the pulmonologist who recognised Long Covid with respiratory hyperventilation. She put the diagnosis in writing</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and in a way</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> it was a relief.”</italic> This <bold>recognition</bold> not only provided an explanation for their ailments but also reduced uncertainty and anxiety. Gratitude was often directed towards healthcare providers and supportive relatives: <italic toggle="yes">“I don’t give up</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I am very fortunate to be surrounded by my wonderful family and friends</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and my GP on whom I can rely.”</italic> Such expressions strengthened social bonds and contributed to emotional resilience.</p><p id="Par39">Not surprisingly, <bold><underline>negative emotions</underline></bold> were pervasive, with fear being the most recurrent. <bold>Fear</bold> was omnipresent among Long Covid patients. <bold>Stress and anxiety</bold> were mainly linked to uncertainty about recovery and fear of lasting impairment, and could be triggered by the onset of new symptoms. <bold>Anger</bold> was often directed at the healthcare system, fuelled by feelings of abandonment or invalidation: <italic toggle="yes">“I am very angry because they let me down last year.” “Right now</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I feel quite alone and abandoned by everyone.”</italic> This anger was intensified when patients felt disbelieved: <italic toggle="yes">“These sensations are hard to explain</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and people don’t understand them</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> as if everything is in my head or I’m exaggerating.”</italic></p><p id="Par40">Finally, <bold>sadness</bold> was frequently tied to the perceived loss of a “normal” life. <italic toggle="yes">“I cried for 5 days. No one could tell me if I would get better or not</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I could barely walk.”</italic> Daily functional challenges and the absence of a clear recovery horizon often deepened this sadness, sometimes leading to withdrawal or hopelessness.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>The social and behavioural experience</title><p id="Par41">The social experience encompassed multifaceted interactions with family, friends, and healthcare professionals, while the behavioural experience referred to the range of strategies adopted by patients to cope with and manage symptoms. Together, these dimensions illustrate the ways in which patients adapt to a new reality and navigate their recovery trajectory.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Social experience: The role of family and healthcare professionals</title><p id="Par42">Interactions with family and friends were were described as both supportive and, at times, a source of frustration for LC patients (see Appendix <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). While relatives often provided emotional encouragement and practical help, some patients perceived a lack of understanding or empathy, which contributed to feelings of isolation. Several chose to conceal the severity of their symptoms to avoid being perceived as complaining, as in the testimony: <italic toggle="yes">“I hide certain signs from my family because I feel like I’m always complaining.”</italic> This self-censorship, however, could exacerbate stress and hinder emotional expression.</p><p id="Par43">In some cases, patients found reassurance and validation from healthcare professionals (see Appendix <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), who offered compassionate listening and acknowledgment of the condition: <italic toggle="yes">“I quickly discussed Long Covid with my doctor. She knows me</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> listens to me</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and believes me.”</italic> Yet, experiences were heterogeneous, and others reported feeling dismissed or denied recognition of their illness, leading to emotional distress and diminished trust: <italic toggle="yes">“My doctor never validated a Covid diagnosis</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> which is very difficult emotionally.”</italic> Such lack of validation may reinforce a sense of invisibility and undermine adherence to medical advice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Behavioural experience</title><p id="Par44">Symptom management strategies varied, encompassing self-management, adapted physical activity, and structured rehabilitation. Some patients resorted to self-medication and preventive routines, for example: <italic toggle="yes">“I treated myself with the medications I had at home.”</italic> These practices reflected a desire to regain control over health and mitigate symptom burden.</p><p id="Par45">Others Others engaged in moderate physical activity despite limitations from fatigue and pain, seeking to maintain functional capacity and psychological well-being: <italic toggle="yes">“To avoid physical decline</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I bought an electric bike</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> and with my husband</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> we leisurely cycled around our region.”</italic> Physical exercise was frequently cited as a means to preserve autonomy, improve mood, and counteract deconditioning. In addition, formal rehabilitation programmes (either prescribed or self-initiated) were used to gradually restore physical endurance and respiratory capacity. As one patient explained: <italic toggle="yes">“For the past 3 weeks</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> I have been in a sports rehabilitation programme at Hôtel Dieu</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> which helps me get used to exercising again.”</italic> Such programmes, often led by healthcare professionals, were perceived as instrumental in regaining lost functions and re-establishing daily routines.</p><p id="Par46">Overall, these behavioural adjustments highlight adaptive strategies that combine physical, psychological, and social dimensions, aiming to minimise the impact of symptoms while fostering a sense of agency in recovery.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Contribution to theory</title><p id="Par47">In this research, we utilized the framework of the Symptom Management Theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and adopted a phenomenological approach, supported by netnography, to analyze the experience of LC symptoms. Our results highlight multidimensional experiences with significant impacts on affective, cognitive, behavioral, physical, and social dimensions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The findings indicate that LC patients experience high levels of anxiety and depression, consistent with literature on chronic diseases, including LC. Beyond the most frequently reported symptom groups (cardiopulmonary difficulties, neurological problems), their profound emotional impact on patients is evident [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. While the Symptom Management Theory emphasizes the importance of symptom perception and evaluation by patients, the reported feelings of abandonment and emotional hypersensitivity demonstrate how symptom evaluation can be influenced by the social and medical support received, or the lack thereof. Hence, our findings enrich the Symptom Management Theory by emphasizing the central role of healthcare services and their personnel, which remain underexplored in the literature.</p><p id="Par48">Cognitive impairments, such as memory problems and brain fog, are frequently reported symptoms. The Symptom Management Theory considers the evaluation of symptom severity as a key element of patient response. Testimonials indicate that these cognitive impairments significantly disrupt daily life and work capacity, amplifying the perception of severity and disability associated with LC. Our work corroborates the findings of Ladds et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] and Rofail et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] on the need to develop specific management strategies for particularly debilitating cognitive symptoms. Patients adapt their behaviors and habits to mitigate these symptoms, illustrating their capacity to adopt coping strategies to manage symptoms, minimize their impact, and maintain a sense of normalcy in their lives. The Symptom Management Theory highlights the importance of these management strategies in a holistic approach to patient experience and calls for healthcare providers to recognize these symptoms to better support patients in managing them.</p><p id="Par49">Our work demonstrates how fundamental the perception and evaluation of physical symptoms are to understanding patient experiences. Recognizing these symptoms is a prerequisite for developing appropriate management by healthcare professionals with targeted clinical interventions as recommended by Perumal et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and Sudre et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par50">Furthermore, the social impacts of LC, such as reduced social interactions and difficulties maintaining relationships, illustrate how LC symptoms can disrupt patients’ social lives. The Symptom Management Theory includes patients’ responses to symptoms, which are often influenced by social interactions and support received. The findings show that the lack of understanding and support from family, friends, and healthcare professionals, along with a deficit of pro-social behavior, can exacerbate patients’ distress and intensify their social isolation, an element still too little considered. These observations are consistent with broader research on the social consequences of COVID-19 and Long Covid, which highlight reductions in social participation, deterioration of family and friendship networks, and stigma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Social isolation has been linked to increased anxiety, depressive symptoms, and poorer quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. In our study, the fluctuating and sometimes invisible nature of symptoms appeared to intensify these social challenges, often leaving patients without sustained or adapted support, as also noted by Rofail et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This convergence between our results and previous work underscores the necessity for healthcare systems to integrate social support interventions into LC management, fostering connectedness, empathy, and collaborative care approaches.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Contribution to methodology</title><p id="Par51">Methodologically, one of the main contributions is the use of netnography to collect and analyze patient testimonies deposited on the digital space of an online support community (#ApresJ20). This method provides access to spontaneous and authentic narratives, where patients share their experiences without being influenced by researchers’ questions, offering rich and unbiased data. Additionally, testimonies are often posted in real-time, reflecting patients’ perceptions and experiences as they are lived. Unlike traditional qualitative approaches based on interviews that may rely on memory, this research is based on pre-existing patient narratives, reducing data collection biases. The narratives are collected without the direct influence of research questions and interviewers, capturing more natural experiences and reflecting patients’ spontaneous perceptions and priorities.</p><p id="Par52">The simultaneous use of TROPES and NVIVO software for data coding brings an interesting complementarity. TROPES detects semantic relationships between words, helps understand associations, and identifies recurring linguistic patterns (large semantic categories). NVIVO organizes data and identifies sub-categories of coding (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This dual approach strengthens the robustness of the analysis.</p><p id="Par53">We acknowledge, however, that qualitative analysis is inherently interpretative, and the personality, prior experiences, and disciplinary background of the researchers may shape coding choices and thematic emphasis. To mitigate this potential bias, coding was performed collaboratively, with iterative discussions and reflexive notes to document interpretative decisions, in line with qualitative research standards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. This reflexive stance aimed to enhance transparency, ensure alignment with the data, and limit the influence of individual perspectives on the veracity of findings.</p><p id="Par54">From a methodological perspective, our study adds to the growing body of work demonstrating the potential of netnography in health research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], particularly for emerging conditions where traditional recruitment and interview protocols may be challenging.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Contribution to practice</title><p id="Par55">By incorporating spontaneous patient testimonies into this research, our study contributes to enriching the scientific understanding of LC and provides leverage to improve clinical practices for managing this complex condition. The application of the Symptom Management Theory structures patients’ perceptions and proposes interventions based on their lived experiences, essential for developing effective and inclusive treatment strategies.</p><p id="Par56">Our findings emphasize the need for an integrated approach to LC management that considers all dimensions of symptom experience. Healthcare professionals should be trained to recognize and treat LC’s multidimensional symptoms, offering cognitive, emotional, and social support, as well as accurate information on the physical manifestations of the disease and behaviors to adopt. Moreover, health policies should more prominently include strategies to reduce stigma and improve LC recognition in the medical and social community. These recommendations align with previous calls for comprehensive post-COVID care models integrating physical rehabilitation, psychological support, and social reintegration strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. While patient associations’ work on LC has begun to bear fruit, the persistence of symptoms several years after infection requires continued efforts. Long Covid symptoms have not disappeared despite the reduced media presence on the topic. Encouraging practical exchanges between healthcare professionals and LC patient associations could help better adjust healthcare delivery and foster collaboration among different healthcare professionals around LC patients to better structure care pathways for these patients. In addition, the experience remains “unique” for each patient in terms of the duration and intensity of the symptoms, emotions that are not only negative but that for some patients have positive aspects, which requires that truly individualized care be considered. Such an approach promotes a patient/doctor and patient/caregiver relationship of essential quality to offer quality health services and to best support patients in the management of symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par57">Several limitations should be acknowledged. First, although netnography allows for the collection of spontaneous narratives, participants self-selected to post on the online support community, which may limit the representativeness of the sample. Second, demographic and clinical information was not systematically available, preventing subgroup analyses by age, gender, comorbidity, or infection variant. Third, the analysis is interpretative by nature; despite reflexive practices and collaborative coding, the researchers’ disciplinary backgrounds and perspectives may have influenced data interpretation. Fourth, the study focuses on the French context and a single online community, which may limit transferability to other cultural or healthcare settings. Future studies could triangulate these findings with longitudinal interviews and clinical assessments to strengthen external validity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par58">The analysis of LC patient testimonies shows that this condition profoundly and variably impacts their daily lives. By relying on the Symptom Management Theory and a phenomenological approach, this study highlights the complexity of LC symptom experiences and the need for an integrated approach to their management. The results reinforce the importance of recognizing and treating LC holistically, considering affective, cognitive, behavioral, physical, and social dimensions to improve patients’ quality of life. This is fundamental in a context where the World Health Organization estimated in 2023 that more than 2 million people worldwide are affected.</p><p id="Par59">Beyond documenting the wide range of symptoms, our findings stress how social and medical support (or its absence) shapes patients' perception, coping strategies and emotional burden.This illustrates the critical role of healthcare services and professionals in mitigating distress and improving adaptation. Finally, this study demonstrates the value of netnography for health research, particularly for emerging conditions where traditional data collection is difficult.</p><sec id="Sec22"><title>Recommendations for future research</title><p id="Par60">Although this study offers a unique view on LC which relied on a phenomenological analysis of individuals’ narratives, it presents some overall limitations. Firstly, this study focuses on French individual testimonials. France possesses a public universal healthcare system, which is not the case in all developed countries. Secondly, each individual country opted for its own specific measures and guidelines during the pandemic. Hence, we expect that individuals’ perceptions differ in other countries and cultures. These limitations argue in favour of additional research in other countries and other medical systems. Complementary studies on other online communities or relying on qualitative interviews would increase the external validity of our results. Besides, by enriching these results with a refined qualitative analysis based on qualitative semi-structured interviews could aim at developing a scale to measure LC symptoms, manifestations and coping strategies. Lastly, it would also be of interest to contrast our findings to healthcare providers’ perceptions of LC symptoms and coping strategies to see how they behave in front of long COVID patients, the actions they take and the strategies they adopt.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec23" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12913_2025_13469_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Audrey Milton who copy edited this article and also the research chair “Health and territories” and university of Clermont Auvergne for funding this research.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>C.R. and A.F.A.P presented the conceptual framework ad conceived the theoretical background C.R. was responsible for data collection. C.R. presented the methodology. J.F. and C.R. coded the data, extracted the results. C.R. analysed and interpreted the data. C.R. and A.F A.P. discussed the results and wrote the conclusion. C.R. and A.F.A.P. wrote the main manuscript text. C.R. coordinated the revisions. All authors reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research is a part of the research undertaken under the research chair “Health and territories” (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.chaire-sante-territoires.org/">https://www.chaire-sante-territoires.org/</ext-link>) of the Foundation of University Clermont Auvergne. The research chair arranges payment of processing charges.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Dataset file is available upon request from corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par61">Not applicable: The data analysed in this research was collected from a community online and open access called #ApresJ20. Considering the current national regulations, our study does not require ethical approval from an ethics committee nor consent for participation because the data used are freely accessible online. Our research is non-interventional and therefore not subject to the rules of the Jardé law (law n° 2012–300, March 5, 2012) on biomedical research conducted in France. This category of research, based on the collection of anonymised and freely accessible accounts of individual experience of long covid, does not require written consent. Concerning the protection of personal data, in the European Union and in France, the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) (Regulation 2016/679 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 27 April 2016) came into force on 25 May 2018. The French Data Protection Act (Law No. 78–17 of January 6, 1978 on information technology, files and freedoms) has been adapted accordingly by the Personal Data Protection Act currently being enacted. These two texts now form the basis of the new regulation on personal data protection. The GDPR defines personal data as “any information relating to an identified or identifiable natural person”, i.e. a natural person who can be identified, directly or indirectly. In practice, this may include identification data such as surname, first name, address or telephone number, information relating to the patient’s personal life (e.g. number of children), social security coverage (e.g. compulsory health insurance, supplementary health insurance, etc.) and, above all, information relating to the patient’s health (prescriptions, care, etc.), and any professionals involved in his or her care. In our study, we do not use any of these data because they are only testimonies on the experience of long covid and are freely available on the page <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.apresj20.fr/temoignagesof">https://www.apresj20.fr/temoignagesof</ext-link> the “après J 20” association website.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par62">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par63">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perumal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shunmugam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naidoo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdool Karim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garzino-Demo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: a review and proposed visualization of the complexity of long COVID</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1117464</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1117464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37153597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10157068</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Perumal R, Shunmugam L, Naidoo K, Abdool Karim SS, Wilkins D, Garzino-Demo A, et al. Long COVID: a review and proposed visualization of the complexity of long COVID. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1117464. 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1117464.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37153597</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1117464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10157068</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perego</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stras</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melville-Jóhannesson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alwan</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why the patient-made term ‘long covid’ is needed</article-title><source>Wellcome Open Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>224</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/wellcomeopenres.16307.1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Perego E, Callard F, Stras L, Melville-Jóhannesson B, Pope R, Alwan NA. Why the patient-made term ‘Long Covid’ is needed. Wellcome Open Res. 2020;5:224. 10.12688/wellcomeopenres.16307.1.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-de-Las-Peñas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martín-Guerrero</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro-Pardo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cancela-Cilleruelo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moro-López-Menchero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pellicer-Valero</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring trajectory curves from loss of smell and taste in previously hospitalized COVID-19 survivors: the LONG-COVID-EXP-CM multicenter study</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1821</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-022-07459-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35194745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8863099</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Fernández-de-Las-Peñas C, Martín-Guerrero JD, Navarro-Pardo E, Cancela-Cilleruelo I, Moro-López-Menchero P, Pellicer-Valero OJ. Exploring trajectory curves from loss of smell and taste in previously hospitalized COVID-19 survivors: the LONG-COVID-EXP-CM multicenter study. J Gen Intern Med. 2022;37:1821–3. 10.1007/s11606-022-07459-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35194745</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-022-07459-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8863099</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladds</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rushforth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieringa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Persistent symptoms after Covid-19: qualitative study of 114 long Covid patients and draft quality principles for services</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-020-06001-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7750006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33342437</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Ladds E, Rushforth A, Wieringa S, Taylor S, Rayner C, Husain L, et al. Persistent symptoms after Covid-19: qualitative study of 114 long Covid patients and draft quality principles for services. BMC Health Serv Res. 2020;20:1–13. 10.1186/s12913-020-06001-y.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-020-06001-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7750006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33342437</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rofail D, McGale N, Podolanczuk AJ, Rams A, Przydzial K, Sivapalasingam S, et al. Patient experience of symptoms and impacts of COVID-19: a qualitative investigation with symptomatic outpatients. BMJ Open. 2022;12. 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-055989.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-055989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9062460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35501077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Macpherson K, Cooper K, Harbour J, Mahal D, Miller C, Nairn M. Experiences of living with long COVID and of accessing healthcare services: a qualitative systematic review. BMJ Open. 2022;12. 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-050979.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-050979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8753091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35017239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pignon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Depressive symptoms and sex differences in the risk of post-COVID-19 persistent symptoms: a prospective population-based cohort study</article-title><source>Nat Mental Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s44220-024-00290-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Matta J, Pignon B, Kab S, et al. Depressive symptoms and sex differences in the risk of post-COVID-19 persistent symptoms: a prospective population-based cohort study. Nat Mental Health. 2024;2:1053–61. 10.1038/s44220-024-00290-6.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Oraibi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarrant</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of long COVID on UK healthcare workers and their workplace: a qualitative study of healthcare workers with long COVID, their families, colleagues and managers</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>519</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-025-12677-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40205414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11980223</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Al-Oraibi A, Tarrant C, Woolf K, et al. The impact of long COVID on UK healthcare workers and their workplace: a qualitative study of healthcare workers with long COVID, their families, colleagues and managers. BMC Health Serv Res. 2025;25:519. 10.1186/s12913-025-12677-x.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40205414</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-025-12677-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11980223</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skipper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long COVID quality of life and healthcare experiences in the UK: a mixed method online survey</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-023-03513-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37740144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10784347</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Owen R, Ashton RE, Skipper L, Phillips BE, Yates J, Thomas C, et al. Long COVID quality of life and healthcare experiences in the UK: a mixed method online survey. Qual Life Res. 2024;33(1):133–43. 10.1007/s11136-023-03513-y.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37740144</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11136-023-03513-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10784347</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Callard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perego</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How and why patients made long Covid</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>113426</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33199035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7539940</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Callard F, Perego E. How and why patients made Long Covid: Soc Sci Med. 2021;268:113426. 10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113426.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33199035</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7539940</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>COVID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Major findings, mechanisms and recommendations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Topol EJ, Long COVID. Major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023;21:133–46. 10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lambert NJ, Corps S. COVID-19 “long hauler”symptoms survey report. 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudre</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varsavsky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penfold</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowyer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Attributes and predictors of long COVID</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.10.19.20214494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33692530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7611399</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Sudre CH, Murray B, Varsavsky T, Graham MS, Penfold RS, Bowyer RC, et al. Attributes and predictors of long COVID. Nat Med. 2021;27:626–31. 10.1101/2020.10.19.20214494.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33692530</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-021-01292-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7611399</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Townsend L, Dyer AH, Jones K, Dunne J, Mooney A, Gaffney F, et al. Persistent fatigue following SARS-CoV-2 infection is common and independent of severity of initial infection. PLoS ONE. 2020;15. 10.1371/journal.pone.0240784.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0240784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7652254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33166287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fletcher BAS, Dodd MJ, Schumacher KL, Miaskowski C. Symptom experiences of family care-givers with cancer. Oncol Nurs Forum. 2008;35. 10.1188/08.ONF.E23-E44.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1188/08.ONF.E23-E44</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19405245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donesky</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dracup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puntillo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/><etal/></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liehr</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><etal/><etal/></person-group><article-title>Theory of symptom management</article-title><source>Middle range theory for nursing</source><year>2014</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer Publishing Company</publisher-name><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="book">Humphreys J, Janson S, Donesky DA, Dracup K, Lee KA, Puntillo K, et al. Theory of symptom management. In: Smith MJ, Liehr PR, editors. Middle range theory for nursing. 3rd ed. New York: Springer Publishing Company; 2014. pp. 141–64.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van den Bergh</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Illness and symptom perception: a theoretical approach towards an integrative measurement model</article-title><source>Clin Psychol Rev</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2010.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21146271</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Petersen S, van den Berg RA, Janssens T, Van den Bergh O. Illness and symptom perception: a theoretical approach towards an integrative measurement model. Clin Psychol Rev. 2011;31:428–39. 10.1016/j.cpr.2010.11.002.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21146271</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cpr.2010.11.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrierri-Kohlman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faucett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Froelicher</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A model for symptom management</article-title><source>J Nurs Scholarsh</source><year>1994</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1547-5069.1994.tb00333.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Larson PJ, Carrierri-Kohlman V, Dodd MJ, Douglas M, Faucett J, Froelicher ES, et al. A model for symptom management. J Nurs Scholarsh. 1994;26:272–6.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Landers MG. Symptom management theory. In: Theories Guiding Nursing Research and Practice: Making Nursing Knowledge Development Explicit. 2014. p. 35.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eicher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delmas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baeriswyl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Python</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The French version of symptom management theory and its application</article-title><source>Rech Soins Infirm</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3917/rsi.112.0014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23671983</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Eicher M, Delmas P, Cohen C, Baeriswyl C, Python NV. The French version of Symptom Management Theory and its application. Rech Soins Infirm. 2013;112(1):14–25. 10.3917/rsi.112.0014.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23671983</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>ALHosni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Qadire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omari</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symptom prevalence, severity, distress and management among patients with chronic diseases</article-title><source>BMC Nurs</source><year>2023</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>155</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12912-023-01296-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37149599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10162903</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">ALHosni F, Al Qadire M, Omari OA, et al. Symptom prevalence, severity, distress and management among patients with chronic diseases. BMC Nurs. 2023;22:155. 10.1186/s12912-023-01296-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37149599</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12912-023-01296-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10162903</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhou W, Larson JL, Veliz PT, Kitto K, Smith S. Profiles of long COVID symptoms and self-efficacy for self-management: a cross-sectional survey. Appl Nurs Res. 2025;151968. 10.1016/j.apnr.2025.151968.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.apnr.2025.151968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40744539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The development and initial validation of the memorial symptom assessment Scale-Long COVID (MSAS-LC): a promising tool for measuring long COVID</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2025</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>728</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph22050728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40427844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12110800</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Sommer SB, Dietrich MS, Barroso JV. The development and initial validation of the Memorial Symptom Assessment Scale-Long COVID (MSAS-LC): a promising tool for measuring long COVID. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2025;22:728. 10.3390/ijerph22050728.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40427844</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph22050728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12110800</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The theory, practice, and evaluation of the phenomenological method as a qualitative research procedure</article-title><source>J Phenomenol Psychol</source><year>1997</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/156916297X00103</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Giorgi A. The theory, practice, and evaluation of the phenomenological method as a qualitative research procedure. J Phenomenol Psychol. 1997;28:235–60. 10.1163/156916297X00103.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kozinets RV. Netnography 2.0. In: Handbook of qualitative research methods in marketing. Edward Elgar Publishing; 2006. 10.4337/9781847204127.00018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pine</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Welcome to the experience economy</article-title><source>Harv Bus Rev</source><year>1998</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10181589</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Pine BJ, Gilmore JH. Welcome to the experience economy. Harv Bus Rev. 1998;76:97–105.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10181589</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentile</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How to sustain the customer experience: an overview of experience components that co-create value with the customer</article-title><source>Eur Manag J</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.emj.2007.08.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Gentile C, Spiller N, Noci G. How to sustain the customer experience: An overview of experience components that co-create value with the customer. Eur Manag J. 2007;25:395–410. 10.1016/j.emj.2007.08.005.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemon</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding customer experience throughout the customer journey</article-title><source>J Mark</source><year>2016</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1509/jm.15.0420</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Lemon KN, Verhoef PC. Understanding customer experience throughout the customer journey. J Mark. 2016;80:69–96. 10.1509/jm.15.0420.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>CPXP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jason</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining patient experience</article-title><source>Patient Exp J</source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.35680/2372-0247.1004</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Wolf CPXP, Jason A. Defining patient experience. Patient Exp J. 2014;1:7–19. 10.35680/2372-0247.1004.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fioretti C, Mazzocco K, Riva S, Oliveri S, Masiero M, Pravettoni G. Research studies on patients’ illness experience using the Narrative Medicine approach: a systematic review. BMJ Open. 2016;6. 10.1136/bmjopen-2016-011220.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-011220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4947803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27417197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschman</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hedonic consumption: emerging concepts, methods and propositions</article-title><source>J Mark</source><year>1982</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/002224298204600314</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Hirschman EC, Holbrook MB. Hedonic consumption: emerging concepts, methods and propositions. J Mark. 1982;46:92–101. 10.1177/002224298204600314.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschman</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The experiential aspects of consumption: consumer fantasies, feelings, and fun</article-title><source>J Consum Res</source><year>1982</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/208906</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Holbrook MB, Hirschman EC. The experiential aspects of consumption: Consumer fantasies, feelings, and fun. J Consum Res. 1982;9:132–40. 10.1086/208906.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwager</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding customer experience</article-title><source>Harv Bus Rev</source><year>2007</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>116</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17345685</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Meyer C, Schwager A. Understanding customer experience. Harv Bus Rev. 2007;85:116.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17345685</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schmitt BH. Customer experience management: A revolutionary approach to connecting with your customers. Wiley; 2010.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemon</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parasuraman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roggeveen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsiros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Customer experience creation: determinants, dynamics and management strategies</article-title><source>J Retail</source><year>2009</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jretai.2008.11.001</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Verhoef PC, Lemon KN, Parasuraman A, Roggeveen A, Tsiros M, Schlesinger LA. Customer experience creation: determinants, dynamics and management strategies. J Retail. 2009;85:31–41. 10.1016/j.jretai.2008.11.001.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Facione</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faucett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Froelicher</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Advancing the science of symptom management</article-title><source>J Adv Nurs</source><year>2001</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2648.2001.01697.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298204</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Dodd M, Janson S, Facione N, Faucett J, Froelicher ES, Humphreys J, et al. Advancing the science of symptom management. J Adv Nurs. 2001;33:668–76. 10.1046/j.1365-2648.2001.01697.x.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298204</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2648.2001.01697.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozinets</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Valck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wojnicki</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilner</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Networked narratives: Understanding word-of-mouth marketing in online communities</article-title><source>J Mark</source><year>2010</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1509/jm.74.2.71</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Kozinets RV, De Valck K, Wojnicki AC, Wilner SJ. Networked narratives: Understanding word-of-mouth marketing in online communities. J Mark. 2010;74:71–89. 10.1509/jm.74.2.71.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kozinets R. (2019). Netnography: The essential guide to qualitative social media research.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaitán</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramírez-Correa</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and telemedicine: A netnography approach</article-title><source>Technol Forecast Soc Change</source><year>2023</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>122420</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2023.122420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36816867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9928743</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Gaitán JA, Ramírez-Correa PE. COVID-19 and telemedicine: A netnography approach. Technol Forecast Soc Change. 2023;190:122420. 10.1016/j.techfore.2023.122420.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36816867</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.techfore.2023.122420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9928743</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewster</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarrant</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fidelity or flexibility: an ethnographic study of the implementation and use of the patient activation measure</article-title><source>Patient Educ Couns</source><year>2018</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>932</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pec.2017.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29287677</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Chew S, Brewster L, Tarrant C, Martin G, Armstrong N. Fidelity or flexibility: an ethnographic study of the implementation and use of the patient activation measure. Patient Educ Couns. 2018;101:932–7. 10.1016/j.pec.2017.12.012.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29287677</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pec.2017.12.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Narrative medicine</article-title><source>Palgrave encyclopedia of the health humanities</source><year>2022</year><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="book">Charon R. Narrative medicine. In: Palgrave encyclopedia of the health humanities. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2022. pp. 1–11.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Content analysis as a tool for consumer research</article-title><source>J Consum Mark</source><year>1992</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/EUM0000000002593</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Sayre S. Content analysis as a tool for consumer research. J Consum Mark. 1992;9:15–25. 10.1108/EUM0000000002593.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapoton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werlen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regnier Denois</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol in TV series popular with teens: a content analysis of TV series in France 22 years after a restrictive law</article-title><source>Eur J Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckz163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31539037</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Chapoton B, Werlen AL, Regnier Denois V. Alcohol in TV series popular with teens: a content analysis of TV series in France 22 years after a restrictive law. Eur J Public Health. 2020;30:363–8. 10.1093/eurpub/ckz163.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31539037</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurpub/ckz163</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lune</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>Qualitative research methods for the social sciences</source><year>2017</year><edition>9</edition><publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="book">Berg BL, Lune H. Qualitative research methods for the social sciences. 9th ed. Boston: Pearson; 2017.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carson D, Gilmore A, Perry C, Gronhaug K. Qualitative Marketing Research. SAGE; 2001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garry</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of content analysis</article-title><source>Mark Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1362/146934703771910080</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Harwood TG, Garry T. An overview of content analysis. Mark Rev. 2003;3:479–98. 10.1362/146934703771910080.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaismoradi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turunen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bondas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Content analysis and thematic analysis: implications for conducting a qualitative descriptive study: Qualitative descriptive study</article-title><source>Nurs Health Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nhs.12048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480423</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Vaismoradi M, Turunen H, Bondas T. Content analysis and thematic analysis: implications for conducting a qualitative descriptive study: qualitative descriptive study. Nurs Health Sci. 2013;15:398–405. 10.1111/nhs.12048.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480423</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/nhs.12048</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loades</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatburn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higson-Sweeney</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brigden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid systematic review: the impact of social isolation and loneliness on the mental health of children and adolescents in the context of COVID-19</article-title><source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year><volume>59</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1218</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2020.05.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32504808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7267797</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Loades ME, Chatburn E, Higson-Sweeney N, Reynolds S, Shafran R, Brigden A, et al. Rapid systematic review: the impact of social isolation and loneliness on the mental health of children and adolescents in the context of COVID-19. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2020;59(11):1218–39. 10.1016/j.jaac.2020.05.009.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32504808</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaac.2020.05.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7267797</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elton-Marshall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nigatu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jankowicz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loneliness in the COVID-19 pandemic: associations with age, gender and their interaction</article-title><source>J Psychiatr Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.01.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33582608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8635289</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Wickens CM, McDonald AJ, Elton-Marshall T, Wells S, Nigatu YT, Jankowicz D, Hamilton HA. Loneliness in the COVID-19 pandemic: associations with age, gender and their interaction. J Psychiatr Res. 2021;136:103–8. 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.01.047.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33582608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.01.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8635289</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowell</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moules</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thematic analysis: striving to Meet the trustworthiness criteria</article-title><source>Int J Qual Methods</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1609406917733847</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1609406917733847</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Nowell LS, Norris JM, White DE, Moules NJ. Thematic analysis: striving to meet the trustworthiness criteria. Int J Qual Methods. 2017;16(1):1609406917733847. 10.1177/1609406917733847.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>