<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12658530</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12658530.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12658530</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12658530</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41271424</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2025-099776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2025-099776</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cardiovascular Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1683</subject><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Depression as a moderator and mediator of functional status in patients with Long COVID: a cross-sectional and longitudinal observational study from the PERCEIVE cohort in Australia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8309-5986</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Seboka</surname><given-names initials="BT">Binyam Tariku</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names initials="J">Joel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names initials="K">Kristyn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baranow</surname><given-names initials="B">Brodie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howden</surname><given-names initials="E">Erin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names initials="J">Jayashri</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names initials="QL">Quan L</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><xref rid="senior-authorship1" ref-type="author-notes">0</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H Marwick</surname><given-names initials="T">Thomas</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="senior-authorship1" ref-type="author-notes">0</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Baker Department of Cardiometabolic Health</institution>, <institution>The University of Melbourne</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Melbourne</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Victoria</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Imaging Research Laboratory</institution>, <institution>Baker Heart and Diabetes Institute</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Melbourne</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Victoria</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Menzies Institute for Medical Research</institution>, <institution>University of Tasmania</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Hobart</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Tasmania</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Baker Heart and Diabetes Institute</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Melbourne</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Victoria</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Melbourne</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Victoria</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>None declared.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Dr Quan L Huynh; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="quan.huynh@baker.edu.au">quan.huynh@baker.edu.au</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="senior-authorship1"><p>QLH and THM are joint senior authors.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">500127</issue-id><elocation-id>e099776</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-28 16:25:13.263"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2025. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title> Abstract     </title></sec><sec><title>Background</title><p>In patients with post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC), depression has been associated with symptom severity, the duration since infection and ongoing functional impairment. However, the interconnections between these factors remain inadequately understood.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>This study aimed to explore the roles of depressive symptoms in moderating and mediating the relationships between post-COVID-19 conditions and functional capacity.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The PERCEIVE study recruited 1794 participants from Victoria and Tasmania through online advertisements based on possible PASC for a cross-sectional study. Of these, 461 participated in the longitudinal study. Post-COVID-19 duration and symptoms were recorded, and depressive symptoms and functional capacity were self-reported using the 9-item Patient Health Questionnaire and the Duke Activity Status Index (DASI), respectively. The association of depression with functional capacity was explored using ordinary least squares (OLS) regression, with companion OLS models, Sobel-Goodman tests and 1000 bootstrap iterations to assess mediation. Longitudinal data were analysed to assess changes in functional capacity and depressive symptoms over time, with mediation analysis using mixed models to explore depression as a mediator.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Participants had a mean DASI score of 35 (SD 21). Fatigue (18%), shortness of breath (11%) and chest pain (6%) were common symptoms, with severe depression linked to fatigue (93%) and shortness of breath (66%). The severity of post-COVID-19 symptoms was associated with severe depression (β=6.31, 95% CI 5.42 to 7.21) and reduced functional capacity (β=−6.40, 95% CI −9.20 to –3.61), with depression mediating 36% of the association between post-COVID-19 symptom severity and functional capacity. PASC was associated with higher depression scores (β=2.06, 95% CI 1.15 to 2.97) and lower functional capacity (β=−3.99, 95% CI −6.21 to –1.77), with depression mediating 51% of the association between PASC and reduced functional capacity. The longitudinal analysis suggested that depression is associated with the relationship between PASC and changes in functional capacity over time (unstandardised estimate=−5.16, p&lt;0.001).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Depression plays a key role in exacerbating post-COVID-19 functional impairment. This observation underscores the need for targeted physical and mental health interventions to enhance long-term recovery for those with severe conditions.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Post-Acute COVID-19 Syndrome</kwd><kwd>Depression &amp; mood disorders</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Cardiac Epidemiology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Medical Research Future Fund (MRFF)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2005874</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY</title></caption><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>We used both cross-sectional and longitudinal data from the PERCEIVE cohort to examine changes in depressive symptoms and functional capacity over time.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Depressive symptoms and functional ability were assessed using well-established tools: the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) and the Duke Activity Status Index, respectively.</p></list-item><list-item><p>To mitigate symptom overlap between the long covid questionnaire and PHQ-9, we conducted a sensitivity analysis excluding the fatigue item from the PHQ-9.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The mediation analysis followed a parsimonious model, which simplifies interpretation but does not capture complex or bidirectional relationships.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The study was based on observational data without pre-COVID-19 mental health baselines, limiting causal inference and the ability to attribute depressive symptoms solely to post-acute sequelae of COVID-19.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> The post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection (PASC), commonly known as ‘Long COVID’, continue to pose significant challenges. The WHO defines PASC as the persistence or emergence of symptoms at least 3 months after infection, lasting a minimum of 2 months without any alternative explanation.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1 2</sup></xref> The symptoms are diverse, ranging from mild fatigue and cough to severe respiratory issues, which can profoundly affect individuals’ health.</p><p>As of October 2024, the WHO estimates 775 million COVID-19 cases worldwide,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> with 10–20% potentially developing PASC.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Early meta-analyses indicated that more than 70% of COVID-19 patients reported ongoing symptoms.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> A 2022 meta-analysis of over 100 studies found that nearly half of COVID-19 survivors experienced at least one unresolved symptom.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> More recent studies have shown similar figures, with prevalence rates for post-COVID-19 symptoms (ie, PASC) approximating around 40%.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> The prevalence of PASC, as reported in the reviews, was assessed at various time points, ranging from 30 days to 12 months after recovery.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> In Australia, prevalence estimates for PASC vary widely, with estimates up to 67% reported in a national data set,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> 18% in Western Australia,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> 0.17–4% in Victoria<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> and 5.7% in Melbourne.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> A projection study estimated that over 1 million Australians could have experienced PASC by September 2022, with cases expected to range from 172 530 to 872 799 by December 2024.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> These estimates suggest that a large number of individuals with COVID-19 face health challenges for months or even a year after recovery.</p><p>In particular, various studies show that long-term effects on physical capacity are a substantial concern, with reports of reduced mobility, exercise tolerance and limitations in daily activities.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> These impairments can limit social interactions, bearing consequences for individual, societal and economic health.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> In addition to physical symptoms, PASC is closely associated with mental health challenges. Depression, a common challenge among COVID-19 survivors,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> is known to contribute to chronic health conditions,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> yet its role in post-COVID-19 outcomes remains underexplored.</p><p>Understanding the relationship between depression and PASC is crucial, as it may offer insights into recovery and rehabilitation strategies. Thus, this study aimed to examine the moderation and mediation effects of depression on post-COVID-19 conditions and functional status. We hypothesised that depression may (1) exacerbate the severity of post-COVID-19 conditions, (2) hinder functional recovery and (3) mediate the relationship between post-COVID-19 symptom severity and functional capacity.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Method and material</title><p>This study used data from the PERCEIVE study (Persistent Cardiovascular Effects of COVID-19 Viral Infection). The overall aim of the PERCEIVE study is to identify individuals with impaired functional capacity and cardiac complications as a consequence of COVID-19 infection and to test exercise and medical treatments that can improve these conditions.</p><sec id="s2-1"><title>Design</title><p>This study used both cross-sectional and longitudinal data from PERCEIVE. The PERCEIVE study, which included an online survey component, was conducted in accordance with the Checklist for Reporting Results of Internet E-Surveys guidelines for online survey reporting.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Participants</title><p>Participants from Victoria and Tasmania were recruited into the PERCEIVE study through a comprehensive recruitment strategy involving both hospital records and online advertisements. Participants with PCR-confirmed COVID-19 were invited using mailing lists obtained from hospital records at Western Health, Alfred Hospital, Northern Hospital in Melbourne and the Menzies Institute of Medical Research in Hobart, Tasmania. Additionally, the study was advertised through social media platforms (including Facebook), the Baker Heart and Diabetes Institute homepage and QR codes shared at various health facilities. Additionally, participants were also able to complete the survey in person.</p><p>Recruitment materials described the study as investigating the long-term effects of COVID-19, including cardiac complications and functional impairment. Participants were informed that there is some evidence that COVID-19 infection may result in impaired functional capacity and/or increase the risk of heart disease. The study aimed to determine whether information from simple tests of the cardiorespiratory system could guide treatment to improve exercise capacity and protect patients from developing heart failure. If abnormalities were detected, the goal was to prevent progression to heart failure through medications and lifestyle changes, including exercise training.</p><p>A total of 1794 individuals with a confirmed COVID-19 infection between 2021 and 2022 completed the survey on the Research Electronic Data Capture platform, hosted locally at the Baker Heart and Diabetes Institute. Of these, 446 participants attended a clinical visit between 2021 and 2024 and 461 participants responded to follow-up requests as part of the longitudinal study in 2024. The detailed participant flow is provided in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 1</xref>.</p><p>Participants with known heart failure, valvular stenosis or mobility impairment were excluded to reduce confounding and ensure safety during exercise testing. Those with a history of myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome or who reported post-exertional malaise were advised to consult their physicians before participation. Comprehensive clinical assessments were conducted during clinical visits to differentiate post-COVID-19 sequelae from other medical conditions. </p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Functional capacity</title><p>The Duke Activity Status Index (DASI) questionnaire was used to assess functional capacity. This questionnaire consists of 12 items that evaluate activities of daily living, such as household chores, locomotion, personal hygiene, sexual function and recreation, and the score has been validated against oxygen consumption. Each item is assigned a corresponding metabolic equivalent value, representing the amount of oxygen consumed during the activity. Participants indicated whether they could perform each activity by answering ‘yes’ or ‘no’. The total score ranges from 0 to 58.2, with higher scores signifying better functional capacity.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> The reliability of the scale was 0.998.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Depression</title><p>The Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) was used to assess depressive symptoms. The PHQ-9 questions reflect the diagnostic criteria for major depressive disorder found in the DSM-5 (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th edition). The items pertain to the person’s experience in the past 2 weeks. The total score varies from 0 to 27, where higher scores reflect more severe depression. The cut-off scores used were 1–4 for minimal depression, 5–9 for mild depression, 10–14 for moderate depression, 15–19 for moderately severe depression and 20–27 for severe depression.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> The reliability of the scale was 0.887.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Overall health and well-being</title><p>The Assessment of Quality of Life-8 Dimensions (AQoL-8D) was used to measure health-related quality of life. This score assesses overall quality of life across physical and psychosocial domains, without being limited to any specific disease. It consists of eight dimensions: independent living, happiness, mental health, coping, relationships, self-worth, pain and senses. Responses are evaluated on a Likert scale, with scores reflecting the degree of impairment in each dimension.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> The total AQoL-8D score was used for analysis, with higher scores indicating better quality of life. The reliability of the AQoL-8D scale was 0.867.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Post COVID-19 conditions</title><p>Post-COVID-19 conditions were recorded, including the presence of PASC, the severity of symptoms and the duration since infection. PASC (‘Long COVID’) was defined, according to the WHO, as the presence of symptoms that persist for at least 2 months and begin typically within 3 months of a probable or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, which cannot be explained by an alternative diagnosis. Common symptoms include fatigue, shortness of breath and cognitive dysfunction. These symptoms may be new following initial recovery or may persist from the original illness, and they can fluctuate or relapse over time.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1 26</sup></xref> Post-COVID-19 symptom severity was categorised based on criteria established in a previous study by our group.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Post-COVID-19 symptoms were categorised as severe if individuals reported shortness of breath, fatigue, chest pain or palpitations. Other symptoms, such as fever, cough, sneezing, runny nose and influenza-like symptoms, were classified as mild. Individuals reporting no post-COVID-19 symptoms were categorised as having none.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Descriptive statistics were employed to summarise the baseline characteristics of participants and their post-COVID-19 conditions. One-way analysis of variance was used to test differences in functional capacity across categories, and a Pearson correlation matrix was employed to explore correlations among continuous variables. We then employed ordinary least squares regression models to investigate the roles of depression as both a mediator and moderator in the relationship between post-COVID-19 conditions and functional capacity. These models assessed how post-COVID-19 conditions, including symptom severity, PASC and duration since infection, affect functional capacity, as detailed below. The univariable associations and the adjusted direct effect of post-COVID-19 conditions and depression on functional capacity were estimated in the multivariable analysis. Bootstrapping with 1000 resamples was used to estimate CIs for the indirect effect, providing robust mediation estimates. Sobel-Goodman tests were employed to evaluate if depression mediated the relationship between post-COVID-19 conditions and functional capacity.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28 29</sup></xref> An interaction analysis was employed to assess whether depression modified the association between post-COVID-19 conditions and functional capacity, and the results were illustrated using an interaction plot. To complement the cross-sectional findings, longitudinal data were analysed to examine changes in functional capacity and depressive symptoms over time. We employed mixed-effects mediation analysis to examine the role of depression as a mediator in these changes. Additionally, we conducted a sensitivity analysis to assess the robustness of our findings by removing fatigue from the PHQ-9, given that it is a common symptom in both the DASI and PASC. We assessed the robustness of our mediation effect to unmeasured confounding using VanderWeele’s sensitivity analysis, which evaluates the correlation (ρ) between mediator and outcome errors. Robustness was classified by the ρ range at which the average causal mediation effect crosses zero: not robust (–0.1 to 0.1), weakly robust (±0.2 to 0.3), moderately robust (±0.4 to 0.6) and strongly robust (beyond ±0.7). Furthermore, subgroup analyses were performed based on demographic and clinical characteristics. The performance of the models was checked using residual plots, which are shown in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 2A,B</xref>. All statistical analyses were performed using Python and Stata (StataCorp, 2021; Stata (SE V.17); StataCorp, College Station, Texas, USA) software, and a p value&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Patient and public involvement statement</title><p>Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Patient characteristics</title><p><xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarises DASI scores stratified by participants’ baseline characteristics. More female participants (74%) participated in the study than males. Most study participants (74%) had persistent symptoms, and there were significant differences in DASI scores across all post-COVID-19 conditions. The mean DASI score was 35 (95% CI 34 to 36). There were a range of symptoms reported by patients after COVID-19 (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1A</xref>); the most frequently reported being fatigue (18%) and shortness of breath (11%). Depressive symptoms were highly prevalent (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1B</xref>), with the most reported being little energy (48%), sleep disturbances (38%) and changes in appetite (24%). Patients with symptoms of PASC had a higher prevalence of severe depression (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>). Among those with severe depression, 93% reported fatigue, 66% experienced shortness of breath, 45% had chest pain and 40% experienced palpitations.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Participant baseline characteristics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="4" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Baseline characteristics</th><th colspan="4" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">DASI score</th></tr><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th valign="bottom" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANOVA statistic</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1112</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.89</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="top" colspan="1">Education group</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;High school</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.17</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.56</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.42</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.94</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.87</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postgrad</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" colspan="1">COVID-19 symptom group</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.53</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.42</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">402</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.46</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.94</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">PASC</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" valign="top" colspan="1">Months since COVID-19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;1 month</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–3 months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.62</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–6 months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.63</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.43</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–12 months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.43</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over 12 months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.62</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Full vaccination</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.79</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.56</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.59</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.85</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="top" colspan="1">Assessment of quality of life</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No burden/low burden</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">380</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.97</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.62</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0149</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild burden</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.72</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.56</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.96</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate burden</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.74</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.84</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe burden</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.88</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Atrial fibrillation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">533</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.42</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.80</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7202</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.27</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Hyperlipidaemia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">497</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.88</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8812</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.30</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Cardiomyopathy</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">553</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.99</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.97</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0622</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.01</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Myocardial infarction</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">550</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.99</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.87</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5983</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.06</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Deep vein thrombosis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.89</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3767</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Renal disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.56</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.81</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9495</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">555</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.46</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.93</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.89</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6653</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.62</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.84</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Psychiatric disorder</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">482</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.54</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.88</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8838</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.46</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.76</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.72</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Asthma</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.90</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6751</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.71</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.74</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Chronic lung disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.01</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.91</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9324</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.01</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">522</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.55</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.24</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>ANOVA, analysis of variance; DASI, Duke Activity Status Index; PASC, post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Prevalence of post-COVID-19 symptoms ((<bold>A</bold>) influenza-like symptoms; (<bold>B</bold>) PHQ-9 depression symptoms). (<bold>A</bold>) shows the percentage of individuals reporting various symptoms after a COVID-19 infection, with the symptoms listed on the y-axis and the x-axis representing the percentage of individuals who reported each symptom. The symptoms range from common ones like fever, shortness of breath, fatigue and cough, sneeze, runny nose, to less common symptoms such as skin rash or other skin conditions and loss of appetite. Additionally, some symptoms are grouped to capture-related experiences, such as influenza-like symptoms (including sore throat, chills, muscle ache, headache and lack of energy) and insomnia (hard to fall asleep). (<bold>B</bold>) Illustrates the percentage of individuals reporting symptoms related to the PHQ-9 depression scale, with similar axes. The data shows varying levels of prevalence for these symptoms, and the exact percentages are displayed on the respective bars. PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Proportion of post-COVID-19 symptoms by depression level.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Association of depression with functional capacity</title><p>The PHQ-9 score and COVID-19 status were associated with functional capacity (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref>). The combined and interaction effects of the depression subscales are detailed in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figures 3 and 4</xref>, highlighting the strongest associations of trouble concentrating, little energy and little interest subscores with reduced functional capacity.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Correlation matrix between DASI and continuous demographic and clinical predictors. This heatmap presents the Pearson correlation coefficients among selected continuous variables: DASI score, PHQ-9 score, age, height, weight, BMI, average heart rate and average systolic blood pressure. Pearson correlation values vary between −1 and 1, with 1 indicating a perfect positive correlation, −1 a perfect negative correlation and 0 indicating no correlation. The colour gradient illustrates the strength and direction of these correlations, with warmer colours indicating stronger positive correlations and cooler colours indicating stronger negative correlations. BMI, body mass index; DASI, Duke Activity Status Index; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Severe post-COVID-19 symptoms were significantly associated with reduced functional capacity, with a large negative effect in unadjusted analyses (β=−13.93, p&lt;0.001). In contrast, mild post-COVID-19 symptoms did not show a significant association with functional capacity (β=−1.53, p=0.435) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). These severe symptoms were also strongly linked to higher depression scores (β=6.31, p&lt;0.001), indicating that individuals with more severe post-COVID-19 symptoms were more likely to experience greater depressive symptoms (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). After accounting for depression in the analysis, the effect of severe post-COVID-19 symptoms on functional capacity remained significant but with a smaller effect size (β=−6.40, p&lt;0.001) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). Depression was linked to reduced functional capacity, even after considering other factors (β=−1.19, p&lt;0.001) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). Bootstrapped analysis confirmed that post-COVID-19 symptom severity significantly associated with reduced functional capacity, partly through its relationship with depression (β=−3.98, 95% CI −4.77 to –3.19) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref>). The Sobel test further supported this result, showing that depression is significantly associated with the relationship between symptom severity and functional capacity (z=−13.01, p=0.000) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref>). However, the interaction effect analysis showed no significant interaction between depression and post-COVID-19 symptom severity on functional status (β=−0.04, p=0.826) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>), indicating that depression did not moderate the effect of symptom severity on functional status.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Univariable analysis between depression and post-COVID-19 conditions</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-COVID-19 conditions</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DASI score</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHQ9 score</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-COVID-19 symptom severity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mild symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.2826 (−6.468 to 1.903)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6318 (−0.772 to 2.036)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.377</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.9253 (−16.590 to –11.261)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3130 (5.419 to 7.207)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PASC</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No PASC</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Had PASC</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.8567 (−9.379 to –4.335)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0600 (1.150 to 2.970)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>DASI, Duke Activity Status Index; PASC, post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Mediation effects of depression between post-COVID-19 conditions and functional capacity </title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Predictors</th><th colspan="4" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">DASI score</th></tr><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association of PASC</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3: interaction</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-COVID-19 symptom severity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mild symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.5299 (−5.373 to 2.313)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.435</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.4478 (−5.362 to 2.467)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.468</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe symptoms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.4043 (−9.196 to –3.613)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.1425 (−9.783 to –2.502)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PHQ-9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.1913 (−1.405 to –0.978)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.1147 (−1.830 to –0.399)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Interaction term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0427 (−0.423 to 0.337)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.826</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bootstrapped indirect effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.9804 (−4.7689 to –3.1920)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PASC</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No PASC</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Had PASC</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.9890 (−6.205 to –1.773)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.6385 (−7.879 to –1.398)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PHQ-9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.3921 (−1.579 to –1.205)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.4685 (-1.803 to –1.133)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Interaction term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1110 (−0.293 to 0.515)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.590</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bootstrapped indirect effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.8767 (−4.1281 to –1.6252)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>DASI, Duke Activity Status Index; PASC, post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Mediating effect of depression on the relationship between post-COVID-19 symptoms and functional capacity (Path D). This diagram represents the pathway analysis of COVID-19 symptom severity, PHQ-9 score and DASI score. Arrows indicate the direction of influence, with coefficient values provided for each path. Path A shows the effect of COVID-19 symptom severity on PHQ-9 score, with coefficients for mild and moderate/severe symptoms. Path B depicts the effect of PHQ-9 score on DASI score. Path D illustrates the indirect effect of COVID-19 symptom severity on DASI score. The percentage mediated for moderate/severe symptoms is 36.48%, supported by a Sobel test statistic of −13.0185 and a p value of 0.0000. DASI, Duke Activity Status Index; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Association of PASC with functional capacity</title><p>Individuals with PASC had significantly reduced functional capacity (β=−6.86, p&lt;0.001), indicating a strong negative association between PASC and functional status (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). PASC was also significantly associated with higher depression scores (β=2.06, p&lt;0.001), suggesting that individuals with PASC are more likely to experience depressive symptoms (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). In the adjusted model (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>), both PASC (β=−3.99, p&lt;0.001) and depression (β=−1.39, p&lt;0.001) were significantly associated with reduced functional capacity. When depression was included in the model, the effect of PASC on functional capacity was reduced, suggesting that its association with depression (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref>) explains part of the effect of PASC on functional capacity. Bootstrapped analysis showed a significant relationship between PASC and functional capacity through depression (β=−2.88, 95% CI −4.13 to −1.63), accounting for 51% of the overall association. The Sobel test further confirmed that depression was significantly associated with the relationship between PASC and functional capacity (z=−13.01, p&lt;0.001). However, the interaction effect analysis showed no significant interaction between depression and PASC on functional capacity (β=0.11, 95% CI −0.29 to 0.51, p=0.590), indicating that depression did not moderate the effect of PASC on functional status (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Mediating effect of depression on the relationship between PASC and functional capacity (Path D). Pathway diagram showing the mediating effect of PHQ-9 score on the relationship between PASC and DASI score. Edge labels represent coefficients: 1.030 (PASC to PHQ-9 score), −1.392 (PHQ-9 score to DASI score) and −1.995 (PASC to DASI score). Dashed edge indicates an indirect effect of −2.877. Paths are labelled as follows: Path A (PASC → PHQ-9 score), Path B (PHQ-9 score → DASI score) and Path D (PASC → DASI score via indirect effect). Percentage mediated for having PASC is 51%. Sobel test results show a statistic of −2.767 and a p value of 0.0057. DASI, Duke Activity Status Index; PASC, post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Association between longer duration of COVID-19 infection and functional capacity</title><p>Longer durations since COVID-19 infection were significantly associated with higher levels of depression, which, in turn, were linked to reduced functional capacity. Mediation analysis revealed that depression partially mediated the negative impact of 3–6 months and 6–12 months of infection on functional capacity. Bootstrapped analysis and the Sobel test confirmed a significant relationship between the longer duration of infection and functional capacity through depression. Additionally, depression moderated the relationship between infection duration and functional capacity, as demonstrated by significant interaction effects (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental</xref>
<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material"/><xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material"/><xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">figure 5</xref>, <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental</xref>
<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material"/><xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material"/><xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>Longitudinal associations of depression</title><p>There were changes in functional capacity from baseline to follow-up (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 6</xref>), but severely depressed individuals showed negative changes in function compared with non-depressed individuals (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 7</xref>). We then examined the role of depression in the relationship between PASC and functional capacity. The results showed that depression was significantly associated with deterioration of functional capacity (unstandardised estimate=−4.18, p&lt;0.001), while PASC was significantly associated with changes in functional capacity over time (unstandardised estimate=−5.26, p&lt;0.001). When depression was included in the model, the effect of PASC on the evolution of functional capacity was reduced, with depression accounting for 44% of the overall association (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">figure 6</xref>). These findings suggest that depression partially explains the relationship between PASC and the deterioration of functional capacity.</p><fig position="float" id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Longitudinal mediating effect of depression on the relationship between PASC and functional capacity (Path D). The longitudinal pathway diagram illustrates the mediating effect of the PHQ-9 score on the relationship between PASC and the DASI score. The edge labels represent the following coefficients: 3.58 (PASC to PHQ-9 score), −1.17 (PHQ-9 score to DASI score) and −5.26 (PASC to DASI score). The dashed edge indicates an indirect effect of −4.18. The paths are labelled as: Path A (PASC → PHQ-9 score), Path B (PHQ-9 score → DASI score) and the direct effect (PASC → DASI score). Depression accounts for 44.24% of the association between PASC and reduced functional capacity. The Sobel test statistic is −4.43, with a p value of 0.000. DASI, Duke Activity Status Index; PASC, post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-6"><title>Sensitivity analysis</title><p>We explored the hypothesised relationship by removing fatigue as a component from the PHQ-9 tool, as it is also common to the DASI and PASC status. This analysis confirmed that depressive symptoms mediate the relationship between both PASC and post-COVID-19 symptom severity with functional capacity (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2 and 3</xref>). We also employed VanderWeele’s sensitivity analysis, which showed that the mediation effect remains robust at ρ=–0.5 (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 8</xref>), suggesting reasonable robustness to unmeasured confounding.</p></sec><sec id="s3-7"><title>Subgroup analysis</title><p>We conducted subgroup analyses to explore how vaccination status, education level and quality of life influenced the role of depression as a mediator in the relationship between post-COVID-19 conditions and functional capacity (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 9</xref>). The non-vaccinated group showed a marginally significant association between moderate/severe symptoms and reduced functional capacity (−21.59, p=0.054), while the vaccinated group exhibited a weaker effect (−12.06, p&lt;0.0001). Additionally, PHQ-9 scores were significantly associated with reductions in DASI scores in both groups, with coefficients of −1.29 (p=0.010) for non-vaccinated individuals and −1.22 (p&lt;0.0001) for vaccinated individuals.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The results of this study indicate that individuals with severe post-COVID-19 conditions experience higher levels of depressive symptoms, which are associated with reduced functional capacity. Previous research has shown that PASC is significantly associated with reductions in functional capacity, with symptoms like fatigue and shortness of breath contributing to long-term physical limitations.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">1213 30</xref><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Depression is known to negatively affect functional capacity,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19 27</sup></xref> and our findings align with this. However, our study expands on this by emphasising that although mood, cognitive, somatic and suicidal ideation symptoms show a significant association with functional capacity, somatic symptoms account for the largest proportion of the variance. Furthermore, somatic symptoms were associated with poorer functional recovery over time.</p><p>The role of depression in chronic medical conditions is complicated as it can be both a contributor and consequence of severe disease. Evidences have shown depression to be a risk factor and prognostic indicator,<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> increasing the likelihood of developing chronic illnesses such as cardiovascular disease, cancer, diabetes and stroke, while also worsening outcomes. Depression that results from chronic illness<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> creates a cyclical pattern in which each condition exacerbates the other. A similar view has been applied to post-COVID-19 conditions. Some studies suggest that COVID-19 can directly affect the nervous system and increase vulnerability to depression.<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40 41</sup></xref> Findings from early research reported a 25% global rise in anxiety and depression due to the pandemic.<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> In addition, individuals with more severe initial infections have been found to exhibit higher levels of depression post-recovery.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> Post-COVID-19 symptoms such as chronic fatigue, brain fog and reduced motivation have also been strongly associated with depressive symptoms,<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> making it difficult to disentangle the specific role of depression in post-COVID-19 conditions.</p><p>Our results confirm that individuals with PASC experience higher levels of depression, consistent with previous studies.<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref><xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> We further expand on this through mediation analysis, which examines how depression (the mediator) links post-COVID-19 conditions (the independent variable) to reduced functional capacity (the dependent variable). We observed that post-COVID-19 conditions are associated with lower functional capacity, both directly and indirectly through depressive symptoms. These patterns were consistent in both cross-sectional and longitudinal analyses. Given these findings, we believe that addressing depression could not only help alleviate mental health challenges but also support physical recovery, offering a more holistic approach to care for individuals with post-COVID-19 conditions.</p><p>To further explore the overlap of symptoms between depression, PASC and functional capacity, a sensitivity analysis was conducted to examine the hypothesised relationship by removing fatigue as a component of depression. Although further replication is needed, the depressive symptoms other than fatigue continue to mediate the relationship between PASC and functional capacity. These findings align with previous literature suggesting that depression plays a key mediating role in chronic illness and functional impairment.<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref></p><p>A notable finding from our subgroup analysis is the greater magnitude of functional impairment seen in unvaccinated individuals. This aligns with prior research demonstrating that vaccination can reduce the risk of severe functional limitations following post-COVID-19 conditions.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7 47</sup></xref> Our results highlight the protective effect of vaccination against functional decline, reinforcing the critical need for continued vaccination efforts, especially among vulnerable groups who are more susceptible to severe PASC-related disabilities.</p><p>A major strength of this study was the use of both cross-sectional and longitudinal data from the PERCEIVE cohort, which allowed for a thorough examination of temporal changes. We also used validated tools to measure depressive symptoms (PHQ-9) and functional capacity (DASI). This is one of the first studies to explore the roles of depressive symptoms in moderating and mediating the relationships between post-COVID-19 conditions and functional capacity in patients with PASC. Looking ahead, further research is needed to explore additional factors that mediate or moderate the relationship between post-COVID-19 conditions and functional capacity. For example, social support, physical rehabilitation and coping strategies may influence recovery dynamics and should be investigated to provide a more comprehensive understanding of the recovery process. This will enable the development of tailored interventions that address the complex interplay between physical and mental health in PASC populations.</p><p>Nevertheless, several limitations in our study should be acknowledged. The study used observational data and is, therefore, unable to determine causality or to disentangle the potential bidirectional relationships between PASC, depressive symptoms and functional capacity. Additionally, the absence of pre-COVID-19 baseline mental health data, which prevents definitive attribution of depressive symptoms solely to PASC. Another limitation is potential recruitment bias, as participation relied partly on self-selection through online advertisements and mailing lists, likely including only individuals who were motivated to participate. Further, the mediation model was based on the parsimonious model, which eliminates multiple and bidirectional links to facilitate data interpretation. It is also important to interpret our findings with caution, as there is potential symptom overlap between depression and PASC. Our sensitivity analysis, which excluded the fatigue item from the PHQ-9, yielded consistent results; however, the possibility of residual confounding remains.</p><sec id="s4-1"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Individuals experiencing severe post-COVID-19 symptoms have markedly higher levels of depression, which may contribute to reduced functional capacity. The findings emphasise the need for integrated or comprehensive interventions that address both the physical and mental health in the recovery process following COVID-19, particularly for individuals with severe symptoms or prolonged symptoms.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2025-099776</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-11-s001.docx" id="d67e1522" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We wish to acknowledge the support of the PERCIVE study (Persistent Cardiovascular Effects of COVID-19 Viral Infection), of which this research is a part. Funding for this project was awarded in January 2021 to the value of $A2.5 million by the Medical Research Future Fund (MRFF) under Grant number 2005874, as part of the MRFF 2020 Rare Cancers Rare Diseases Unmet Need COVID-19 Grant Opportunity. We also wish to thank the participants of the study for their invaluable contribution to this research.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This research is part of the PERCEIVE study, which was funded in January 2021 with a grant of $A2.5 million from the Medical Research Future Fund (MRFF) under Grant number 2005874, as part of the MRFF 2020 Rare Cancers Rare Diseases Unmet Need COVID-19 Grant Opportunity. BTS is supported by a Melbourne Research Scholarship, a Rowden White Scholarship, and the Baker Bright Spark Top-Up Scholarship.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Prepub:</bold> Prepublication history and additional supplemental material for this paper are available online. To view these files, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2025-099776" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2025-099776</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> The Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee (72455) and the University of Tasmania Human Research Ethics Committee (27543) approved the study. Participants gave informed consent to participate in the study before taking part.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> We are committed to sharing de-identified individual participant data underlying the results of this study, including data in text, tables, figures and appendices. Researchers with methodologically sound proposals, including individual participant data meta-analysis, may contact tom.marwick@baker.edu.au to request access. Data will be made available immediately following publication, with no end date, upon signing a data access agreement. Additional materials, such as the study protocol and analytic code, are also available upon request. For more details, visit our Data Sharing page (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://baker.edu.au/research/laboratories/imaging-research/data-sharing" ext-link-type="uri">https://baker.edu.au/research/laboratories/imaging-research/data-sharing</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>e102</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>WHO Regional Office for Europe</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Post COVID-19 condition (long COVID)</article-title><year>2023</year><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-COVID-19-condition" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-COVID-19-condition</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>11-Aug-2024</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization(WHO)</collab>
</person-group><article-title>WHO COVID-19 dashboard</article-title><year>2024</year><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int" ext-link-type="uri">https://covid19.who.int</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>27-Sep-2024</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nasserie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hittle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Assessment of the Frequency and Variety of Persistent Symptoms Among Patients With COVID-19: A Systematic Review</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e2111417</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.11417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34037731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8155823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>O’Mahoney</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Routen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The prevalence and long-term health effects of Long Covid among hospitalised and non-hospitalised populations: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2023</year><volume>55</volume><elocation-id>101762</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36474804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9714474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sk Abd Razak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul Aziz</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Post-COVID syndrome prevalence: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>1785</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-19264-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38965510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11223303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pryor</surname><given-names>AJG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Melville</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The lingering symptoms of post-COVID-19 condition (long-COVID): a prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Intern Med J</source><year>2024</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imj.16251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38008902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Woldegiorgis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cadby</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ngeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID in a highly vaccinated but largely unexposed Australian population following the 2022 SARS-CoV-2 Omicron wave: a cross-sectional survey</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2024</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/mja2.52256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38508863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Szanyi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Epidemiologic and economic modelling of optimal COVID-19 policy: public health and social measures, masks and vaccines in Victoria, Australia</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health West Pac</source><year>2023</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>100675</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2022.100675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36694478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9851841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fineberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marceau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Alfred Health post-COVID-19 service, Melbourne, 2020-2022: an observational cohort study</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2024</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/mja2.52192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38130117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grafton</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kompas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The public health and economic burden of long COVID in Australia, 2022-24: a modelling study</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2024</year><volume>221</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/mja2.52400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39154292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Battistella</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Pretto</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long-term functioning status of COVID-19 survivors: a prospective observational evaluation of a cohort of patients surviving hospitalisation</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e057246</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-057246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9334693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35896292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long-Term Functional Limitations and Predictors of Recovery After COVID-19: A Multicenter Prospective Cohort Study</article-title><source>Am J Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>990</fpage><lpage>1000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2024.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38878946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Johani</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Mohaimeed</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 fatigue and health-related quality of life in Saudi Arabia: a population-based study</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1254723</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1254723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37869192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10585179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long COVID and Significant Activity Limitation Among Adults, by Age - United States, June 1-13, 2022, to June 7-19, 2023</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7232a3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37561665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10415000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Angeles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dinh</surname><given-names>TTN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The economic burden of long COVID in Australia: more noise than signal?</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2024</year><volume>221 Suppl 9</volume><fpage>S31</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/mja2.52468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39489519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taube</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Depression and brain fog as long-COVID mental health consequences: Difficult, complex and partially successful treatment of a 72-year-old patient-A case report</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1153512</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1153512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37032935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10079873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taquet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geddes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>6-month neurological and psychiatric outcomes in 236 379 survivors of COVID-19: a retrospective cohort study using electronic health records</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatry</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(21)00084-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33836148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8023694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Orban</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Persistent neurologic symptoms and cognitive dysfunction in non-hospitalized Covid-19 “long haulers”</article-title><source>Ann Clin Transl Neurol</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acn3.51350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33755344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8108421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Palladini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poletti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 Depressive Symptoms: Epidemiology, Pathophysiology, and Pharmacological Treatment</article-title><source>CNS Drugs</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40263-022-00931-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35727534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9210800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Depression and cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>Curr Opin Lipidol</source><year>2021</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOL.0000000000000749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33859128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eysenbach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Improving the quality of Web surveys: the Checklist for Reporting Results of Internet E-Surveys (CHERRIES)</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e34</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.6.3.e34</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15471760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1550605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hlatky</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boineau</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Higginbotham</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A brief self-administered questionnaire to determine functional capacity (the Duke Activity Status Index)</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>1989</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9149(89)90496-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2782256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kroenke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1525-1497.2001.016009606.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1495268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Iezzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Validity and reliability of the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL)-8D multi-attribute utility instrument</article-title><source>Patient</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40271-013-0036-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24271592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3929769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Characterizing long COVID in an international cohort: 7 months of symptoms and their impact</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2021</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>101019</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34308300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wexler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Associations between symptoms and functional capacity in patients after COVID-19 infection and community controls</article-title><source>Intern Med J</source><year>2023</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1540</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imj.16185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37490523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10947235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sobel</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Asymptotic Confidence Intervals for Indirect Effects in Structural Equation Models</article-title><source>Sociol Methodol</source><year>1982</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>290</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/270723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>On the Exact Variance of Products</article-title><source>J Am Stat Assoc</source><year>1960</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01621459.1960.10483369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Siles</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of Long COVID patients presenting to a dedicated academic post-COVID-19 clinic in Central Texas</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>21971</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-48502-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38081885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10713530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brus</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spronk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haagsma</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The prolonged impact of COVID-19 on symptoms, health-related quality of life, fatigue and mental well-being: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Front Epidemiol</italic>
</source><year>2023</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>1144707</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fepid.2023.1144707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38455946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10911032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A one-year follow-up study of systematic impact of long COVID symptoms among patients post SARS-CoV-2 omicron variants infection in Shanghai, China</article-title><source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>2220578</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2023.2220578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37272336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10281439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ceban</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>LMW</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Fatigue and cognitive impairment in Post-COVID-19 Syndrome: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Brain Behav Immun</source><year>2022</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2021.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34973396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8715665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pookarnjanamorakot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Impact of fatigue as the primary determinant of functional limitations among patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome: a cross-sectional observational study</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e069217</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-069217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10335413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37286327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wulf Hanson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abbafati</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aerts</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Estimated Global Proportions of Individuals With Persistent Fatigue, Cognitive, and Respiratory Symptom Clusters Following Symptomatic COVID-19 in 2020 and 2021</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2022</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.18931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36215063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9552043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Commodore-Mensah</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Psychological Health, Well-Being, and the Mind-Heart-Body Connection: A Scientific Statement From the American Heart Association</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2021</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>e763</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33486973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Voinov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Richie</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Depression and chronic diseases: it is time for a synergistic mental health and primary care approach</article-title><source>Prim Care Companion CNS Disord</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>PCC.12r01468</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/PCC.12r01468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23930236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3733529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Depression, anxiety and their relationship with chronic diseases: a review of the epidemiology, risk and treatment evidence</article-title><source>Medical Journal of Australia</source><year>2009</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>S54</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/j.1326-5377.2009.tb02471.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19351294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>M-Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H-X</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Influence of chronic diseases on the occurrence of depression: A 13-year follow-up study from the Survey of Health, Ageing and Retirement in Europe</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>326</volume><fpage>115268</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2023.115268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37270866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Depression and Anxiety During the COVID-19 Pandemic: Epidemiology, Mechanism, and Treatment</article-title><source>Neurosci Bull</source><year>2023</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12264-022-00970-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36411394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9685018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ayari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Madry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Relationship Between COVID-19 and the Development of Depression: Implications on Mental Health</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Insights</italic>
</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>26331055231191513</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/26331055231191513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37608908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10441207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Organization(WHO), W.H</collab>
</person-group><article-title>COVID-19 pandemic triggers 25% increase in prevalence of anxiety and depression worldwide</article-title><year>2022</year><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news/item/02-03-2022-covid-19-pandemic-triggers-25-increase-in-prevalence-of-anxiety-and-depression-worldwide" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news/item/02-03-2022-covid-19-pandemic-triggers-25-increase-in-prevalence-of-anxiety-and-depression-worldwide</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9998057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35414629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Adingupu</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soroush</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Brain hypoxia, neurocognitive impairment, and quality of life in people post-COVID-19</article-title><source>J Neurol</source><year>2023</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>3303</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-023-11767-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37210689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10200033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Almeria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cejudo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Neurocognitive and Neuropsychiatric Sequelae in Long COVID-19 Infection</article-title><source>Brain Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>604</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/brainsci14060604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38928604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11202095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Almeria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cejudo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long Neurocognitive and Neuropsychiatric Sequelae in Participants with Post-COVID-19 Infection: A Longitudinal Study</article-title><source>Neurol Int</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/neurolint16040064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39195566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11357167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Azizi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Achak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Post-COVID-19 mental health and its associated factors at 3-months after discharge: A case-control study</article-title><source>Clin Epidemiol Glob Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>101141</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cegh.2022.101141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36119409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9465475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bota</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Razvan</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A Three-Year Cross-Sectional Analysis of Depression, Anxiety, and Quality of Life in Patients with Post-COVID-19 Syndrome</article-title><source>Int J Gen Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJGM.S453247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38476627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10929241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Teopiz</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Presence of Depression Is Associated with Functional Impairment in Middle-Aged and Elderly Chinese Adults with Vascular Disease/Diabetes Mellitus—A Cross-Sectional Study</article-title><source>IJERPH</source><year>2023</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1602</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph20021602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36674357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9864745</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data are available upon reasonable request.</p></sec></back><sub-article id="sub-article1" article-type="aggregated-review-documents"><front-stub><title-group><article-title>Review Process File</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date></front-stub><body><fig id="d67e2756" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2025-099776.reviewer_comments.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig></body></sub-article></article></pmc-articleset>