<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">52</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcopht</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2415</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12911088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12911088.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12911088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12911088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41580699</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12886-025-04575-x</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4575</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long-term retinal dysfunction following COVID-19 infection: a one-year prospective observational study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mou</surname><given-names initials="K">Kefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuzhu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yifan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names initials="S">Shulei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="H">Hanyue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="M">Ming</given-names></name><address><email>mingzhangscu@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/011ashp19</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13291.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0807 1581</institution-id><institution>Department of Ophthalmology, West China Hospital, </institution><institution>Sichuan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chengdu, Sichuan 610041 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503765</issue-id><elocation-id>96</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-18 10:25:12.893"><day>18</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12886_2025_Article_4575.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="structured"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">COVID-19, caused by SARS-CoV-2, may lead to long-term retinal changes. Visual symptoms and retinal alterations have been reported in Long COVID; however, the available evidence remains limited. Swept-source OCT (SS-OCT) and OCT angiography (SS-OCTA) enable non-invasive evaluation of retinal structure and microvasculature. This study aimed to assess retinal alterations before and one year after COVID-19 using SS-OCT and SS-OCTA in a longitudinal design.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This prospective longitudinal study was conducted at West China Hospital, Sichuan University. All enrolled participants underwent SS-OCT and SS-OCTA before infection, and at 1 month, and 1 year after severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection. Retinal structural and microvascular alterations were quantified using the Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) grid, including the thickness of peripheral retinal nerve fiber layer (pRNFL), ganglion cell inner plexiform layer (GCIPL), inner nuclear layer (INL) and outer retina, and the vessel density (VD) of superficial vascular plexus (SVP), intermediate capillary plexus (ICP) and deep capillary plexus (DCP). The foveal avascular zone (FAZ) area was measured in the inner retinal layer.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 44 eyes from 22 participants were analyzed (mean age: 30.59 ± 9.36 years; 17 females and 5 males). Significant reduction in thickness of pRNFL, GCIPL, and outer retina, increased thickness of INL, decreased VD of SVP, and increased VD of ICP and DCP were observed in participants one month after COVID-19 infection (All <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), which remained persistently altered one year after COVID-19 infection (All <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">These findings indicate long-term retinal dysfunction following COVID-19 infection, highlighting the importance of ongoing ophthalmic monitoring. Non-invasive SS-OCT and SS-OCTA could offer valuable tools for detecting and managing retinal alterations associated with long COVID in the post-pandemic era.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Retinal dysfunction</kwd><kwd>SS-OCT and SS-OCTA</kwd><kwd>Retinal thickness</kwd><kwd>Vessel density</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>1·3·5 project for disciplines of excellence–Clinical Research Fund, West China Hospital, Sichuan University</institution></funding-source><award-id>2023HXFH043</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Ming</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection, primarily affects the respiratory system, posing unprecedented challenges to healthcare systems worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Increasing evidence indicates that COVID-19 may lead to multi-organ complications, including significant ocular and retinal manifestations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The long-term sequelae of COVID-19, also known as “Long COVID”, brings an increasing burden on global health over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Various organ-related symptoms have been reported among individuals experiencing Long COVID, affecting the cardiovascular, respiratory, neurological, and visual systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. </p><p id="Par6">Given the unique capability of the retinal structures to visualize structures and microvasculature directly, ocular manifestations have attracted considerable attention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Ocular symptoms, such as dry eye disease, visual disturbances, convergence insufficiency, neuro-visual deficits, retinal vascular occlusion, uveitis and eye movement dysfunctions, are reported in individuals with Long COVID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Additionally, cognitive impairment associated with Long COVID has been shown to contribute to reduced visual function indirectly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. </p><p id="Par7">Optical coherence tomography (OCT) and angiography (OCTA) have been utilized to evaluate the potential impact of COVID-19 on the visual system, especially the retina and optic nerve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Previous studies have indicated that irreversible retinal alterations may occur following COVID-19 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. For instance, Schlick et al. reported sustained reductions in retinal microvasculature among post-COVID-19 individuals, especially those with chronic fatigue, suggesting a persistent retinal microvascular dysfunction. Significant changes in retinal thickness and vascular density, detected by swept-source OCT (SS-OCT) and OCTA (SS-OCTA), were also reported three months after COVID-19 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Notably, Cennamo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] reported a significant reduction in retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL) thickness and vessel density (VD) in both the superficial capillary plexus (SCP) and deep capillary plexus (DCP) in participants six months after COVID-19 infection compared with healthy controls. However, no significant differences were observed in the thickness of the ganglion cell complex (GCC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. This inconsistency may be attributed to the differences in imaging devices, follow-up duration, and the lack of self-comparative longitudinal analyses.</p><p id="Par8">Currently, the long-term implications of COVID-19 on retinal structure and future ocular health require further investigation. Hence, this study aimed to assess the retinal alterations in participants before and after COVID-19 using SS-OCT and SS-OCTA and to detect the potential associations between the alterations in retinal structure and microvasculature.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par9">This prospective longitudinal study recruited hospital staff and medical students at West China Hospital, Sichuan University, from January 2022 to January 2024. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee on Biomedical Research, West China Hospital of Sichuan University, China, and conducted according to the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p><p id="Par10">All participants were originally recruited as healthy controls and had comprehensive documented normal ophthalmic examinations and SS-OCT/SS-OCTA imaging at our hospital prior to COVID-19 with complete records available; anyone with retinal/ocular disease was excluded. All participants had confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, verified by nasopharyngeal swab reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) testing. The exclusion criteria included a prior history of (1) ocular conditions, such as glaucoma, pathological myopia, and macular disease; (2) systemic conditions, such as diabetes mellitus and hypertension; (3) neurological disorders, such as multiple sclerosis; (4) ocular surgery or ocular trauma, with the exception of cataract extraction and intraocular lens implantation.</p><p id="Par11">All participants underwent ophthalmic evaluations, including slit-lamp biomicroscopy, best-corrected visual acuity (BCVA), intraocular pressure (IOP), axial length, SS-OCT, and SS-OCTA, before COVID-19 infection. Baseline information, including age, sex, and body mass index, were recorded. Follow-up evaluations, including slit-lamp biomicroscopy, SS-OCT, and SS-OCTA, were performed one month and one year following the onset of the initial COVID-19-related symptom. Detailed clinical data, including systemic symptoms over the follow-up period and the frequency of subsequent COVID-19 infections, were collected and analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>SS-OCT and SS-OCTA</title><p id="Par12">SS-OCT and SS-OCTA images were captured using the SS-OCT device (VG200; SVision Imaging), with a tunable laser at a central wavelength of 1050 nm, a scanning speed of 200,000 A-scans/s, a tissue penetration depth of 6 mm, and an axial digital resolution of 1.8 μm. All SS-OCT and SS-OCTA images were automatically segmented and quantified. An experienced ophthalmologist conducted all imaging procedures and was fully masked to clinical status and time point. The scanning modes included 3 mm × 3 mm and 6 mm × 6 mm centered on the macula, as well as 6 mm × 6 mm centered on the optic nerve head (ONH). Images with a signal strength index greater than 8/10 were included.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Outcome measurements</title><p id="Par13">The primary aim was to assess alterations in retinal structure and microvasculature at one month and one year post-COVID-19 infection, including the thickness of the peripapillary RNFL (pRNFL), the ganglion cell inner plexiform layer (GCIPL), the inner nuclear layer (INL) and the outer retina and the VD of the superficial vascular plexus (SVP), intermediate capillary plexus (ICP) and DCP. Additionally, the circular index (CI) and VD of foveal avascular zone (FAZ) area on the inner retinal layer were measured within a 3 mm × 3 mm macular region. Relationships between retinal structural and microvascular alterations were also explored. All SS-OCT and SS-OCTA parameters were quantified automatically, and vitreous status was independently assessed by two ophthalmologists (M.K and G.Y).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par14">Continuous variables were presented as means (standard deviations), and categorical variables as frequency distributions; baseline characteristics were compared using the χ² test. A generalized estimating equation (GEE) model, adjusted for inter-eye dependency, age, gender, body mass index (BMI), and symptoms, was applied to evaluate longitudinal changes in SS-OCT and SS-OCTA parameters across follow-up visits. Pearson correlation analysis was used to examine associations between the rates of change in SS-OCT and SS-OCTA parameters over the one-year period. A two-tailed P-value &lt; 0.05 after correction was considered statistically significant. To account for multiple comparisons, Bonferroni correction was applied by dividing the significance threshold by the number of tested parameters. All statistical analyses were performed using IBM SPSS Statistics version 29.0 (SPSS Inc.), and figures were generated using R software (version 4.1.2). Post-hoc power calculation was performed using the online tool (Kane SP. Post. ClinCalc: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clincalc.com/stats/power.aspx">https://clincalc.com/stats/power.aspx</ext-link>. Updated June 23, 2024. Accessed December 1, 2025.) for primary SS-OCT and SS-OCTA parameters to clarify detectable effect sizes at the current sample size.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par15">A total of 44 eyes of 22 participants were enrolled in this study at baseline (mean age: 30.59 ± 9.36 years; 17 females and 5 males). No participant had pre-existing retinal or ocular disease, as confirmed by prior normal ophthalmic evaluations and imaging. The demographics and clinical characteristics of the participants are summarized in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. During the one-year follow-up period, 14 participants (63.64%) experienced a single COVID-19 infection, 7 participants (31.82%) experienced two infections, and 1 participant (4.54%) experienced three infections. Ocular symptoms were reported in 2 participants (9.01%), described as dry eye (1 participant, 4.53%) and ocular pain (1 participant, 4.53%). Common respiratory symptoms were noted in 18 participants (81.82%), including fever (17 participants, 77.27%) and itchy throat (16 participants, 72.73%). Neurological symptoms were reported in 9 participants (40.91%), including headache (6 participants, 27.27%) and anosmia (4 participants, 18.18%). Additional symptom details are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. All participants had fully recovered from COVID-19 infection at the one-year follow-up, as confirmed by negative oropharyngeal swab results. Besides, post hoc power estimates for all primary outcomes exceeded 80%.</p><p id="Par16">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of patients(eyes)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (44)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female (male)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, mean (SD, range)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.59 (9.36, 24–60)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI, mean (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.44 (2.84)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BCVA, mean (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IOP, mean (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.56 (1.35)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AL, mean (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.39 (1.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Times of infection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41 (0.59)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (63.64%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (31.82%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (4.55%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (9.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–7 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (72.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Over 7 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (18.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ocular symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (9.01%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cold symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (81.82%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Respiratory symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (4.55%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Circulatory symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (4.55%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urinary symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Digestive System symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (4.55%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neurological symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (40.91%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Endocrine symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (9.01%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychological symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (4.55%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>BMI, body mass index; BCVA, best-corrected visual acuity (Snellen chart); COVID‐19, coronavirus disease 2019; IOP, intraocular pressure; AL, axial length</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>SS-OCT findings</title><p id="Par17">SS-OCT results were shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). A significant reduction in the thickness of the pRNFL was observed in both the 0–2 mm and 0–4 mm rings at 1-month and 1-year follow-ups compared with baseline (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). However, no significant differences were shown in the 2–4 mm ring. (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.493; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.320, respectively). Similarly, the GCIPL thickness significantly decreased across all regions (0–1 mm, 1–3 mm, 3–6 mm, and 0–6 mm rings) at both follow-up visits compared with baseline (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). However, the thickness of the INL significantly increased within the 0–1 mm, 3–6 mm, and 0–6 mm rings at the 1-month and 1-year visits compared with baseline (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) but showed no significant difference in the 1–3 mm ring (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.651; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.389, respectively). Significant thinning of the outer retina was only detected in the 0–1 mm ring at both 1-month (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and 1-year (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010) follow-ups compared with baseline. Overall, no significant changes in any SS-OCT parameters were noted when comparing the 1-month follow-up with the 1-year follow-up (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><p id="Par18">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Swept - source optical coherence tomography findings in pre -, 1 - month and 1 year post - COVID-19 patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SS-OCT parameters</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Pre <sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1-month <sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1-year <sup>c</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pre vs.1-month</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pre vs.1-year</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1-mon vs. 1-year</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pRNFL(µm)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">480 (16.26)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">439.48 (16.26)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">430.72 (16.26)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.334</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–4</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131.62 (5.06)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129.3 (5.06)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128.25 (5.06)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.596</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.493</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.320</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.758</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–4</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">218.16 (7.31)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">206.35 (7.31)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">203.38 (7.31)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004 <sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.471</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GCILP(µm)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.3 (2.08)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.01 (2.08)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.1 (2.08)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.875</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.04 (1.49)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.85 (1.49)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.88 (1.49)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.931</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.32 (1.34)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.83 (1.34)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.82 (1.34)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.980</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.11 (1.27)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.70 (1.27)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.69 (1.27)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.979</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">INL(µm)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.85 (0.60)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.14 (0.60)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.09 (0.60)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.890</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.75 (0.43)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.68 (0.43)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.61 (0.43)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.690</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.651</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.389</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.682</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.44 (0.33)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.33 (0.33)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.24 (0.33)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.667</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.56 (0.32)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.25 (0.32)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.16 (0.32)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.631</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outer retina(µm)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">187.59 (2.00)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">184.64 (2.00)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185.66 (2.00)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.176</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">172.16 (1.55)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">171.97 (1.55)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">172.47 (1.55)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.624</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.708</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.556</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.336</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148.63 (1.48)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148.26 (1.48)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148.63 (1.48)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.611</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.391</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.998</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.389</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154.99 (1.44)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154.61 (1.44)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155.01 (1.44)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.577</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.376</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.966</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.353</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019; SS‐OCT, swept‐source optical coherence tomography; pRNFL, peripheral retinal nerve fiber layers; GCIPL, ganglion cell‐inner plexus layer; INL, inner nuclear layer</p><p>P-values from χ² tests (categorical) and GEE models (continuous), with Bonferroni correction applied</p><p><sup>a</sup> Pre, pre-COVID-19</p><p><sup>b</sup> 1- month, one-month post-COVID-19</p><p><sup>c</sup> 1- year, one-year post-COVID-19</p><p><sup>*</sup>Statistically significant below <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0167 (Bonferroni)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par19">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Swept-source optical coherence tomography (SS-OCT) images of the ganglion cell inner plexiform layer (GCIPL) of a patient pre-, 1 month, and 1 year after COVID-19. (<bold>A</bold>), (<bold>D</bold>), (<bold>G</bold>) SS-OCT images show the thickness of the GCIPL measured with the Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) grid in pre-, 1 month, and 1 year after COVID-19 status. (<bold>B</bold>), (<bold>E</bold>), (<bold>H</bold>), Heat map of the thickness of the GCIPL in pre-, 1 month, and 1 year after COVID-19 status. (<bold>C</bold>), (<bold>F</bold>), (<bold>I</bold>), The B-scan of the macula in pre-, 1 month, and 1 year after COVID-19 status. The automatically segmented GCIPL was marked between the blue lines</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e965" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12886_2025_4575_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par20">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Line chart of swept-source optical coherence tomography (SS-OCT) parameters during the 1-year follow-up. Thickness changes of the ganglion cell inner plexiform layer (GCIPL) (<bold>A</bold>), inner nuclear layer (INL) (<bold>B</bold>), outer retina (<bold>C</bold>), and peripheral retinal nerve fiber layer (pRNFL) (<bold>D</bold>) are shown at different time points: before infection,1-month post-infection, and 1-year post-infection. Different colors represent different areas of the detected rings: 0–1 mm(red), 1–3 mm(blue), 3–6 mm(yellow), 0–6 mm(green). Or 0–2 mm(red), 2–4 mm(blue), 0–4 mm(yellow). Asterisk (*** <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, ** <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) indicates retinal layers with statistically significant thickness changes according to the GEE analysis</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e995" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12886_2025_4575_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>SS-OCTA findings</title><p id="Par21">SS-OCTA results were shown in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. The VD of SVP in the 0–1 and 1–3 mm ring was significantly decreased at the 1-month follow-up (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.011; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.015, respectively), and the decrease remained at 1-year follow-up in the 1–3 mm ring (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010); however, VD in the 0–1 mm ring recovered by the 1-year follow-up (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.073). The VD of ICP and DCP were significantly increased during follow-up (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), except in the 0–1 mm ring of ICP, where no significant difference was noted during both follow-ups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.288; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.487, respectively). As for the FAZ, no significant difference was found during the follow-ups when considering the area (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.987; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.616, respectively) or the perimeter (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.245; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.872, respectively). The CI of the FAZ showed no significant difference at the follow-ups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.080, respectively) with Bonferroni correction applied. In contrast, the VD of FAZ demonstrated a significant reduction across follow-ups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.009, respectively).</p><p id="Par22">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Swept - source optical coherence tomography angiography findings in pre -, 1 month and 1 year post - COVID-19 patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SS-OCTA parameters</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Pre <sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1-month <sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1-year <sup>c</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pre vs.1-month</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pre vs.1-year</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1-mon vs. 1-year</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SVP (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.99 (0.98)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.91 (0.98)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.23 (0.98)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.032<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.011<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.073</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.450</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.09 (0.81)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.76 (0.81)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.68 (0.81)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.015<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.015<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.891</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.87 (0.59)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.81 (0.59)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.57 (0.59)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.761</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.899</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.488</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.570</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.76 (0.57)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.39 (0.57)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.2 (0.57)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.410</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.387</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.189</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.654</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ICP (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.98 (1.25)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.68 (1.25)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.44 (1.25)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.559</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.288</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.487</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.714</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.96 (0.61)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.79 (0.61)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.19 (0.61)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.315</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.31 (0.72)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.01 (0.72)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.46 (0.72)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.443</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.32 (0.61)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.93 (0.61)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.37 (0.61)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.383</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DCP (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.71 (0.52)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.98 (0.52)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.80 (0.52)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.576</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.25 (0.86)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.07 (0.86)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.14 (0.86)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.095</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.27 (0.78)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.63 (0.78)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.38 (0.78)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.88 (0.74)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.96 (0.74)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.81 (0.74)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.064</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FAZ</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Area(mm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32 (0.02)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32 (0.02)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31 (0.02)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.850</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.987</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.616</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.628</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Perim(mm)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.25 (0.08)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.31 (0.08)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.26 (0.08)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.453</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.245</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.872</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.317</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CI</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76 (0.01)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73 (0.01)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74 (0.01)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.061</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.024</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.080</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.614</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VD</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.13 (0.64)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.93 (0.64)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.49 (0.64)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.363</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019; SS-OCTA, swept‐source optical coherence tomography angiography; SVP, superficial vascular plexus; ICP, intermediate capillary plexus; DCP, deep capillary plexus; FAZ, foveal avascular zone; CI, circularity index; VD, vessel density</p><p>P-values from χ² tests (categorical) and GEE models (continuous), with Bonferroni correction applied</p><p><sup>a</sup> Pre, pre-COVID-19</p><p><sup>b</sup> 1- month, one-month post-COVID-19</p><p><sup>c</sup> 1- year, one-year post-COVID-19</p><p><sup>*</sup>Statistically significant below <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0167 (Bonferroni)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par23">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Swept-source optical coherence tomography angiography (SS-OCTA) images of the superficial vascular plexus (SVP) of a patient pre-, 1 month, and 1 year after COVID-19. (<bold>A</bold>), (<bold>D</bold>), (<bold>G</bold>) SS-OCTA images show the pre-, 1-month, and 1-year after COVID-19 status. (<bold>B</bold>), (<bold>E</bold>), (<bold>H</bold>), Heat map of vessel density of the SVP measured with the Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) grid in pre-, 1-month, and 1-year after COVID-19 status. (<bold>C</bold>), (<bold>F</bold>), (<bold>I</bold>), The B-scan of the macula in pre-, 1-month, and 1-year after COVID-19 status. The automatically segmented SVP was marked between the blue lines</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1534" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12886_2025_4575_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Correlation analysis</title><p id="Par24">Correlation analyses were conducted to evaluate associations between the rates of change in SS-OCT and SS-OCTA parameters at the 1-month and 1-year follow-ups (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Significant positive correlations were identified between the rate of change in the VD of SVP and GCIPL thickness within the 0–1 mm and 3–6 mm rings at the 1-year follow-up (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.664, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.383, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010, respectively) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). No significant correlations were found between the GCIPL thickness and the VD of ICP and between the INL thickness and the VD in ICP or DCP (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Correlations between SSOCT and SSOCTA parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Change rates</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1-month</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1-year</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T-GCIPL and VD-SVP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.585</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.664</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.027</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.863</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.097</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.530</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.373</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.383</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.266</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.081</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.272</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.074</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T-GCIPL and VD-ICP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.905</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.080</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.607</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.174</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.257</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.181</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.240</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.090</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.563</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.031</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.841</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.108</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.484</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.067</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.664</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T-INL and VD-ICP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.183</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.234</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.122</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.432</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.014</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.930</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.015</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.924</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.080</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.605</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.144</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.350</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.025</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.873</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.096</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.536</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T-INL and VD-DCP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.206</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.202</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.308</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.053</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.021</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.890</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.053</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.733</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.128</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.408</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.203</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.187</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.060</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.697</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.102</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.511</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SS-OCT, swept‐source optical coherence tomography; SS‐OCTA, swept‐source optical coherence tomography angiography; GCIPL, ganglion cell‐inner plexus layer; SVP, superficial vascular plexus; ICP, intermediate capillary; DCP, deep capillary plexus</p><p>P-values from Pearson correlation analysis, with Bonferroni correction applied</p><p><sup>*</sup>Statistically significant below <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0167 (Bonferroni)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par26">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Scattered map showing correlations between the change rates of the thickness of ganglion cell inner plexiform layer (GCIPL) and vessel density (VD) of superficial vascular plexus (SVP) at different time-points in different areas of detected rings: 1 month post-infection (<bold>A</bold>) and 1 year post-infection (<bold>B</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1849" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12886_2025_4575_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par27">In this study, we identified the long-term impact of COVID-19 infection on retinal structure and microvasculature using SS-OCT and SS-OCTA. Our findings revealed significant and persistent retinal structure and microvasculature alterations one year after COVID-19 infection. To our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate the long-term alterations in retinal structure and microvasculature within individuals before and after COVID-19 infection, providing valuable insights into the ocular manifestations associated with long COVID in the post-pandemic period.</p><p id="Par28">The significant thinning of the pRNFL and GCIPL layer observed in this study aligns with previous findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Jeong et al. demonstrated the presence of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in retinal ganglion cells in mouse models, suggesting direct viral involvement leading to GCIPL thinning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In addition, previous study has confirmed that SARS-CoV-2 RNA remains in the retina long after infection, indicating long-term damage incuded by infection of the virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Regarding RNFL thinning, Jevnikar et al. proposed that the thinning of RNFL might predominantly reflect reactive regeneration rather than progressive atrophy due to SARS-CoV-2 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Given that the RNFL is composed of axons of ganglion cells, the loss of ganglion cells might directly contribute to the thinning of RNFL. However, some studies have reported increased RNFL thickness in participants after COVID infection. For instance, Burgos-Blasco found increases in global RNFL thickness in participants after COVID-19 infection, potentially due to neuroinflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Similar alterations have also been reported in retinal diseases, such as diabetic retinopathy and glaucoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. </p><p id="Par29">Our study also found significantly increased INL thickness in individuals one year after COVID-19 infection, which is consistent with our previous findings at 1-month follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The INL contains the cell bodies of retinal neurons. Additionally, the deep retinal capillary network is situated within the INL, highlighting the crucial role of INL in maintaining the integrity of the retinal microvasculature. The thickening of INL may result from Müller cell activation and gliosis, as seen in diabetic retinopathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Moreover, increased INL thickness was also reported in multiple sclerosis patients with a history of optic neuritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], suggesting potential subclinical inflammation in the retina.</p><p id="Par30">The outer retina, which primarily consists of photoreceptor cells and retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) cells, is particularly susceptible to ischemia and oxidative stress due to the high metabolic activity of photoreceptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Thinning of the outer retina has been reported in previous studies. Recently, Talebnejad et al. found that severe COVID-19 patients, especially those needing respiratory support, may develop ischemia and atrophy of outer plexiform layer (OPL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 has also been shown to disrupt RPE barrier function and phagocytic activity in animal models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. These findings indicate that long-term photoreceptor and RPE dysfunction may result from post-acute viral sequelae, which is consistent with the thinning of the outer retina one year post-infection in our study.</p><p id="Par31">Increasing evidence suggests COVID-19 is primarily a microvascular disease, highlighting endothelial and perivascular cells’ involvement. However, previous findings regarding COVID-19-associated alterations in retinal microvasculature remain inconsistent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. A previous study comparing individuals six months after SARS-CoV-2 infection to healthy controls, reported a significant reduction in VD of the SCP and DCP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. In contrast, Savastano et al. found no significant difference in VD of SCP and DCP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] in individuals 1 month after COVID-19 infection, when compared with healthy controls. Our findings suggest significantly decreased VD of SVP and increased VD of ICP and DCP, consistent with our previous research at 3-month follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. We hypothesized that these retinal vascular alterations may be attributed to two primary mechanisms. First, both endothelial and perivascular cells express high levels of angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE)-2, a receptor of SARS-CoV-2. Hence, direct viral invasion may compromise vascular integrity, leading to impaired retinal microcirculation in individuals after COVID-19 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Second, retinal blood flow is closely regulated by oxygen availability. SARS-CoV-2 infection can cause chronic inflammation, oxidative stress, and endothelial dysfunction, leading to decreased vascular density in SVP and potentially resulting in ganglion cell loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. This observation is also supported by our study, which demonstrates an association between GCIPL thinning with decreased VD of SVP. Similar microvascular alterations have also been observed in patients with diabetes and glaucoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], where ischemia and hypoxia contribute to retinal degeneration.</p><p id="Par32">The above retinal changes suggest a more prolonged impact of COVID-19 on ocular health than previously anticipated. Moreover, none of the participants in our cohort experienced vision loss or reported other ocular symptoms related to vision, and standard ophthalmic examinations did not identify significant clinical abnormalities. These findings may indicate that COVID-19 infection may induce widespread subclinical retinal microvascular damage, as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. However, these findings should be interpreted with caution because subtle segmentation errors and other subtle artifacts may have introduced variability into the quantitative measurements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. </p><p id="Par33">Our longitudinal analysis revealed significant changes in both retinal structure and microvasculature at 1 month and 1 year post-infection compared to pre-infection baselines. However, no significant differences were found between the two follow-up time points (All <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05), suggesting that these alterations are sustained over time. Notably, the similar retinal changes observed at both time points may be driven by different underlying pathophysiological mechanisms. Based on our findings and existing literature, we attempt to interpret the structural effects of SARS-CoV-2 infection on the retina as follows:</p><p id="Par34">Following SARS-CoV-2 infection, retinal changes appear to evolve progressively rather than in distinct phases. Early on, the virus may directly invade retinal vascular endothelial cells via ACE2 receptors, causing microvascular and ganglion cell damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. This triggers Müller glial cell activation and the release of pro-inflammatory cytokines (e.g., IL-6, TNF-α), initiating a neuroinflammatory response that likely underlies GCIPL thinning and reactive INL thickening due to immune cell infiltration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. As inflammation deepens, endothelial injury would be expected to reduce vascular density (VD) globally; however, we observed a selective reduction in SVP VD alongside paradoxical increases in ICP and DCP VD. This suggests localized hemodynamic adaptations, possibly driven by the metabolic demands of immune and glial cells. Over time, as viral activity wanes, the retina appears to shift from acute inflammation to low-grade chronic inflammation with persistent hypoxia. Upregulation of GFAP and VEGF points to ongoing vascular remodeling, though retinal thickness and VD only partially recover within the observation period, indicating that full restoration may require longer follow-up.</p><p id="Par35">Our study has several strengths. First, we conducted within-subject comparisons in individuals before and after SARS-CoV-2 infection, which provides a more accurate assessment of the potential impact of the infection on individuals. Additionally, we performed long-term follow-ups on individuals recovering from COVID-19 infection, helping us better understand the possible long-term effects of SARS-CoV-2 infection on the retina.</p><p id="Par36">Our study has several limitations. First, the sample size was relatively small and consisted predominantly of young healthcare workers and medical students. Although the post hoc power values exceeded 80% for the primary SS-OCT and SS-OCTA parameters, the restricted age distribution still limits the generalizability of the findings. Therefore, the results should be interpreted with caution. Second, subgroup analyses based on the severity of SARS-CoV-2 infection or the burden of post-infection symptoms were not feasible, as nearly all participants experienced mild disease and the sample size was limited. Third, although rigorous quality control procedures were applied to all included images, we acknowledge that subtle artifacts may have influenced the interpretation of the quantitative measurements. In addition, comprehensive functional assessments—such as visual field testing or electrophysiological measurements—were not performed, which limits our ability to evaluate potential functional correlates of the observed structural changes.</p><p id="Par37">Future studies with larger and more diverse cohorts are warranted to enable meaningful subgroup analyses and to further elucidate the potential differences across disease severity, symptom burden, and the number of SARS-CoV-2 infections. In addition, incorporating contemporaneous uninfected control groups, multicenter recruitment, and extended longitudinal follow-up will be important for improving generalizability and distinguishing COVID-19–related retinal changes from normal physiological variation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par38">In conclusion, our study indicates that retinal alterations can persist for one year following COVID-19 recovery, highlighting the long-term impact of COVID-19 infection on the retina. Noninvasive SS-OCT and SS-OCTA could help detect subclinical retinal changes associated with Long COVID-19. </p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Kefan Mou and Yuzhu Gao co-first authors: these authors contributed equally to this project.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We sincerely thank all the participants for their time and patience.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>K.F.M. and Y.Z.G. designed the study, collected the participants, conducted the examination, contributed to the discussion, and drafted the initial version of the manuscript. M.Z. reviewed and revised the manuscript for intellectual content. Y.C., Y.F.Z., S.L.M., H.Y.X., and Q.C. contributed to the participants’ follow-ups and participated in manuscript review and revision. All authors approved the final version of the manuscript. M.Z. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the 1·3·5 project for disciplines of excellence–Clinical Research Fund, West China Hospital, Sichuan University (2023HXFH043).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par39">The study was approved by the Ethics Committee on Biomedical Research, West China Hospital of Sichuan University, China, and conducted according to the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par40">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="funding"><title>Commercial relationships disclosure</title><p id="Par41">All authors certify that they have no affiliations with or involvement in any organization or entity with any financial or non-financial interest in the subject matter or materials discussed in this manuscript.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par42">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par43">Coronavirus disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SARS-CoV-2</term><def><p id="Par44">Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SS‐OCT</term><def><p id="Par45">Swept‐source optical coherence tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SS‐OCTA</term><def><p id="Par46">Swept‐source optical coherence tomography angiography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>pRNFL</term><def><p id="Par47">Peripheral retinal nerve fiber layers</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GCIPL</term><def><p id="Par48">Ganglion cell‐inner plexus layer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>INL</term><def><p id="Par49">Inner nuclear layer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VD</term><def><p id="Par50">Vessel density</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GCC</term><def><p id="Par51">Ganglion cell complex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BCVA</term><def><p id="Par52">Best-corrected visual acuity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IOP</term><def><p id="Par53">Intraocular pressure</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ONH</term><def><p id="Par54">Optic nerve head</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SVP</term><def><p id="Par55">Superficial vascular plexus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICP</term><def><p id="Par56">Intermediate capillary plexus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DCP</term><def><p id="Par57">Deep capillary plexus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAZ</term><def><p id="Par58">Foveal avascular zone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par59">Circularity index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GEE</term><def><p id="Par60">Eneralized estimating equation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p id="Par61">Body mass index</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Invernizzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parrulli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zicarelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retinal vessels modifications in acute and post-COVID-19</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19373</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-98873-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34588541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8481283</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Invernizzi A, Schiuma M, Parrulli S, Torre A, Zicarelli F, Colombo V, et al. Retinal vessels modifications in acute and post-COVID-19. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1):19373.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34588541</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-98873-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8481283</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiersinga</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathophysiology, Transmission, Diagnosis, and treatment of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): A review</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><volume>324</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.12839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32648899</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Wiersinga WJ, Rhodes A, Cheng AC, Peacock SJ, Prescott HC. Pathophysiology, Transmission, Diagnosis, and treatment of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): A review. JAMA. 2020;324(8):782–93.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32648899</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2020.12839</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RLM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>DSW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>KHW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruamviboonsuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19: ocular manifestations and the APAO prevention guidelines for ophthalmic practices</article-title><source>Asia Pac J Ophthalmol (Phila)</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/APO.0000000000000308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32739937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7480794</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Wong RLM, Ting DSW, Wan KH, Lai KHW, Ko CN, Ruamviboonsuk P, et al. COVID-19: ocular manifestations and the APAO prevention guidelines for ophthalmic practices. Asia Pac J Ophthalmol (Phila). 2020;9(4):281–4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32739937</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/APO.0000000000000308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7480794</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinal and choroidal manifestations of COVID-19</article-title><source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source><year>2021</year><volume>32</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ICU.0000000000000801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34605447</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Zhang Y, Stewart JM. Retinal and choroidal manifestations of COVID-19. Curr Opin Ophthalmol. 2021;32(6):536–40.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34605447</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ICU.0000000000000801</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elam</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sidhom</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ugoh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Lott</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disparities in eye care utilization during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2022</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajo.2021.07.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34324852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8312151</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Elam AR, Sidhom D, Ugoh P, Andrews CA, De Lott LB, Woodward MA, et al. Disparities in eye care utilization during the COVID-19 pandemic. Am J Ophthalmol. 2022;233:163–70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34324852</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajo.2021.07.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8312151</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ely EW, Brown LM, Fineberg HV. Long Covid defined. N Engl J Med. 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsb2408466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39083764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevelink</surname><given-names>SAM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post COVID-19 syndrome among 5248 healthcare workers in england: longitudinal findings from NHS CHECK</article-title><source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>81</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oemed-2024-109621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39358009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11503206</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Dempsey B, Blake HA, Madan I, Stevelink SAM, Greenberg N, Raine R, et al. Post COVID-19 syndrome among 5248 healthcare workers in england: longitudinal findings from NHS CHECK. Occup Environ Med. 2024;81(9):471–9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39358009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/oemed-2024-109621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11503206</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DAR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danesh-Meyer</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGhee</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niederer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ocular manifestations of COVID-19</article-title><source>Prog Retin Eye Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>101285</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.preteyeres.2024.101285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38925508</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Ng HW, Scott DAR, Danesh-Meyer HV, Smith JR, McGhee CN, Niederer RL. Ocular manifestations of COVID-19. Prog Retin Eye Res. 2024;102:101285.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38925508</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.preteyeres.2024.101285</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploring the characteristics and antecedents of clinically significant long COVID: A longitudinal cohort study</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>357</volume><fpage>123114</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2024.123114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39369845</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Tang CC, Chang JC, Ho SJ, Liu WD, Pan MY, Chang SC, et al. Exploring the characteristics and antecedents of clinically significant long COVID: A longitudinal cohort study. Life Sci. 2024;357:123114.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39369845</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lfs.2024.123114</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>The Lancet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID: Understanding the neurological effects</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2021</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>247</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(21)00059-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33743226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7969137</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">The Lancet N. Long COVID: Understanding the neurological effects. Lancet Neurol. 2021;20(4):247.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33743226</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1474-4422(21)00059-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7969137</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poças</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendonça</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barroqueiro</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ocular repercussions in COVID-19 patients: structural changes of the retina and choroid</article-title><source>Strabismus</source><year>2023</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09273972.2023.2278639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38053303</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Poças IM, Lino P, Silva C, Mendonça P, Cunha JP, Barroqueiro O, et al. Ocular repercussions in COVID-19 patients: structural changes of the retina and choroid. Strabismus. 2023;31(4):271–80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38053303</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09273972.2023.2278639</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanjay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahendradas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute macular neuroretinopathy and COVID-19 vaccination</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2022</year><volume>70</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijo.IJO_2542_21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34937289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8917606</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Sanjay S, Kawali A, Mahendradas P. Acute macular neuroretinopathy and COVID-19 vaccination. Indian J Ophthalmol. 2022;70(1):345–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34937289</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/ijo.IJO_2542_21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8917606</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunnarsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuelsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiprofessional neurorehabilitation after COVID-19 infection should include assessment of visual function</article-title><source>Arch Rehabil Res Clin Transl</source><year>2022</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>100184</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35128374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arrct.2022.100184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8802546</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Johansson J, Levi R, Jakobsson M, Gunnarsson S, Samuelsson K. Multiprofessional neurorehabilitation after COVID-19 infection should include assessment of visual function. Arch Rehabil Res Clin Transl. 2022;4(2):100184.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35128374</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arrct.2022.100184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8802546</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liao X, Wong ACC, Wong JOY, Jia R, Chen W, Wong HYM, et al. Investigating the impact of COVID-19 infection on dry eye parameters. Diagnostics (Basel). 2023;13(9). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/diagnostics13091524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10177256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37174916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dihan</surname><given-names>QA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alshammari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhusseiny</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rickels</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shakarchi</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long COVID and the development of new-onset uveitis: a large database study</article-title><source>J Ophthalmic Inflamm Infect</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>79</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12348-025-00527-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41186895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12586249</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Dihan QA, Alshammari N, Elhusseiny AM, Rickels KL, Shakarchi AF, Chauhan MZ, et al. Long COVID and the development of new-onset uveitis: a large database study. J Ophthalmic Inflamm Infect. 2025;15(1):79.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41186895</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12348-025-00527-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12586249</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of ophthalmic complications associated with Emerging/Re-Emerging viruses: focus on ZIKV, DENV, SARS-CoV-2, and MPXV</article-title><source>Rev Med Virol</source><year>2025</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e70056</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rmv.70056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40670321</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Li Q, Jiao W, Li X, Liang L. An overview of ophthalmic complications associated with Emerging/Re-Emerging viruses: focus on ZIKV, DENV, SARS-CoV-2, and MPXV. Rev Med Virol. 2025;35(4):e70056.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40670321</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/rmv.70056</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Douaud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro-Almagro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arthofer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 is associated with changes in brain structure in UK biobank</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>604</volume><issue>7907</issue><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04569-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35255491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9046077</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Douaud G, Lee S, Alfaro-Almagro F, Arthofer C, Wang C, McCarthy P, et al. SARS-CoV-2 is associated with changes in brain structure in UK biobank. Nature. 2022;604(7907):697–707.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35255491</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41586-022-04569-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9046077</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Płatkowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biskup</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optical coherence tomography angiography – use in ophthalmological practice</article-title><source>Med Studies/Studia Medyczne</source><year>2020</year><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>205</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Płatkowska B, Kal M, Biskup M. Optical coherence tomography angiography – use in ophthalmological practice. Med Studies/Studia Medyczne. 2020;36(3):195–205.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgos-Blasco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Güemes-Villahoz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal-Villegas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-de-la-Casa</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donate-Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martín-Sánchez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optic nerve and macular optical coherence tomography in recovered COVID-19 patients</article-title><source>Eur J Ophthalmol</source><year>2022</year><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/11206721211001019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33719624</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Burgos-Blasco B, Güemes-Villahoz N, Vidal-Villegas B, Martinez-de-la-Casa JM, Donate-Lopez J, Martín-Sánchez FJ, et al. Optic nerve and macular optical coherence tomography in recovered COVID-19 patients. Eur J Ophthalmol. 2022;32(1):628–36.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33719624</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/11206721211001019</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schlick S, Lucio M, Wallukat G, Bartsch A, Skornia A, Hoffmanns J, et al. Post-COVID-19 syndrome: retinal microcirculation as a potential marker for chronic fatigue. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23(22). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms232213683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9690863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36430175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kal M, Płatkowska-Adamska B, Zarębska-Michaluk D, Rzymski P. Reduced vessel density and enlarged foveal avascular zone in the macula as a result of systemic hypoxia caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection. J Pers Med. 2023;13(6). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jpm13060926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10301350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37373915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of alterations in the retina and vitreous in pre- and post-COVID-19 patients using swept-source optical coherence tomography and angiography: A comparative study</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>2023</year><volume>95</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e29168</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.29168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37815403</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Gao Y, Zhang Y, Mou K, Liu Y, Chen Q, Man S, et al. Assessment of alterations in the retina and vitreous in pre- and post-COVID-19 patients using swept-source optical coherence tomography and angiography: A comparative study. J Med Virol. 2023;95(10):e29168.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37815403</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jmv.29168</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alterations in the outer retina and choroid in patients after COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>J Infect</source><year>2023</year><volume>87</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2023.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37774846</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Gao Y, Zhang Y, Mou K, Man S, Chen Q, Liu Y, et al. Alterations in the outer retina and choroid in patients after COVID-19 infection. J Infect. 2023;87(6):584–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37774846</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2023.09.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jevnikar K, Meglič A, Lapajne L, Logar M, Vidovič Valentinčič N, Globočnik Petrovič M, et al. The comparison of retinal microvascular findings in acute COVID-19 and 1-Year after hospital discharge assessed with multimodal imaging-a prospective longitudinal cohort study. Int J Mol Sci. 2023;24(4). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms24044032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9966689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36835445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cennamo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reibaldi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montorio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D’Andrea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fallico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Triassi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optical coherence tomography angiography features in Post-COVID-19 pneumonia patients: A pilot study</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2021</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajo.2021.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33781767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7997850</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Cennamo G, Reibaldi M, Montorio D, D’Andrea L, Fallico M, Triassi M. Optical coherence tomography angiography features in Post-COVID-19 pneumonia patients: A pilot study. Am J Ophthalmol. 2021;227:182–90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33781767</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajo.2021.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7997850</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marfany EBD. G. The relevance of oxidative stress in the pathogenesis and therapy of retinal dystrophies. Antioxid (Basel). 2020;9(4).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox9040347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7222416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32340220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talebnejad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Badie</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahriari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowroozzadeh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of retinal sublayers in patients with systemic COVID-19 illness with varying degrees of severity</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2877</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-87446-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39843961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11754636</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Talebnejad MR, Badie MR, Shahriari H, Nowroozzadeh MH. Analysis of retinal sublayers in patients with systemic COVID-19 illness with varying degrees of severity. Sci Rep. 2025;15(1):2877.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39843961</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-025-87446-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11754636</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hultgren</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petcherski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torriano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komirisetty</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Productive infection of the retinal pigment epithelium by SARS-CoV-2: initial effects and consideration of long-term consequences</article-title><source>PNAS Nexus</source><year>2024</year><volume>3</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>pgae500</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39712068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11660945</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Hultgren NW, Petcherski A, Torriano S, Komirisetty R, Sharma M, Zhou T, et al. Productive infection of the retinal pigment epithelium by SARS-CoV-2: initial effects and consideration of long-term consequences. PNAS Nexus. 2024;3(12):pgae500.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39712068</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11660945</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bilbao-Malavé V, González-Zamora J, Saenz de Viteri M, de la Puente M, Gándara E, Casablanca-Piñera A, et al. Persistent retinal microvascular impairment in COVID-19 bilateral pneumonia at 6-months follow-up assessed by optical coherence tomography angiography. Biomedicines. 2021;9(5). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines9050502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8147391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34063291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrishami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emamverdian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoeibi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omidtabrizi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daneshvar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeidi Rezvani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optical coherence tomography angiography analysis of the retina in patients recovered from COVID-19: a case-control study</article-title><source>Can J Ophthalmol</source><year>2021</year><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcjo.2020.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33249111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7666612</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Abrishami M, Emamverdian Z, Shoeibi N, Omidtabrizi A, Daneshvar R, Saeidi Rezvani T, et al. Optical coherence tomography angiography analysis of the retina in patients recovered from COVID-19: a case-control study. Can J Ophthalmol. 2021;56(1):24–30.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33249111</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jcjo.2020.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7666612</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">González-Zamora J, Bilbao-Malavé V, Gándara E, Casablanca-Piñera A, Boquera-Ventosa C, Landecho MF, et al. Retinal microvascular impairment in COVID-19 bilateral pneumonia assessed by optical coherence tomography angiography. Biomedicines. 2021;9(3). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines9030247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7998142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33801324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aksoy Aydemır</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydemır</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atesoglu</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goker</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kızıltoprak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative assessment of retinal changes in COVID-19 patients</article-title><source>Clin Exp Optom</source><year>2021</year><volume>104</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08164622.2021.1916389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34016010</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Oren B, Aksoy Aydemır G, Aydemır E, Atesoglu HI, Goker YS, Kızıltoprak H, et al. Quantitative assessment of retinal changes in COVID-19 patients. Clin Exp Optom. 2021;104(6):717–22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34016010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/08164622.2021.1916389</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>GU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ocular tropism of SARS-CoV-2 in animal models with retinal inflammation via neuronal invasion following intranasal inoculation</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7675</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-35225-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36509737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9743116</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Jeong GU, Kwon HJ, Ng WH, Liu X, Moon HW, Yoon GY, et al. Ocular tropism of SARS-CoV-2 in animal models with retinal inflammation via neuronal invasion following intranasal inoculation. Nat Commun. 2022;13(1):7675.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36509737</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-022-35225-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9743116</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P-P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A cohort autopsy study defines COVID-19 systemic pathogenesis</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-021-00523-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34135479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8208380</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Yao X-H, Luo T, Shi Y, He Z-C, Tang R, Zhang P-P, et al. A cohort autopsy study defines COVID-19 systemic pathogenesis. Cell Res. 2021;31(8):836–46.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34135479</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41422-021-00523-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8208380</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sreenivasaiah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optical coherence tomography angiography and progressive retinal nerve fiber layer loss in mild to moderate open-angle glaucoma</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2025</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e0319903</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0319903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40131916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11936279</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Pradhan ZS, Srinivasan T, Sreenivasaiah S, Rao DA, Shroff S, Devi S, et al. Optical coherence tomography angiography and progressive retinal nerve fiber layer loss in mild to moderate open-angle glaucoma. PLoS ONE. 2025;20(3):e0319903.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40131916</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0319903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11936279</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karkhur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethambutol-Induced optic neuropathy: A retrospective study of incidences and risk factors</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2025</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e79160</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.79160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11921821</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Singh P, Karkhur S, Verma V. Ethambutol-Induced optic neuropathy: A retrospective study of incidences and risk factors. Cureus. 2025;17(2):e79160.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109812</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.79160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11921821</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenway</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetic Müller-Glial-Cell-Specific Il6ra knockout mice exhibit accelerated retinal functional decline and thinning of the inner nuclear layer</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>64</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.64.15.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38038619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10697173</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Glass J, Robinson RL, Greenway G, Jones G, Sharma S. Diabetic Müller-Glial-Cell-Specific Il6ra knockout mice exhibit accelerated retinal functional decline and thinning of the inner nuclear layer. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2023;64(15):1.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38038619</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.64.15.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10697173</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parratt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inner nuclear layer thickening is Inversley proportional to retinal ganglion cell loss in optic neuritis</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e78341</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0078341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24098599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3789678</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Kaushik M, Wang CY, Barnett MH, Garrick R, Parratt J, Graham SL, et al. Inner nuclear layer thickening is Inversley proportional to retinal ganglion cell loss in optic neuritis. PLoS ONE. 2013;8(10):e78341.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24098599</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0078341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3789678</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balk</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coric</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behbehani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alroughani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retinal inner nuclear layer volume reflects inflammatory disease activity in multiple sclerosis; a longitudinal OCT study</article-title><source>Mult Scler J Exp Transl Clin</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>2055217319871582</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31523449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/2055217319871582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6728683</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Balk LJ, Coric D, Knier B, Zimmermann HG, Behbehani R, Alroughani R, et al. Retinal inner nuclear layer volume reflects inflammatory disease activity in multiple sclerosis; a longitudinal OCT study. Mult Scler J Exp Transl Clin. 2019;5(3):2055217319871582.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31523449</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/2055217319871582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6728683</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savastano</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gambini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cozzupoli</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crincoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savastano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vico</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retinal capillary involvement in early post-COVID-19 patients: a healthy controlled study</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>2021</year><volume>259</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2157</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00417-020-05070-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33523252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7848665</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Savastano MC, Gambini G, Cozzupoli GM, Crincoli E, Savastano A, De Vico U, et al. Retinal capillary involvement in early post-COVID-19 patients: a healthy controlled study. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2021;259(8):2157–65.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33523252</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00417-020-05070-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7848665</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banderas García</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez-Moltalvá</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falcó</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otero-Romero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arcos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retinal microvascular abnormalities in patients after COVID-19 depending on disease severity</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2022</year><volume>106</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjophthalmol-2020-317953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33328184</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Zapata M, Banderas García S, Sánchez-Moltalvá A, Falcó A, Otero-Romero S, Arcos G, et al. Retinal microvascular abnormalities in patients after COVID-19 depending on disease severity. Br J Ophthalmol. 2022;106(4):559–63.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33328184</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bjophthalmol-2020-317953</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleine-Weber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krüger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erichsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 cell entry depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and is blocked by a clinically proven protease inhibitor</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>181</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>271</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32142651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102627</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Hoffmann M, Kleine-Weber H, Schroeder S, Krüger N, Herrler T, Erichsen S, et al. SARS-CoV-2 cell entry depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and is blocked by a clinically proven protease inhibitor. Cell. 2020;181(2):271–. – 80.e8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32142651</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102627</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karakahya</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korkmaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korkmaz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased retinal nerve fiber and choroidal thickness in chronic rhinosinusitis</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2021</year><volume>278</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2863</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-020-06552-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33704528</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Karakahya RH, Korkmaz M, Korkmaz H. Decreased retinal nerve fiber and choroidal thickness in chronic rhinosinusitis. Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol. 2021;278(8):2863–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33704528</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00405-020-06552-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei-Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaysar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlation between vessel density and thickness in the retina and choroid of severe non-proliferative diabetic retinopathy patients</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1373363</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2024.1373363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38808107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11130367</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">He K, Wei-Zhang S, Li Z, Kaysar P, Yang T, Sun Z, et al. Correlation between vessel density and thickness in the retina and choroid of severe non-proliferative diabetic retinopathy patients. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2024;15:1373363.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38808107</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2024.1373363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11130367</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couturier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erginay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadayoni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaudric</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced vessel density in the superficial and deep plexuses in diabetic retinopathy is associated with structural changes in corresponding retinal layers</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e0219164</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0219164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31318880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6638849</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Lavia C, Couturier A, Erginay A, Dupas B, Tadayoni R, Gaudric A. Reduced vessel density in the superficial and deep plexuses in diabetic retinopathy is associated with structural changes in corresponding retinal layers. PLoS ONE. 2019;14(7):e0219164.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31318880</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0219164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6638849</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kook</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of superficial macular vessel density with visual field progression in open-angle glaucoma with central visual field damage</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7190</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-34000-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37137927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10156675</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Yoon J, Lee A, Song WK, Kim KE, Kook MS. Association of superficial macular vessel density with visual field progression in open-angle glaucoma with central visual field damage. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):7190.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37137927</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-34000-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10156675</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borrelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viggiano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evangelista</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mastropasqua</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eyelashes artifact in Ultra-Widefield optical coherence tomography angiography</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg Lasers Imaging Retina</source><year>2019</year><volume>50</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>740</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3928/23258160-20191031-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31755975</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Borrelli E, Viggiano P, Evangelista F, Toto L, Mastropasqua R. Eyelashes artifact in Ultra-Widefield optical coherence tomography angiography. Ophthalmic Surg Lasers Imaging Retina. 2019;50(11):740–3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31755975</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3928/23258160-20191031-11</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>