<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">63</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcph</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12798015</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12798015.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12798015</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12798015</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41354797</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-025-25774-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">25774</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Persistent poverty, glycemic control and adverse COVID-19 outcomes: a retrospective study using real-world data</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names initials="S">Shiori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names initials="S">Shanquela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="L">Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names initials="N">Nengjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garvey</surname><given-names initials="WT">W. Timothy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherrington</surname><given-names initials="AL">Andrea L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names initials="CR">Carrie R.</given-names></name><address><email>chowell@uabmc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/008s83205</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.265892.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0634 4187</institution-id><institution>Department of Medicine, Division of Internal General Medicine and Population Science, </institution><institution> University of Alabama at Birmingham, </institution></institution-wrap>701 19th Street South, Birmingham, AL 35294 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/008s83205</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.265892.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000106344187</institution-id><institution>Department of Health Behavior, </institution><institution>School of Public Health, University of Alabama at Birmingham, </institution></institution-wrap>1665 University Blvd, AL Birmingham, 35233 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0567t7073</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.249335.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2218 7820</institution-id><institution>Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, </institution><institution>Fox Chase Cancer Center, </institution></institution-wrap>333 Cottman Ave, PA Philadelphia, 19111 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/008s83205</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.265892.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000106344187</institution-id><institution>Department of Biostatistics, </institution><institution>School of Public Health, University of Alabama at Birmingham, </institution></institution-wrap>1665 University Blvd, Birmingham, AL 35233 USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/008s83205</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.265892.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0634 4187</institution-id><institution>Department of Nutrition Sciences, </institution><institution>School of Health Professions, University of Alabama at Birmingham, </institution></institution-wrap>1675 University Blvd, Birmingham, AL 35233 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503732</issue-id><elocation-id>159</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-14 10:25:13.577"><day>14</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12889_2025_Article_25774.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has highlighted the profound impact of diabetes and neighborhood environments on health outcomes. Persistent poverty areas, characterized by long-standing economic deprivation, may contribute to increased risk for severe COVID-19 outcomes, particularly among individuals with poor glycemic control. This study investigated the associations between persistent poverty, longitudinal glycemic control by diabetes status, and adverse COVID-19 outcomes using real world data.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We conducted a retrospective analysis using electronic health record (EHR) data from a large Academic health system. The sample included 3,681 adults diagnosed with COVID-19 between March 2020 and January 2021, with available HbA1c and neighborhood level data. Residence in census-tract level persistent poverty areas was categorized as yes vs. no while diabetes status and glycemic control were categorized into five groups based on history of diagnosis and HbA1c measured up to three years prior to infection. Bayesian multivariable logistic regression models assessed independent and multiplicative associations between living in a persistent poverty census tract, glycemic control by diabetes status, and adverse COVID-19 outcomes [e.g. hospitalization, intensive care unit (ICU) admission, and death during hospitalization], controlling for demographics and other social risk factors.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Among 3,681 patients (mean age 54 years; 60% female; 47% Black), 41.4% were hospitalized, 19.2% were admitted to the ICU, and 6.2% died. Overall, 18.0% resided in persistent poverty areas, 36.2% had diabetes [16.6% undiagnosed diabetes, and 11.1% poorly controlled T2DM]. Residing in persistent poverty areas was associated with an increased risk of hospitalization (OR 1.28, 95% CI: 1.02–1.61), ICU admission (OR 1.40, 95% CI: 1.08–1.80), and mortality (OR 1.50, 95% CI: 1.01–2.22). Patients with undiagnosed diabetes had an increased risk of hospitalization (OR 3.05, 95% CI 2.41–3.86) and mortality (OR 1.96, 95% CI: 1.30–2.97).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">This study highlights that residing in a persistent poverty census tract as well as poor glycemic control independently contribute to COVID-19 outcomes. Ongoing management of glycemic control and early preventive strategies in persistent poverty areas may mitigate adverse outcomes in COVID-19 infection and subsequent sequalae like Long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12889-025-25774-7.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Persistent poverty</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Electronic health record</kwd><kwd>HbA1c</kwd><kwd>Diabetes</kwd><kwd>Glycemic control</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>NIH NIMHD</institution></funding-source><award-id>U54MD008176</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>Carrie R.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100000968</institution-id><institution>American Heart Association</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>931540</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>Carrie R.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par24">Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is a known risk factor for severe coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Individuals with diabetes pre-infection face a higher risk of severe symptoms, hospitalization, and mortality due to an impaired immune response, chronic inflammation, and endothelial dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The COVID-19 pandemic highlighted disparities in health outcomes, revealing the significant role of neighborhood environments in shaping risk of infection and long-term consequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Recent findings indicated that both clinical markers of cardiometabolic disease and neighborhood level exposures were predictive of adverse COVID-19 outcomes, with social determinants of health – such as the Social Vulnerability Index (SVI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] – significantly improving prediction of severe COVID-19 outcomes, underscoring the need for an integrated approach to risk assessment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. While the SVI has been used to identify high-risk communities, it does not capture long-standing economic disadvantages, particularly in persistent poverty areas, where health risks are compounded by decades of economic deprivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">Persistent poverty areas, defined as counties where at least 20% of the population has lived in poverty for the past 30 years, capture multi-generational economic hardships and represent a unique and underexplored determinant of health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Residents of these areas are often characterized with poor lifestyle behaviors and chronic socioeconomic deprivation as well as limited healthcare access, making residents at risk for adverse health outcomes such as diabetes and stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Moreover, individuals living in persistent poverty are exposed to obesogenic environments, food deserts, and psychosocial stressors that contribute to poor glycemic control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Therefore, this exposure to persistent poverty, combined with ongoing dysregulated glycemic control, likely contributes multi-fold to adverse COVID outcomes.</p><p id="Par26">This study aimed to examine the associations of persistent poverty, pre-infection glycemic control by diabetes status, and acute adverse COVID-19 outcomes. Understanding these associations are important for identifying high-risk populations, informing targeted interventions, and reducing or minimizing long term sequalae such as Long COVID.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par27">This retrospective analysis used electronic health record (EHR) data from a large academic health system in the Southern United States. We requested EHR data for patients with a positive COVID-19 polymerase chain reaction (PCR) test between December 2020 and January 2021 who also had clinical data available up to three years prior to infection (2017-2020), including, applicable clinical follow-up to define COVID-19 outcome measures. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The original data analysis was based on available glucose in the EHR, while this sub study filtered based on patients with available HbA1c for glycemic control categorization. This study was approved by the institution’s internal review board, and informed consent from study participants was waived.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par28">Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the patients included in the present study. Eligible participants for this analysis were determined as having no prior diagnosed type 1 diabetes, individuals 18 years or older, and no missing data on age, sex, census tract, body mass index (BMI) , race, and insurance status. Patients with complete data vs. incomplete data varied by sex (more males had incomplete data) and slightly by race (more White patients had incomplete data) (Supplemental table 1).</p><p id="Par29">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study flow</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e460" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_25774_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>COVID-19 outcomes</title><p id="Par30">Three outcomes of interest were examined: (1) hospitalization, defined as a new hospital admission with a positive COVID-19 PCR documented in the EHR within 14 days; (2) ICU admission, defined as admission to the ICU during the initial hospitalization; and (3) in-hospital death, determined by discharge disposition and notification of death in the clinical record. Each outcome was modeled separately.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>T2DM and other diagnosed diseases</title><p id="Par31">History of T2DM and other comorbidities was identified using disease classification codes (e.g., International Classification of Diseases 10th revision (ICD-10), Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine (SNOMED)). To account for cardiometabolic related comorbidities, we generated a comorbidity count variable considering coronary artery disease (CAD), chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), chronic kidney disease (CKD), and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). Patients were assigned a value from 0 to 4.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Assessment of glycemic control by diabetes status</title><p id="Par32">We used HbA1c values within three years prior to COVID-19 (mean values for those with multiple labs) and applied different HbA1c cut-off values for individuals with and without T2DM to determine glycemic control status considering diabetes status. For patients without a T2DM diagnosis, we categorized those with an HbA1c &lt; 5.7% as normal, 5.7% to &lt; 6.4% as prediabetes, and ≥ 6.5% as potentially undiagnosed diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Since we did not have data on other forms of diabetes (e.g. gestational), we were not able to differentiate other forms of diabetes among patients classified as having undiagnosed diabetes. For individuals with T2DM, we categorized those with HbA1c &lt; 7.0% as controlled T2DM, and ≥ 7.0% as poorly controlled T2DM.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Exposures of interest</title><p id="Par33">In 2023, the National Cancer Institute launched an initiative to alleviate the cumulative effects of persistent poverty on health, especially cancer outcomes. Persistent poverty is a place-based and community phenomenon that captures broad structural, generational, and systemic disadvantages, while the SVI reflects the characteristics of individuals or households in an aggregated area. While the SVI does not account for how long the ‘place’ or area has been exposed to such deprivation, the concept of persistent poverty does. For this reason, we focus on persistent poverty but also examined the SVI due to these subtle nuances and to compare to prior work.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Persistent poverty</title><p id="Par34">Patients in the EHR were geocoded and linked to census tract of residence if address data were available. Persistent poverty areas were defined using the predefined classifications from the American Community Survey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Data were downloaded and merged based on census tract of residence. Patients were categorized as ever residing in (yes) or not residing in (no) a persistent poverty area at any time during the study period (2017–2021).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Social vulnerability index</title><p id="Par35">To compare with prior work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], we also linked SVI to census tract of residence, which is a composite measure based on 15 social factors grouped into four categories: socioeconomic, household composition and disability, minority status and language, and housing and transportation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Each patient was assigned a composite SVI value ranging from 0 (least vulnerable) to 1 (most vulnerable), which was then categorized as low (0.0 to &lt; 0.33, reference), moderate (0.33 to &lt; 0.66), or high (0.66 to 1.00) vulnerability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Covariates</title><p id="Par36">Demographic characteristics included age at COVID-19 diagnosis, sex (female or male), BMI, comorbidity count (0–4), insurance status (private, or public/no insurance), and race (non-Hispanic Black, non-Hispanic White, and other). Other neighborhood-level factors included rurality and health care access. Rurality was defined at the census tract level using the 2010 United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) Rural-Urban Commuting Area codes and grouped based on living in a metropolitan area; micropolitan area; small town; or rural area. Census tract data were linked to the US Health Resources and Services Administration Data Warehouse Primary Care Service Area Data to determine health professional shortage areas (HPSAs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. HPSAs indicate census tracts with populations that have a shortage of health care providers and were classified as designated vs. not designated as reference.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par37">Basic characteristics of the study population by COVID-19 outcome were summarized. The characteristics were compared by outcomes using 2-sampled t-tests and Chi-squared tests as appropriate. Bayesian logistic regression models were run to examine the associations between living in a persistent poverty census tract, glycemic control by diabetes status, and COVID-19 outcomes, adjusted for covariates. We assigned weakly informative priors with Cauchy distributions with center 0 and scale 2.5 to the coefficients in the logistic regressions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. This approach provides minimal prior information to constrain coefficients in a reasonable range, stabilizing the model fitting, and improving the prediction performance. SVI was also examined in another model.</p><p id="Par38">To examine if the association between glycemic control by diabetes status and poor COVID outcomes varied as a function of neighborhood risk status, we tested an interaction term between persistent poverty areas and glycemic control by diabetes status. We also conducted subgroup analyses by persistent poverty census tract. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant in all analyses. We conducted the analyses in R software (version 4.3.1), using the BhGLM package (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nyiuab/BhGLM">https://github.com/nyiuab/BhGLM</ext-link>) for Bayesian logistic regression.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><p id="Par39">Among patients diagnosed with COVID-19 between December 2020 and January 2021 within the hospital health system, a total of 4,563 patients had an available HbA1c within three years prior to COVID-19 diagnosis. We excluded 16 ineligible individuals (type 1 diabetes: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4; age ≤ 18 or missing age: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10; missing data on sex: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2), yielding 4,547 eligible subjects. After removing those with missing data on key covariates— census tract level measures (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 787), BMI (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 28), race (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 45), and health insurance status (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6)—a total of 3,681 patients were included in the analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par40">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents baseline characteristics by COVID-19 outcomes. Patients had a mean age of 54.4 years (SD: 16.4), with a majority female (60.2%), and non-Hispanic White race (48.3%). Of the patients, 37.7% had a normal glycemic status, 26.2% were prediabetic, 8.4% had controlled T2DM, 11.1% had poorly controlled T2DM, and 16.7% had potentially undiagnosed diabetes. Overall, 41.4% were hospitalized, 19.2% admitted to the ICU, and 6.2% died during hospitalization. Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the distribution of social determinants of health by COVID-19 status. Roughly 40% lived in a high SVI census tract and 18% lived in a persistent poverty census tract. Patients who were older, had public health insurance, lived in persistent poverty or high SVI areas, and had undiagnosed diabetes or poorly controlled diabetes were likely to experience hospitalization, admission to the ICU, or mortality.</p><p id="Par41">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Basic characteristics of the study population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Hospitalization</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">ICU admission</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Mortality</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 3681)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 2,158, 58.6%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1,523, 41.4%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 2,973, 80.8%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 708, 19.2%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 3,452, 93.8%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 229, 6.2%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="11" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Demographic characteristics</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, years (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.4 (16.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.2 (15.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.9 (17.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.3 (16.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.2 (16.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.7 (16.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.9 (17.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2215 (60.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1421 (64.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">794 (35.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1895 (85.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">320 (14.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2103 (94.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112 (5.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1466 (39.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">737 (50.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">729 (49.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1078 (73.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">388 (26.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1349 (92.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117 (8.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11" rowspan="1">Race</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Black</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1722 (46.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">952 (55.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">770 (44.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1384 (80.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">338 (19.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1604 (93.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118 (6.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1778 (48.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1112 (62.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">666 (37.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1445 (81.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">333 (18.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1673 (94.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105 (5.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">181 (4.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (51.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 (48.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">144 (79.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (20.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">175 (96.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (3.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Clinical characteristics</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup>, Mean (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.7 (7.74)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.0 (7.46)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.2 (8.09)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.9 (7.66)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.8 (7.99)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.7 (7.71)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.6 (8.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Normal (18.5 to &lt; 25.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">614 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">273 (44.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">341 (55.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">436 (71.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">178 (29.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">562 (91.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (8.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Overweight (25.0 to &lt; 30.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">973 (26.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">568 (58.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">405 (41.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">787 (80.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">186 (19.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">916 (94.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (5.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Obese (≥ 30.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2094 (56.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1317 (62.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">777 (37.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1750 (83.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">344 (16.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1974 (94.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120 (5.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HbA1c, % (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.46 (1.62)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.16 (1.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.88 (1.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.36 (1.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.87 (1.84)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.42 (1.61)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.96 (1.72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11" rowspan="1">Glycemic control by diabetes status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Undiagnosed diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">613 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232 (37.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">381 (62.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">414 (67.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">199 (32.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">544 (88.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (11.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Poorly controlled T2DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">408 (11.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">183 (44.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">225 (55.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">312 (76.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (23.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">370 (90.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (9.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Controlled T2DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">308 (8.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">157 (51.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151 (49.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">234 (76.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (24.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">283 (91.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (8.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Prediabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">966 (26.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">615 (63.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">351 (36.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">811 (84.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155 (16.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">917 (94.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (5.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Normal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1386 (37.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">971 (70.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">415 (29.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1202 (86.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">184 (13.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1338 (96.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (3.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coronary artery disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1319 (35.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">615 (46.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">704 (53.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">968 (73.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">351 (26.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1199 (90.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120 (9.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">COPD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">494 (13.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (45.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">271 (54.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">370 (74.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124 (25.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">447 (90.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (9.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic kidney disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1108 (30.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">427 (38.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">681 (61.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">792 (71.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">316 (28.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">985 (88.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">123 (11.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obstructive Sleep Apnea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">296 (8.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161 (54.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135 (45.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">244 (82.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (17.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274 (92.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (7.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comorbidity count (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.794 (0.988)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.586 (0.891)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09 (1.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.716 (0.961)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12 (1.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.762 (0.977)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27 (1.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are number (%) unless otherwise indicated</p><p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> Body mass index, <italic toggle="yes">COPD</italic> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, <italic toggle="yes">HPSA</italic> Health professional shortage area, <italic toggle="yes">ICU</italic> Intensive care unit, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> Standard deviation, <italic toggle="yes">SVI</italic> Social vulnerability index, <italic toggle="yes">T2DM</italic> Type 2 diabetes mellitus</p><p><sup>1</sup>Comorbidity count was derived based on the history of CAD, COPD, CKD, and OSA, and ranges from 0 to 4</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par42">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Measures of social determinants of health overall and by COVID-19 outcome status</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1188" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_25774_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par43">Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> illustrates adjusted odds ratios (ORs) and corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for COVID-19 outcomes by persistent poverty census tract residence and glycemic control by diabetes status. Living in a persistent poverty area was significantly associated with higher risk of hospitalization (OR 1.28, 95% CI: 1.02–1.61), ICU admission (OR 1.40, 95% CI: 1.08–1.80), and mortality (OR 1.50, 95% CI: 1.01–2.22). Compared to those with normal glycemic status without diagnosed T2DM, patients with undiagnosed diabetes had an increased risk of hospitalization (OR 3.05, 95% CI: 2.41–3.86), ICU admission (OR 2.47, 95% CI: 1.90–3.20), and mortality (OR 1.96, 95% CI: 1.30–2.97). Those with poorly controlled T2DM also had an increased risk of hospitalization (OR 1.51, 95% CI: 1.16–1.99). Male sex (OR 1.41, 95% CI: 1.06–1.88 for mortality) and having public or no insurance coverage (OR 4.15, 95% CI: 2.74–6.30 for mortality) were independently associated with increased risk of COVID-19 outcomes while living outside of a metropolitan area was associated with increased risk of ICU admission.</p><p id="Par44">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Association of living in persistent poverty areas, glycemic control by diabetes status, and COVID-19 outcomes. BMI: body mass index; HPSA: health professional shortage area; ICU: intensive care unit; SVI: Social Vulnerability Index; T2DM: type 2 diabetes mellitus. Adjusted odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) from a Bayesian logistic regression model evaluating the association between living in persistent poverty areas, glycemic control by diabetes status, and the risk of (<bold>a</bold>) hospitalization, (<bold>b</bold>) ICU admission, and (<bold>c</bold>) mortality among patients with a COVID-19 diagnosis. Persistent poverty areas indicate patients ever residing during the study period in census tracts with ≥ 20% poverty over the past 30 years. Glycemic control by diabetes status categories were defined by HbA1c levels as follows: undiagnosed diabetes (HbA1c ≥ 6.5% with no prior diabetes diagnosis), poorly controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) (HbA1c ≥ 7.0%), controlled T2DM (HbA1c &lt; 7.0%), and prediabetes (HbA1c 5.7–&lt;6.5%), with normal glycemic status (HbA1c &lt; 5.7%) as the reference group. The comorbidity count ranged from 0 to 4, and was calculated based on the history of coronary artery disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic kidney disease, and obstructive sleep apnea. Arrows indicate odds ratios that extend beyond the x-axis scale</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1213" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_25774_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par45">Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the ORs for COVID-19 outcomes by SVI and diabetes status with similar results. Living in a high-SVI area was independently associated with hospitalization (OR 1.95, 95% CI: 1.54–2.46), ICU admission (OR 1.90, 95% CI: 1.44–2.50), and mortality (OR 1.57, 95% CI: 1.01–2.45) compared to living in low-SVI areas. Models incorporating SVI showed similar results for patients with undiagnosed diabetes and poorly controlled T2DM as models using persistent poverty areas. Controlled T2DM and prediabetes were not significantly associated with COVID-19 outcomes.</p><p id="Par46">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Association of Social Vulnerable Index (SVI), glycemic control by diabetes status, and COVID-19 outcomes. BMI: body mass index; HPSA: health professional shortage area; ICU: intensive care unit; SVI: Social Vulnerability Index; T2DM: type 2 diabetes mellitus. Adjusted odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) from a Bayesian logistic regression model evaluating the association between the Social Vulnerability Index (SVI), diabetes status, and the risk of (<bold>a</bold>) hospitalization, (<bold>b</bold>) ICU admission, and (<bold>c</bold>) mortality among patients at the COVID-19 diagnosis. SVI is a composite measure ranging from 0 to 1, with higher values indicating greater vulnerability based on socioeconomic and demographic factors at the census tract level. SVI was categorized as low (0.00 to &lt; 0.33), moderate (0.33 to &lt; 0.66), and high (0.66–1.00). Lycemic control by diabetes status categories were defined by HbA1c levels as follows: undiagnosed diabetes (HbA1c ≥ 6.5% with no prior diabetes diagnosis), poorly controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) (HbA1c ≥ 7.0%), controlled T2DM (HbA1c &lt; 7.0%), and prediabetes (HbA1c 5.7–&lt;6.5%), with normal glycemic status (HbA1c &lt; 5.7%) as the reference group. The Gcomorbidity count ranged from 0 to 4 and was calculated based on the history of coronary artery disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic kidney disease, and obstructive sleep apnea. Arrows indicate odds ratios that extend beyond the x-axis scale</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1238" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2025_25774_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par47">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the interaction estimates between glycemic control by diabetes status and living in persistent poverty; terms were not statistically significant, indicating persistent poverty did not modify the association between glycemic control by diabetes status and COVID-19 outcomes in our sample. When analyses were stratified by persistent poverty census tract, patients with undiagnosed diabetes generally had elevated risks of hospitalization, ICU admission, and mortality overall. Those living in the persistent poverty tracks showed slightly higher odds of hospitalization (OR 3.55, 95% CI 2.00–6.30) versus those not living in a persistent poverty track (OR 2.96, 95% CI 2.29–3.82 (Supplemental fig. 1). We found similar results using SVI and glycemic status as the interaction term (Supplemental table 2).</p><p id="Par48">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The estimates of multiplicative interaction between glycemic status and persistent poverty</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Glycemic control by diabetes status X persistent poverty areas</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hospitalization</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">ICU admission</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mortality</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coefficient</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coefficient</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coefficient</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Undiagnosed diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poorly controlled T2DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Controlled T2DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prediabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>A Bayesian logistic regression model incorporating interaction terms between glycemic control by diabetes status and living in persistent poverty areas to assess the presence of interaction on hospitalization, ICU admission, and mortality among patients at the COVID-19 diagnosis. Covariates included age at diagnosis, sex, race, health insurance, health professional shortage area, rurality, body mass index, and comorbidity count. Glycemic control by diabetes status categories were defined by HbA1c levels as follows: undiagnosed diabetes (HbA1c ≥ 6.5% with no prior diabetes diagnosis), poorly controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) (HbA1c ≥ 7.0%), controlled T2DM (HbA1c &lt; 7.0%), and prediabetes (HbA1c 5.7–&lt;6.5%), with normal glycemic status (HbA1c &lt; 5.7%) as the reference group. The comorbidity count ranged from 0 to 4 and was calculated based on the history of coronary artery disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic kidney disease, and obstructive sleep apnea</p><p><italic toggle="yes">ICU</italic> Intensive care unit, <italic toggle="yes">T2DM</italic> Type 2 diabetes mellitus</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par49">Leveraging EHR data from a large academic medical center in the Deep South in the United States, we found persistent poverty, and longitudinal glycemic control by diabetes status, were independently associated with increased risk of hospitalization, ICU admission, and mortality among COVID-19 patients. Specifically, we found that patients living in persistent poverty were at a 1.2- and 1.5-fold increased risk of hospitalization and mortality, respectively. Patients with undiagnosed diabetes were at a roughly 2- to 3-fold increased risk across all adverse COVID outcomes. Although we did not find evidence of an interaction between living in persistent poverty and glycemic control by diabetes status, subgroup analysis trended towards higher risk estimates for poor outcomes for those living in persistent poverty. To our knowledge, this is the first study to assess whether living in persistent poverty areas is associated with higher risk of hospitalization, ICU admission, and mortality after COVID-19 infection, even after adjusting for pre-infection glycemic and diabetes status. Although numerous studies have investigated neighborhood deprivation in relation to COVID-19 outcomes, most have relied on general indices of socioeconomic disadvantage. In contrast, persistent poverty areas, a construct emphasized by the National Cancer Institute as a potential driver of long-term health disparities, capture the chronic and structural dimensions of neighborhood disadvantage that can influence health outcomes across generations. By focusing on these areas, our study provides novel evidence on how long-standingpoverty relates to severe COVID-19 outcomes and highlights a population identified by federal agencies as a priority for infrastructure and health system investment.</p><p id="Par50">Our findings indicate that living in neighborhood vulnerability, captured by both persistent poverty and SVI, is associated with increased odds of COVID-19 outcomes regardless of glycemic and diabetes status. People living in persistent poverty areas experience significant barriers to well-being due to lack of adequate infrastructure, support services, and sustained socioeconomic deprivation in the community. Residents of these areas also face limited access to healthcare, substandard housing, transportation barriers, food deserts, and civic engagement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Similarly, SVI was a strong and consistent predictor of COVID-19 outcomes, aligning with previous research linking high SVI to greater COVID-19 mortality risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. SVI reflects broader social determinants, including economic instability, limited educational attainment, and housing insecurity, that may contribute both to increased COVID-19 exposure and adverse clinical outcomes. While persistent poverty captures sustained deprivation, SVI provides a more immediate lens on neighborhood-level vulnerabilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Both indicators underscore the need for policy-level solutions to address contextual drivers of chronic disease and health emergency vulnerabilities – such as in the COVID-19 pandemic – and beyond what individual-level clinical care can accomplish.</p><p id="Par51">We found no significant interaction between glycemic control by diabetes status and persistent poverty areas on COVID-19 outcomes. Initially, we hypothesized that living in persistent poverty areas might exacerbate the association between glycemic control status in both those with and without T2DM and risk of COVID-19 outcomes, given the compounded neighborhood disadvantages. The lack of observed effect modification may reflect a true absence of interaction or could be due to limited statistical power. However, analysis stratified by persistent poverty indicated that although the magnitude of the association between glycemic control by diabetes status and COVID-19 outcomes was similar across areas, the greater prevalence of high-risk groups in persistent poverty areas suggests a higher burden of disease among this population. This higher burden underscores a need for system-level interventions in vulnerable communities that address underlying contextual barriers to reduce both the burden of diabetes and its contribution to disparities in COVID-19 outcomes.</p><p id="Par52">Our results also draw attention to the burden of undiagnosed diabetes where patients with undiagnosed diabetes had nearly threefold higher odds of hospitalization, along with significantly increased ICU admission and mortality, consistent with previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. A prior study reported that having undiagnosed diabetes was associated with no health care encounters or hospitalizations in the past year and was more common among younger adults aged 20–44 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. These findings suggest that individuals with undiagnosed diabetes may have limited healthcare engagement, leading to missed opportunities for early detection and management—not only of diabetes but also of other comorbidities associated with COVID-19 outcomes. As shown in our previous study, male sex and public or no insurance status were also significant predictors of COVID-19 outcomes. Being uninsured or reliant on public insurance has been correlated with delayed or limited access to COVID-19 testing and treatment, higher likelihood of hospitalization and ICU admission due to more advanced disease upon presentation and increased mortality rates.</p><p id="Par53">Our study has limitations that should be considered. First, reliance on EHR data likely introduced selection bias, since this sample was limited to those with access to healthcare, systematically excluding those who may be at highest risk. Second, unmeasured confounders, such as healthcare-seeking behavior, could have influenced results. Third, the focus on a single healthcare system may limit generalizability. Fourth, neighborhood-level SDoH indicators may not fully capture individual-level socioeconomic status (SES) and may be prone to the ecological fallacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Fifth, using average HbA1c values from up to three years before infection may not fully capture glycemic control immediately prior to COVID-19 infection, although our analysis focused on long-term pre-infection control. Finally, our diabetes status variable was based on diagnostic documentation in the EHR which often contains errors. Our classification of undiagnosed diabetes may have included other forms such as gestational or secondary diabetes, potentially attenuating the observed associations. However, these cases were rare (0.006% and 0.016% of primary care patients, respectively), and using the three-year average HbA1c likely minimized the impact of transient gestational diabetes.</p><p id="Par54">Despite these limitations, a major strength of our study is our assessment of disease severity in emergent diseases like COVID-19 using real-world data collected in real time, providing important information beyond traditional epidemiological cohorts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Unlike most studies using single-time-point HbA1c measurements near hospital admission, our assessment of longitudinal glycemic control by diabetes status up to 3 years before infection provides important information on prior risk factors – such as glycemic control and living in a socially vulnerable area – that should be assessed in the context of acute infection presentation. Moreover, social vulnerability indicators can help healthcare systems and policymakers identify high-risk communities for outreach, screening and intervention. Furthermore, disproportionately high rates of undiagnosed and poorly controlled diabetes among those with worst COVID-19 outcomes highlight a critical need to close diagnostic and treatment gaps in primary care – and particularly among those living in socially vulnerable neighborhoods. Long-term investment in healthcare infrastructure and economic development in persistent poverty areas are pathways that could aid in addressing poor outcomes in future pandemics and other public health crises.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par55">In summary, our study provides evidence that both living in persistent poverty areas and longitudinal glycemic control by diabetes status independently contribute to higher risk of poor COVID-19 outcomes. These findings emphasize the need for clinical, public health and system-level interventions targeting those living in persistent poverty areas, including expanded screening, improved access to preventive care, chronic disease management, and broader policy for future public health crises.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12889_2025_25774_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>T2DM</term><def><p id="Par5">Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par6">Coronavirus Disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SVI</term><def><p id="Par7">Social Vulnerability Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EHR</term><def><p id="Par8">Electronic Health Record</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCR</term><def><p id="Par9">Polymerase Chain Reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICU</term><def><p id="Par10">Intensive Care Unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICD-10</term><def><p id="Par11">International Classification of Diseases, 10th Revision</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNOMED</term><def><p id="Par12">Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAD</term><def><p id="Par13">Coronary Artery Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COPD</term><def><p id="Par14">Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CKD</term><def><p id="Par15">Chronic Kidney Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OSA</term><def><p id="Par16">Obstructive Sleep Apnea</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HbA1c</term><def><p id="Par17">Hemoglobin A1c</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>USDA</term><def><p id="Par18">United States Department of Agriculture</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HPSAs</term><def><p id="Par19">Health Professional Shortage Areas</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p id="Par20">Odds Ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par21">Confidence Interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SES</term><def><p id="Par22">Socioeconomic Status</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDoH</term><def><p id="Par23">Social Determinants of Health</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>CRH, WTG and ALC contributed to the study conception and design. Material preparation and data collection were performed by ST, SW, LZ, NY and CRH. Data analysis and interpretation were performed by ST, SW, LZ, NY and CRH. The first draft of the manuscript was written by ST, SW, and CRH and all authors commented on previous versions of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by funding from the National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (U54MD008176). Additional funding was provided by American Heart Association Grant # 931540/Carrie R. Howell/2022, the National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (Howell − 1K01 MD0172706). The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities or others supporting this work.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. The data are not publicly available due to them containing information that could compromise patient privacy.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par56">Our study used retrospective de-identified data and was considered exempt by the University of Alabama at Birmingham’s Institutional Review board in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par57">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par58">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corrao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinelli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vacca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raspanti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Argano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Type 2 diabetes mellitus and COVID-19: a narrative review</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>609470</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2021.609470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33868163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8044543</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Corrao S, Pinelli K, Vacca M, Raspanti M, Argano C. Type 2 diabetes mellitus and COVID-19: a narrative review. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2021;12:609470. 10.3389/fendo.2021.609470.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33868163</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2021.609470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8044543</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganjkhanloo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghobadi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolving patterns of COVID-19 mortality in US counties: a longitudinal study of healthcare, socioeconomic, and vaccination associations</article-title><source>PLoS Glob Public Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>4</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e0003590</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0003590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39255264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11386416</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Ganjkhanloo F, Ahmadi F, Dong E, Parker F, Gardner L, Ghobadi K. Evolving patterns of COVID-19 mortality in US counties: a longitudinal study of healthcare, socioeconomic, and vaccination associations. PLoS Glob Public Health. 2024;4(9):e0003590. 10.1371/journal.pgph.0003590.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39255264</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pgph.0003590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11386416</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhuiyan</surname><given-names>MAN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using the social vulnerability index to assess COVID-19 vaccine uptake in Louisiana</article-title><source>GeoJournal</source><year>2023</year><volume>88</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>3239</fpage><lpage>3248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10708-022-10802-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36531533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9734623</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Bhuiyan MAN, Davis TC, Arnold CL, et al. Using the social vulnerability index to assess COVID-19 vaccine uptake in Louisiana. GeoJournal. 2023;88(3):3239–48. 10.1007/s10708-022-10802-5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36531533</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10708-022-10802-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9734623</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faraji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social vulnerability and initial COVID-19 community spread in the US South: a machine learning approach</article-title><source>BMJ Health Care Inform</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjhci-2022-100703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10373713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37487688</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Tatar M, Faraji MR, Wilson FA. Social vulnerability and initial COVID-19 community spread in the US South: a machine learning approach. BMJ Health Care Inform. 2023. 10.1136/bmjhci-2022-100703.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjhci-2022-100703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10373713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37487688</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>County-level social vulnerability is associated with in-hospital death and major adverse cardiovascular events in patients hospitalized with COVID-19: an analysis of the American Heart Association COVID-19 cardiovascular disease registry</article-title><source>Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes</source><year>2022</year><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e008612</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.121.008612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35862003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9387665</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Islam SJ, Malla G, Yeh RW, et al. County-level social vulnerability is associated with in-hospital death and major adverse cardiovascular events in patients hospitalized with COVID-19: an analysis of the American Heart Association COVID-19 cardiovascular disease registry. Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2022;15(8):e008612. 10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.121.008612.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35862003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.121.008612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9387665</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Contribution of Individual- and Neighborhood-Level Social</collab></person-group><article-title>Demographic, and health factors to COVID-19 hospitalization outcomes</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>175</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M21-2615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35188790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8982172</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Contribution of Individual- and Neighborhood-Level Social. Demographic, and health factors to COVID-19 hospitalization outcomes. Ann Intern Med. 2022;175(4):505–12. 10.7326/M21-2615.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35188790</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M21-2615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8982172</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherrington</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garvey</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations between cardiometabolic disease severity, social determinants of health (SDoH), and poor COVID-19 outcomes</article-title><source>Obesity</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1483</fpage><lpage>1494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.23440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35352489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9088642</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Howell CR, Zhang L, Yi N, Mehta T, Cherrington AL, Garvey WT. Associations between cardiometabolic disease severity, social determinants of health (SDoH), and poor COVID-19 outcomes. Obesity. 2022;30(7):1483–94. 10.1002/oby.23440.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35352489</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/oby.23440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9088642</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>County-level social vulnerability is associated with in-hospital death and major adverse cardiovascular events in patients hospitalized with COVID-19: an analysis of the American Heart Association COVID-19 cardiovascular disease registry</article-title><source>Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes</source><year>2022</year><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e008612</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/circoutcomes.121.008612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35862003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9387665</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Islam SJ, Malla G, Yeh RW, et al. County-level social vulnerability is associated with in-hospital death and major adverse cardiovascular events in patients hospitalized with COVID-19: an analysis of the American Heart Association COVID-19 cardiovascular disease registry. Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2022;15(8):e008612. 10.1161/circoutcomes.121.008612.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35862003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.121.008612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9387665</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croyle</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistent poverty and cancer mortality rates: an analysis of county-level poverty designations</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source><year>2020</year><volume>29</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1949</fpage><lpage>1954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.Epi-20-0007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32998949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7534551</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Moss JL, Pinto CN, Srinivasan S, Cronin KA, Croyle RT. Persistent poverty and cancer mortality rates: an analysis of county-level poverty designations. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2020;29(10):1949–54. 10.1158/1055-9965.Epi-20-0007.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32998949</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-20-0007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7534551</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Craig Benson AB, Brian G. Persistent Poverty: Identifying Areas With Long-Term High Poverty. U.S. Census Bureau. Updated 05/22/2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2023/05/persistent-poverty-areas-with-long-term-high-poverty.html#:~:text=About%2010.9%25%20of%20the%20nation%E2%80%99s%203%2C142%20counties%20experienced,the%20three%20decades%20period%20from%201989%20to%202015-2019">https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2023/05/persistent-poverty-areas-with-long-term-high-poverty.html#:~:text=About%2010.9%25%20of%20the%20nation%E2%80%99s%203%2C142%20counties%20experienced,the%20three%20decades%20period%20from%201989%20to%202015-2019</ext-link>. Accessed 2024 Oct 23.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Broyles</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heymsfield</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetes prevalence is associated with different community factors in the diabetes belt versus the rest of the United States</article-title><source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source><year>2017</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.21725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28009108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5269515</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Myers CA, Slack T, Broyles ST, Heymsfield SB, Church TS, Martin CK. Diabetes prevalence is associated with different community factors in the diabetes belt versus the rest of the United States. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2017;25(2):452–9. 10.1002/oby.21725.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28009108</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/oby.21725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5269515</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kabangu J-LK, Newsome-Cuby T, Hernandez A, et al. The role of county-level persistent poverty in stroke mortality in the USA. J Racial Ethn Health Disparities. 2024(3). 10.1007/s40615-024-01981-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40615-024-01981-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38528179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mujahid</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maddali</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oo</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of neighborhoods on diabetes risk and outcomes: centering health equity</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2023</year><volume>46</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1609</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dci23-0003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37354326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10465989</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Mujahid MS, Maddali SR, Gao X, Oo KH, Benjamin LA, Lewis TT. The impact of neighborhoods on diabetes risk and outcomes: centering health equity. Diabetes Care. 2023;46(9):1609–18. 10.2337/dci23-0003.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37354326</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dci23-0003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10465989</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>ElSayed</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aleppo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aroda</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>6. Glycemic Targets: Standards of Care in Diabetes—2023</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2022</year><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>S97</fpage><lpage>S110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc23-S006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9810469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36507646</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">ElSayed NA, Aleppo G, Aroda VR, et al. 6. Glycemic Targets: Standards of Care in Diabetes—2023. Diabetes Care. 2022;46(1):S97–110. 10.2337/dc23-S006.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc23-S006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9810469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36507646</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallisey</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring community vulnerability to natural and anthropogenic hazards: the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention's social vulnerability index</article-title><source>J Environ Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>80</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7179070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32327766</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Flanagan BE, Hallisey EJ, Adams E. Measuring community vulnerability to natural and anthropogenic hazards: the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s social vulnerability index. J Environ Health. 2018;80(10):34–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7179070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32327766</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Health Resource and Service Administration. HPSA Data Downloads. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.hrsa.gov/data/download">https://data.hrsa.gov/data/download</ext-link>. Accessed on 30 April 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakulin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pittau</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A WEAKLY INFORMATIVE DEFAULT PRIOR DISTRIBUTION FOR LOGISTIC AND OTHER REGRESSION MODELS</article-title><source>Ann Appl Stat</source><year>2008</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1360</fpage><lpage>1383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/08-aoas191</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Gelman A, Jakulin A, Pittau MG. A WEAKLY INFORMATIVE DEFAULT PRIOR DISTRIBUTION FOR LOGISTIC AND OTHER REGRESSION MODELS. Ann Appl Stat. 2008;2(4):1360–83. 10.1214/08-aoas191.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Miller KK, Crandall MS, Weber BA. Persistent poverty and place: how do persistent poverty and poverty demographics vary across the rural-urban continuum. Measuring Rural Divers. 2002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karmakar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lantz</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tipirneni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of social and demographic factors with COVID-19 incidence and death rates in the US</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e2036462</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.36462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33512520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7846939</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Karmakar M, Lantz PM, Tipirneni R. Association of social and demographic factors with COVID-19 incidence and death rates in the US. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(1):e2036462. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.36462.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33512520</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.36462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7846939</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollings</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noppert</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griggs</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melendez</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of two area-level socioeconomic deprivation indices: implications for public health research, practice, and policy</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e0292281</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0292281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37797080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10553799</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Rollings KA, Noppert GA, Griggs JJ, Melendez RA, Clarke PJ. Comparison of two area-level socioeconomic deprivation indices: implications for public health research, practice, and policy. PLoS One. 2023;18(10):e0292281. 10.1371/journal.pone.0292281.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37797080</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0292281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10553799</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diabetes, even newly defined by HbA1c testing, is associated with an increased risk of in-hospital death in adults with COVID-19</article-title><source>BMC Endocr Disord</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>56</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12902-021-00717-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33771154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7995677</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Liu Y, Lu R, Wang J, et al. Diabetes, even newly defined by HbA1c testing, is associated with an increased risk of in-hospital death in adults with COVID-19. BMC Endocr Disord. 2021;21(1):56. 10.1186/s12902-021-00717-6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33771154</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12902-021-00717-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7995677</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khunti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Prato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabbay</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buse</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19, Hyperglycemia, and New-Onset Diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2021</year><volume>44</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2645</fpage><lpage>2655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc21-1318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34625431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8669536</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Khunti K, Del Prato S, Mathieu C, Kahn SE, Gabbay RA, Buse JB. COVID-19, Hyperglycemia, and New-Onset Diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2021;44(12):2645–55. 10.2337/dc21-1318.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34625431</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc21-1318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8669536</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casagrande</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avilés-Santa</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with being unaware of having diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2017</year><volume>40</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e55</fpage><lpage>e56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc16-2626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28289042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5399654</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Menke A, Casagrande S, Avilés-Santa ML, Cowie CC. Factors associated with being unaware of having diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2017;40(5):e55–6. 10.2337/dc16-2626.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28289042</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc16-2626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5399654</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higginbotham</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segovia</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohm</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breitenstein</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social vulnerability index and health outcomes in the united states: a systematic review</article-title><source>Fam Community Health</source><year>2025</year><volume>48</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/fch.0000000000000421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39807786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11832337</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Higginbotham JK, Segovia LM, Rohm KL, Anderson CM, Breitenstein SM. Social vulnerability index and health outcomes in the united states: a systematic review. Fam Community Health. 2025;48(2):81–96. 10.1097/fch.0000000000000421.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39807786</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/FCH.0000000000000421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11832337</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Estiri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Individualized prediction of COVID-19 adverse outcomes with MLHO</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5322</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-84781-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33674708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7935934</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Estiri H, Strasser ZH, Murphy SN. Individualized prediction of COVID-19 adverse outcomes with MLHO. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1):5322. 10.1038/s41598-021-84781-x.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33674708</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-84781-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7935934</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>