<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Thorac Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Thorac Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1685</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jtd</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JTD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Thoracic Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2072-1439</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2077-6624</issn><publisher><publisher-name>AME Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12433019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12433019.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12433019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12433019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40950924</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-433</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jtd-17-08-5654</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chest computed tomography findings do not influence the decision of pneumologists regarding the diagnosis and management of pulmonary long coronavirus disease: a single center retrospective study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meiler</surname><given-names initials="S">Stefanie</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7324-2532</contrib-id><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmalenberger</surname><given-names initials="D">Daniel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malfertheiner</surname><given-names initials="M">Maximilian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names initials="I">Iris</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strotzer</surname><given-names initials="Q">Quirin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stroszczynski</surname><given-names initials="C">Christian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names initials="OW">Okka Wilkea</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Radiology</institution>, <institution>Regensburg University Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Regensburg</addr-line>, <country country="de">Germany</country>;</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Pneumology, Caritas Hospital St. Maria Donaustauf, Donaustauf</institution>, <country country="de">Germany</country>;</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Pneumology</institution>, <institution>Bayreuth Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Bayreuth</addr-line>, <country country="de">Germany</country>;</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Radiology, Caritas Hospital St. Maria Donaustauf, Donaustauf</institution>, <country country="de">Germany</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="afn1"><p><italic toggle="yes">Contributions:</italic> (I) Conception and design: OW Hamer, S Meiler; (II) Administrative support: C Stroszczynski; (III) Provision of study materials or patients: OW Hamer, M Malfertheiner, C Stroszczynski; (IV) Collection and assembly of data: S Meiler, D Schmalenberger, M Malfertheiner; I Dvorak; (V) Data analysis and interpretation: S Meiler, Q Strotzer, OW Hamer; (VI) Manuscript writing: All authors; (VII) Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><italic toggle="yes">Correspondence to:</italic> Stefanie Meiler, MD. Department of Radiology, Regensburg University Medical Center, Franz-Josef-Strauss-Allee 11, 93053 Regensburg, Germany. Email: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="stefanie.meiler@ukr.de">stefanie.meiler@ukr.de</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">496852</issue-id><fpage>5654</fpage><lpage>5662</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-09-15 15:25:19.733"><day>15</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025 AME Publishing Company. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>AME Publishing Company.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><italic toggle="yes">Open Access Statement:</italic> This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0), which permits the non-commercial replication and distribution of the article with the strict proviso that no changes or edits are made and the original work is properly cited (including links to both the formal publication through the relevant DOI and the license). See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jtd-17-08-5654.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Pulmonary symptoms are common in long coronavirus disease (COVID), yet the diagnostic value of chest computed tomography (CT) in these patients remains unclear, particularly when physical examination and pulmonary function tests are normal. This study investigates whether chest CT influences the decision of pneumologists regarding the measures taken for diagnostic work-up, the final diagnosis, the confidence in the diagnosis, and the downstream management of patients suspected to suffer from pulmonary long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>All patients presented in a dedicated long COVID outpatient clinic of a secondary care hospital that specializes in lung diseases between April 2020 and August 2021. Inclusion criteria were age ≥18 years, suspicion for long COVID syndrome of pulmonary origin according to the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) criteria and availability of a chest CT acquired during work-up. Three pneumologists evaluated the patient’s records in two rounds (round 1 without and round 2 with knowledge of CT results). Identical parameters were queried in the two runs: diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID, confidence of the diagnosis on a scale from 0 to 3, need for: bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL), transbronchial biopsy (TBB), cryobiopsy, video-assisted thoracoscopy (VATS), ergospirometry, ventilation/perfusion scintigraphy, follow-up appointment, rehabilitation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Forty-one patients were included (24 male; age 21 to 72 years, mean 55 years). In the first and second round diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID was made in an average of 10 (24%) and 11 (27%) patients (P=0.69). Confidence of diagnosis was 1.9 and 2.6 (P&lt;0.001). No statistical difference was found regarding the frequency of diagnostic measures and downstream management.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Chest CT did not influence the diagnostic decision of pneumologists for patients suspected to suffer from pulmonary long COVID. However, the confidence in the diagnosis was improved by chest CT. Still, based on our results chest CT does not routinely have to be included in the work-up of long COVID, when pulmonary function tests and auscultation are normal.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords: </title><kwd>High resolution computed tomography (HRCT)</kwd><kwd>interstitial lung disease (ILD)</kwd><kwd>long coronavirus disease (long COVID)</kwd><kwd>downstream management</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="ba" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Highlight box</title></caption><sec><title>Key findings</title><p>• Chest computed tomography (CT) did not influence the diagnostic decision for patients suspected to suffer from pulmonary long coronavirus disease (COVID). The confidence in the diagnosis, on the contrary, was improved by chest CT.</p></sec><sec><title>What is known and what is new?</title><p>• As for pulmonary long COVID chest imaging is recommended for a subgroup of patients. However, there is a lack of scientific evidence on the timing of imaging and the adequate modality. To our knowledge a prior study has not been conducted to evaluate the impact of CT on the work-up of patients suspected to suffer from pulmonary long COVID.</p><p>• We closed this gap with the present study by assessing the effect of CT on the diagnostic decision regarding the measures taken for diagnostic work-up, regarding the final diagnosis, the confidence in the diagnosis, and on the downstream management of patients. Our findings suggest that chest CT seems not to be justified in the work-up of long COVID when pulmonary function tests and auscultation are normal. Interobserver variability regarding the diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID was slight to moderate and did not increase by chest CT.</p></sec><sec><title>What is the implication, and what should change now?</title><p>• Obviously, the existing guidelines are not specific enough to allow for a clear classification of patients.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Recent years have shown that not only the acute complications, but also long-term health consequences of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection can be devastating. This includes a variety of physical, cognitive, and psychological symptoms that negatively impact daily functioning and quality of life. The term “long coronavirus disease (COVID)”, initially coined in social media, is defined by the United Kingdom National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) guideline recommendation as health complaints that persist or re-emerge 4 weeks beyond the acute illness phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>According to an Umbrella review, the frequency of long COVID in studies of adults without hospitalization varied from 7.5% to 41% (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Among adults hospitalized for COVID-19 disease, long-term health sequelae were reported in 37.6% (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Due to the magnitude of patients affected, this is a major problem not only for healthcare providers but also for economy. Currently, specialized outpatient clinics are being set up in Germany to meet the needs of the long COVID clientele. In this regard, current national and international guidelines recommend algorithms for the management of this syndrome. These include a sequence that begins with primary care, continues through specialized inpatient care or acute inpatient hospitalization, and, if long COVID syndrome persists, recommend remediation or rehabilitation (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). As for pulmonary long COVID chest imaging is recommended for a subgroup of patients (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), however, there is a lack of scientific evidence on the timing of imaging and the adequate modality. Do the benefits outweigh the effort and radiation exposure especially associated with computed tomography (CT)? What impact does imaging have on the diagnosis and the downstream management of patients?</p><p>To our knowledge a prior study has not been conducted to evaluate the impact of CT on the work-up of patients suspected to suffer from pulmonary long COVID. We closed this gap with the present study by assessing the effect of CT on the diagnostic decision regarding the measures taken for work-up, regarding the final diagnosis, the confidence in the diagnosis, and on the downstream management of patients. We present this article in accordance with the STROBE reporting checklist (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/rc" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/rc</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and its subsequent amendments. The study was approved by institutional ethics committee of the University of Regensburg (No. 20-1784-104) and individual consent for this retrospective analysis was waived.</p><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Patients</title><p>All patients presented in a dedicated long COVID outpatient clinic of a secondary care hospital specialized on lung diseases (Caritas Hospital St. Maria Donaustauf) between April 2020 and August 2021. The referring physicians were either a primary care physician or a pulmonologist in line with algorithms recommended by the guidelines. The inclusion criteria were age ≥18 years, suspicion for long COVID syndrome [as defined in the NICE guideline (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)] of pulmonary origin (e.g., chronic cough, dyspnea) and availability of a chest CT acquired during work-up. Patient data (gender, age, eventual lung diseases existing before the acute COVID infection) and characteristics of the acute COVID-infection [like need for hospital admission, acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), need for ventilation and/or extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO)] were extracted from electronic patient records or from letters provided by the referring physicist.</p></sec><sec><title>Patient work-up</title><p>Work-up in the long COVID outpatient clinic was standardized and consisted of clinical examination including auscultation, blood gas analysis, laboratory diagnostics, pulmonary function test and 6-minute walking test. CT was performed when one of the following was altered: lung function and/or diffusion capacity and/or auscultation. CT was done without contrast unless pulmonary artery embolism (PAE) was suspected. PAE was suspected in patients for whom at least one of the following was true: dyspnea and/or thoracic pain, signs of right heart strain, D-dimer increased in the three-digit range (normal range 45–500 ng/mL) without any other recognizable cause or diffusion impairment [diffusing capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide (DCLO) &lt;80%] together with at least one of the first three parameters mentioned.</p></sec><sec><title>CT image acquisition</title><p>The CT protocol in the study hospital was as follows: acquisition on a 128-slice Somatom Definition AS by Siemens Healthcare, Erlangen, Germany, automatic tube voltage selection with a reference tube voltage of 120 kV, automatic tube current modulation with the reference mAs between 20–352. Multiplanar reformations (MPR) were reconstructed in the axial plane with a slice thickness of 1 mm in lung kernel and soft tissue kernel. Additional sagittal and coronal MPRs were reconstructed with a slice thickness of 1 mm in lung kernel. In total, 51% (21/41) of the scans were contrast enhanced (CE) and 49% (20/41) unenhanced (UE). Iohexal (Accupaque 350, GE Healthcare, Chicago, Illinois, USA) was administered in a weight-adapted dose, but not more than 70 mL. Flow rate was 3 or 4 mL/s.</p><p>Nine of the 41 CT scans were performed at external hospitals. Two of them were CE and seven of them without contrast. The slice thickness varied between 1 and 4 mm in the lung kernel (four times 1 mm, one time 1.25 mm, one time 1.5 mm, two times 3 mm, one time 4 mm) and between 3 and 5 mm in the soft tissue kernel (five times 3 mm, two times 4 mm, two times 5 mm). All pictures were sent to the picture archiving and communication system (PACS, Syngo Imaging, Siemens, Erlangen, Germany).</p></sec><sec><title>CT image analysis</title><p>All CT images (acquired both in house and outside) were evaluated by a dedicated chest radiologist with 23 years of experience. Fleischner criteria were applied (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). All available prior imaging (if performed) including imaging of the acute phase was considered for the final report. The final report contained a description of all pathologies, a comment on the disease course and a statement about the most likely diagnosis [in terms of scarring, inflammation, interstitial lung disease (ILD)…].</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of patient data</title><p>All cases were evaluated independently by three senior pneumologists (I.D., D.S, M.M.) with 22, 14 and 14 years of experience, respectively. Pneumologist 1 and 3 worked in the secondary care hospital specialized on lung diseases, pneumologist 2 worked in the Department of Pneumology of the Affiliated University Hospital. All pneumologists evaluated the patients in two rounds. The time in between the two rounds was at least 2 months in order to avoid a recall bias. In the first round, the pneumologists were unaware of the results of the CT scan performed in the context of long COVID work-up. In the second round, the CT report was revealed. The remainder of information was identical in the two rounds. The three evaluators were given the patient’s records. The evaluators were blinded to personal data such as name and age. All clinical and laboratory data as well as results of prior imaging could be reviewed. For every patient the following identical parameters were queried in both of the two runs: diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID (yes/no), confidence of the diagnosis on a scale from 0 to 3 (0: very uncertain, 1: uncertain, 2: certain, 3: very certain), need for: bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) (yes/no), TBB (yes/no), cryobiopsy (yes/no), video-assisted thoracoscopy (VATS) (yes/no), ergospirometry (yes/no), ventilation/perfusion scintigraphy (yes/no), follow-up appointment (yes/no), rehabilitation (yes/no).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Age is presented as mean [standard deviation (SD)] and all categorical variables as absolute and relative frequencies. Continuous data are reported as mean (SD), ordinal data as median (range), and categorical data as absolute frequencies (percentage). SD or 95% confidence intervals (CIs) are reported where applicable. The statistical analysis did not require controlling for the family-wise error rate (FWER). Cohen’s kappa coefficient was used to quantitatively assess interrater reliability. Strength of agreement was measured according to Landis and Koch: &lt;0= poor, 0.01–0.2= slight, 0.21–0.4= fair, 0.41–0.6= moderate, 0.61–0.8= substantial and 0.81–1= almost perfect (<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Paired sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests were used to compare the confidence of diagnosis with and without knowledge of the CT report. Differences of decisions regarding diagnosis of COVID-associated pulmonary disease (PD), further diagnostic measures, and all parameters of downstream management between the two rounds were analyzed by using the McNemar-Test. A P value ≤0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p><p>All analyses were performed using R, version 3.6.1 (The R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Overall, 628 patients presented in the long COVID outpatient clinic during the inclusion period. Five hundred eighty-seven patients had to be excluded because they did not receive a chest CT. Forty-one patients met the inclusion criteria of the study. The study population consisted of 24 males (59%) and 17 females (41%) patients, aged from 21 to 72 years (mean 55 years, SD 9).</p><sec><title>Before and during acute COVID-19 infection</title><p>Twelve percent (5/41) of patients had a pre-existing ILD. These included two cases of hypersensitivity pneumonitis, one case of sarcoidosis and two cases of unclassifiable ILD. Apart from asthma in four more cases, no other lung diseases were present. In the acute phase of the infection, 17% of patients (7/41) needed mechanical ventilation, 7% (3/41) needed ECMO treatment and 15% (6/41) suffered from ARDS. In 32% (13/41) of patients a chest X-ray of the acute phase was available. In 49% (20/41) of cases, a chest CT scan of the acute phase was available. Out of these 20 scans, PAE was seen in 20% (4/20) and ruled out in 50% (10/20). The remaining 30% of scans (6/20) had been performed UE. Please see <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 1</italic></xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Parameters before and during the acute phase of COVID-19 infection</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="61.33%" span="1"/><col width="38.67%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before and during acute phase</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Values (N=41)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (male)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 [59]</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55±9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-existing lung disease</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 [12]</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mechanical ventilation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 [17]</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECMO</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 [7]</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARDS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 [15]</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest radiograph available</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 [32]</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest CT available</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 [49]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation or n [%]. ARDS, acute respiratory distress syndrome; COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019; CT, computed tomography; ECMO, extracorporeal membrane oxygenation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Diagnostic decisions depending on knowledge of CT result</title><sec><title>Diagnosis of COVID-associated PD</title><sec><title>First round (without knowledge of the findings of CT performed during work up for long COVID)</title><p>In an average of 24% (10/41) of patients, a diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID was made. For the individual assessments of the pneumologists please see <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Decisions of pneumologists without (round 1) and with (round 2) knowledge of CT findings</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="18.89%" span="1"/><col width="10.92%" span="1"/><col width="9.64%" span="1"/><col width="6.6%" span="1"/><col width="0.38%" span="1"/><col width="9.82%" span="1"/><col width="9.48%" span="1"/><col width="6.63%" span="1"/><col width="0.38%" span="1"/><col width="9.86%" span="1"/><col width="10.23%" span="1"/><col width="7.17%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1">Decisions</th><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">Pneumologist 1</th><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1"/><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">Pneumologist 2</th><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1"/><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">Pneumologist 3</th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">Round 1</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Round 2</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">Round 1</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Round 2</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">Round 1</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Round 2</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-associated PD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 [15]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 [15]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 [39]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 [49]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 [20]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 [17]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean confidence (95% CI)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (1.8, 2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (2.8, 3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (1.4, 1.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.8, 2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (2, 2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (2.6, 2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 [5]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 [12]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 [10]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 [5]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [2]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBB</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [2]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 [5]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cryobiopsy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [2]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VATS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ergospirometry</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 [15]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [2]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 [68]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 [98]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 [100]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 [100]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT UE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 [10]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 [34]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 [17]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT CE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 [27]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 [12]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 [39]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 [39]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 [10]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V/P scintigraphy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 [10]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 [5]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 [41]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 [37]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 [7]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 [7]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">   Total number of diagnostic measures<sup>†</sup> per round</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">   Total number of diagnostic measures<sup>†</sup> overall</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1">31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1">145</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1">95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 [34]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 [41]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 [68]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 [51]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 [100]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 [100]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rehabilitation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 [39]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 [34]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 [44]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 [29]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 [59]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 [7]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as n [%] unless otherwise specified. <sup>†</sup>, the following were counted as diagnostic measures: BAL, TBB, cryobiopsy, VATS, ergospirometry, CT CE and V/P scintigraphy. CT UE was only captured in the first round and was therefore not counted. Follow-up and rehabilitation were not counted as diagnostic measures. BAL, bronchoalveolar lavage; CI, confidence interval; COVID, coronavirus disease; CT, computed tomography; CT CE, CT contrast enhanced; CT UE, CT unenhanced; NA, not applicable; PD, pulmonary disease; TBB, transbronchial biopsy; VATS, video-assisted thoracoscopy; V/P scintigraphy, ventilation perfusion scintigraphy.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Second round (with knowledge of the findings of CT performed during work up of long COVID)</title><p>Diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID was made in an average of 27% (11/41) of patients. For the individual assessments of the pneumologists please see <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>.</p><p>The decision of all three raters taken together regarding COVID-associated PD did not change significantly without and with knowledge of the CT report (P=0.69). Please see <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Decisions of pneumologists overall without (round 1) and with (round 2) knowledge of CT findings</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="31.98%" span="1"/><col width="28.16%" span="1"/><col width="26.62%" span="1"/><col width="13.24%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decisions (overall)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Round 1</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Round 2</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-associated PD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 [24]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 [27]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean confidence (95 % CI)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (1.8, 2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (2.4, 2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 [6]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 [6]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBB</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [1]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 [2]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cryobiopsy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [1]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VATS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 [0]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ergospirometry</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 [61]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 [67]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT UE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 [20]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT CE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 [25]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 [17]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V/P scintigraphy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 [20]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 [16]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">   Total number of diagnostic measures<sup>†</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 (R1 =21, R2 =67, R3 =50)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (R1 =10, R2 =78, R3 =45)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 [67]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 [64]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rehabilitation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 [47]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 [24]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as n [%] unless otherwise specified. <sup>†</sup>, the following were counted as diagnostic measures: BAL, TBB, cryobiopsy, VATS, ergospirometry, CT CE and V/P scintigraphy. CT UE was only captured in the first round and was therefore not counted. Follow-up and rehabilitation were not counted as diagnostic measures. R1, Rater 1; R2, Rater 2; R3, Rater 3. BAL, bronchoalveolar lavage; CI, confidence interval; COVID, coronavirus disease; CT CE, computed tomography contrast enhanced; CT UE, CT unenhanced; NA, not applicable; PD, pulmonary disease; TBB, transbronchial biopsy; VATS, video-assisted thoracoscopy; V/P scintigraphy, ventilation perfusion scintigraphy.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Confidence of diagnosis</title><p>Between the two rounds the mean (95% CI) confidence of diagnosis increased from 1.9 (1.8, 2.1) to 2.9 (2.8, 3) in Rater 1 (P&lt;0.001) and from 2.2 (2, 2.5) to 2.7 (2.6, 2.9) in Rater 3 (P&lt;0.001), see <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>. Although not evident from mean and CI, the frequency distribution also shows a significant increase in confidence for Rater 2 between rounds 1 and 2 (P=0.02), see <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>. Overall, the mean confidence of diagnosis increased from 1.9 (1.8, 2.1) to 2.6 (2.4, 2.7) (P&lt;0.001), see <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Further diagnostic measures and downstream management depending on knowledge of CT result</title><p>The decision of Rater 1 regarding further diagnostic measures and downstream management did not change significantly. Rater 2 ordered significantly more ergospirometries (P=0.001) and significantly less follow-ups (P=0.05) after knowledge of the CT findings. Rater 3 was significantly less likely to initiate rehabilitation with knowledge of the CT findings (P&lt;0.001). Please see <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 1</italic></xref> and <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Tables 2,4</italic></xref><xref rid="t4" ref-type="table"/>.</p><fig position="float" id="f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Decisions of pneumologists regarding diagnostic measures and downstream management without (round 1) and with (round 2) knowledge of CT findings. BAL, bronchoalveolar lavage; CT, computed tomography; CT CE, CT contrast enhanced; CT UE, CT unenhanced; TBB, transbronchial biopsy; VATS, video-assisted thoracoscopy; V/P scintigraphy, ventilation perfusion scintigraphy.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jtd-17-08-5654-f1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Total number of diagnostic measures—Rater 1 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Rater 2 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Rater 3</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="23.37%" span="1"/><col width="24.51%" span="1"/><col width="29.19%" span="1"/><col width="22.93%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1">Raters</th><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">P value</th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">R1</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R2</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R1 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> R2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R1 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> R3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R2 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> R3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>R1, Rater 1; R2, Rater 2; R3, Rater 3.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Interobserver variability</title><p>Without knowledge of the CT findings, pneumologist 1 and 2 showed a slight strength of agreement for diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID (κ=0.19), pneumologist 1 and 3 showed a fair strength of agreement (κ=0.31) and pneumologist 2 and 3 showed a moderate strength of agreement (κ=0.44). With knowledge of the CT findings, pneumologist 1 and 2 showed a slight strength of agreement (κ=0.11), pneumologist 1 and 3 showed a moderate strength of agreement (κ=0.54) and pneumologist 2 and 3 showed a slight strength of agreement (κ=0.16). Please see also <xref rid="t5" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 5</italic></xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Interobserver variability regarding diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID without and with knowledge of CT findings</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="27.53%" span="1"/><col width="23.18%" span="1"/><col width="27.6%" span="1"/><col width="21.69%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1">The knowledge of CT findings</th><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">κ</th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">R1 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> R2</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R1 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> R3</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R2 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> R3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>COVID, coronavirus disease; CT, computed tomography; R1, Rater 1; R2, Rater 2; R3, Rater 3.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The number of patients complaining of prolonged symptoms regarding their physical health and wellbeing long after an acute infection SARS-CoV-2 is increasing (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The term long COVID was initially coined in social media by Dr. Elisa Perego in May 2020 (<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). It took no less than 7 months for it to be defined for the first time by the United Kingdom National Health Service (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), followed by the adoption by other institutions worldwide (<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The disease, which did not exist 3 years ago, currently affects approximately 1.9 million Britons according to National Health Service (NHS) (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Chest CT played and continues to play an important role in the work-up of COVID-19. A vast number of studies have been published on pulmonary abnormalities during and after acute infection with SARS-CoV-2. Several papers have reported on long term lung sequelae (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>-<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Given the current situation, there is likely to be an increasing demand for imaging (<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). However, to the best of our knowledge the role of CT in the assessment, diagnosis and management of pulmonary long COVID has not yet been explored. The aim of this retrospective study was to fill this gap.</p><p>A total of 41 patients suspected to suffer from pulmonary long COVID were independently analyzed by three pneumologists. For all patients a chest CT was performed as part of the work-up. In the first round, pneumologist were blinded to the results of CT, in the second round CT findings were revealed.</p><sec><title>Diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID</title><p>Pulmonary long COVID was diagnosed in 24% of patients in the first round and 27% in the second round. Thus, the diagnosis was confirmed only in a minority of patients although all of them had demonstrated an impaired lung function test or a conspicuous auscultation. Knowledge of the CT results did not influence the pneumologists’ assessment. However, the confidence of diagnosis was significantly higher knowing the CT findings.</p><p>Interobserver variability was slight to moderate and did overall not reach clinical requirements. Of note, knowledge of CT findings did not improve the level of agreement. Obviously, clinicians seem to have difficulties to classify the clinical picture adequately. Pulmonary long COVID is a complex condition with a heterogeneous appearance and the existing guidelines seem not to be suited to allow for a robust classification.</p></sec><sec><title>Further diagnostic measures and downstream management</title><p>In the vast majority of cases, decision on further diagnostic measures and downstream management of patients was not altered by the knowledge of the CT findings. One rater wished for significantly more ergospirometries but significantly less follow-ups when provided with the CT findings. Another rater opted for significantly less rehabilitation measures. Only one rater wished for significantly less diagnostic measures in total, but the other two raters did not show a significant difference regarding their request of examinations. Overall, there also was no significant difference without and with knowledge of the CT report. Thus, CT might increase the wish for further functional assessment but help to avoid unnecessary downstream measures.</p><p>Interestingly a significant difference was found between the raters regarding the number of further diagnostic measures wished for. This difference persisted independently of CT findings. The pneumologist employed in the university hospital (Rater 2) ordered significantly more examinations than the other two raters who worked in the district hospital (specialized lung clinic). Patient handling seems to be influenced by the available resources. Also, Rater 1 ordered significantly less examinations than Rater 2 and Rater 3. Rater 1 was by far the most experienced physician, which may be the reason for this finding.</p><p>The study has limitations. According to the hospital specific standard operating procedure the indication for a CT in the work-up of suspected pulmonary long COVID was limited to patients with restriction on body plethysmography, diffusion impairment (DLCO &lt;60%) or sclerosiphonia on auscultation. Thus, the cohort represented a subset of patients with a rather high probability for lung parenchyma pathologies. Even in this subgroup CT did not alter the diagnostic decisions. Hence, it is very unlikely that this would be the case for less severely affected patients.</p><p>The long term outcome of the patients was not registered. It is therefore not possible to evaluate if the pneumologists classified the patients correctly or if the CT findings could have predicted the outcome. However, the aim of the study was to identify the impact of CT findings on the diagnostic decisions regardless of the long term consequences.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, our analysis revealed that chest CT did not influence the diagnostic decision for patients suspected to suffer from pulmonary long COVID. The confidence in the diagnosis, on the contrary, was improved by chest CT. Still, based on our results CT seems not to be justified in the work-up of long COVID when pulmonary function tests and auscultation are normal. Interobserver variability regarding the diagnosis of pulmonary long COVID was rather low and did not increase by chest CT. Obviously, the existing guidelines are not specific enough to allow for a clear classification of patients.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary</title><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><p>The article’s supplementary files as</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="anchor" id="su1" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-08-5654-rc.pdf" id="d67e1101" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-433</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-08-5654-coif.pdf" id="d67e1104" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-433</object-id></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>None.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><italic toggle="yes">Reporting Checklist:</italic> The authors have completed the STROBE reporting checklist. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/rc" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/rc</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><italic toggle="yes">Funding:</italic> None.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><italic toggle="yes">Conflicts of Interest:</italic> All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/coif" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/coif</ext-link>). The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/dss" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/dss</ext-link>
<fig id="d67e1137" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-08-5654-dss.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-433</object-id></media></fig>
</p></sec><notes><p content-type="note added in proof"><italic toggle="yes">Ethical Statement:</italic> The authors are accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and its subsequent amendments. The study was approved by institutional ethics committee of the University of Regensburg (No. 20-1784-104) and individual consent for this retrospective analysis was waived.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">National Institute for Health and Care Excellence: Clinical Guidelines. COVID-19 rapid guideline: managing the long-term effects of COVID-19. London: National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE). Copyright © NICE 2020; 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nittas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Long COVID Through a Public Health Lens: An Umbrella Review.</article-title>
<source>Public Health Rev</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<elocation-id>1604501</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/phrs.2022.1604501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35359614</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8963488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koczulla</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ankermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrends</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>S1-Leitlinie Long-/Post-COVID.</article-title>
<source>Pneumologie</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>855</fpage>-<lpage>907</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-1946-3230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36479679</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clinical management of COVID-19: living guideline. World Health Organization; 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35917394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansell</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bankier</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacMahon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Fleischner Society: glossary of terms for thoracic imaging.</article-title>
<source>Radiology</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>246</volume>:<fpage>697</fpage>-<lpage>722</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2462070712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18195376</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data.</article-title>
<source>Biometrics</source>
<year>1977</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">843571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations.</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Margalit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss-Ottolenghi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Persistence of Long COVID Symptoms Two Years After SARS-CoV-2 Infection: A Prospective Longitudinal Cohort Study.</article-title>
<source>Viruses</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1955</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v16121955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39772261</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11680455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Perego E. Twitter post.Available online: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/elisaperego78/status/1263172084055838721" ext-link-type="uri">https://twitter.com/elisaperego78/status/1263172084055838721</ext-link> (accessed August 23, 2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabady</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altenberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Guideline S1: Long COVID: Diagnostics and treatment strategies.</article-title>
<source>Wien Klin Wochenschr</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00508-021-01974-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34851455</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8633909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniou</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasarmidi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>European Respiratory Society statement on long COVID follow-up.</article-title>
<source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<elocation-id>2102174</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.02174-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35144991</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9349784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Office for National Statistics (ONS). Prevalence of ongoing symptoms following coronavirus (COVID-19) infection in the UK: 30 March 2023. Statistical bulletin. Released 30 March 2023. Available online: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ons.gov.uk/</ext-link> (accessed August 23, 2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alwalid</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Six-month Follow-up Chest CT Findings after Severe COVID-19 Pneumonia.</article-title>
<source>Radiology</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>299</volume>:<fpage>E177</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2021203153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33497317</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7841877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnweber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahanic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizzini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cardiopulmonary recovery after COVID-19: an observational prospective multicentre trial.</article-title>
<source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<elocation-id>2003481</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.03481-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33303539</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7736754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pulmonary function and chest computed tomography abnormalities 6-12 months after recovery from COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
<source>Respir Res</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-022-02163-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36068582</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9446643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical status of patients 1 year after hospital discharge following recovery from COVID-19: a prospective cohort study.</article-title>
<source>Ann Intensive Care</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13613-022-01034-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35816225</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9272871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Longitudinal Assessment of Chest CT Findings and Pulmonary Function after COVID-19 Infection.</article-title>
<source>Radiology</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>307</volume>:<elocation-id>e222888</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.222888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36786698</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9969419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic Lung Injury after COVID-19 Pneumonia: Clinical, Radiologic, and Histopathologic Perspectives.</article-title>
<source>Radiology</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>310</volume>:<elocation-id>e231643</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.231643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38193836</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10831480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocchino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capitelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Chest CT Lung Abnormalities 1 Year after COVID-19: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis.</article-title>
<source>Radiology</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>308</volume>:<elocation-id>e230535</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.230535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37404150</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>CT-based Assessment at 6-Month Follow-up of COVID-19 Pneumonia patients in China.</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>5028</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-54920-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38424447</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10904828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alghamdi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>REM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Post-acute COVID syndrome (long COVID): What should radiographers know and the potential impact for imaging services.</article-title>
<source>Radiography (Lond)</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>28</volume>
<issue>Suppl 1</issue>:<fpage>S93</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.radi.2022.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36109264</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9468096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article id="jtd-17-08-5654-prf" article-type="reviewer-report"><front-stub><title-group><article-title>Peer Review File</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p>Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/prf" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-433/prf</ext-link></p><fig id="d67e1696" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-08-5654-prf.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig></body></sub-article></article></pmc-articleset>