<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4691</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjph</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjph</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2753-4294</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12581019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12581019.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12581019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12581019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41190342</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjph-2024-002082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjph-2024-002082</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Residual cardiopulmonary manifestations following COVID-19: a Tanzanian ambispective study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1192-4148</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Osati</surname><given-names initials="EFO">Elisha Fred Otieno</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagu</surname><given-names initials="TJ">Tumaini Joseph</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangeda</surname><given-names initials="RZ">Raphael Z</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shayo</surname><given-names initials="GA">Grace Ambrose</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Internal Medicine</institution>, <institution>Muhimbili National Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Dar es Salaam</addr-line>, <country>Tanzania, United Republic of</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Internal Medicine</institution>, <institution>Muhimbili University of Health and Allied Sciences</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Dar es Salaam</addr-line>, <country>Tanzania, United Republic of</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Ministry of Health</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Dar es Salaam</addr-line>, <country>Tanzania, United Republic of</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Pharmaceutical Microbiology</institution>, <institution>Muhimbili University of Health and Allied Sciences</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Dar es Salaam</addr-line>, <country>Tanzania, United Republic of</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><p>Additional supplemental material is published online only. To view, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjph-2024-002082" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjph-2024-002082</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>None declared.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Dr Elisha Fred Otieno Osati; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elishaoosati@gmail.com">elishaoosati@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">481910</issue-id><elocation-id>e002082</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-05 09:25:13.180"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2025. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjph-2-Suppl_1.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjph-2-Suppl_1.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Residual COVID-19 sequelae create a public health concern as they add to the already heavy burden of non-communicable diseases. We set out to investigate the magnitude of residual cardiopulmonary manifestations postacute COVID-19 and their associated factors in Tanzania.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This was an ambispective study conducted between 26 March 2021 and 30 July 2021, among 712 hospitalised adults confirmed with SARS-CoV-2 in five tertiary-level hospitals in Tanzania. Retrospective data were analysed to determine baseline characteristics of the patients during acute COVID-19 admission. This was linked to prospective data that were collected 2 years postacute hospitalisation with COVID-19 to determine cardiopulmonary complications among these patients. Radiological pulmonary abnormalities were assessed by contrasted CT scan. Lung function tests were measured using a spirometer. Pulmonary hypertension and heart failure were confirmed by a transthoracic echocardiography. Generalised estimating equations were used to assess the associations between sociodemographic factors, clinical characteristics, treatment modalities and residual cardiopulmonary sequelae.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>About half 317/712 (44.5%) were diagnosed with residual cardiopulmonary complications. Approximately 54% of participants were male. Median age (IQR) was 60 (48–69) years. Cardiopulmonary sequelae were significantly associated with body mass index (BMI) ≥25.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup> compared with those with BMI &lt;25.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (adjusted OR (aOR) (95% CI)=3.4 (2.47 to 4.84), p&lt;0.001), smokers compared with non-smokers (aOR (95% CI)=2.39 (1.09 to 5.23), p=0.030] and among participants who did not receive steroids during the acute COVID-19 (aOR (95% CI)= 1.62(1.16 to 1.92), p=0.042].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The independent predictors of residual cardiopulmonary manifestations due to COVID-19 were overweight, cigarette smoking, hypoxia and non-use of steroids during the acute phase of COVID-19 disease. Public health interventions addressing weight reduction and smoking cessation in conjunction with steroid use in acute COVID-19 may largely reduce the incidence of cardiopulmonary long COVID-19.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>Cardiovascular Diseases</kwd><kwd>Disease Outbreaks</kwd><kwd>HIV</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Ministry of Health Tanzania</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>Grant/Award Number: Not Applicable</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec><title>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Long-term cardiopulmonary sequelae following COVID-19 recovery are observed more often in individuals in the Americas, Europe and Asia compared with Africa.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The majority of the affected individuals are mainly male, aged 60 years and above, with comorbidities like diabetes mellitus, hypertension, obesity and smoking.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Long-term complications of COVID-19 present more or less the same in an African country, Tanzania, as they do in other parts of the world.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Overweight, cigarette smoking, hypoxia and non-use of steroids at admission predicted long-term cardiopulmonary sequelae of COVID-19 in Tanzania, signifying more or less the same complications of COVID-19 patients worldwide.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, PRACTICE OR POLICY</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Public health interventions addressing weight reduction and smoking cessation in conjunction with steroid use in acute COVID-19 may largely reduce the incidence of long-term cardiopulmonary sequelae of COVID-19.</p></list-item><list-item><p>This study fills a gap in African data on post-COVID sequelae, and it will inform future regional health policies or guidelines for care and management of COVID-19 complications.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> COVID-19 affects not only the respiratory system but also various organs and systems with an extensive spectrum of local and systemic clinical presentation. Although primarily a respiratory illness, COVID-19 is associated with complications across multiple systems, including cardiovascular,<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> haematological,<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1 5</sup></xref> hepatic, neurological<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 6</sup></xref> and renal.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1 7</sup></xref> During the acute phase, common presentations included fever (60–87%), cough (72–85%) and fatigue (20–36%).<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Dyspnoea and chest pain were also frequently reported (around 25%),<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11 12</sup></xref> along with neurological symptoms like headache (34%) and altered smell/taste (7%).<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 13 14</sup></xref> Other reported acute symptoms included myalgia (up to 34%),<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8 10 12</sup></xref> nausea, anorexia, sore throat and gastrointestinal issues.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 6</sup></xref></p><p>Some of the survivors have chronic features and functional limitations that can be considered a pandemic within a pandemic.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> The symptoms and functional limitations are found not only in the respiratory system but also in cardiovascular, neurologic, musculoskeletal and other systems. Collectively, these limitations are termed ‘postacute sequelae of COVID-19’ (PASC).<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> The term ‘long COVID<italic toggle="yes">’ </italic>refers to symptoms lasting more than 30 days, while the term ‘post<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>COVID syndrome’ is used for symptoms persisting for at least 12 weeks.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> About 5–10% of previous COVID-19 patients have been experiencing PASC.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> This is to say, PASC is expected to occur in approximately 37.7–75.3 million people out of 753 million COVID-19 survivors reported as of March 2023.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> This high number adds to the pool of non-communicable disease burden.</p><p>A recent meta-analysis of pulmonary function tests of previous COVID-19 patients found a decreased diffusing capacity for carbon monoxide in 35% of COVID-19 survivors.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> The findings correlated with residual ground-glass opacity, reticulation and air trapping.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></p><p>Spirometry findings are often normal or only mildly abnormal, even for severe cases, although total lung capacity is mildly decreased in some patients with CT abnormalities 3 months after mechanical ventilation.<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> The restrictive and obstructive lung function abnormalities are relatively uncommon findings.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20 21</sup></xref> A 1-year multicentre follow-up study of 287 patients reported restrictive lung function abnormalities in 7% of COVID-19 survivors, an obstructive lung function abnormality in 3.8%.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Similar frequencies are reported in a meta-analysis.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref></p><p>While imaging abnormalities often improve over time, some patients may experience persistent lung damage. A study on severe COVID-19 illness found that 58% of patients had complete resolution of lung damage within 6 months. However, 35% showed fibrosis, suggesting potential long-term scarring.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Some patients with severe COVID-19 have substantial lung abnormalities, including fibrosis, requiring lung transplantation in some cases.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref></p><p>COVID-19 survivors, regardless of pre-existing conditions, have been reported to have abnormal left ventricular ejection fraction, abnormal tricuspid annular plane systolic excursion (TAPSE) and higher left ventricular volume than healthy controls.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> Other studies reported COVID-19 survivors have a 2.3 risk of developing heart failure (HF), a 1.62 risk of developing cardiomyopathy and 1.75 risk of developing cardiac arrest.<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref></p><p>Previous studies in COVID-19 patients reported that patients who were 60 years or older, male or presented with low oxygen saturation (SpO<sub>2</sub>) levels at the time of admission were at higher risk of developing late complications of COVID-19 and mortality.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Studies on postacute COVID-19 sequelae showed that smoking is one of the risk factors for the development of cardiopulmonary complications from COVID-19.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></p><p>The most common baseline comorbidities associated with post-COVID-19 sequelae in other studies included hypertension (affecting 7.7% of COVID-19 patients),<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12 29</sup></xref> diabetes mellitus (4.6%),<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12 29</sup></xref> cardiovascular disease (2.6%)<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> and other comorbidities (2.6%) at baseline.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref></p><p>Management of COVID-19 and its complications is largely symptomatic,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> targeting to address inflammation, hypercoagulability, oxygenation, vitamin and supplements, restoration and maintenance of hydration, prophylactic antibiotics and use of promising antivirals.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> It has been found that COVID-19 patients who received systemic steroids had a lower risk of developing adverse outcomes such as mortality and long-term complications of postacute COVID-19.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Other medications reported to reduce the risk for long-term complications of postacute COVID-19 include remdesivir<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> and ivermectin.<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> However, the recent clinical trial report does not recommend ivermectin in COVID-19 patients.<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> COVID-19 patients who received COVID-19 vaccines presented with less severe disease and adverse outcomes of SARS-CoV-2 infection.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9 36</sup></xref> In Tanzania, over 40 000 confirmed cases resulted in 846 deaths.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> In January 2022, just 2.8% of Tanzanians were vaccinated against COVID-19. By May 2023, vaccination rates increased to 58.3% of the eligible individuals.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref></p><p>Post-COVID-19 complications 2 years after the acute illness remain understudied globally. This study therefore aimed at investigating residual cardiopulmonary manifestations of patients who survived COVID-19 in selected referral hospitals in Tanzania.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study design and setting </title><p>This was an ambispective study involving both retrospective and prospective data collections. The third variant of cohort studies, ambispective or ambidirectional studies, uses pre-existing data, documents events and phenomena that have already occurred, and allows for prospective/future monitoring.</p><p>Data were collected in five tertiary hospitals representing all zones of Tanzania. The hospitals were selected conveniently due to their ability to manage and treat severe respiratory diseases, like COVID-19. The management of COVID-19 in all included hospitals followed the 2021 COVID-19 treatment guidelines of Tanzania.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> COVID-19 vaccines were not accessible in Tanzania until September 2021.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Data collection</title><p>We reviewed electronic and hardcopy medical record data of patients aged 18 years or older who were admitted to participating hospitals between 26 March 2021 and 30 July 2021, with PCR-confirmed COVID-19. PCR tests/reagents were not always available in the country before March 2021; thus, patients seen in those hospitals during that time were not included in this study. Selection of patients admitted between 26 March 2021 and 30 July 2021 was also due to the severe Delta variant of COVID-19, which was predominant during that period as compared with the Omicron variant, which came later. Patients with the Delta variant were expected to have more and more severe sequelae of COVID-19 than Omicron.</p><p>Patients who had more than 10% incomplete sociodemographic and clinical features data were excluded from the analysis. Also, patients who were missing radiological imaging at admission were excluded from analysis. In the present study, retrospective data collection was done to determine baseline characteristics of patients when they were admitted with acute COVID-19. Prospective data were collected to determine cardiopulmonary complications 2 years postacute COVID-19 infection. A total of 864 eligible patients were available and invited to participate in the prospective study; among them, 712 consented and were then recruited to participate in the prospective study (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). Most of the participants who declined to participate had similar sociodemographic characteristics to those who consented to be involved in the study. The majority of them declined due to their busy schedules. All patients underwent a contrasted CT scan of the chest with the following exceptions: 13 pregnant women were not subjected to CT scans, while 31 patients with renal impairments did CT scans without contrast.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Distribution of comorbidities and/or risk factors of COVID-19 at baseline. CKD, chronic kidney disease; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; TB, tuberculosis.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjph-2-Suppl_1-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Data were collected for 6 months, from November 2022 to May 2023. Electronic clinical research forms created in Research Electronic Data Capture (REDCap) software<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> were used to document both retrospective (baseline) and prospective (follow-up) patient data. Baseline sociodemographic factors, clinical characteristics including comorbidities, radiological findings at admission, treatment modalities and in-hospital mortality were collected from the patients’ files. A total of 712 participants were conveniently selected to participate in the prospective study from the list of patients identified during retrospective data collection.</p><p>Lung functions were measured using spirometry (EasyOne) manufactured by ndd Medizintechnik AG from Zurich. Switzerland. Forced expiratory volume in the first second (FEV<sub>1</sub>), forced vital capacity (FVC) and the ratio of FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC were determined. Participants with FEV<sub>1</sub> ≤75% of predicted were defined as having obstructive lung disease, while those with FVC ≤80% and a normal or increased ratio of FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC or merely decreased FVC ≤80% of predicted were defined as having restrictive lung disease. Mixed lung obstruction and restriction were defined as a decrease of both FEV<sub>1</sub> and FVC below expected values with a normal or increase of their ratio.<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref></p><p>Pulmonary hypertension (PHT) estimation and HF were determined using transthoracic echocardiogram (GE Vivid 3 Ultrasound 2D Machine, made in Milwaukee County, Wisconsin, USA, in 2010). PHT was measured using Spectro Doppler (if there was no tricuspid regurgitation) or continuous wave Doppler (if tricuspid regurgitation was present) in apical four-chamber view with the tricuspid valve fully opened; the cursor was placed at the middle of the fully opened tricuspid valve, and tricuspid velocity was measured. A value of more than 25 mm Hg was defined as PHT.<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> Right ventricular heart function was determined by measuring TAPSE.<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> TAPSE &lt;17 mm was defined as right ventricular systolic dysfunction. The radiology and cardiology teams agreed on the measurement modalities of CT scans, echocardiography and electrocardiography. Final results were entered after the consensus of the teams through teleradiology discussion.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>With the sample size of 712, there was an 80% power to detect a risk factor with a prevalence of 0.06 if it had an OR of at least 1.4. Study data were collected and managed using REDCap software.<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> Analysis was performed using STATA V.17. The sociodemographic, clinical and radiological characteristics of the patients were categorised, presented as frequencies and proportions and compared using the χ<sup>2</sup> test. The McNemar test was used to compare cardiopulmonary manifestations observed at baseline to those in the follow-up time of the study. Continuous variables were presented as medians and IQRs and were compared by the Wilcoxon rank sum test. Generalised estimating equations (GEEs) model analysis was used to assess the associations between sociodemographic factors, clinical presentations, comorbidities, treatment modalities and residual cardiopulmonary post-COVID-19 complications. 95% CIs and p values were used to decide on the statistical significance. Some potential risk factors that have been widely reported in the literature were included in the univariate model. Variables with p values ≤0.2 in the univariate model were included in a multivariate model. Variables with low diversity (eg, binary variables with a prevalence of under 2% in one category) and variables with large numbers of missing data were not included in the model regardless of whether they met other criteria. A p value &lt;0.05 was considered significant in all analyses.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>Permission to use patients’ archived data for the retrospective study was obtained from the heads of the participating hospitals. All participants consented to participate in the prospective study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Sociodemographic</title><p>The median age (IQR) of the participants was 60 (48–69) years, with 380 (53.4%) in the age group above 60 years. Smokers comprised 38 (5.3%) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Sociodemographic and baseline characteristics of the study participants</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Age group (years)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;45</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45–59</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥60</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">380</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">380</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Cigarette smoking</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smokers</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-smokers</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">674</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Radiological chest abnormalities</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ground-glass opacity</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">553</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pulmonary consolidation</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pulmonary nodules</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Reticular interstitial opacity</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Baseline oxygen saturation</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;94%</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">467</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Baseline respiratory rate (N=591)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥30</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used ivermectin</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used steroids</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Comorbidities and symptoms at the time of hospital admission due to acute COVID-19 illness</title><p>The most common comorbidities among the 712 participants during the acute admission were hypertension (41%), body mass index (BMI) ≥25.0 kg/m² (35.7%) and diabetes mellitus (21.6%) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). At admission, the majority of patients presented with cough (74.1%), dyspnoea (68.8%), fever (55.5%), fatigue (53.8%), chest pain (33.1%) and headache (27.5%). With regard to chest roentgenograms at admission, the majority presented with ground-glass opacity 553 (77.7%), followed by reticular interstitial opacity 255 (35.8%), pulmonary consolidation 228 (32.0%) and pulmonary nodules 63 (8.8%) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). Two-thirds of patients had an SpO<sub>2</sub> of less than 94%, 497 (65.6%) and were tachypnoeic based on the WHO definition<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> with a respiratory rate ≥30 at admission (101, 17.1%) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>).</p><p>Nearly half of participants, 317/712 (44.5%), were diagnosed with residual cardiopulmonary complications. Among 712 patients, 640 had the radiological abnormalities of COVID-19 at baseline. Out of 640 with radiological abnormalities at baseline, 317 (49.5%) remained with the abnormalities 2 years later, which is statistically significant; the McNemar test gives p&lt;0.001 (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Changes in radiological features 2 years postacute COVID-19 compared with baseline.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjph-2-Suppl_1-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Residual cardiopulmonary abnormalities were significantly more often seen in patients who presented with abnormalities in chest roentgenograms than in patients without abnormalities at baseline (during the acute hospital admission). Respectively, these cardiopulmonary abnormalities were bronchiectasis (22.2% vs 11.9, p=0.005), cavities in the lungs (18.2% vs 9%, p=0.005), PHT (32.3% vs 19.7%, p=0.005) and HF (30.3% vs 22.1%, p=0.04) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>The association between baseline radiological chest abnormalities and follow-up COVID-19 radiological features, N=712</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Residual Chest abnormalities</th><th colspan="3" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Baseline radiological chest abnormalities</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">P value</th></tr><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present<break/>n (%)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent<break/>n (%)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total, N=712<break/>n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Fibrotic reticulations (N=686)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (29.3)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163 (27.6)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (26.5)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">0.732</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (70.7)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">427 (72.4)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">497 (69.8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Honey combing fibrosis (N=689)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (6.1)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (3.4)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">0.247</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (93.9)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">570 (96.6)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">663 (93.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Bronchiectasis (N=696)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (22.2)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (11.9)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (13.9)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (77.8)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">520 (88.1)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">597 (83.8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Lung cavities (N=689)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (18.2)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (9.0)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (9.9)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (81.8)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">537 (91.0)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">618 (86.8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Pulmonary hypertension (N=687)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (32.3)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (19.7)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (20.8)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (67.7)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">472 (80.3)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">539 (75.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Heart failure (N=688)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (30.3)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (22.1)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (22.5)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (69.7)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">459 (77.9)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">528 (74.2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Obstructive lung disease (N=680)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (23.5)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (21.8)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (21.1)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">0.716</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (76.5)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">455 (78.2)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">530 (74.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1">Restrictive lung disease (N=676)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (27.6)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (27.3)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185 (25.9)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">0.965</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (72.4)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">420 (72.7)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">491 (68.9)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Baseline radiological chest abnormalities were not significantly associated with residual reticular fibrosis (29.3% vs 27.6%, p=0.732); honeycombing fibrosis (6.1% vs 3.4%, p=0.247); obstructive lung disease (23.5% vs 21.8%, p=0.716) and restrictive lung disease (27.6% vs 27.3%, p=0.965) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).</p><p>However, the median FVC% was significantly higher only in men 2.84 (2.23, 2.99) compared with women 2.60 (1.97, 2.92), p&lt;0.001; and in participants with baseline ground-glass opacity 2.79 (1.97, 2.96) compared with those without baseline ground-glass opacity 2.24 (2.23, 2.97), p=0.002 (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 1</xref>).</p><p>The median FEV<sub>1</sub>% was significantly higher also in men 2.24 (1.91, 2.69) compared with women 2.12 (1.69, 2.55), p=0.004; and in participants with baseline ground-glass opacity 2.24 (1.89, 2.69) compared with those without baseline ground-glass opacity 2.16 (1.67, 2.66), p=0.033 (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>GEE multivariate model results</title><p>Always report both crude and adjusted ORs with 95% CI. Clarify when models are multivariate and whether any interaction terms were tested. Indicate the directionality of findings (eg, ‘higher odds of… vs ‘protective effect…’).</p><p>After controlling for other factors in the GEE multivariate analysis, participants who were overweight/obese had 3.5 higher odds of developing residual cardiopulmonary manifestations of COVID-19 (adjusted OR (aOR) (95% CI)=3.46 (2.47 to 4.84), p&lt;0.001) as compared with non-obese/overweight participants. Participants who have a history of smoking had 2.39 higher odds of developing residual cardiopulmonary manifestations of COVID-19 than non-smokers (aOR (95% CI)=2.39 (1.09 to 5.23), p=0.030). The odds of residual cardiopulmonary manifestations were 33% higher in patients with hypoxia than in patients without hypoxia (aOR (95% CI)=1.33 (0.99 to 1.78), p=0.045). Use of steroids was 62% more protective from developing residual cardiopulmonary manifestations than non-use of steroids (aOR (95% CI)=1.62 (1.16 to 1.92), p=0.042) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Generalised estimating equation analysis of factors predicting the occurrence of residual cardiopulmonary manifestations among COVID-19 survivors</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Category</th><th colspan="3" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Univariable analysis</th><th colspan="3" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Multivariable analysis</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cOR</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Age group (years)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥60</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 to 1.48</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 to 1.33</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45–59</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 to 0.98</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 to 1.06</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;45</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 to 1.83</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 to 1.41</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.606</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Insurance</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not insured</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 to 1.26</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.532</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insured</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">BMI ≥25.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76 to 5.03</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 to 4.84</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37 to 6.99</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 to 5.23</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Alcohol dependency</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26 to 8.18</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 to 1.37</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 to 2.64</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 to 1.26</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Diabetic mellitus</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 to 1.98</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 to 1.20</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.405</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">HIV coinfection</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 to 2.48</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.363</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Heart failure</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 to 1.59</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.664</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">CKD</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 to 1.79</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.560</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">History of TB</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 to 7.56</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 to 1.13</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Pregnancy</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 to 1.39</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">COPD</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 to 3.26</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Respiratory rate</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥30</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 to 2.24</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 to 2.24</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;30</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Oxygen saturation</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;94</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 to 1.70</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 to 1.78</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥94</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Ivermectin</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 to 1.65</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 to 1.23</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Steroids</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 to 1.63</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 to 1.92</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>aOR, adjusted OR; BMI, body mass index; CKD, chronic kidney disease; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; cOR, crude OR; TB, tuberculosis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study investigated the cardiopulmonary sequelae in 712 adult patients with PCR-confirmed COVID-19 across five tertiary-level hospitals in Tanzania. Nearly half of these patients exhibited residual cardiopulmonary manifestations 2 years after acute COVID-19 illness. Baseline chest roentgenogram abnormalities were significantly associated with the development of bronchiectasis, lung cavities, PHT and HF at follow-up.</p><p>Independent predictors of residual cardiopulmonary manifestations following acute COVID-19 in this study included BMI ≥25.0 kg/m², smoking, hypoxia and non-steroid use during acute illness. Age, sex, hypertension, diabetes mellitus or HIV did not predict residual cardiopulmonary manifestations postacute COVID-19.</p><p>Similar to other studies,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 42 43</sup></xref> the majority of patients in our study were male and over 60 years old. Age and sex were not associated with the development of PASC. Previous studies have consistently demonstrated male sex as an independent risk factor for severe COVID-19, associated late complications and increased mortality.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11 12 44</sup></xref> The previous retrospective analysis found that the majority of deaths occurred in males aged 60 years and older.<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref></p><p>Nearly half of participants were diagnosed with residual cardiopulmonary complications 2 years postacute COVID-19. This is the same as the results of a cohort study of post-COVID-19 condition done in South Africa by Jassat <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>,<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> though Jassat’s study followed up patients only for 6 months post-COVID-19.</p><p>Among patients with baseline radiological chest abnormalities, approximately one-third developed PHT and HF 2 years postacute COVID-19. The prevalence of PHT and HF in our study is higher than the findings of other studies.<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47 48</sup></xref> Pagnesi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. reported a prevalence of PHT and HF of 12.5% and 14.3%, respectively<italic toggle="yes">.</italic><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> In contrast to Pagnesi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., who reported findings from a 3-month follow-up of 200 hospitalised COVID-19 patients only at a single centre, our study examined cumulative outcomes of 712 COVID-19 patients across five tertiary hospitals over a 2-year period.</p><p>Among patients with radiological chest abnormalities at baseline, 18.2% of them had cavities in their lungs. The prevalence is lower compared with the findings of a study done by Abdel-Hamid <italic toggle="yes">et al,</italic> which showed 38.5% of participants had pulmonary residuals, including lung cavities, after 6 months of follow-up.<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> However, Abdel-Hamid <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>’s study was a single-centre study of only 211 admitted COVID-19 patients. Similar to Abdel-Hamid <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>’s findings, baseline radiological abnormalities in chest roentgenograms were identified as an independent risk factor for adverse outcomes.<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> Although the specific process of cavitation in COVID-19 patients is unknown, autopsy reports have suggested that it may arise following diffuse alveolar injury, intra-alveolar haemorrhage and parenchymal cell necrosis.<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref></p><p>Among patients with baseline radiological chest abnormalities, 20% developed bronchiectasis. While not a classic manifestation of COVID-19 pneumonia, bronchiectasis has been increasingly recognised as a post-COVID-19 complication.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> A longitudinal study by Han <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> identified bronchiectasis in 24% of patients at 6 months follow-up compared with 7% during acute COVID-19 illness.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Moreover, Hanley <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> reported traction bronchiectasis in 53% of postmortem cases, often associated with pulmonary fibrosis.<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref> In our cohort, most patients with bronchiectasis also exhibited pulmonary fibrotic changes.</p><p>Despite the above findings, there is an apparent paradox where no significant difference in residual restrictive lung disease is seen despite a strong association between obesity and lung impairment. The mechanism by which COVID-19 infection causes restriction is not clear. But based on the follow-up studies post SARS-COV, Hui <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> found the evidence of self-healing of the lungs and continuous remodelling after severe damage in their study.<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref> SARS-CoV has genomic and structural homology (76% amino acid identity) between the spike glycoproteins of SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2.<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref><xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> The evidence from recent follow-up studies found that the majority of COVID-19 survivors have resolving pulmonary sequelae or inflammatory residual lung abnormalities, but only a minority have overt lung fibrosis and impaired pulmonary function tests.<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56 57</sup></xref> This evidence could explain the non-significant differences seen in residual restrictive and obstructive lung disease in our study. However, the median FVC% and FEV<sub>1</sub>% were significantly higher only in men compared with women and among those presented with baseline ground-glass opacity. This showed that being a man and having ground-glass opacity at the baseline could be a proxy for restrictive lung diseases.</p><p>Overweight and smoking independently predicted the occurrence of cardiopulmonary sequelae postacute COVID-19 in our study. Overweight individuals in our study were 3.46 times more likely to develop cardiopulmonary sequelae postacute COVID-19 compared with those of normal weight. This is twice the odds reported in an Italian study by Vimercati <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, which found overweight participants to be 1.6 times more likely to develop cardiovascular or respiratory sequelae following COVID-19.<xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr"><sup>58</sup></xref> The Vimercati <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> article reported the autopsy findings of only 21 COVID-19 patients. The combination of chronic inflammation, metabolic dysregulation, cardiovascular risk factors, respiratory dysfunction and immune impairment associated with overweight and obesity could be associated with increased risk of developing late complications following COVID-19 infection.</p><p>In the present study, smokers had a higher likelihood of developing cardiopulmonary sequelae following acute COVID-19 compared with non-smokers in our study. Paul and Fancourt also reported an association between smoking and cardiopulmonary sequelae.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Smoking has been shown to induce CXCL9 cytokine.<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref> CXCL9 is a cytokine involved in the migration of a cell and lymphocytes in response to a chemical stimulus.<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref> CXCL9 has also been identified as a potential biomarker of PHT and HF.<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref> This association of CXCL9 cytokine might be a link between smoking and cardiopulmonary sequelae of long COVID-19.</p><p>Hypoxia was also an independent risk factor for developing residual cardiopulmonary sequelae of COVID-19 in our study.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 46</sup></xref> Hypoxia, a common manifestation of severe COVID-19,<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48 49</sup></xref> is associated with increased risk of permanent lung damage,<xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref><xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> as evidenced by the cardiopulmonary sequelae observed in our study.</p><p>In this study, we found that systemic steroid use was protective against developing residual cardiopulmonary sequelae of COVID-19. The findings were similar to a review performed by the WHO Rapid Evidence Appraisal for COVID-19 Therapies Working Group, which reported that administration of systemic corticosteroids was associated with lower 28-day all-cause mortality and late cardiopulmonary complications of COVID-19. <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> The use of steroids during acute illness is believed to reduce the COVID-19-induced inflammatory response and hence halt the pathogenesis of the disease.<xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref> This, in turn, reduces lung damage, improves clinical outcomes and prevents mortality.<xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref> In this analysis, we included patients who used corticosteroids during acute illness. Patients were given high doses of corticosteroids during acute illness for a period of less than 7 days, according to the national guideline for the management of COVID-19 in Tanzania.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref></p><p>The strengths of this study include its relatively larger sample size of COVID-19 patients than studies performed in the same setting and multicentre nature across the country, thus giving a national representation. To our knowledge, this is the first large-scale PASC study in sub-Saharan Africa, as it fills an important evidence gap in resource-limited settings.</p><p>The limitation of this study was its first part being retrospective, which was based on documented patient records with some missing data. The severity of postacute COVID-19 manifestations might have been affected by variants of SARS-CoV-2, which were not taken into account. The residual cardiopulmonary manifestations reported could not directly be attributed to COVID-19, as they might have been there even before the disease or appeared after acute COVID-19 as a result of other insults. Other possible prior confounding factors, like undiagnosed asthma/COPD, occupational exposures or air quality, were not taken into account. Again, there was a lack of baseline pre-COVID-19 lung imaging/function data. The generalisability of this study could be affected by selection bias, since all study patients underwent advanced imaging even though CT and echocardiography are not widely available in Tanzania, which may lead to an overestimation of abnormality detection in the general population. Findings of this study may not reflect the general Tanzanian population due to the selection of tertiary-level hospitals.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Ensuring good oxygenation and provision of systemic steroids to patients early during an acute COVID-19 illness is important to avoid long-term cardiopulmonary complications of the SARS-CoV-2 infection. Maintaining normal body weight and avoiding cigarette smoking are public health interventions worth advocating to prevent long-term cardiopulmonary manifestations of COVID-19. Hospitals should initiate early screening programmes for post-COVID patients to diagnose long-term complications and initiate comprehensive management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjph-2024-002082</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjph-2-Suppl_1-s001.docx" id="d67e1501" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge the director of the National Public Health Laboratory (NPHL) in Tanzania for allowing us to access the COVID-19 database for PCR results. We would also like to acknowledge the management of Muhimbili National Hospital, Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Center, Bugando Medical Center, Benjamin Mkapa Hospital and Mbeya Zonal Referral Hospital for allowing us to access patient databases. We would also like to acknowledge Evarist Msaki, Rafael Shayo, Amulike Mwakitalu, Christopher Mbije, Mary Nicholaous, Naveeda Adams, Athumani Ramadhani, Denis Reiner, Anna Jazza, Erick Mbuguje, Mwajuma Jumbe and Martha Nkya for their coordination of data collection.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> We acknowledge the Ministry of Health Tanzania for supporting data collection in this study. Grant/award number: not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> Ethical approval for this study was obtained from the Muhimbili University of Health and Allied Sciences (MUHAS) institutional review board, with approval number (MUHAS-REC-10-2022-1404). Participants gave informed consent to participate in the study before taking part.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to the Methods section for further details.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical course and outcomes of critically ill patients with SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a single-centered, retrospective, observational study</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30079-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32105632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hasabo</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ayyad</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alam Eldeen</surname><given-names>SAM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical manifestations, complications, and outcomes of patients with COVID-19 in Sudan: a multicenter observational study</article-title><source>Trop Med Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>91</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41182-021-00382-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34776007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8590864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Science Underlying COVID-19</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2020</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.120.047549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32293910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Madjid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Safavi-Naeini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Potential Effects of Coronaviruses on the Cardiovascular System: A Review</article-title><source>JAMA Cardiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamacardio.2020.1286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32219363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tosca</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Filippo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Special Issues for Coronavirus Disease 2019 in Children and Adolescents</article-title><source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source><year>2020</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.22878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32396994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P-I</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Extra-respiratory manifestations of COVID-19</article-title><source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source><year>2020</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>106024</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.106024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32450197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7243791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Renal dysfunction in hospitalised children with COVID-19</article-title><source>Lancet Child Adolesc Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e28</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30178-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32553126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7295466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>WHO</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Statement on the second meeting of the international health regulations (2005) emergency committee regarding the outbreak of novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV)</article-title><publisher-name>News</publisher-name><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>
</person-group><article-title>WHO coronavirus (COVID-19) dashboard with vaccination data</article-title><year>2021</year><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/vaccines" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/vaccines</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oldfield</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malwal</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and Other Pandemics: How Might They Be Prevented?</article-title><source>ACS Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1563</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsinfecdis.0c00291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32478500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al Mutair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alhumaid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alhuqbani</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical, epidemiological, and laboratory characteristics of mild-to-moderate COVID-19 patients in Saudi Arabia: an observational cohort study</article-title><source>Eur J Med Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>61</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40001-020-00462-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33239068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7686832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beg</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Majeed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Epidemiological and Clinical Characteristics of COVID-19: A Retrospective Multi-Center Study in Pakistan</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>644199</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2021.644199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33937174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8079641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández‐de‐las‐Peñas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro‐Santana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez‐Mayordomo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Headache as an acute and post‐COVID‐19 symptom in COVID‐19 survivors: A meta‐analysis of the current literature</article-title><source>Euro J of Neurology</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3820</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ene.15040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8444899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34327787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>WHO coronavirus (COVID-19) dashboard _ who coronavirus (COVID-19) dashboard with vaccination data</article-title><year>2022</year><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases." ext-link-type="uri">https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases.</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Chronic Pulmonary Manifestations of COVID-19 Infection: Imaging Evaluation</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2023</year><volume>307</volume><elocation-id>e222379</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.222379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36692398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9888022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nalbandian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01283-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8893149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Burdens of post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 by severity of acute infection, demographics and health status</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>6571</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-26513-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34772922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8589966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization (WHO)</collab>
</person-group><article-title>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic</article-title><publisher-name>WHO Document Production Services, Geneve Switzerland</publisher-name><year>2023</year><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Faverio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luppi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rebora</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>One-year pulmonary impairment after severe COVID-19: a prospective, multicenter follow-up study</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-022-01994-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8934910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35313890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Quantitative inspiratory-expiratory chest CT findings in COVID-19 survivors at the 6-month follow-up</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>7402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-11237-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35513692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9070972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Gassel</surname><given-names>RJJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bels</surname><given-names>JLM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raafs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>High Prevalence of Pulmonary Sequelae at 3 Months after Hospital Discharge in Mechanically Ventilated Survivors of COVID-19</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>203</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.202010-3823LE</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33326353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7874313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pulmonary function and chest computed tomography abnormalities 6-12 months after recovery from COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>233</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-022-02163-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36068582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9446643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alwalid</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Six-month Follow-up Chest CT Findings after Severe COVID-19 Pneumonia</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2021</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>E177</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2021203153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33497317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7841877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bharat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Querrey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Markov</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Lung transplantation for patients with severe COVID-19</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.abe4282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8050952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33257409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Puntmann</surname><given-names>VO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carerj</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wieters</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Outcomes of Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance Imaging in Patients Recently Recovered From Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19)</article-title><source>JAMA Cardiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1265</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamacardio.2020.3557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32730619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7385689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long-term cardiovascular outcomes of COVID-19</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01689-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35132265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8938267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>M-R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Sociodemographic determinants and clinical risk factors associated with COVID-19 severity: a cross-sectional analysis of over 200,000 patients in Tehran, Iran</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-06179-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8146170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34034649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nlandu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mafuta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Predictors of mortality in COVID-19 patients at Kinshasa Medical Center and a survival analysis: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-06984-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8686084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34930174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kassam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aghan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Factors Associated with Mortality Among Hospitalized Adults with COVID-19 Pneumonia at a Private Tertiary Hospital in Tanzania: A Retrospective Cohort Study</article-title><source>Int J Gen Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>5431</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJGM.S330580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34526810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8436253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fancourt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Health behaviours the month prior to COVID-19 infection and the development of self-reported long COVID and specific long COVID symptoms: a longitudinal analysis of 1581 UK adults</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1716</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-14123-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36085055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9462889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Ministry of Health (Tanzania)</collab>
</person-group><source>COVID-19_MoHCDGEC treatment guidelines_8-11 June, morogoro version (2)</source><edition>2nd</edition><comment>edn</comment><publisher-loc>Dodoma</publisher-loc><year>2021</year><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.afro.who.int/sites/default/files/2021-07/WCO%20Progress%20Report_%20July-December%202020.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.afro.who.int/sites/default/files/2021-07/WCO%20Progress%20Report_%20July-December%202020.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>WHO Rapid Evidence Appraisal for COVID-19 Therapies (REACT) Working Group</collab>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sterne</surname><given-names>JAC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Association Between Administration of Systemic Corticosteroids and Mortality Among Critically Ill Patients With COVID-19</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><volume>324</volume><fpage>1330</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.17023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32876694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7489434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beckerman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jeyakumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Remdesivir for the treatment of patients hospitalized with COVID-19 receiving supplemental oxygen: a targeted literature review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>9622</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-13680-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35688854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9186282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Charpentrat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>'Miracle' drug ivermectin unproven against COVID, scientists warn</article-title><publisher-name>CTV News</publisher-name><year>2021</year><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/lifestyle/article/miracle-drug-ivermectin-unproven-against-covid-scientists-warn/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ctvnews.ca/lifestyle/article/miracle-drug-ivermectin-unproven-against-covid-scientists-warn/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wijewickrema</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banneheke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pathmeswaran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of oral ivermectin in the treatment of mild to moderate Covid-19 patients: a multi-centre double-blind randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>719</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-024-09563-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39039459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11264372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stefano</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kream</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stefano</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A Novel Vaccine Employing Non-Replicating Rabies Virus Expressing Chimeric SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein Domains: Functional Inhibition of Viral/Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptor Complexes</article-title><source>Med Sci Monit</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><elocation-id>e926016</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/MSM.926016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32463026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7278327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thielke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Research electronic data capture (REDCap)—A metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support</article-title><source>J Biomed Inform</source><year>2009</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2008.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18929686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2700030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ravimohan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kornfeld</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Tuberculosis and lung damage: from epidemiology to pathophysiology</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>170077</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0077-2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29491034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6019552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kitabatake</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Asao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Noninvasive evaluation of pulmonary hypertension by a pulsed Doppler technique</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1983</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.cir.68.2.302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6861308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Colalillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pellicano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Romaniello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>In systemic sclerosis TAPSE/sPAP ratio is correlated with ventilatory efficiency and exercise capacity assessed by CPET</article-title><source>Clin Exp Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10238-022-00804-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35150361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10224825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bertagnolio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thwin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical features of, and risk factors for, severe or fatal COVID-19 among people living with HIV admitted to hospital: analysis of data from the WHO Global Clinical Platform of COVID-19</article-title><source>Lancet HIV</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e486</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(22)00097-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35561704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9090268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cecconi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Piovani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brunetta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><comment>n.d.</comment><article-title>Early Predictors of Clinical Deterioration in a Cohort of 239 Patients Hospitalized for Covid-19 Infection in Lombardy, Italy</article-title><source>JCM</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1548</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9051548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7290833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32443899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grasselli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zangrillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zanella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Baseline Characteristics and Outcomes of 1591 Patients Infected With SARS-CoV-2 Admitted to ICUs of the Lombardy Region, Italy</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><volume>323</volume><fpage>1574</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.5394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32250385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7136855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Risk factors for severity and mortality in adult COVID-19 inpatients in Wuhan</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2020</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2020.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32294485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7152876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Osati</surname><given-names>EFO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shayo</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sangeda</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical manifestations and treatment outcomes among hospitalised COVID-19 patients in tertiary hospitals in Tanzania, 2021-2022: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>BMJ Public Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e000881</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjph-2023-000881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40018602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11816690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jassat</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mudara</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vika</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A cohort study of post-COVID-19 condition across the Beta, Delta, and Omicron waves in South Africa: 6-month follow-up of hospitalized and nonhospitalized participants</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2022.12.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36587841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9800016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elshafey</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Study of pulmonary hypertension in post-COVID-19 patients by transthoracic echocardiography</article-title><source>Egypt J Bronchol</source><year>2023</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>27</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43168-023-00201-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pagnesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baldetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beneduce</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Pulmonary hypertension and right ventricular involvement in hospitalised patients with COVID-19</article-title><source>Heart</source><year>2020</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>1324</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/heartjnl-2020-317355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32675217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7476272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Hamid</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rizk</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Magdy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Occurrence of pulmonary residuals as one of the sequelae of COVID-19 and it’s predictors among moderate and severe cases</article-title><source>Indian J Tuberc</source><year>2021</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijtb.2021.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34752312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7857115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Menter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haslbauer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nienhold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Postmortem examination of COVID‐19 patients reveals diffuse alveolar damage with severe capillary congestion and variegated findings in lungs and other organs suggesting vascular dysfunction</article-title><source>Histopathology</source><year>2020</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/his.14134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32364264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7496150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Youd</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Autopsy in suspected COVID-19 cases</article-title><source>J Clin Pathol</source><year>2020</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jclinpath-2020-206522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32198191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The 1-year impact of severe acute respiratory syndrome on pulmonary function, exercise capacity, and quality of life in a cohort of survivors</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2005</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>2247</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.128.4.2247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7094276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tortorici</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Structure, Function, and Antigenicity of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Glycoprotein</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32155444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kleine-Weber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Cell Entry Depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and Is Blocked by a Clinically Proven Protease Inhibitor</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32142651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X-L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X-G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>579</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32015507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7095418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fabbri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Parenchymal lung abnormalities following hospitalisation for COVID-19 and viral pneumonitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2023</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2021-218275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35338102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long-term radiological and pulmonary function abnormalities at 3 years after COVID-19 hospitalisation: a longitudinal cohort study</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2024</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>2301612</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01612-2023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38387969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11255387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vimercati</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Maria</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Quarato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><comment>n.d.</comment><article-title>Association between Long COVID and Overweight/Obesity</article-title><source>JCM</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>4143</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10184143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Altara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hessel</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>CXCL10 Is a Circulating Inflammatory Marker in Patients with Advanced Heart Failure: a Pilot Study</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Transl Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12265-016-9703-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27271043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pezzuto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fortarezza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Pulmonary pathology and COVID-19: lessons from autopsy. The experience of European Pulmonary Pathologists</article-title><source>Virchows Arch</source><year>2020</year><volume>477</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00428-020-02886-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32642842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7343579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Pathological study of the 2019 novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) through postmortem core biopsies</article-title><source>Mod Pathol</source><year>2020</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41379-020-0536-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32291399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7156231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Pathological findings of COVID-19 associated with acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30076-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32085846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7164771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Korteweg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pathology and Pathogenesis of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2007</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2353/ajpath.2007.061088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1829448</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data are available upon reasonable request.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>