<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Prev Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ Health Prev Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">839</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ehpmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHPM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health and Preventive Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1342-078X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1347-4715</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Japanese Society for Hygiene</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12583970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12583970.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12583970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12583970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41161755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1265/ehpm.25-00293</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">25-00293</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ehpm-30-084</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Japanese nationwide survey to track the impact of long COVID over 3 years</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names initials="T">Takuya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff01" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="afn01" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terai</surname><given-names initials="H">Hideki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff01" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff02" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><address><email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hidekiterai@keio.jp">hidekiterai@keio.jp</email></address></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names initials="H">Hiromu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff01" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="afn01" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iba</surname><given-names initials="A">Arisa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff03" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosozawa</surname><given-names initials="M">Mariko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff03" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hori</surname><given-names initials="M">Miyuki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff03" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muto</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yoko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff03" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida-Kohno</surname><given-names initials="E">Eiko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff03" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Namkoong</surname><given-names initials="H">Ho</given-names></name><xref rid="aff04" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chubachi</surname><given-names initials="S">Shotaro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff01" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takemura</surname><given-names initials="R">Ryo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff05" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names initials="K">Kengo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff05" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yasunori</given-names></name><xref rid="aff05" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names initials="M">Makoto</given-names></name><xref rid="aff06" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iso</surname><given-names initials="H">Hiroyasu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff03" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names initials="K">Koichi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff01" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>the Japan long COVID research group</collab></contrib><aff id="aff01"><label>1</label>Division of Pulmonary Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Keio University School of Medicine, <addr-line>35 Shinano-machi, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 160-8582, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff02"><label>2</label>Keio Cancer Center, Keio University School of Medicine, <addr-line>35 Shinano-machi, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 160-8582, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff03"><label>3</label>Institute for Global Health Policy Research, Bureau of Global Health Cooperation, Japan Institute for Health Security, <addr-line>1-21-1 Toyama, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 162-8655, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff04"><label>4</label>Department of Infectious Diseases, Keio University School of Medicine, <addr-line>35 Shinano-machi, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 160-8582, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff05"><label>5</label>Department of Biostatistics, Keio University School of Medicine, <addr-line>35 Shinano-machi, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 160-8582, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff06"><label>6</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Nagoya University Graduate School of Medicine, <addr-line>65 Tsurumai-cho, Showa-ku, Nagoya 466-8550, Japan</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="equal" id="afn01"><label>†</label><p>These authors contributed equally as co-first authors</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>30</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">479959</issue-id><elocation-id>84</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-05 00:25:12.910"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ehpm-30-084.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The long-term impact of symptom classification on quality of life (QOL) and economic outcomes among individuals with long coronavirus disease (COVID) remains poorly understood. This study aimed to clarify the situation of long COVID in Japan by analyzing patients using cluster classification.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This multicenter, retrospective cohort study enrolled 515 patients with COVID-19 and followed up for 36 months via standardized questionnaires. Patients were classified based on: 1) symptom trajectory over time and 2) symptom cluster profiles at 3 months.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>While the number of symptoms decreased, fatigue and dyspnea frequently persisted, whereas anosmia and dysgeusia declined. Cough and sputum decreased gradually. The proportion of patients with 5–9 symptoms increased. The mean (interquartile range) presenteeism scores were lower in the continuous (60 [50–80]) and relapse groups (65 [48–80]) than in the recovered group (70 [50–80]). The multiple symptoms cluster had the worst SF-36, presenteeism, and absenteeism scores (47.2 [44.7–49.8], 48.8 [27.5–72.5], and 10.9 [0.0–11.0], respectively).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Patients with continuous and multiple symptoms experienced persistently lower QOL and greater economic burden up to 36 months after COVID-19 diagnosis. The long-term effects of long COVID are not only physical but also mental and economical. Thus, further research is needed to clarify the economical and physiological impact of long COVID.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1265/ehpm.25-00293" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1265/ehpm.25-00293</ext-link>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>Coronavirus disease 2019</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Quality of life</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Even 4 years after the outbreak of the novel coronavirus disease in 2019 (COVID-19), a significant number of patients still experience long-term symptoms after severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection, commonly referred to as “long COVID,” [<xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] which continues to have socioeconomic impacts. While studies investigating long COVID up to 3 years after the first wave remain limited, existing research highlights several important findings. These include a decrease in the overall frequency of long COVID symptoms over time, with certain symptoms such as fatigue, dyspnea, and alopecia persisting; a higher risk of long COVID symptoms among hospitalized patients than among non-hospitalized patients; and a significant decline in quality of life (QOL) attributed to long COVID symptoms [<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Even with the Omicron variant, which has a less severe acute phase, it is unclear whether the incidence of long COVID is also reduced. Although research focus has shifted to the current Omicron variants rather than earlier, more virulent strains, it remains crucial to clarify the long-term impact of the initial waves of infection.</p><p>Long COVID is still debated, suggesting that it could be a complicated condition to understand [<xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In a systematic review [<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], fatigue was reported as the most common symptom, and long COVID affected not only physical health but also mental health, such as anxiety and depression. Several cluster analyses have been conducted to understand this mechanism; specifically, there were two clusters where symptoms recovered or persisted [<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. It is expected that analyzing patients by dividing them into specific clusters, rather than analyzing them as a whole, may lead to a better understanding of long COVID.</p><p>Large-scale reports on long COVID over 3 years have been limited. Moreover, the number of studies that have examined the long-term economic impact is also scarce. Thus, this study aimed to clarify the situation of long COVID in Japan by analyzing patients using cluster classification.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study design and participants</title><p>This multicenter, retrospective cohort study included patients from our previous study [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], recruited from 26 medical facilities across Japan (Hokkaido, Tochigi, Saitama, Tokyo, Kanagawa, Aichi, Osaka, and Fukuoka), covering urban, suburban, and rural areas [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Briefly, we included patients who were aged ≥18 years, diagnosed with COVID-19 via SARS-CoV-2 polymerase chain reaction or antigen test, and hospitalized during the first to third waves of COVID-19 between January 2020 and February 2021. Patients were asked to complete a questionnaire on paper or via a smartphone application regarding their symptoms associated with long COVID at 36 months after diagnosis. The definition of long COVID at 36 months was the presence of symptoms that persisted after COVID-19 diagnosis or recurred after discharge, in accordance with the definition of Centers for Disease Control and Prevention [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The survey period was from November 2023 to February 2024. In addition to the 24 symptoms investigated in a previous study, seven symptoms (nasal discharge, chest pain, palpitations, anorexia, nausea or vomiting, erectile dysfunction, and menstrual changes) were included. Additionally, information on anxiety and depression (assessed by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale), health-related QOL (assessed by the SF-8 scale), economic conditions, and vaccination status were gathered. Economic conditions were assessed using presenteeism and absenteeism scores from the World Health Organization Health and Work Performance Questionnaire. The specific questionnaire items and calculation methods are provided in Supplementary Appendix <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">1</xref> (Additional file).</p><p>To confirm consent to participate in the study, an explanatory letter and a return envelope indicating the willingness to participate and cooperate were sent. This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Keio University School of Medicine (approval number: 20200243). Each participating institution obtained approval and permission to conduct this study from the institutional ethical review committee or a specified nonprofit organization of the Japan Clinical Research Council.</p></sec><sec><title>Patient enrollment</title><p>In the original cohort study, informed consent was obtained from 1,196 participants. We excluded those whose clinical information from each facility was obtained using an electronic data capture system or whose questionnaire results were lacking (n = 130). The number of participants with clinical information and patient-reported outcomes at 3 months was 1,066. Moreover, we excluded patients who were lost to follow-up (n = 39), died (n = 8), or provided reversed informed consent due to reasons such as being too old to answer (n = 43) and others (n = 2). We also excluded the patients whose reported outcomes at 6, 12, or 36 months after diagnosis were lacking (n = 459). Finally, data from 515 patients were included in the analysis. A consort diagram is presented in Fig. <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S1</xref> (Additional file). Regarding ethnicity, 513 patients were Japanese, and 2 were from other countries. Figure <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S2</xref> (Additional file) shows the chronological changes in the individual symptoms from 3 to 36 months. The cases were classified into five groups according to the pattern of appearance of long COVID as follows: “Continuous,” symptoms always present; “Recovered,” symptoms disappeared after a certain point during follow-up; “Relapse,” symptoms present at admission, disappeared once, then reappeared; “Late-onset,” no symptoms at admission but symptoms appeared after 3 months; and “Never,” symptoms always absent. Furthermore, based on the cluster analysis of symptoms at 3 months using the same patient group [<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], the current cases were classified into clusters. The clusters were named according to the previous cluster analysis, as follows: minimal symptom, anosmia and dysgeusia, fatigue and dyspnea, cough and sputum, and multiple symptoms clusters.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using JMP Pro 17.2 program (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). Continuous variables are presented as mean and interquartile range (IQR), while categorical variables are presented as the number and percentage of cases. Using the 24 symptom variables evaluated at 3 months post-infection, hierarchical cluster analysis was performed by the Ward’s minimum-variance method, as described in our previous study [<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The method for calculating absolute presenteeism and absenteeism is presented in the Appendix. Continuous variables were analyzed using Mann–Whitney U (two groups) or Kruskal–Wallis (exceeding two groups) tests, and categorical variables using Pearson’s χ<sup>2</sup> test. Two-tailed p-values &lt;0.05 indicated statistical significance.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Table <xref rid="tbl01" ref-type="table">1</xref> represents the characteristics of patients with long COVID at 36 months after diagnosis compared with those without symptoms. No differences were observed in age, sex, or disease severity between the groups. Regarding comorbidities, the prevalence of asthma was higher in the long COVID group than in the asymptomatic group (n = 13 [10.1%] vs 14 [3.7%], p &lt; 0.01), whereas the prevalence of cardiovascular disease was lower (n = 1 [0.8%] vs 25 [6.6%], p &lt; 0.01), although the number of patients with each comorbidity was small. The proportion of patients admitted to the intensive care unit did not differ between the groups; however, the use of mechanical ventilation was higher (n = 12 [9.6%] vs 15 [4.0%], p = 0.02) in the long COVID group than in the asymptomatic group. Reinfection was observed in 34 patients (27.0%) in the long COVID group and in 87 patients (23.5%) in the asymptomatic group, with no significant difference (p = 0.42). To address the potential impact of dropouts over time, we compared patient characteristics at 3 and 36 months after diagnosis to identify differences between the retained and lost participants (Table <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S1</xref>, Additional file). There were no clear differences between the two groups. Furthermore, symptoms at 36 months were compared between patients with and without reinfection (Table <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S2</xref>, Additional file). Fever was more frequent in the reinfection group (n = 7 [5.8%] vs n = 5 [1.3%], p = 0.006), while the percentage of other symptoms showed no differences.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl01" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics according to the presence or absence of long COVID at 36 months</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>Long COVID at 36 months</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>+ (n = 132)</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>− (n = 383)</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>p value</bold>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Age</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">60 (57–63)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">59 (57–60)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.64</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Sex, male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">88 (66.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">230 (60.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Severity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.35</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Asymptomatic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">7 (1.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Mild</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">16 (12.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">72 (19.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Moderate I</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">55 (44.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">173 (45.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Moderate II</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">37 (29.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">84 (22.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Severe</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">15 (12.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">41 (10.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Comorbidities</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Hypertension</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">48 (36.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">139 (36.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.91</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Diabetes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">24 (18.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">65 (17.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.68</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Cardiovascular disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">25 (6.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Malignancy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">9 (6.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">22 (5.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.67</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Autoimmune disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">6 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.58</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> COPD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">6 (4.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">11 (2.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.33</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Asthma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">13 (10.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">14 (3.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.005</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Hyperuricemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">16 (12.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">46 (12.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.92</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Chronic liver disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (3.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">13 (3.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.85</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Chronic kidney disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">19 (5.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.60</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Admission to ICU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">15 (12.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">39 (10.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.60</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Mechanical ventilation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">12 (9.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">15 (4.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.016</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Past history</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Infection</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">10 (7.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">17 (4.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.16</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Mental disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">7 (5.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">10 (2.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.14</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Respiratory disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">12 (9.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">20 (5.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.11</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Reinfection</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">34 (27.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">87 (23.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.42</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Number of symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4.6 (4.3–4.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.0 (−0.2–0.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Type of symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Continuous</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">79 (59.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Recovered</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">344 (89.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Relapse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">53 (40.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">39 (10.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Economic condition</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Become very bad</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">14 (11.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">10 (2.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Worse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">28 (22.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">49 (13.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> No change</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">78 (61.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">295 (78.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Become better</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">6 (4.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">15 (4.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Improved very much</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">7 (1.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Absolute presenteeism</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">58.7 (53.9–63.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">66.2 (63.5–68.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.003</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Absolute absenteeism</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">−3.7 (−13.0–5.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">−12.1 (−17.2–6.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.94</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">SF-36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">48.0 (46.9–49.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">52.1 (51.5–52.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> PCS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">46.8 (45.8–47.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">49.5 (48.8–50.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> MCS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">49.1 (44.6–50.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">52.8 (52.1–53.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; ICU, intensive care unit; MCS, mental component survey; PCS, physical component survey; SF-36, MOS 36-item short-form health survey</p><p>Missing values were excluded. Continuous variables are shown as the mean (95% confidence interval) and categorical variables as n (%).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Figure <xref rid="fig01" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a illustrates the changes over time in the proportion of patients reporting the indicated number of symptoms, showing the trends across the follow-up period. Compared to the acute phase of infection, the number of patients reporting any symptoms decreased by half at 3 months (n = 238 [46.2%]), then gradually decreased further at 6, 12, and 36 months (n = 207 [40.2%], n = 180 [35.0%], and n = 138 [26.8%], respectively). Thus, the number of patients reporting any symptoms decreased from 3 to 36 months, except for those reporting 5–9 and ≥10 symptoms. Furthermore, a notable increase was identified in the proportion of patients reporting five to nine symptoms between 12 and 36 months (n = 36 [7.0%] and n = 46 [8.9%], respectively). The small number of patients with ≥10 symptoms did not significantly change over time.</p><fig position="float" id="fig01" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Chronological changes from diagnosis to 36 months after onset of long COVID</p><p>a) Changes in the number of long COVID cases over time. b) Trends of 515 patients with at least one symptom at each time point. COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ehpm-30-084-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Figure <xref rid="fig01" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b shows the trends in patients reporting at least one symptom, categorized into long COVID symptom subgroups: 92 (17.9%), 344 (66.8%), and 79 (15.3%) patients were categorized into the “relapse,” “recovered,” and “continuous,” subgroups, respectively, at 36 months. At 36 months, a substantial proportion of the patients continued to have persistent or relapsed symptoms. Although the prevalence of most symptoms showed a declining trend, certain symptoms, including fatigue, dyspnea, muscular weakness, alopecia, and cough, persisted over time (Fig. <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S2</xref>, Additional file).</p><p>The absolute numbers of representative symptoms, such as fatigue, memory impairment, poor concentration, and alopecia, are documented for up to 36 months (Fig. <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S3</xref>, Additional file). In addition, the corresponding percentages for each symptom, as well as the percentage of patients with at least one symptom, are also shown (Fig. <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S4</xref>, Additional file). Patients with no symptoms at any time point were excluded for clear interpretation. Symptoms remained continuous in a certain number of patients, and patients with relapsed or late-onset symptoms were observed as late as 36 months.</p><p>We classified the five clusters based on the results of the cluster analysis of symptoms at 3 months using the same patient group. Patients were classified into the same clusters defined by their symptoms at 3 months after diagnosis (Table <xref rid="tbl02" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The mean (IQR) number of symptoms was the smallest in the minimal symptoms cluster and the largest in the multiple symptoms cluster at 0.5 (0.2–0.8) and 5.0 (4.0–6.0), respectively. Similarly, the mean (IQR) SF-36 QOL score was the highest in the minimal symptoms cluster and the lowest in the multiple symptoms cluster at 52.2 (51.4–52.9) and 47.2 (44.7–49.8), respectively. The absolute presenteeism score was higher in the multiple symptoms cluster than in the other clusters. The multiple symptoms cluster mostly comprised the continuous group, whereas the other clusters mainly comprised the recovered group. In the multiple symptom cluster, the symptoms tended to persist for 36 months.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl02" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics compared by cluster</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="5" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>Cluster</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>Minimal</bold>
<break/>
<bold>symptoms</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>Anosmia and</bold>
<break/>
<bold>Dysgeusia</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>Fatigue and</bold>
<break/>
<bold>Dyspnea</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>Cough and</bold>
<break/>
<bold>Sputum</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>Multiple</bold>
<break/>
<bold>symptoms</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>p value</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>n = 307</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>n = 45</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>n = 111</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>n = 26</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">
<bold>n = 26</bold>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Age</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">61 (59–63)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">55 (51–59)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">55 (52–57)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">62 (59–67)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">60 (55–66)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Sex, male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">199 (64.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">21 (46.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">66 (59.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">15 (57.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">17 (65.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.19</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Severity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.017</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Asymptomatic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">6 (2.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (0.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Mild</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">48 (16.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">17 (38.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">19 (17.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Moderate I</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">146 (48.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">17 (38.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">44 (41.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">12 (46.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">9 (34.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Moderate II</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">70 (23.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">7 (15.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">30 (28.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">6 (23.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">8 (30.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Severe</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">30 (10.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (4.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">12 (11.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (19.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">7 (26.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Comorbidities</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Hypertension</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">124 (40.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">9 (20.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">35 (32.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">11 (42.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">8 (30.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.059</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Diabetes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">60 (19.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">18 (16.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (19.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (19.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Cardiovascular disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">18 (5.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (8.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (1.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.37</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Malignancy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">23 (7.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (4.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (2.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.43</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Autoimmune disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (0.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (4.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (4.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.04</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> COPD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">9 (3.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (2.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.069</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Asthma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">15 (4.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (9.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (3.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.40</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Hyperuricemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">39 (12.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (11.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">13 (12.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.96</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Chronic liver disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">7 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (4.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">6 (5.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.58</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Chronic kidney disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">16 (5.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (6.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (4.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.53</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Admission to ICU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">31 (10.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (4.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">11 (10.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (19.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (20.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.20</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Mechanical ventilation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">9 (3.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">9 (8.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (20.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Past medical history</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Infection</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">9 (2.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (2.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">13 (11.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.007</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Mental disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">6 (2.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (2.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">8 (7.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.12</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Respiratory disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">16 (5.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (6.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (4.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (15.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (15.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.072</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Number of symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.5 (0.2–0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1.2 (0.4–1.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1.9 (1.4–2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2.5 (1.5–3.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5.0 (4.0–6.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Presence of symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">42 (13.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">15 (33.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">47 (42.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">11 (42.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">17 (65.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Type of symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Continuous</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">10 (3.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">11 (24.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">28 (25.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">10 (38.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">15 (57.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Recovered</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">232 (75.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">30 (66.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">63 (56.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">14 (53.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">10 (38.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Relapse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">65 (21.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (8.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">20 (18.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">2 (7.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Economic condition</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Become very bad</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">9 (2.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (2.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">7 (6.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (15.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Worse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">27 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">6 (13.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">29 (26.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">7 (26.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">8 (30.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> No change</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">247 (80.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">33 (73.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">64 (57.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">16 (61.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">13 (50.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Become better</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">12 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">3 (6.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">5 (4.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">1 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> Improved very much</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (1.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">4 (3.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Absolute presenteeism</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">66.6 (50.0–80.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">68.8 (60.0–80.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">62.1 (50.0–80.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">57.5 (50.0–70.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">48.8 (27.5–72.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.011</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">Absolute absenteeism</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">−14.8 (−20.0–0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">−0.9 (0.0–0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">−6.7 (−20.0–0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">−11.4 (−20.0–0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">10.9 (0.0–11.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.008</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle">SF-36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">52.2 (51.4–52.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">50.9 (48.9–52.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">49.1 (47.8–50.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">51.2 (48.6–53.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">47.2 (44.7–49.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> PCS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">49.2 (48.5–49.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">48.4 (46.5–50.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">47.7 (46.5–48.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">48.6 (46.1–51.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">44.5 (42.0–47.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="middle"> MCS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">52.8 (52.1–53.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">51.6 (49.8–53.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">49.1 (48.0–50.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">50.0 (47.7–52.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">47.8 (45.5–50.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="middle">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; ICU, intensive care unit; MCS, mental component survey; PCS, physical component survey; SF-36, MOS 36-item short-form health survey</p><p>Missing values were excluded. Continuous variables are shown as the mean (95% confidence interval) and categorical variables as n (%).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Figure <xref rid="fig02" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the trend in the frequency of each long COVID symptom by cluster as a heatmap. In the minimal symptom cluster, symptom frequencies remained consistently low across all time points from 3 to 36 months, with no notable changes during the follow-up period. In the anosmia and dysgeusia cluster, the frequencies of anosmia and dysgeusia remained elevated at 12 months (n = 14 [41.1%] and 10 [22.2%]) but declined at 36 months (n = 8 [17.8%] and 2 [4.4%]). In the fatigue and dyspnea group, fatigue and dyspnea were relatively frequent at 12 months (n = 28 [25.2%] and 19 [17.1%]). At 36 months, fatigue decreased (n = 25 [22.5%]), but dyspnea increased (n = 26 [23.4%]). In the cough and sputum cluster, both symptoms were more common at 12 months (n = 6 [23.1%] and 9 [34.6%]), and decreased slightly at 36 months (n = 5 [19.2%] and 6 [23.1%]). In contrast, the number of patients in the multiple symptoms cluster remained high for many symptoms, such as fatigue (n = 11 [42.3%]), dyspnea (n = 10 [38.5%]), alopecia (n = 7 [26.9%]), arthralgia (n = 8 [30.8%]), muscle weakness (n = 10 [38.5%]), numbness (n = 9 [34.6%]), eye-related symptoms (n = 5 [19.2%]), memory impairment (n = 8 [30.8%]), poor concentration (n = 10 [38.5%]), and sleep disorder (n = 5 [19.2%]).</p><fig position="float" id="fig02" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Heatmap of the frequency of long COVID cases compared by clusters</p><p>COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ehpm-30-084-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>In the longitudinal analysis of patients with at least one symptom (Fig. <xref rid="fig01" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a), the proportion of patients with five to nine symptoms increased between 12 and 36 months. Accordingly, we compared patients with five or more symptoms with those with less than five symptoms. Owing to our focus on patients who had any symptoms, we excluded those who had zero symptoms (n = 377) from the analysis and compared groups of patients with one to four symptoms (n = 81) and five or more symptoms (n = 57).</p><p>Figure <xref rid="fig03" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows the comparison between these groups. In all symptoms, the proportion of patients with the symptom was significantly higher in patients with five or more symptoms than those with one to four symptoms. Fatigue, dyspnea, memory impairment, and muscle weakness were the most common symptoms in both groups. Patients with five or more symptoms were more likely to have symptoms such as poor concentration, alopecia, cough, and sleep disorders than those with one to four symptoms.</p><fig position="float" id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of the proportion of each symptom in patient groups stratified by number of symptoms</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ehpm-30-084-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>The patient characteristics, comparing those with five or more symptoms, to those with one to five symptoms, are summarized (Table <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S3</xref>, Additional file). In patients with five or more symptoms, compared with those with fewer symptoms, the proportion whose economic conditions “become very bad” or “become worse” was higher: 47.3% (n = 26) vs 24.3% (n = 19); the mean absenteeism score was higher: 3.5 (IQR: 13.1–20.0) vs −9.8 (IQR: −21.4–1.8); and the mean SF-36 QOL score was lower: 45.3 (IQR: 43.2–47.5) vs 50.3 (IQR: 48.6–52.0).</p><p>Figure <xref rid="fig04" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the number of vaccinations received and proportion of long COVID cases in symptomatic patients at 3 months. When comparing the number of vaccinations received, long COVID was less common in patients who received at least one vaccination (n = 80 [28.0%]) than in those who received no vaccinations (n = 10 [50.0%]). However, no significant difference in the prevalence of long COVID was observed between patients who received fewer than three vaccinations and those who received three or more vaccinations: 26.9% (n = 7) and 28.1% (n = 73), respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of vaccination frequency and symptoms among symptomatic patients at 3 months</p><p>a) Number of vaccinations and symptoms. b) Proportion of long COVID cases by vaccination status.</p><p>COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ehpm-30-084-g004.jpg"/></fig><p>Figure <xref rid="fig05" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a shows the changes in subjective economic conditions according to the patterns of symptom presentation during long COVID. The proportion of patients who answered “become very bad” and “become worse” was the highest in the continuous group followed by the relapse and recovered groups at 43.6% (n = 31), 21.1% (n = 19), and 14.9% (n = 51), respectively. The proportion who answered “no change” was almost the same for the relapse and recovered groups at 75.6% (n = 68) and 78.6% (n = 265), respectively, whereas it was significantly lower for the continuous group at 52.6% (n = 40; p &lt; 0.001).</p><fig position="float" id="fig05" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of economic conditions by type of long COVID symptom transition</p><p>a) Change in subjective economic condition. b) The upper row is absolute presenteeism and lower row indicates absolute absenteeism.</p><p>COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ehpm-30-084-g005.jpg"/></fig><p>Figure <xref rid="fig05" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b compares absolute presenteeism with absenteeism. For absolute presenteeism, both the continuous and relapse groups had lower mean scores compared with the recovered group at 60 (IQR: 50–80), 65 (IQR: 48–80), and 70 (IQR: 50–80) (p &lt; 0.01, p = 0.017), respectively. The mean absolute absenteeism was 0 in all groups, with interquartile ranges (IQRs) of 0–0 for the continuous group, −12–0 for the relapse group, and −20–0 for the recovered group (both p &lt; 0.01).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In this observational study of 515 patients with COVID-19 followed for approximately 3 years after diagnosis, we found that long COVID persisted in a certain number of patients, and patients with multiple symptoms at 3 months (multiple symptoms cluster) also presented them at 36 months. Moreover, this study suggested that long COVID affected not only physical health but also QOL and economic conditions at 36 months; the severity of which varies according to the pattern and course of long COVID. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to classify and compare long COVID by symptom clusters and analyze subjective economic conditions, QOL, and work productivity scores.</p><p>In our previous analysis conducted for up to 12 months after diagnosis, the risk of long COVID was higher in females than in males, with an odds ratio of 2.54 (95% confidence interval: 1.43–4.53) [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, at 36 months, no sex difference was observed in the proportion of patients with and without long COVID, suggesting that the impact of sex on long COVID decreased after 3 years.</p><p>A search of the PubMed database using the keywords “long COVID or PASC” and “three years” in the title or abstract up to December 2024 identified six studies that monitored patients for 36 months after COVID diagnosis (Table <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">S4</xref>, Additional file). The results from long-term follow-up studies conducted in China have been reported [<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Han et al. reported that 728 of 1,359 (54%) patients hospitalized at a Wuhan hospital in China between January and May 2020 had at least one long COVID symptom at the 36-month follow-up [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Zhang et al. reported that for patients with residual lung lesions at discharge from Wuhan hospital, 160 of 728 (22%) had persistent respiratory symptoms at the 36-month follow-up [<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The prevalence of long COVID at 36 months in the present study was lower than that in the previous Chinese studies. The proportion of severe patients who required oxygen supplementation in China was 74.3% (n = 1,004) [<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], relative to 34.4% (n = 177) in the present study. Therefore, our sample of Japanese patients may have had less severe infection compared with the Chinese patients.</p><p>Regarding the number of symptoms, the proportion of patients with one to four symptoms decreased over time. However, the proportion of patients with 5–9 symptoms increased, and the proportion with ≥10 symptoms remained stable from 12 to 36 months, albeit the number of cases was small. The patients with five or more symptoms may overlap with those in the multiple symptoms cluster categorized in our previous cluster analysis [<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. With respect to psychiatric symptoms, Taquet et al. reported in the UK that patients in the recovered cluster at 6 months experienced few symptoms at 2–3 years post-infection, whereas those in the severe-case cluster exhibited decadent depression, fatigue, and subjective cognitive impairment [<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Common and persistent symptoms include fatigue, dyspnea, poor concentration, and memory impairment, whereas olfactory and taste disorders, which are often observed in patients with mild diseases [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], diminished over time. Yang et al. reported that 39.8% of patients had at least one symptom at 3 years, and the most common symptoms were fatigue, sleep disorder, joint pain, dyspnea, and muscle pain [<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], consistent with the findings of our study. Furthermore, analysis at 36 months using cluster classification in this study suggested that anosmia and dysgeusia tended to decrease, while fatigue, dyspnea, cough, and sputum tended to persist, and each cluster had their characteristics. The mechanisms underlying anosmia and dysgeusia in long COVID remain unclear. One hypothesis suggests that SARS-CoV-2 infection of olfactory mucosal supporting cells or pericyte cells may trigger local inflammation and cytokine release, or that local inflammation caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection of ACE2-expressing cells in the tongue epithelium or salivary glands may be involved [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Interestingly, while local symptoms such as anosmia and dysgeusia decreased at 36 months, systemic symptoms such as fatigue and dyspnea tended to persist. This finding indicates that symptoms involving local epithelial symptoms and systemic inflammatory responses in the long-term course of long COVID may have different pathophysiological mechanisms. In fact, regarding the mechanisms underlying fatigue and dyspnea, hypotheses exist suggesting that hyper-inflammatory response associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection trigger abnormal mast cell reactions, or that residual lung injury contributes to these symptoms [<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Further research is needed to elucidate the pathology.</p><p>In the current study, patients with asthma tended to have a long COVID at 36 months, which is consistent with the finding of a previous systematic review and meta-analysis [<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] reporting an odds ratio of 1.55 (95% confidence interval, 1.30–1.86) for long COVID among hospitalized patients with asthma. These findings suggest that asthma may increase the risk of long COVID.</p><p>Herein, we investigated the association between long COVID and vaccination status because the impact of vaccination on changes in long COVID was limited in the previous study [<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. We found that patients who received one or two vaccinations as well as those who received three or more vaccinations tended to exhibit fewer long COVID symptoms compared with unvaccinated patients. Our result is consistent with the finding of a systematic review suggesting that COVID-19 vaccination may reduce the incidence of long COVID [<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>The finding of poor economic situations at 36 months among patients with five or more symptoms was in line with that from a previous study in 2024, wherein 13.9% of patients had not returned to work at 3 months after the COVID diagnosis; however, when limited to patients with five or more symptoms, 27.8% had not returned to work [<xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Regarding the decrease in presenteeism in the continuous and relapsed groups in the present study, previous studies have reported that presenteeism can decrease by remote working [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and that productivity can decrease by the interruption of treatment for underlying diseases [<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Patients who were hospitalized and severely ill were less likely to return to work, had poor SF-36 scores, and could not resume their occupational activities as before [<xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Furthermore, we found a decrease in income among patients with long COVID, implying that long COVID may have a wide-ranging impact on socioeconomic factors.</p><p>Herein, presenteeism decreased in both the continuous and relapsed groups; however, absenteeism tended to worsen only in the continuous group. This suggests that when symptoms persist, going to work becomes challenging, and work performance declines. In contrast, when the symptoms do not persist but recur, going to work is easy, but work performance decreases. Notably, presenteeism and absenteeism were superior in the recovered group than in the other groups.</p><p>Few large-scale studies have evaluated the impact of COVID-19 over approximately 3 years, and even fewer have investigated its socioeconomic impact. We demonstrated that the patients’ economic condition worsened, particularly for those with many symptoms. Furthermore, no other studies have evaluated how the condition of patients classified by previous cluster analysis has changed over 3 years. We found that patients in the multiple symptoms cluster at 3 months after diagnosis also had multiple symptoms at 36 months post-infection, whereas patients in other clusters lost their characteristic symptoms.</p><p>Despite its strengths, this study had certain limitations. First, at 36 months post-infection, some patients may have found it difficult to determine whether their current symptoms were related to COVID-19. Additionally, no clinical investigations such as blood tests or imaging studies were conducted, resulting in a lack of objective indicators. This limitation makes it challenging to differentiate long COVID from SARS-CoV-2 reinfection, particularly in the absence of virological confirmation. Consequently, some cases of symptom recurrence due to reinfection may have been misclassified as long COVID. A certain number of patients were diagnosed with reinfection within 36 months, and fever was more frequent in these patients. Although the questionnaire asked about symptoms since the initial hospitalization, it is possible that the fever reported at 36 months was influenced by recent reinfection. Therefore, future studies should incorporate objective clinical indicators to improve diagnostic accuracy and interpretation of long-term symptoms. Second, healthy controls were not included. Thus, we could not compare the changes occurring in the outcome measures over time between patients and controls to determine any changes unrelated to long COVID. It was unclear whether the changes in economic conditions were due to long COVID or to daily life during the pandemic <italic toggle="yes">per se</italic>. Third, only patients from the first and third waves of the COVID-19 pandemic between January 2020 and February 2021 were included in this study. Therefore, our results cannot be applied to patients with long COVID that developed after that period.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>We clarified the actual long-term situation of long COVID in Japan. Several patients presented with persistent or relapsed symptoms. The long-term effects of long COVID are not only physical but also mental and economical. Thus, further research is needed to clarify the economical and physiological impact of long COVID.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p>coronavirus disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IQR</term><def><p>interquartile range</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>QOL</term><def><p>quality of life</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SARS-CoV-2</term><def><p>severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</p></def></def-item></def-list></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sm01"><title>Supplementary information</title><supplementary-material id="sm01_1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ehpm-30-084-s001.docx" id="d67e1701" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1:</bold>
<bold>Supplementary Appendix 1:</bold> Questionnaire on Economic Conditions. <bold>Table S1.</bold> Patient characteristics according to the presence or absence of long COVID at 36 months. <bold>Table S2.</bold> Symptoms at 36 months compared by reinfection. <bold>Table S3.</bold> Comparison of characteristics between patients with one to four symptoms and those with five or more symptoms. <bold>Table S4.</bold> Other studies researching long COVID up to 36 months. <bold>Figure S1.</bold> Consort diagram. <bold>Figure S2.</bold> Changes in all symptoms determined through questionnaire interview. <bold>Figure S3.</bold> Trends of patients. <bold>Figure S4.</bold> Percentage of patients by pattern of long COVID symptom appearance at each time point.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sm01_2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ehpm-30-084-s002.xlsx" id="d67e1726" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2:</bold>
<bold>Supplementary Appendix 2:</bold> Collaborators.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec><title>Declarations</title><sec><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>To confirm consent to participate in the study, an explanatory letter and a return envelope indicating the willingness to participate and cooperate were sent. This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Keio University School of Medicine (approval number: 20200243). Each participating institution obtained approval and permission to conduct this study from the institutional ethical review committee or a specified nonprofit organization of the Japan Clinical Research Council.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Consent for publication was obtained by the return of the explanatory letter and the consent envelope. All participants who returned the consent envelope agreed to the publication.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and material</title><p>The datasets generated and analyzed during the current study are not publicly available due to ethical restrictions but are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the MHLW Special Research Program [grant numbers JPMH20CA2054 and JPMH20CA2046) and MHLW Research on Emerging and Re-emerging Infectious Diseases and Immunization [grant numbers JPMH21HA2011 and JPMH23HA2011]. This work was also supported by the Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development (AMED) [grant number JP25fk0108707]. The funding sources had no role in the study.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization: H Terai, HI.</p><p>Data curation: TO, H Terai, H Tanaka, RT.</p><p>Format analysis: TO, H Terai, H Tanaka, RT.</p><p>Funding acquisition: HI, KF.</p><p>Investigation: AI, M Hosozawa, M Hori, YM, EK, HN, SC, HI, KF, all members of Japan Long COVID Research group.</p><p>Methodology: H Terai, HI.</p><p>Project administration: H Terai, HI.</p><p>Resources: H Terai, HI.</p><p>Supervision: HI, KF.</p><p>Visualization: TO, H Terai.</p><p>Writing - original draft: TO, H Terai, H Tanaka.</p><p>Writing - review &amp; editing: AI, M Hosozawa, M Hori, YM, EK, HN, SC, RT, KN, YS, HI, KF.</p><p>All authors take responsibility for this study and have approved the final version for publication.</p></sec><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Data management and statistical analysis of the study were supported by 3H Medi Solution (President: Hirotaka Takizawa). We would like to thank Editage (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.editage.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.editage.com</ext-link>) for English language editing and proofreading.</p></sec><sec><title>Collaborators</title><p>All members of the Japan long COVID research group are listed in Supplementary Appendix <xref rid="sm01" ref-type="sec">2</xref>.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r01"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>O’Mahoney</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Khunti</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long covid: risk factors, outcomes, and future directions for research</article-title>. <source>BMJ Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>e000257</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjmed-2022-000257</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9978746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36936586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r02"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>3-year outcomes of discharged survivors of COVID-19 following the SARS-CoV-2 omicron (B.1.1.529) wave in 2022 in China: a longitudinal cohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(23)00387-9</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38000376</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r03"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Topol</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Al-Aly</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Three-year outcomes of post-acute sequelae of COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1564</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-024-02987-8</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38816608</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11186764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r04"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Ely</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Fineberg</surname>
<given-names>HV</given-names></string-name>; <collab>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine Committee on Examining the Working Definition for Long Covid</collab>. <article-title>Long covid defined</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>391</volume>:<fpage>1746</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsb2408466</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39083764</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r05"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Thaweethai</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Jolley</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Karlson</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Levitan</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Levy</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>McComsey</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Development of a definition of postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>329</volume>:<fpage>1934</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2023.8823</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37278994</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10214179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r06"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Natarajan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Shetty</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Delanerolle</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Raymont</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>A systematic review and meta-analysis of long COVID symptoms</article-title>. <source>Syst Rev</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13643-023-02250-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37245047</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10220332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r07"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Franco</surname>
<given-names>JVA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Garegnani</surname>
<given-names>LI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Metzendorf</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Heldt</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Mumm</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Scheidt-Nave</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Post-Covid-19 conditions in adults: systematic review and meta-analysis of health outcomes in controlled studies</article-title>. <source>BMJ Med</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e000723</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjmed-2023-000723</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10826558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38293681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r08"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Moniz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Ruivinho</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Goes</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Soares</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Leite</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long COVID is not the same for everyone: a hierarchical cluster analysis of Long COVID symptoms 9 and 12 months after SARS-CoV-2 test</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1001</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-024-09896-8</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39294567</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11412022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r09"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Terai</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Kondo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Takemura</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Namkoong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Asakura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Cluster analysis of long COVID in Japan and association of its trajectory of symptoms and quality of life</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open Respir Res</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e002111</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2023-002111</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10895225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38395459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Terai</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Ishii</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Takemura</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Namkoong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Shimamoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Masaki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Comprehensive analysis of long COVID in a Japanese nationwide prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Respir Investig</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>802</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resinv.2023.08.008</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37783167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Nakagawara</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Namkoong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Terai</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Masaki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Tanosaki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Shimamoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Comprehensive and long-term surveys of COVID-19 sequelae in Japan, an ambidirectional multicentre cohort study: study protocol</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open Respir Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e001015</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2021-001015</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8628335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34836924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. About long COVID. Atlanta, GA: US Department of Health and Human Services, CDC; 2025. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/long-covid/about/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/long-covid/about/index.html</ext-link>. Accessed 2 Sep 2025.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Alwalid</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Long-term radiological and pulmonary function abnormalities at 3 years after COVID-19 hospitalisation: a longitudinal cohort study</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>2301612</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01612-2023</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38387969</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11255387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Taquet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Skorniewska</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>De Deyn</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Hampshire</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Trender</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Hellyer</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Cognitive and psychiatric symptom trajectories 2–3 years after hospital admission for COVID-19: a longitudinal, prospective cohort study in the UK</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>696</fpage>–<lpage>708</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(24)00214-1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39096931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Miwa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Mori</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Sekine</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Kimura</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Shiga</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Olfactory and taste dysfunctions caused by COVID-19: a nationwide study</article-title>. <source>Rhinology</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4193/Rhin23.034</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37690065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Okada</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Ishida</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Kanzaki</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Kawada</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Nagashima</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Terai</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Upper respiratory symptoms as long COVID: insight from a multicenter cohort study</article-title>. <source>OTO Open</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e120</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oto2.120</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38435484</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10909391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Two- and 3-year outcomes in convalescent individuals with COVID-19: A prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>J Med Virol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>e29566</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.29566</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38572864</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Krishnakumar</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Momtaz</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Sherwani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Mhapanker</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Gonuguntla</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Maleki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Pathogenesis and progression of anosmia and dysgeusia during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>280</volume>:<fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-022-07689-w</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36209486</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9548302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Fernández-de-Las-Peñas</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Palacios-Ceña</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Gómez-Mayordomo</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Palacios-Ceña</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Rodríguez-Jiménez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>de-la-Llave-Rincón</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Fatigue and Dyspnoea as Main Persistent Post-COVID-19 Symptoms in Previously Hospitalized Patients: Related Functional Limitations and Disability</article-title>. <source>Respiration</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000518854</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34569550</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8678253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Terry</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Heidel</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>AQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Dhand</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Risk of long covid in patients with pre-existing chronic respiratory diseases: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open Respir Res</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e002528</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2024-002528</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11784193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39884720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Nakagawara</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Morita</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Namkoong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Terai</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Chubachi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Asakura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Longitudinal long COVID symptoms in Japanese patients after COVID-19 vaccinations</article-title>. <source>Vaccine X</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>100381</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvacx.2023.100381</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37731516</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10507639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Byambasuren</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Stehlik</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Alcorn</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Glasziou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of Covid-19 vaccination on long covid: systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMJ Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e000385</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjmed-2022-000385</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9978692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36936268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Shimura</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Yokoi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Ishibashi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Akatsuka</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Remote work decreases psychological and physical stress responses, but full-remote work increases presenteeism</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>730969</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.730969</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34659039</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8514617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Ishimaru</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Tsuno</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Hori</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Okawara</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Yasuda</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="eastern"><surname>Fujino</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>. <article-title>Disrupted care during the COVID-19 state of emergency and productivity loss attributed to presenteeism in workers: a nationwide cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e050068</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-050068</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8671843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34907047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>