<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Internet Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Med Internet Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">224</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jmir</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMIR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Medical Internet Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1439-4456</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1438-8871</issn><publisher><publisher-name>JMIR Publications Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11982746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11982746.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11982746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11982746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40137051</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/69506</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">v27i1e69506</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physiological Sensors Equipped in Wearable Devices for Management of Long COVID Persisting Symptoms: Scoping Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mavragani</surname><given-names initials="A">Amaryllis</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name name-style="western"><surname>Popa</surname><given-names initials="E">Elena</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names initials="S">Santosh</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names initials="R">Reenu</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kukreti</surname><given-names initials="S">Shikha</given-names></name><degrees>BDS, MPH, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8370-3988</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib2" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="MT">Meng-Ting</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0006-4253-4272</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib3" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names initials="CY">Chun-Yin</given-names></name><degrees>RN, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0164-3468</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib4" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names initials="NY">Nai-Ying</given-names></name><degrees>RN, PhD</degrees><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3007-2537</contrib-id><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><address><institution>Department of Nursing, College of Medicine</institution><institution>National Cheng Kung University</institution><addr-line>No.1, Dasyue Rd, East District</addr-line><addr-line>Tainan City, 701</addr-line><country>Taiwan</country><phone>886 062353535</phone><email>konaiying@gmail.com</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution>Department of Nursing, College of Medicine</institution>
<institution>National Cheng Kung University</institution>
<addr-line>Tainan City</addr-line>
<country>Taiwan</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<institution>Deparment of Public Health, College of Medicine</institution>
<institution>National Cheng Kung University</institution>
<addr-line>Tainan City</addr-line>
<country>Taiwan</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<institution>Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</institution>
<institution>National Cheng Kung University</institution>
<addr-line>Tainan City</addr-line>
<country>Taiwan</country>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<institution>International Doctoral Program in Nursing, Deaprtment of Nursing, College of Medicine</institution>
<institution>National Cheng Kung University</institution>
<addr-line>Tainan City</addr-line>
<country>Taiwan</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding Author: Nai-Ying Ko <email>konaiying@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">479700</issue-id><elocation-id>e69506</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>26</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-11 00:25:35.220"><day>11</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>©Shikha Kukreti, Meng-Ting Lu, Chun-Yin Yeh, Nai-Ying Ko. Originally published in the Journal of Medical Internet Research (https://www.jmir.org), 26.03.2025.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work, first published in the Journal of Medical Internet Research (ISSN 1438-8871), is properly cited. The complete bibliographic information, a link to the original publication on <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.jmir.org/</ext-link>, as well as this copyright and license information must be included.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e69506.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2025/1/e69506"/><abstract><sec sec-type="background"><title>Background</title><p>Wearable technology has evolved in managing COVID-19, offering early monitoring of key physiological parameters. However, the role of wearables in tracking and managing long COVID is less understood and requires further exploration of their potential.</p></sec><sec sec-type="objective"><title>Objective</title><p>This review assessed the application and effectiveness of wearable devices in managing long COVID symptoms, focusing on commonly used sensors and their potential for improving long-term patient care.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>A literature search was conducted across databases including PubMed, Embase, Web of Science, and Cochrane Central, adhering to PRISMA-ScR (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews) reporting guidelines. The search was updated regularly throughout 2024. Abstract and full-text screening and selection were facilitated using Rayyan software developed by Qatar Computing Research Institute. Quality appraisal was conducted using the Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) critical appraisal tool to ensure the methodological rigor of the included studies. Data were extracted on study characteristics, wearable devices, sensors used, and monitored physiological parameters, and the results were synthesized in a narrative format.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 1186 articles were identified, and after duplicate removal and screening, 15 studies were initially included, with 11 studies meeting the criteria for final data synthesis. The included studies varied in design, ranging from observational to interventional trials, and involved sample sizes from 3 to 17,667 participants across different countries. In total, 10 different wearable devices were used to monitor long COVID symptoms, capturing key metrics such as heart rate variability, body temperature, sleep, and physical activity. Smartwatches were the most used wearable devices and fitness trackers with electrocardiography and photoplethysmography sensors were used to monitor heart rate, oxygen saturation, and respiratory rate. Of the 10 devices, 4 were Food and Drug Administration–approved, emphasizing the reliability and validation of the physiological data collected. Studies were primarily conducted in the United States and Europe, reflecting significant regional research interest in wearable technology for long COVID management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This review highlights the potential of wearable technology in providing continuous and personalized monitoring for long COVID patients. Although wearables show promise in tracking persistent symptoms, further research is needed to improve usability, validate long-term efficacy, and enhance patient engagement.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>wearable devices</kwd><kwd>long COVID</kwd><kwd>physiological sensors</kwd><kwd>review</kwd><kwd>COVID</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Wearable devices have emerged as essential tools in the detection and management of COVID-19 due to their ability to continuously monitor key physiological metrics such as heart rate, oxygen saturation, and body temperature in real time [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. These devices provide a proactive approach to identifying early signs of COVID-19, enabling timely interventions even before severe symptoms appear. Unlike acute COVID-19, where symptoms typically manifest and resolve within a few weeks, long COVID involves persistent and varied symptoms that can last for months or even years after the initial infection [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This complexity requires not only the ability to detect acute symptoms but also to monitor and manage chronic and fluctuating conditions over extended periods. Long COVID is a multifaceted condition that requires not only a deep understanding of its complex pathophysiology but also the integration of advanced digital technologies like wearables to effectively monitor, analyze, and manage its persistent and fluctuating symptoms over time. For patients with long COVID, wearable technology offers invaluable insight into persistent and fluctuating symptoms, helping to track and manage the condition over extended periods [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Despite their potential, there is still a need to refine and enhance the effectiveness of wearable technology, ensuring consistency in how different devices capture and analyze data for long COVID’s complex health effects.</p><p>Although a few studies have investigated the use of wearable devices for long COVID detecting symptoms, findings have varied due to differences in device types, sensor configurations, and analytical methods [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This variation underscores the need for a comprehensive review to synthesize existing knowledge, evaluate the effectiveness of different wearable technologies, and identify best practices for their application in long COVID management. A thorough review can help bridge the gaps in this research and guide future innovations in wearable technology for more effective monitoring and management of long COVID.</p><p>Wearable devices equipped with sensors for monitoring heart rate, respiratory rate, oxygen saturation, and body temperature have shown promise in detecting anomalies associated with COVID-19 [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Previous studies have explored the role of wearable devices in the detection of COVID-19 symptoms, demonstrating their potential to provide early warnings and facilitate timely interventions [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Research has demonstrated that changes in these metrics can indicate the onset of infection before severe symptoms manifest [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, while these devices have been effective in detecting acute COVID-19 symptoms, managing long COVID presents a more complex challenge, as it involves tracking persistent, fluctuating symptoms over extended periods, requiring continuous and adaptable monitoring strategies.</p><p>Understanding physiological sensors equipped in wearable devices is crucial because it enables continuous and precise monitoring of post-COVID complex symptoms, providing insights into their patterns and severity over time. Effective management of long COVID relies on identifying which sensors are most used and how they perform in capturing relevant physiological data. Current literature reveals a variety of sensors used in wearable devices, such as those for monitoring heart rate variability, oxygen saturation, and respiratory rate [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Given the urgency to address long COVID effectively, a comprehensive scoping review is essential to consolidate existing research, evaluate the efficacy of different sensors, and inform the development of more targeted and effective monitoring solutions. The primary objective of this scoping review is to evaluate and summarize existing research on the application of wearable technology for monitoring and managing persistent long COVID symptoms. This review seeks to identify the various wearable devices and sensors used, the specific physiological parameters they monitor, and the impact of this monitoring on the management of long COVID.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Overview</title><p>This scoping review was conducted in adherence with the PRISMA-ScR (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews) reporting guidelines [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Ethical approval was not required for this Scoping review. Refer to <xref rid="app1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 1</xref> for the PRISMA checklist.</p></sec><sec><title>Search Strategy and Selection Criteria</title><p>A comprehensive literature search was conducted across electronic databases, including PubMed (MEDLINE), Embase, Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (known as CENTRAL), and the international clinical trials registry platform. An additional search for datasets was conducted by SK using Google Scholar. The reference lists of included articles and reviews were manually searched to identify additional relevant studies for full-text screening. To ensure as current a review as possible, we repeated the above searches on June 15, 2024, and July 10, 2024, and again on November 15, 2024, before final analysis. The search strategy combined keywords related to long COVID (eg, “Long COVID,” “Post-Acute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 Infection,” “PASC”), wearable technology (eg, “wearable devices,” “smartwatches,” “fitness trackers”), and physiological monitoring (eg, “heart rate variability,” “blood oxygen saturation,” “respiratory rate;” <xref rid="app2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Selection Process and Data Extraction</title><p>This scoping review focused on studies that involved the use of wearable technology for monitoring or managing long COVID symptoms, specifically those published in peer-reviewed journals. It included research that reported on specific physiological parameters monitored by wearable devices, such as heart rate, respiratory rate, and oxygen saturation. The review excluded studies that did not specifically focus on long COVID, those that did not involve wearable technology, and those that were not available in full text, including review articles, conference abstracts, or incomplete articles. The initial abstract screening was conducted using Rayyan [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], a web-based tool for systematic reviews. The title and abstracts were independently reviewed by 2 reviewers (SK and MTL), and a third reviewer (NYK or CYL) acted as an arbitrator in case of disagreements between the 2 other reviewers.</p><p>Data were extracted from the included studies using a JBI standardized form. Information on study characteristics (eg, author, year, country), type of wearable device used, sensors used, physiological parameters monitored, and the outcomes related to long COVID management were recorded. A narrative synthesis was conducted to summarize the findings, with a focus on the types of wearable devices and sensors used, the physiological parameters monitored, and the impact on long COVID symptom management.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Overview</title><p>A total of 1186 articles were identified from 3 databases, 1 registry, and Google Scholar. Following the removal of duplicates and the initial eligibility screening, 16 studies were included in the review (<xref rid="figure1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). These 16 studies underwent a JBI quality assessment by the 2 authors, and out of these, only 11 met the criteria for data synthesis. Therefore, a total of 11 studies were included in the final review.</p><fig position="float" id="figure1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) 2020 flow diagram showing identification of studies from search databases.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e69506_fig1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Study Characteristics</title><p>A total of 11 studies met the inclusion criteria and were included in the review [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. These studies varied in design, ranging from observational studies to interventional trials, and were conducted across different countries (<xref rid="table1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The studies’ sample sizes ranged widely from as few as 3 participants [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] to as many as 17,667 participants [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the included 11 studies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="80" span="1"/><col width="190" span="1"/><col width="160" span="1"/><col width="160" span="1"/><col width="90" span="1"/><col width="170" span="1"/><col width="150" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author and year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country and region</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wearable technology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory status</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mekhael et al (2022) [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">New Orleans, United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective observational study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">710</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biostrap</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDA-approved<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lonini et al (2021) [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Illinois, United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pilot study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suprasternal notch device</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mekhael et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biostrap</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDA-approved</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xue et al (2022) [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ireland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Shimmer device, Finapres New Observation and Verification Apparatus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Published study by Schutte et al, 2004</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laguarta-Val et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Madrid, Spain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A nonrandomized parallel controlled trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar Ignite 2 device</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corrado et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pilot</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar H10 chest<break/>Strap or Fitbit Charge 5 smartwatch</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDA-approved (Fitbit)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corrêa et al (2023) [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Samsung mobile phone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Romaszko-Wojtowicz et al (2022) [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aidmed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">American National Standard for Ambulatory Electrocardiographs</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kerling et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective, randomized, parallel-group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Garmin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDA-approved</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stewart et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal case-control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,667</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDA-approved</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radin et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective observational study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">553</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDA-approved</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table1fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>FDA: Food and Drug Administration.</p></fn><fn id="table1fn2"><p><sup>b</sup>Not applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Wearable Devices and Sensors</title><p>The wearable devices identified in the studies included a mix of commercially available devices (eg, smartwatches, fitness trackers) and research-specific devices designed for health monitoring. In total, 10 different wearable devices were used to monitor long COVID symptoms, capturing key metrics such as heart rate variability (HRV), body temperature, sleep, and physical activity, providing a comprehensive understanding of the physiological effects of the condition. The most used devices were smartwatches (eg, Biostrap, Fitbit, Garmin) and fitness trackers, which are widely accessible and user-friendly.</p><p>In the included studies, seven different types of sensors were used, including photoplethysmography (PPG), electrocardiography (ECG), accelerometers, temperature sensors, gyroscopes, near-infrared spectroscopy, and electromyography (<xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). These sensors were used across multiple devices to monitor key physiological metrics such as heart rate, heart rate variability, peripheral capillary oxygen saturation (SpO<sub>2</sub>), respiratory rate, temperature, physical activity, and sleep-related movements [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Sensors integrated into these devices were primarily focused on monitoring cardiovascular and respiratory parameters.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Study wearable device details of included 11 studies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="130" span="1"/><col width="180" span="1"/><col width="310" span="1"/><col width="380" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physiological characteristics</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mekhael et al (2022) [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>PPG<sup>a</sup></p></list-item><list-item><p>Accelerometer</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Heart rate variability</p></list-item><list-item><p>Respiratory rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>SpO2<sup>b</sup></p></list-item><list-item><p>Movement</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lonini et al (2021) [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Adam sensor</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Body motions</p></list-item><list-item><p>Vibrations induced by sounds produced by heartbeats, coughing, or breathing</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mekhael et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>PPG</p></list-item><list-item><p>Accelerometer</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Heart rate variability</p></list-item><list-item><p>Respiratory rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>SpO2</p></list-item><list-item><p>Movement</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xue et al (2022) [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Digital artery photoplethysmography</p></list-item><list-item><p>Near-infrared spectroscopy</p></list-item><list-item><p>Electromyography</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Heart rate variability</p></list-item><list-item><p>SpO2</p></list-item><list-item><p>Fatigue</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laguarta-Val et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>ECG<sup>c</sup></p></list-item><list-item><p>temperature</p></list-item><list-item><p>accelerometer</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Temperature</p></list-item><list-item><p>Physical activity</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corrado et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>ECG</p></list-item><list-item><p>PPG</p></list-item><list-item><p>Accelerometer or gyroscope</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Heart rate variability</p></list-item><list-item><p>Heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sleep rotation movement</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corrêa et al (2023) [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Accelerometers</p></list-item><list-item><p>Gyroscopes (inertia sensors)</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Physical activity or mobility</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Romaszko-Wojtowicz et al (2022) [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>ECG</p></list-item><list-item><p>Temperature</p></list-item><list-item><p>PPG</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Temperature</p></list-item><list-item><p>Respiratory rate</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kerling et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>ECG</p></list-item><list-item><p>Accelerometer</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Physical activity</p></list-item><list-item><p>Heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sleep</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stewart et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>ECG</p></list-item><list-item><p>Accelerometers</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Heart rate variability</p></list-item><list-item><p>Physical activity and step count</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radin et al (2024) [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>ECG</p></list-item><list-item><p>Accelerometers</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Resting heart rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Physical activity and step count</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sleep</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table2fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>PPG: photoplethysmography.</p></fn><fn id="table2fn2"><p><sup>b</sup>SpO<sub>2</sub>: peripheral capillary oxygen saturation.</p></fn><fn id="table2fn3"><p><sup>c</sup>ECG: electrocardiography.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>ECG was used in 6 out of the 10 studies [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and was used to monitor heart rate, and heart rate variability, and to detect arrhythmias and other cardiac abnormalities.</p><p>PPG was used in 3 studies [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and was also used to measure heart rate, SpO₂ levels, and respiratory rate.</p><p>Accelerometers were integrated in 6 studies [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and used to monitor physical activity, sleep patterns, and mobility. They are critical for measuring movements and providing insights into daily activity levels and sleep quality.</p><p>Some studies reported the use of more advanced sensors, such as Adam sensors [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] which are used to monitor body motion as it works on vibrations.</p></sec><sec><title>Food and Drug Administration Approval and Device Validation</title><p>Devices like Fitbit [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], Polar Ignite [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], Garmin [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and Biostrap [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] got Food and Drug Administration (FDA) clearance for ECG functionalities, ensuring regulatory oversight and validation of the accuracy, safety, and reliability of the data collected (<xref rid="table1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In addition, the medical device Aidmed is approved by the American National Standard for Ambulatory Electrocardiographs.</p></sec><sec><title>Physiological Parameters Monitored</title><p>The physiological parameters monitored by these wearable devices included heart rate, heart rate variability, blood oxygen saturation, respiratory rate, skin temperature, and physical activity levels (Figure S1 in <xref rid="app2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 2</xref>). These parameters were chosen for their relevance to the symptoms experienced by individuals with long COVID, such as fatigue, autonomic dysfunction, and respiratory distress.</p></sec><sec><title>Country of Origin and Regional Focus</title><p>The studies were predominantly conducted in the United States and Europe.</p><p>Five studies originated in the United States, reflecting a significant research interest in wearable technology for long COVID in this region. The studies by Mekhael et al [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], Radin et al [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and Lonini et al [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] demonstrated extensive use of wearable devices like Biostrap (Sontakey), Fitbit (Google), and the Suprasternal notch device (Sonica Health<bold>)</bold> [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>European studies (United Kingdom, Spain, Poland, Germany, and Ireland) were also included, indicating a broad European engagement in the field. The study by Xue et al [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] in Ireland used the Shimmer device (Shimmer Sensing) and Finapres NOVA (Finapres Medical Systems), while the United Kingdom–based study by Corrado et al [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] used the Polar H10 chest strap (manufactured by Polar Electro) and Fitbit Charge 5 smartwatch. Similarly, the study by Kerling et al [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] in Germany used a Garmin device (Garmin Ltd).</p></sec><sec><title>Measurement Approaches in Long COVID Studies</title><p>Devices like Biostrap and Fitbit tracked sleep stages, HRV, and physical activity, helping to identify sleep disruptions and reduced physical endurance in patients (<xref rid="app3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 3</xref>). Tools such as the Suprasternal notch device and Shimmer captured critical data on altered respiration, cough frequency, and neurocardiovascular responses, shedding light on the multisystem impacts of long COVID. Interventions using devices like the Polar H10 and Garmin provided insights into HRV biofeedback and energy expenditure, aiding rehabilitation and symptom relief. Overall, these devices offer valuable tools for understanding and managing long COVID symptoms, enabling tailored care and long-term monitoring for affected individuals.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Principal Findings</title><p>This scoping review offers a comprehensive evaluation of the existing literature on the use of wearable health devices for monitoring and managing long COVID symptoms. The findings highlight the potential of wearable devices to revolutionize the management of this complex and persistent of long COVID symptoms by continuous physiological monitoring. This review identifies a wide range of wearable devices used in published studies, including commercially available smartwatches, fitness trackers, and research-specific medical devices. The use of 10 different wearable devices in detecting long COVID symptoms highlights the potential of these technologies in early symptom identification [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Sensors such as PPG, ECG, and accelerometers were commonly used to monitor cardiovascular and respiratory functions, reflecting the prevalence of these symptoms in long COVID patients. These devices continuously track key physiological parameters like heart rate, HRV, SpO<sub>2</sub>, and sleep patterns, allowing for the early detection of subtle health changes and proactive management of symptoms. The widespread use of accelerometers also emphasizes the growing importance of physical activity and sleep monitoring in managing chronic conditions like long COVID.</p><p>One notable finding in this review is that only a limited number of wearable devices have received FDA approval for specific health monitoring features. For instance, Fitbit’s ECG app, cleared by the FDA in 2020, is accessible on models such as the Sense, Sense 2, and Charge 5 [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Garmin has also secured FDA clearance for its ECG app, now available on compatible models like the Venu 2 Plus and Epix Pro series [<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The inclusion of FDA-approved devices brings a level of regulatory oversight, which is critical in clinical settings where wearable data may influence patient care decisions. FDA-approved wearables are validated for safety and effectiveness, offering health care providers more confidence in the data collected, especially when managing complex conditions like long COVID. In contrast, studies that do not emphasize the use of FDA-approved devices may face challenges in translating their findings into clinical practice. Comparing these studies underscores the need for standardized protocols and further validation studies to assess the long-term efficacy of wearable devices, ensuring their integration into routine health care for monitoring and managing long COVID symptoms.</p><p>This review also highlights issues related to user adherence and engagement. The success of wearable technology in managing chronic conditions like long COVID depends not only on the accuracy of the data collected but also on the willingness of users to consistently wear the devices and engage with the data. A few studies reported issues with user adherence, which could be attributed to factors such as device comfort, battery life, and the user interface of the accompanying apps [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Despite advancements in wearable technology, a significant gap exists in ensuring the seamless, secure, and standardized handling of the vast amounts of personal health data collected by these devices. In agreement with Smith et al [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], data interoperability and secure sharing across platforms, underscore the need for improved systems for data management and privacy to effectively integrate wearable technologies into clinical practice [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. These issues highlight the need for more user-centered design approaches in the development of wearable devices, ensuring that they are not only functional but also comfortable and easy to use over extended periods.</p><p>In terms of the geographic distribution of the studies, the majority were conducted in the United States [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and Europe [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>-<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], reflecting a significant research interest in these regions. This regional focus may be influenced by the availability of resources and funding for research on wearable technology, as well as the higher prevalence of long COVID in these areas due to the earlier and more widespread outbreaks of COVID-19. However, there is a need for more research in other regions, particularly in low- and middle-income countries, where the burden of long COVID may be significant but less well-documented. Furthermore, this review also found that while wearable devices offer valuable insights, the complexity and vast symptomatology of long COVID remain underexplored. Included studies focused on specific symptoms, with limited attention to common issues like fatigue, which is less frequently measured by these devices. This highlights the limitations of wearable technology in addressing the full spectrum of long COVID symptoms, underscoring the need for more comprehensive research.</p><p>This review provides a distinct perspective from typical COVID-19 wearable device studies by focusing on the long-term management of long COVID, rather than acute symptom detection. The key difference lies in the chronic nature of long COVID, where persistent and fluctuating symptoms, such as fatigue, cardiovascular issues, and sleep disturbances, require continuous, long-term monitoring. In contrast, COVID-19 reviews often emphasize short-term monitoring for acute symptoms, such as changes in respiratory rate and oxygen saturation, during the active phase of infection. Moreover, this review addresses unique challenges like user adherence and device validation for chronic use, which are less of a concern in acute COVID-19 monitoring.</p><p>There are several limitations to this review that must be acknowledged. One key limitation is the reliance on small sample sizes in some studies, which may reduce the statistical power and the ability to draw broader conclusions. In addition, the use of self-reported data in certain studies could introduce bias and affect the accuracy of the findings. Another limitation is the study design, with most studies lacking a longitudinal approach, which is crucial for assessing the long-term effectiveness of wearable technology in tracking long COVID symptoms. Furthermore, the number of studies available for review remains limited, highlighting the urgent need for more high-quality research to address the evolving challenges of long COVID management through wearable technology.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This review highlights the significant potential of wearable technology in managing long COVID by leveraging sensors like ECG, PPG, and accelerometers to monitor crucial physiological metrics such as heart rate, oxygen saturation, and physical activity. Wearable devices provide real-time insights into persistent and fluctuating symptoms, offering a more personalized approach to patient care. The advancements in device accuracy and the increasing availability of FDA-approved options further reinforce their importance in clinical use. Furthermore, enhancing the usability of these devices to improve user engagement will enable broader adoption and sustained monitoring over extended periods. Ultimately, wearable technology stands out as a promising tool to support individualized care and improve outcomes for long COVID patients, shaping the future of health care monitoring.</p></sec><sec><title>Future Implications and Requirements</title><p>For wearable technology to fully realize its potential in managing long COVID, several future implications are required. Standardization of protocols for sensor use and data interpretation is critical. This will allow for greater consistency across studies and ensure that health care providers can rely on the data generated by wearable devices. Wearability plays a crucial role in adherence, and future innovations should focus on compact, lightweight designs and hypoallergenic materials to enhance comfort and minimize user burden. Equally important is ensuring that sensors are accurate, durable, and capable of sustained performance in diverse real-world conditions. User-centered design is essential for improving adherence to wearable devices, ensuring that they are comfortable, easy to use, and integrated seamlessly into patients’ lives. Longitudinal studies are also needed to assess the sustained benefits of wearable technology in managing long COVID symptoms and improving health outcomes over time.</p><p>Building on the current research, the future applications of wearable health devices extend beyond long COVID management to other infectious diseases, such as influenza or emerging infectious diseases with similar symptomatology. Wearable devices that continuously monitor vital signs such as body temperature, heart rate, and respiratory functions could facilitate early illness detection and proactive management by identifying subtle physiological changes indicative of infection. Such applications are particularly relevant for influenza, where symptoms frequently overlap with long COVID, including fatigue, respiratory issues, and fever. In addition, integrating wearable data into public health systems could provide real-time insights into disease trends and hotspots, supporting more responsive and informed health interventions. Future efforts should also explore the integration of advanced data analytics and artificial intelligence to interpret sensor data more effectively, paving the way for personalized health care solutions.</p><p>This review illustrates that wearables have the potential to reshape not only individual patient care but also population-level disease management, positioning them as vital tools in addressing both chronic and acute public health challenges. Overall, to fully integrate wearable devices into long COVID management, a concerted effort is required to address these challenges. By developing standardized methods, improving device usability, and expanding research across diverse populations, wearable technology could become a cornerstone in the effective long-term management of long COVID.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflicts of Interest: None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><app-group><supplementary-material id="app1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Multimedia Appendix 1</label><p>PRISMA extension for scoping reviews checklist (PRISMA-ScR).</p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e69506_app1.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File , 86 KB" id="d100e1107" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="app2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Multimedia Appendix 2</label><p>Literature search for conducting scoping review: documentation form.</p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e69506_app2.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File , 1013 KB" id="d100e1111" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="app3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Multimedia Appendix 3</label><p>Study outcomes and results.</p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e69506_app3.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File , 23 KB" id="d100e1115" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></app-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="abb1">ECG</term><def><p>electrocardiography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb2">FDA</term><def><p>Food and Drug Administration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb3">HRV</term><def><p>heart rate variability</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb4">JBI</term><def><p>Joanna Briggs Institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb5">PPG</term><def><p>photoplethysmography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb6">PRISMA-ScR</term><def><p>Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb7">SpO2</term><def><p>peripheral capillary oxygen saturation</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijndaele</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wareham</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brage</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wearable-device-measured physical activity and future health risk</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1385</fpage><lpage>1391</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/32807930" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-1012-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">32807930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">10.1038/s41591-020-1012-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32807930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7116559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wearable health devices in health care: narrative systematic review</article-title><source>JMIR mHealth uHealth</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e18907</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://mhealth.jmir.org/2020/11/e18907/" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/18907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33164904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">v8i11e18907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33164904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7683248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ely</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fineberg</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><collab>National Academies of Sciences‚ Engineering‚ Medicine Committee on Examining the Working Definition for Long Covid</collab></person-group><article-title>Long covid defined</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2024</year><month>11</month><day>07</day><volume>391</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>1746</fpage><lpage>1753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsb2408466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">39083764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39083764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lautman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobota</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wearable devices: implications for precision medicine and the future of health care</article-title><source>Annu Rev Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-med-052422-020437?crawler=true&amp;mimetype=application/pdf" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-med-052422-020437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">37983384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37983384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mekhael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Hajjar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noujaim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pottle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dagher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chouman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrouche</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studying the effect of long COVID-19 infection on sleep quality using wearable health devices: observational study</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>24</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e38000</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2022/7/e38000/" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/38000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">35731968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">v24i7e38000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35731968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9258734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dirks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scharbau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennemann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dopfer-Jablonka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lampe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzmann</surname><given-names>JHW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tegtbur</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drick</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pink</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haufe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of a randomized-controlled and online-supported physical activity intervention on exercise capacity, fatigue and health related quality of life in patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome</article-title><source>BMC Sports Sci Med Rehabil</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://bmcsportsscimedrehabil.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13102-024-00817-5" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13102-024-00817-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">38308307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">10.1186/s13102-024-00817-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38308307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10835885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Channa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skibinska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burget</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rise of wearable devices during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review</article-title><source>Sensors (Basel)</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>5787</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/resolver?pii=s21175787" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s21175787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">34502679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">s21175787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34502679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8434481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>SHR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>YJX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wearable technology for early detection of COVID-19: a systematic scoping review</article-title><source>Prev Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>107170</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/35878707" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2022.107170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">35878707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S0091-7435(22)00219-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35878707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9304072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weizman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuss</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of wearable technology to enhance response to the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic</article-title><source>Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/32668337" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2020.06.048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">32668337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S0033-3506(20)30286-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32668337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7328532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capodilupo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lastella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roach</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capodilupo</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyzing changes in respiratory rate to predict the risk of COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e0243693</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0243693" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0243693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33301493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">PONE-D-20-19303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33301493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7728254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Syversen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dosis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wearable sensors as a preoperative assessment tool: a review</article-title><source>Sensors (Basel)</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>482</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/resolver?pii=s24020482" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s24020482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">38257579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">s24020482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38257579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10820534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levac</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horsley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akl</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartling</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldcroft</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garritty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godfrey</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares-Weiser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tunçalp</surname><given-names>Ö</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PRISMA extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>169</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.acpjournals.org/doi/abs/10.7326/M18-0850?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub0pubmed" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M18-0850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">30178033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">2700389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouzzani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammady</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedorowicz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elmagarmid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rayyan-a web and mobile app for systematic reviews</article-title><source>Syst Rev</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>210</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://systematicreviewsjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13643-016-0384-4" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13643-016-0384-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">27919275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">10.1186/s13643-016-0384-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27919275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5139140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lonini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shawen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botonis</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fanton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mummidisetty</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rushin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid screening of physiological changes associated with COVID-19 using soft-wearables and structured activities: a pilot study</article-title><source>IEEE J Transl Eng Health Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4900311</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/33665044" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/JTEHM.2021.3058841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33665044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">4900311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33665044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7924653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duggan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero-Ortuno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel methodology for the synchronous collection and multimodal visualization of continuous neurocardiovascular and neuromuscular physiological data in adults with long COVID</article-title><source>Sensors (Basel)</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1758</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/resolver?pii=s22051758" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s22051758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">35270905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">s22051758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35270905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8914998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laguarta-Val</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varillas-Delgado</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lizcano-Álvarez</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molero-Sánchez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melian-Ortiz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cano-de-la-Cuerda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiménez-Antona</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of aerobic exercise therapy through nordic walking program in lactate concentrations, fatigue and quality-of-life in patients with long-COVID syndrome: a non-randomized parallel controlled trial</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1035</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/resolver?pii=jcm13041035" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm13041035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">38398348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">jcm13041035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38398348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10889227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corrado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iftekhar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halpin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarrant</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HEART rate variability biofeedback for LOng COVID dysautonomia (HEARTLOC): results of a feasibility study</article-title><source>Adv Rehabil Sci Pract. 2024</source><year>2024</year><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.09.09.23295208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10826406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38298551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corrêa</surname><given-names>BDC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>EGR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belgamo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>GHL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>ARN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paranhos</surname><given-names>ACM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>ADS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callegari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa E Silva</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quaresma</surname><given-names>JAS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falcão</surname><given-names>LFM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smartphone-based evaluation of static balance and mobility in long-lasting COVID-19 patients</article-title><source>Front Neurol</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1277408</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/38148981" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2023.1277408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">38148981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38148981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10750373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mekhael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noujaim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Younes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Hajjar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chouman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dagher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreidieh</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrouche</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donnellan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compliance challenges in a longitudinal COVID-19 cohort using wearables for continuous monitoring: observational study</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>e43134</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2023//e43134/" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/43134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">36763647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">v25i1e43134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36763647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10131852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romaszko-Wojtowicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maksymowicz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarynowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaśkiewicz</surname><given-names>Ł</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czekaj</surname><given-names>Ł</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doboszyńska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telemonitoring in long-COVID patients-preliminary findings</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>5268</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/resolver?pii=ijerph19095268" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19095268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">35564663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">ijerph19095268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35564663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9103243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranjan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sankesara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laiou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>RJB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Folarin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological presentation and risk factors of long COVID in the UK using smartphones and wearable devices: a longitudinal, citizen science, case–control study</article-title><source>The Lancet Digital Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e640</fpage><lpage>e650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2589-7500(24)00140-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39138096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11832456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coughlin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadaleta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandit</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinhubl</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term changes in wearable sensor data in people with and without Long Covid</article-title><source>NPJ Digit Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>246</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-024-01238-x" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41746-024-01238-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">39271927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">10.1038/s41746-024-01238-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39271927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11399345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>FDA-cleared wearables and their health benefits</article-title><source>MUO</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-12-02</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.makeuseof.com/fda-cleared-wearables-health-benefits/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.makeuseof.com/fda-cleared-wearables-health-benefits/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Understand your body better with the new ECG app from Garmin</article-title><source>Garmin</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-12-02</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/newsroom/press-release/sports-fitness/understand-your-body-better-with-the-new-ecg-app-from-garmin/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.garmin.com/en-US/newsroom/press-release/sports-fitness/understand-your-body-better-with-the-new-ecg-app-from-garmin/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wearable devices for Long COVID: prospects, challenges and options</article-title><source>Asian Bioeth Rev</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>769</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41649-023-00272-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">39398460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39398460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11465094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>ZTH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reshaping healthcare with wearable biosensors</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>4998</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-26951-z" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-26951-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">36973262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">10.1038/s41598-022-26951-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36973262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10043012</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>