<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yale J Biol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Yale J Biol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">504</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">yjbm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YJBM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0044-0086</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1551-4056</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12466300</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12466300.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12466300</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12466300</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41030634</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.59249/WZRE2458</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">yjbm983341</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group><series-title>Focus: History of Medicine</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>“In-Flu-Enza and Out-Flew Hair:” Post-Epidemic Health and the
Importance of the History of Epidemics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names initials="BL">Bethany L.</given-names></name><role>conceptualized and wrote the essay.</role><xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff>Affiliate Faculty, Health &amp; Medical Humanities Program, University of North
Carolina, Charlotte, NC, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>To whom all correspondence should be addressed:
Bethany L. Johnson, <email>bethanyjohnson@uncc.edu</email>; ORCID:
<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1949-041X">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1949-041X</uri>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>98</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">497599</issue-id><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-01 09:26:11.207"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©2025, Yale Journal of Biology and
Medicine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons CC BY-NC license, which permits use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.
You may not use the material for commercial purposes.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="yjbm_98_3_341.pdf"/><abstract><p>When COVID-19 survivors reported ongoing symptoms or new health concerns
following their infections in 2020 and early 2021, many medical practitioners
and health agencies questioned the connection between novel viruses and
long-term health impacts. Medical historians studying epidemics understand the
connection between viral infection and health complications emerging immediately
or years or decades later. In this essay, I explore the similarities between the
medical fallout of the 1918 influenza and COVID-19 pandemics. Despite the
differences between the viruses, these novel strains produced similar medium-
and long-term health difficulties, including cardiovascular dysfunction and
crushing fatigue. As I demonstrate, a significant difference between these two
pandemics is in the response by medical practitioners. Following influenza,
practitioners expected new and worsening health issues and took their patients’
complaints seriously, offering support through food delivery, convalescent care,
specialist oversight, and in-home nursing. Early in the COVID-19 pandemic, many
practitioners characterized ongoing or new symptoms as anxiety. Patients led
efforts to recognize Long COVID as an authentic medical condition, and today,
physicians around the country refer their patients to Long COVID clinics. The
value of medical history is apparent in this comparison—if practitioners
understand how historical epidemics impacted various populations, they expect
that in the epidemic aftermath or the period following an acute epidemic crisis,
not all patients get well. Including the history of epidemics in public health
education, continuing education programming, and even medical school curricula
can resist epidemic erasure and empower medical practitioners to expect the
unexpected.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>influenza</kwd><kwd>history of medicine</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>medical education</kwd><kwd>Long COVID&#x2028;</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>Funding for this research was provided by the Consortium for
History of Science, Technology and Medicine, Philadelphia,
PA.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>In January 2020, as the COVID-19 pandemic drew international attention, Americans
watched the 2011 movie <italic toggle="yes">Contagion</italic>, pushing the film to No. 10 on the
“iTunes Top Movie List” [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In the film, the
character Beth Emhoff contracts a flu-like illness on a business trip abroad and
dies two days later in the United States. The disease becomes a pandemic, and the
film traces the efforts of various physicians and institutions, like the CDC, to
isolate the virus and create a vaccine, even as public panic results in widespread
social disorder. At the end of the film, the US government distributes an effective
vaccine via lottery, and those with vaccine bracelets can move about freely. Like
me, millions of Americans viewed this and other familiar imaginaries of a pandemic
world (eg, <italic toggle="yes">Outbreak</italic>, 1995) to consider how a not-yet-here pandemic
might reshape our lives.<sup>1</sup> As COVID-19 exploded in the US and subsequent
waves continued to complicate daily life with quarantines, social distancing, and
shifting masking regulations, it became even more evident that epidemics do not end
as they do in movies. Instead, they linger as individuals and communities contend
with epidemic fallout, including the health impacts experienced by survivors.</p><p>As a historian of medicine and epidemics, living through a global pandemic deepened
my certainty that studying historical epidemics has value in the present—for
individuals, communities, and institutions, including medical schools. While plague
historians were long engaged with disease history, Rosenberg’s 1968 <italic toggle="yes">The
Cholera Years</italic> helped catalyze focused attention on modern epidemics
within American historical scholarship.<sup>2</sup> In 1976, Alfred Crosby explored
the 1918 influenza epidemic in <italic toggle="yes">Epidemic and Peace 1918</italic>, tracing the
disease through the US with a close study of Philadelphia and San Francisco. Crosby
considered how politicians, public health systems, and local inhabitants responded
to the outbreak, and his incisive work encouraged generations of historians to study
influenza.<sup>3</sup> Today, medical history is a diverse and growing field,
including the work of historians of epidemics and pandemics, and, recently, epidemic
ends [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Epidemic historians publish in diverse journals, including the
<italic toggle="yes">Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</italic>. In 2020, the
<italic toggle="yes">American Historical Review</italic> featured Monica Green’s “The Four
Black Deaths,” highlighting the utility of paleogenetics in historical epidemic
analysis and the importance of studying plague beyond Europe [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Studying historical epidemics allows scholars to observe communities, regions, and
nations under threat from an external force, ostensibly with the power to sicken or
kill individuals of any rank and from any class or ethnic group. Often recounted as
events with discernable temporal boundaries, studies of epidemics generally begin
just before an outbreak, follow the epidemic to its zenith, discuss the days or
weeks following the worst of the crisis, and conclude with an overview of the impact
years later (eg, the rise of flu season). This traditional narrative arc provides
insights into disease epidemiology, social responses to public health crises, and
the intersections between local and national politics and individual health. This
structure, termed “dramaturgical” by epidemic historian Charles Rosenberg, depicts
epidemics as biological and social phenomena in which communities “act out
proprietary rituals that incorporate and reaffirm fundamental social values and
modes of understanding” [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. How epidemics
interrupt social hierarchies or affirm social values is explored, in part, by
examining how societies respond to the needs of victims and survivors.</p><p>When the novel virus COVID-19 entered the grand drama of human biology, media sources
sought historians who could describe how societies responded to global pandemics in
the past. Newspapers such as <italic toggle="yes">The New York Times</italic> published pieces on
the 1918 influenza outbreak, including the epidemic in Philadelphia [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. As COVID-19 spread and communities worldwide
went into lockdown, scholars interested in the questions posed by epidemics and
their outcomes reconsidered how and when epidemics end. Are epidemic ends defined by
dropping case rates and hospitalizations, the end of political recognition, the
cessation of large-scale public health response, individual behavioral adjustment,
some combination of these, or something else altogether [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]?</p><p>In 2022, a special issue of <italic toggle="yes">Centaurus</italic> edited by historian Erica
Charters titled “How Epidemics End” offered theories on epidemic ends from
mathematicians, geographers, bioarcheologists, and historians, among others.
Historian Virginia Berridge distinguished between the medical end of epidemics,
marked by case drop-off following the introduction of medical technologies, like
vaccines or pharmaceutical treatments, the definitional end when the acute epidemic
crisis is over and the disease “assimilates into dominant trends in contemporary
public health,” and the political end, when an epidemic becomes politically neutral
among the voting public [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The work of Erica
Charters, Virginia Berridge, Einar Wigen, and other historians encouraged me to
reconsider the dramaturgical arc of the 1918 influenza outbreak.</p><p>Most influenza scholarship highlights the precipitous drop-off of cases at the end of
the fall 1918 wave. However, as COVID-19 demonstrated, survivors can experience
unexpected health problems in the wake of infection. My earlier interest in
epidemics shifted toward epidemic ends, particularly as I read new media calling the
influenza of 1918 “forgotten” [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. I focused
on Philadelphia—one of the hardest-hit cities in America—as a site for the study of
epidemic ends because the high morbidity rate offered me a path into the
aftermath.<sup>4</sup> As I mined untapped archival resources, including the
student and institutional records of Girard College and the papers of the Emergency
Aids of Pennsylvania, I found surprising overlaps between the health problems and
chronic illnesses that followed influenza in 1918 and COVID-19 in 2020 and 2021,
despite the etiological differences between the diseases. Familiarity with these
overlaps demonstrates the utility of epidemic history as a resource for
reconsidering how and when epidemics end, including for survivors who struggle to
get well.</p><p>I also observed that the response from medical practitioners varied significantly
between the two pandemics, particularly the post-infection response. In the early
20th century, when epidemic disease still took many lives each year, physicians
understood that a novel disease could cause unusual health problems in survivors.
Early in the COVID-19 pandemic, many medical practitioners resisted the notion that
survivors could remain unwell or become sicker, in part because many were unfamiliar
with the long history of viral infection and latent health complications. Long-term
viral conditions like post-polio syndrome may be unfamiliar to doctors trained in
the last two decades; some will never meet a polio survivor, much less treat the
late onset of symptoms. Conversely, pediatricians are familiar with subacute
sclerosing panencephalitis (SSPE), a condition that causes progressive brain
inflammation and is nearly always fatal. While SSPE kills infants in America each
year, the public is likely unaware that among measles survivors, 1:1367 children
under 5 years and 1:609 children under 12 months at the time of infection will
experience SSPE [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The disease has a latency
period of about 9 years, meaning SSPE does not afflict survivors until they are
around 12-years-old [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. A 2016 study
concluded, “SSPE demonstrates the high human cost of ‘natural’ measles immunity”
[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. If we do not understand the medical
implications of epidemic survival, we cannot communicate the complications of
surviving infectious diseases to the public. This is particularly important today,
as local, state, and federal policy changes could prompt the return of widespread
outbreaks of tuberculosis, measles, and other preventable diseases.</p><p>As history demonstrates, the medical fallout from a novel viral strain in humans can
create all kinds of health complications, even among healthy adults who experienced
light cases. Physicians, nurses, and other medical practitioners discussed the
health challenges following influenza in detail in the months following the fall
1918 influenza outbreak. Many feared the “wicked malady” influenza permanently
harmed their patients, even though they were unsure what said malady was [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. By exploring the overlapping sequelae of the
1918 influenza and COVID-19, we begin to see that our expectations for epidemic ends
do not reflect the reality of survivors whose lives are permanently altered by viral
infection.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s2"><title>Similarities: Hair Loss and Other Post-Infection Health Problems</title><p>On Sunday, August 3, 1919, an advertisement in the <italic toggle="yes">Richmond Times-Dispatch
</italic>displayed a young woman with long, lush, wavy tresses smiling down at a dog
beneath the phrase “In-Flu-Enza and Out-Flew Hair” [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]<sup>5</sup>. This advertisement for Sergeant’s Mange Medicine echoed
a story familiar to many Americans that summer, as many survivors of the fall 1918
influenza wave grappled with severe debility, chronic disease, and prolonged
symptoms like coughing, fatigue, and loss of appetite. The advertisement stated that
the outbreak “left most people in a run down [<italic toggle="yes">sic</italic>] condition; some
developed rheumatism, a few got deaf; but the greatest malady caused mental anguish
rather than physical pain. It was the loss of hair [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].” Author and historian Francis Russell, who was a third grader in
Dorchester, Massachusetts, during the 1918 outbreak, recalled a rhyme that students
sang while jumping rope at recess:</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">I had a little bird</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">And its name was Enza</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">I opened the window</italic>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes">And in-flew-Enza</italic> [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</p><p>The short poem became enough of a cultural touchpoint that nearly a year later, the
purveyors of Sergeant’s Mange Medicine knew readers were in on the joke, as it were.
But how many readers were still waiting for their hair to return? How many others
continued to struggle with other influenza-related health problems? As my research
on the influenza aftermath in Philadelphia suggests, many thousands of Americans
struggled with ongoing ill health and chronic illness well into 1919 and
beyond.</p><p>Hair loss is one of the many symptoms 17-year-old survivor Grace Meyercord faced
after her near-death brush with influenza. After becoming ill in October 1918, her
high fever turned her hair white and then it fell out in clumps [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Author Katherine Anne Porter described her
hair loss in several interviews, and the story appears in at least two biographies.
Givner [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] reported that during Porter’s
bout with influenza, a dangerously high fever caused her dark hair to turn white and
fall out; Unrue [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] stated that her hair
also grew back white. In Porter’s novella <italic toggle="yes">Pale Horse Pale Rider</italic>
(1939), which explored the influenza outbreak in Colorado, the character Miranda Gay
described her unusual symptoms: “I can’t smell or see or hear today. I must have a
fearful cold [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].” During the COVID-19 waves
in 2020 and early 2021, loss of smell or taste was also an early indicator of an
infection.</p><p>In early 2020, Americans did not just watch epidemic films. They also flocked to
social media—especially the new platform TikTok—sharing sourdough starters, family
dance routines, and animal antics to escape the loneliness and uncertainty of
lockdown. Alongside these posts, social media users asked questions about their
post-COVID experience, including the experience of hair loss. Dermatologists posted
videos on YouTube explaining the phenomenon [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Researchers in Saudi Arabia found that 52% of their study
participants (n=806) experienced hair loss after a COVID-19 infection, particularly
those who experienced a high fever [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. As
dermatologists on TikTok and YouTube shared, this type of hair loss, known as
<italic toggle="yes">telogen effluvium</italic>, occurs when the hair growth cycle shifts 3
to 4 months after a stressful health event like a viral infection, a high fever, or
a severe life stressor.<sup>6</sup> Most COVID-19 survivors’ hair returned over
time, just as it did for influenza survivors. Interestingly, temporary and permanent
sensory loss and hair loss are not the only similarities between the health
aftermath of COVID-19 and influenza.</p><p>Each epidemic imprints vestiges of itself in survivors and their communities, whether
physical, social, economic or all of these. Physical changes like scars (eg,
smallpox) or paralysis (eg, polio) are readily apparent after some outbreaks.
Respiratory illnesses, like influenza and COVID-19, affect the body internally,
making their impact less visible. Often, the echoes of respiratory epidemics are
heard rather than seen—survivors struggling for breath after the 1918 influenza
pandemic or the irregular, rapid heartbeat of some COVID-19 survivors heard through
a stethoscope [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The experience of the COVID-19 infection lives on in some,
causing dizziness, memory impairment, extreme fatigue, depression, and deep,
unrelenting pain, symptoms which are also difficult to see. Similarly, after
influenza, survivors faced lingering symptoms such as limb weakness, exhaustion,
cardiac dysfunction, cognitive difficulties, headaches, and what was then termed
“poor mental hygiene,” or what today we call mental illness.</p><p>The physical fallout from the 1918 influenza was severe and varied. Institutions
caring for orphaned children described pediatric survivors with hair loss, hearing
issues, strabismus, impaired heart function, post-influenzal paralysis, and even
“cases of insanity” [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Among adults, doctors reported post-influenzal
tuberculosis, nephritis (ie, kidney disease), and a lengthy recovery period during
which some patients were too weak to work [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The director of the Visiting Nurses Society in Philadelphia stated that
‘recovered’ is not a word that can be generally applied…people apparently recover,
though often without regaining normal vigor, and then weeks later a serious malady
directly traceable appears [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].”</p><p>Well-known Philadelphian surgeon John Deaver noted that the “insidious disease”
affected nearly every organ and bodily system and, thus, the body’s resistance to
other diseases or complications, including neuralgias, phlebitis, and parotitis (ie,
mumps) [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Some physicians believed that a
global pandemic of what was called encephalitis lethargica (EL) emerged because of a
widespread, lowered resistance to disease among survivors [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. EL causes brain swelling, heavy somnolence, and sometimes
coma and paralysis. In 1919, Philadelphia’s Department of Public Health and
Charities made EL a reportable disease. Philadelphia neurologist Dr. Charles Frazier
treated post-influenza headaches, brain fog, and other neurological conditions as
part of his treatments for EL. Patient intakes asked about past influenza infections
to help Frazier assess neurological dysfunction and possible encephalitic
inflammation [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Whether or not these
diseases were related, medical practitioners in Philadelphia were confident that
neurological dysfunction and infections like EL could and did follow influenza
survival.</p><p>Beginning early in the COVID-19 pandemic, some patients did not improve after getting
a negative test result or they developed new symptoms months after their infection.
In the edited collection <italic toggle="yes">The Long Covid Reader</italic> written by
self-identified “long haulers,” patients like Vanessa Svihla described months of
chest pain, fatigue, tachycardia, brain fog, headaches, and dizziness [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].<sup>7</sup> During Ellen MacKenzie’s
second COVID-19 infection, she developed hypertension and suffered a heart attack.
Eighteen months later, she continued to struggle with high blood pressure, fatigue,
cognitive challenges, and a lost sense of taste [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Judith Rosenbaum shared that her daily experiences vary: “It’s the
uncertainty that gets me,” she wrote. “I reach tentatively into my limbs to take
stock. Will this be a good day or a bad day [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]?” Brian Burke, who fell ill in early 2021, shared that he rarely
ventures beyond the local library or neighborhood grocery store, as even short trips
leave him drained. “I have to lie down when I get home—if I even make it home before
collapsing,” he says [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>Influenza and COVID-19 come from different virus
families—<italic toggle="yes">Orthomyxoviridae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Coronaviridae</italic>,
respectively— and spread through the body in distinct ways. Nevertheless, survivors
of novel virus strains in 1918 and 2020 reported some of the same health struggles
in the aftermath, including weakness and fatigue, cardiac conditions, brain fog,
hair loss, and lowered resistance to other diseases. Yet the experience of influenza
and COVID-19 survivors diverged in their pursuit of medical care tailored to
post-viral medical issues. In an oral history interview, Rowan Reyes recounted
surviving COVID twice, only to spend 2 years searching for a cardiologist who took
their sudden, erratic heartbeats and frequent lightheadedness seriously [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
The process of seeking medical support differed because many doctors in 2020 lacked
sufficient knowledge of epidemic history and did not anticipate patients struggling
with lingering or new health issues following their infections.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>Differences: Seeking Medical Support and Formal Diagnosis</title><p>In 1918, visiting nurses, hospital physicians, and specialists observed the ongoing
health struggles of survivors as a standard—even expected—consequence of viral
infection. Despite the assumption that some patients would experience lasting health
conditions, doctors remained humbled by their lack of knowledge—practitioners were
not sure if influenza was bacterial, filterable (viral), or something else as yet
undiscovered. Physicians admitted that the scientific advancements and life-saving
interventions effective for other epidemics (eg, diphtheria) proved irrelevant for
the influenza of 1918. Despite their inability to treat flu cases effectively,
medical practitioners in Philadelphia understood that patients needed care and
support via daily nursing, special diets, extended rest, and referrals to
specialists like the neurologist Dr. Charles Frazier, or the experts at the Henry
Phipps Institute, who treated tuberculosis. Although the extent of medical
discoveries limited treatments at the time—neither antibiotic nor steroidal
treatments were available—doctors supported patients using the full range of
available treatments including convalescent care, extended rest, and nutritional
support to aid the return of vitality and health.</p><p>Follow-up care at major institutions like the Philadelphia General Hospital continued
through 1919. A doctor at Philadelphia General shared that in the year after the
fall influenza wave, medical practitioners observed “many manifestations of the
aftermath. Here appeared a case of tuberculosis, unmistakably traceable to a
previous acute influenzal infection, and there a toxic or other psychosis, appearing
days, or even weeks after…influenza had disappeared [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].” The Visiting Nurses Society of Philadelphia continued to raise
funds for survivor care, up to and including the payment of rental bills and the
provision of food, which provided ailing survivors additional time to convalesce
with the oversight of medical providers.</p><p>Unfortunately, many COVID-19 survivors did not receive this kind of support from
their medical practitioners, particularly between the spring of 2020 and October of
2021. More than a dozen doctors dismissed Candice Johnson’s account of the unusual
symptoms that followed her COVID-19 infection [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. When Dr. Lee Bar-Eli didn’t fully recover after her COVID-19
infection, she faced an uncomfortable change in perspective. “I not only became a
patient,” she reflects, “but a patient whose symptoms weren’t always taken
seriously. Experiencing that firsthand was incredibly painful [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].” Many patients experienced medical professionals
dismissing their symptoms or blaming them on anxiety. In <italic toggle="yes">The Long Covid
Reader</italic>, patient John Zeising argued that some medical practitioners
held an “unsaid (or stated) presumption that our physical symptoms are
manifestations of depression or anxiety [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].”<sup>8</sup> According to one review of Long COVID literature,
doctors can mistake dysautonomia, or dysregulation in the autonomic nervous system,
for a psychiatric or psychological condition [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The authors note that “anxiety scales often include autonomic
symptoms such as tachycardia and depression scales include symptoms such as fatigue,
“resulting in misdiagnosis and frustration for Long COVID patients and medical
providers [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].” And of course, not being
believed can prompt both anxiety and depression.</p><p>Early in the COVID-19 pandemic (2020-2021), online communities took seriously the
reality of complicated health after a COVID-19 infection. Within these groups, folks
began to refer to themselves as “long-haulers” [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Patient-led advocacy groups formed and campaigned through online
networks for over a year before leading health organizations formally recognized
Long COVID [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. By mid-2022, many physicians
acknowledged Long COVID, and the ongoing scientific effort to understand the
potential long-term impacts of COVID-19 infection resulted in thousands of
scientific publications [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Self-described
physician scientist Dr. Ziyah Al-Aly testified before the United States Senate on
Long COVID. In July 2024, Al-Aly noted that “COVID-19 can still wreak havoc in many
organs years after the initial viral infection [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].” While millions of Long COVID patients have seen an improvement in
symptoms or regained the health they lost in the aftermath of their infection, many
millions remain debilitated or disabled, even bedridden. Experts place this number
at over 65 million people worldwide [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p><p>Like influenza survivors with lingering symptoms and new health conditions, many
COVID-19 survivors face limited treatment options. However, their medical outlook is
comparatively better. Scientists rapidly sequenced COVID-19 strains early in the
pandemic, and pharmaceutical companies developed new vaccines and antivirals like
Paxlovid. In contrast, influenza researchers struggled for over a decade to identify
the virus. Today, there is still no scientific consensus on what caused the
virulence of the 1918 strain or the disease’s diverse post-viral sequalae.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s4"><title>Conclusions and Outlook</title><p>My study of the aftermath of influenza in Philadelphia and my experience living
through a global pandemic shifted my perspective on how epidemics end. The epidemic
aftermath, or the period following an epidemic crisis when cases are highest, varies
in length, depending on the community in question. For survivors facing ongoing or
new symptoms post-infection, the end of an epidemic is not obvious; some suffering
from Long COVID still await the end of their epidemic experience. Wigen observes
that “it becomes almost impossible to distinguish between the life and the
afterlife” of an outbreak [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, p.280]. While
President Biden announced that the pandemic was “over” in September 2022, the
federal health emergency status and related resource provision lasted until April
2023. So, when did the acute phase of COVID-19 end? And how does an ongoing increase
in Long COVID cases complicate how we understand and define the end of the COVID-19
pandemic? According to Dr. Al-Aly, the rate at which new Long COVID patients
received a diagnosis in 2024 is on par with rates in 2022 [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. While the development of Long COVID cases has slowed
significantly since late 2020, particularly among the vaccinated, Long COVID remains
a risk because of repeat infections.</p><p>Although the 1918 pandemic is often described as “forgotten,” scholars such as Guy
Beiner argue that the 1918 pandemic is unevenly remembered; survivor experiences
remain underrepresented in public narratives [<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. This dynamic can contribute to an unfamiliarity with the outcomes
of historical epidemics, preventing practitioners from recognizing Long COVID. The
success of infectious disease prevention and the ensuing decline in public knowledge
about epidemics encourages the development of fantastical theories on pandemic
source and spread (eg, 5G cell phone signals caused COVID-19) [<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Without a working knowledge of historical epidemics,
communities will be continually unprepared for and surprised by the diffuse,
entrenched social problems caused by epidemics—including debilitating health
conditions—and the high costs and challenges of resolving those problems.</p><p>As historians like Einar Wigen demonstrate, understanding the varying temporalities
driving epidemic ends requires that we study epidemics. Understanding that the
medical fallout of viral pandemics does not end with the acute crisis allows
practitioners and public health officials to consider new ways to support the
well-being of survivors who remain ill or experience new chronic conditions. One way
to shift cultural expectations around epidemic ends is education, including the
education offered by medical schools.</p><p>Studying historical epidemics and their aftermaths could have direct clinical
implications, guiding what physicians should expect among surviving patients. For
example, following the outbreak of a novel virus, doctors are likely to observe a
small percentage of patients who survive their initial infection and then fail to
get well or experience emerging health problems or new chronic diseases in the weeks
and months following their infection. This reality, well established in the study of
historical epidemics, might be one of the only exceptions to the adage that
physicians should not look for a zebra where they are likely to find a horse. While
viruses like influenza and SARS-CoV-2 are common causes of illness (“horses”), their
long-term effects—such as encephalitis or dysautonomia—are less expected (“zebras”)
and can go unrecognized without knowledge of a historical precedent.</p><p>Lacking a context for zebra-sighting, new and experienced physicians face the
daunting task of understanding and treating survivors without the benefit of
hindsight. When COVID-19 emerged, a global pandemic resulting in quarantine, school
closures, and other lifestyle changes had not occurred at a similar scale since the
fall wave of influenza in 1918. Recent research suggests that medical students are
only loosely acquainted with epidemic history, which is understandable given the
amount of material students must learn. In the late aughts, medical students’
knowledge of influenza was insufficient; a quarter of the medical students in one
study misidentified the transmission route, and more than 60 percent affirmed that
drugs aimed to kill bacteria could treat flu cases [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].<sup>9</sup> These educational gaps signify the importance of the
history of medicine and epidemics as distinct units within required courses,
additional coursework, or continuing education programs.</p><p>These lessons cannot come soon enough as the return of infectious diseases from early
in the 20th century highlights the need for this education today. Unfortunately,
current medical students might treat diseases that the last two generations of
doctors have never observed in person. In February 2025, measles and tuberculosis
are plaguing communities in multiple states around the country. The influenza strain
H5N1 has circulated in wild bird populations for years—the recent spread into
industrial avian settings brings the virus closer to a zoonotic leap. This threat is
particularly alarming in a political context where some appointed officials do not
support vaccination or the study of contagious diseases.</p><p>The danger we face without a detailed understanding of the long-term cultural,
social, and medical consequences of pandemics is playing out now as Americans forget
the lessons of COVID-19; a few deny the virus exists or existed. Americans remain
uninformed about Long COVID, and few understand that it could be a pressing public
health issue for the foreseeable future [<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
As we plan for future pandemics, we must rediscover and maintain the institutional
and social flexibility we created in early 2020, when the world abruptly changed.
Public health institutions must reintegrate the history of epidemics as well as
epidemic response planning into medical education, community outreach, and patient
support systems. How can clinics, research studies, and treatments be tailored to
support patients who do not get well or experience new chronic conditions in the
aftermath? What kinds of work and school accommodations can medical practitioners
recommend? How might nutritionists, physical therapists, and mental health
professionals offer care that reflects the unique needs of pandemic survivors with
post-infection health conditions? These are all questions policy planners and
institutions can be asking now, in response to COVID-19, but also as it pertains to
future outbreaks.</p><p>Because our world maintains the dramaturgy of epidemics and pandemics in the wings,
understanding the long and complex endings of outbreaks allows patients and
practitioners to resist forgetting the lessons of the past. This question— how do we
resist forgetting? —posed by patients and practitioners alike, reminds us that
epidemic endings must be understood not only epidemiologically but
experientially.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Thank you to the <italic toggle="yes">Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</italic> and reviewers
for editorial feedback.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p><sup>1</sup> For more on pandemic narratives and public and media discourse see
Albert [<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and Wald [<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</p></fn><fn id="FN2"><p><sup>2</sup> Throughout this section, I’m generalizing—there are more fissures
and fault lines among and intersections between medical history, plague
historians, and other epidemic historians. Within plague studies, the watershed
finding that <italic toggle="yes">Yersinia pestis</italic> did cause the Black Death, or as
it was termed “the Great Mortality,” completely changed the course of plague
research. The original publication is Bos [<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p></fn><fn id="FN3"><p><sup>3</sup> See Crosby [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. This book
was re-released as <italic toggle="yes">America’s Forgotten Pandemic: The Influenza of
1918</italic> and is now in its 3rd edition. There is ongoing disagreement
around the 1920 wave as we cannot confirm the genetic signature of the 1920
outbreak. However, given the multiple waves of COVID-19, it is not unreasonable
to assume the 1920 outbreak, which was etiologically similar, was a direct
descendant of the fall 1918 influenza strain (ie, as Omicron and Delta were
COVID-19 strains).</p></fn><fn id="FN4"><p><sup>4</sup> The 1918 influenza pandemic strain spread throughout the world from
the late summer of 1918 and through early 1919. The fall 1918 marks the acute
wave or the epidemic crisis of the pandemic, though some historians and
scientists today include the 1919 and 1920 winter waves in the pandemic. Bristow
[<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], Mamelund [<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and Siddharth [<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].</p></fn><fn id="FN5"><p><sup>5</sup> Sergeant’s Mange Medicine advertisements regularly featured in
southern newspapers, including <italic toggle="yes">The News Leader of Richmond</italic>. On
June 27, 1919, p. 7 [<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], the company
used the same image in an advertisement titled “We the Barbers of Richmond,”
which listed the names of barbers who used and endorsed the product. In “Can A
Hair Root Smell?” published in <italic toggle="yes">The News Leader</italic>, August, 4 1919,
p. 16 [<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], the copy notes that that
product helps “if you are losing your hair.”</p></fn><fn id="FN6"><p><sup>6</sup> Some doctors who posted on TikTok include Dr. Monica Kieu who posted
in March 18, 2022 and cited <italic toggle="yes">telogen effluvium</italic> as a common side
effect of COVID
<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.tiktok.com/@drfinlaysprivatepractice/video/7388045077102202144">https://www.tiktok.com/@drfinlaysprivatepractice/video/7388045077102202144</uri>,
and Dr. Finlay who posted through the account @dr.FinlaysPrivatePractice and
shared that he lost a lot of his hair when he suffered from Long COVID:
<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.tiktok.com/@drfinlaysprivatepractice/video/7388045077102202144">https://www.tiktok.com/@drfinlaysprivatepractice/video/7388045077102202144</uri>.</p></fn><fn id="FN7"><p><sup>7</sup> Throughout this section, I draw patient narratives from the
collection by Ladd et al [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and I rely
on interviews I conducted with individuals with Long COVID.</p></fn><fn id="FN8"><p><sup>8</sup> As Callard and Perego argued in [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] “patients continue to experience epistemic injustice—their
long-term symptoms misunderstood or reduced to anxiety.” Unlike patients dealing
with the sequelae of influenza, COVID-19 “long haulers” were not taken seriously
for some time ([<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, p.113426])</p></fn><fn id="FN9"><p><sup>9</sup> In Herman et al. [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>],
researchers surveyed 69% of medical students at the medical school at the
University of Alberta. Regarding treatment, 28 or 7.9% of students stated that
antibiotics could treat influenza while 58.8% said that antibacterial drugs
could treat the disease ([<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, p.1781]) Antivirals can treat influenza if taken
within 48 hours of symptom onset, and users experience one to two fewer days of
symptomatic illness.”</p></fn></fn-group><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>BLJ conceptualized and wrote the essay.</p></notes><glossary><def-list><def-item><term>SSPE</term><def><p>subacute sclerosing panencephalitis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EL</term><def><p>encephalitis lethargica</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahsan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>In the Wake of the Coronavirus, Movies like Contagion and
Outbreak Have Become Very Popular</article-title>. [Internet] <source>National Post</source>.
<month>January</month>
<day>29</day>, <year>2020</year>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited 2025 February 1</date-in-citation>. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://nationalpost.com/entertainment/movies/in-the-wake-of-the-coronavirus-movies-like-contagion-and-outbreak-have-become-very-popular" ext-link-type="uri">https://nationalpost.com/entertainment/movies/in-the-wake-of-the-coronavirus-movies-like-contagion-and-outbreak-have-become-very-popular</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Charters</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Information, Expertise and Authority: The Many
Ends of Epidemics</article-title>. <source>Centaurus</source>.
<year>2022</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1484/J.CNT.5.130193</pub-id><issn>0008-8994</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berridge</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Many Endings of Recent Epidemics: HIV/AIDS,
Swine Flu 2009, and Policy</article-title>. <source>Centaurus</source>.
<year>2022</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1484/J.CNT.5.129441</pub-id><issn>0008-8994</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wigen</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Multiple Temporalities of Epidemic
Endings</article-title>. <source>Centaurus</source>.
<year>2022</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1484/J.CNT.5.129943</pub-id><issn>0008-8994</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Four Black Deaths.</article-title>
<source>The Am
Hist Rev</source>. <year>2020</year>;125(5):1601-31. p. 1603. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ahr/rhaa511</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>What is an Epidemic? AIDS in Historical
Perspective.</article-title>
<source>Bull Hist of Med</source>.
<year>2020</year>;94(4):563-77. p. 564. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://dx.doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1353/bhm.2020.0082" ext-link-type="uri">https://dx.doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1353/bhm.2020.0082</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1353/bhm.2020.0082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33775939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Dickerson C. <article-title>The Silent Killer of 1918: A
Philadelphia Story</article-title>. <source>The New York Times</source>. <year>2020</year> Apr. 5; Sec.A1, 1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wendorf</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harriman</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zipprich</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schechter</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hacker</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Subacute Sclerosing Panencephalitis: the Devastating Measles
Complication is More Common Than We Think</article-title>. <source>Open
Forum Infect Dis</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>
<issue>suppl 1</issue>:<fpage>916</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofw194.81</pub-id><issn>2328-8957</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28387784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper">Mystery. <source>Evening
Public Ledger</source>. <year>1920</year>, <month>Feb.</month>
<day>18</day>;8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>In-Flu-Enza and
out-flew-hair</article-title>. <source>Richmond Times-Dispatch</source>. <year>1919</year>, <month>Aug</month>
<day>12</day>;12.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crosby</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Epidemic and Peace, 1918</source>.
<publisher-loc>Westport</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Greenwood</publisher-name>; <year>1976</year>. p.
<fpage>53</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A Journal of the Plague: The 1918
Influenza</article-title>
<comment>[Internet]</comment>. <source>Yale Rev</source>.
<year>1958</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.
[<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited 2025 Feb
1</date-in-citation>] Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://yalereview.org/article/journal-plague" ext-link-type="uri">https://yalereview.org/article/journal-plague</ext-link><issn>0044-0124</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Grace Meyercord to Carlton Jackson.</collab></person-group> MSS 581 Carlton Luther Jackson, 1933-2014, Box 13, Folder 5.
Manuscripts &amp; Folklife Archives. West Kentucky University;
<month>May</month>
<day>21</day>, <year>1976</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Givner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Katherine Anne Porter: a Life</source>.
<publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Georgia
Press</publisher-name>; <year>1991</year>. p.
<fpage>128</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Unrue</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Katherine Anne Porter: The Life of an Artist</source>.
<publisher-loc>Jackson</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University Press of
Mississippi</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>. p.
<fpage>63</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Pale horse, Pale Rider: Three Short Novels</source>.
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harcourt, Brace and
Co</publisher-name>; <year>1939</year>. p.
<fpage>204</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suarez</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>COVID Hair Loss Explained, Regrowth &amp; Recovery,
Dermatologist @DrDrayzday</source>. [Internet] <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited 2025 January 15</date-in-citation>.
Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://youtu.be/P8Ygwl4Ohig" ext-link-type="uri">https://youtu.be/P8Ygwl4Ohig</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alkeraye</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alrashidi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alotaibi</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Almajli</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alkhalifah</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bajunaid</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The Association Between Hair Loss and COVID-19: The Impact of
Hair Loss After COVID-19 Infection on the Quality of Life Among Residents in
Saudi Arabia</article-title>. <source>Cureus</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Oct</month>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<elocation-id>e30266</elocation-id>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.30266</pub-id><issn>2168-8184</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36381793</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9653091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>W.H.</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Skip-Stop and Step-Stops</article-title>. <source>Evening Public Ledger</source>. <year>1919</year>,
<month>Jan.</month>
<day>3</day>; 11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>'Dragging Themselves Up the
Stairs:’ The Viral Aftermath of Twentieth Century Influenza
and Twenty-First Century COVID.</article-title> Public Talk for the University of North Carolina
at Charlotte Center for Professional and Applied Ethics. <year>2023</year>
<month>Mar</month>
<day>13</day>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Children’s
Asylums Need Rooms and Funds; Institutions Crowded and Executives Working
Overtime Hunting Accommodations</article-title>. <source>Evening Public Ledger</source>. <year>1919</year>
<month>Mar</month>
<day>5</day>; 11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Girard College.</collab></person-group>
<source>Student Records (1919-1922), Girard College Historical
Collection</source>. Philadelphia, PA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Visiting Nurse Society of Philadelphia.</collab></person-group>
<source>Annual Report</source>, <year>1919</year>, p. 15-16.
MC5 Box 2, Folder 11. <source>Barbara Bates Center for the Study of the History of
Nursing</source>. University of Pennsylvania. Philadelphia, PA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Influenza Shows Increase.</collab></person-group>
<month>December</month>
<day>19</day>, <year>1918</year>. Clippings, 1918. Visiting Nurse Society of
Philadelphia. MC5 VNS Box 52, Folder2A. Series 9, Clippings and Publications,
1872-1977. <source>Barbara Bates Center for the Study of the History of Nursing</source>.
University of Pennsylvania. Philadelphia, PA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deaver</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The Surgical Complications and Sequelae of
Influenza.</article-title> MSS2/036-01, John B. Deaver Speeches. Box 36,
Folder 1, p. 1-2. <source>The College of Physicians of Philadelphia</source>. Philadelphia,
PA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Sleeping sickness. Now My Idea
is This! Daily Talks with Thinking Philadelphians on Subjects they Know Best.</article-title>
<source>Evening Public Ledger</source>; <year>1920</year>, <month>Sep.</month>
<day>10</day>. p. 8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frazier</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Inflammations and Influenza, 1915-1935. Patient files in MSS
2/033 <source>Charles H. Frazier Papers, 1915-1935. Series 3</source>. Medical Case Files
(Patient Records), 1900-1945, Vol. 2 M. The College of Physicians of
Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ladd</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>The Long Covid Reader</source>. <publisher-loc>San
Francisco</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Long Hauler
Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>. pp.
<fpage>31</fpage>, 38-40, 68, 120, 145, 164, 179.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Interviewed by Bethany Johnson</article-title>,
<month>February</month>
<day>29</day>, <year>2024</year>, 7:30 p.m., via Zoom.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Bureau of Charities of the City of Philadelphia.</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Annual Report of the Bureau of Charities of the
City of Philadelphia for the Year Ending</article-title>
<month>December</month>
<day>31</day>, <year>1919</year>. Philadelphia: Bureau of Charities of the City
of Philadelphia; 1919, p. 3. ACC 1193-14. <source>Barbara Bates Center for the Study of
the History of Nursing</source>. University of Pennsylvania. Philadelphia,
PA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yoojin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>When Doctors become long Covid patients—and Still Aren’t
Believed</article-title>. <source>The Guardian</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Oct.</month>
<day>13</day>. [Internet] <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited
2025 January 5</date-in-citation>. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2022/oct/13/long-covid-patients-not-believed-doctors" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.theguardian.com/society/2022/oct/13/long-covid-patients-not-believed-doctors</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCorkell</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Long COVID: Major Findings, Mechanisms and Recommendations</article-title>. <source>Nat
Rev Micro</source>. <year>2023</year>; 21:133-146. p. 142. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s4157f9-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Callard</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perego</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>How and why patients made Long
Covid</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2021</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>268</volume>:<elocation-id>113426</elocation-id>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113426</pub-id><issn>1873-5347</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33199035</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7539940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Aly</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Long COVID Puzzle Pieces are Falling into Place—The Picture is
Unsettling</article-title>. <source>The Conversation</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>Jul.</month>
<day>18</day>. [Internet]. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited
2025 February 1</date-in-citation>. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://theconversation.com/long-covid-puzzle-pieces-are-falling-into-place-the-picture-is-unsettling-233759" ext-link-type="uri">https://theconversation.com/long-covid-puzzle-pieces-are-falling-into-place-the-picture-is-unsettling-233759</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Beiner</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <part-title>Conclusion: Rediscovering the Great Flu Between Pre-Forgetting
and Post-Forgetting</part-title>. In ed. Guy Beiner. <source>Pandemic Re-Awakenings; The Forgotten
&amp; Unforgotten “Spanish” Flu of 1918-1919</source>. 346-372. Oxford: Oxford
University Press; <year>2022</year>. p. 370.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><mixed-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>In the Aftermath of the “Lost” Pandemic: Philadelphia,
1918-1923</article-title>. Unpublished Dissertation. Columbia: University of South Carolina;
<year>2025</year>, p. 288-289.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosychuk</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lake</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yonge</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marrie</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Medical students and pandemic
influenza</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2007</year>
<month>Nov</month>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1781</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1311.070279</pub-id><issn>1080-6040</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18217571</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3375803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mazor</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldthwait</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abu Ghazaleh</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Long COVID awareness and receipt of medical care: a survey among
populations at risk for disparities</article-title>. <source>Front Public
Health</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>May</month>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>1360341</elocation-id>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2024.1360341</pub-id><issn>2296-2565</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38873310</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11173587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenberg</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mordechai</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Diseased Cinema: Plagues, Pandemics and Zombies in
American Movies</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>;
<year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wald</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Contagious: Cultures, Carries and the Outbreak
Narrative</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>;
<year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bos</surname>
<given-names>KI</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schuenemann</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Golding</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burbano</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waglechner</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coombes</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A draft genome of Yersinia pestis from victims of the Black
Death</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2011</year>
<month>Oct</month>;<volume>478</volume>(<issue>7370</issue>):<fpage>506</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10549</pub-id><issn>1476-4687</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21993626</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3690193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bristow</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>American Pandemic: The Lost Worlds of the 1918
Influenza Epidemic</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>.
p. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mamelund</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>COVID-19: The Power of Historical Lessons</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>.
<year>2021</year>; 11(3) 405-406, p. 406.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2020.306030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7893351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33566662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siddharth</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paneth</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Pandemic Reemergence and Four Waves of Excess Mortality
Coinciding With the 1918 Influenza Pandemic in Michigan: Insights for COVID-19</article-title>.
<source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2021</year>; 11(3)430-434, p. 431.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2020.305969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7893337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33566641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab><italic toggle="yes">The News Leader of Richmond</italic>.</collab></person-group>
<month>June</month>
<day>27</day>, <year>1919</year>:7. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.virginiachronicle.com/?a=d&amp;d=RTD19190627.1.7" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.virginiachronicle.com/?a=d&amp;d=RTD19190627.1.7</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab><italic toggle="yes">The News Leader of Richmond</italic>.</collab></person-group> August, 4 <year>1919</year>:16. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.virginiachronicle.com/?a=d&amp;d=NEL19190804.1.16" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.virginiachronicle.com/?a=d&amp;d=NEL19190804.1.16</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>