<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Nurs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Nurs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">51</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcnurs</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Nursing</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6955</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12857044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12857044.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12857044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12857044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41484589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12912-025-04249-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4249</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Task delegation in emerging chronic diseases: Long COVID care as a paradigm - a cross-sectional study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamdem</surname><given-names initials="OL">Odette Linda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupre</surname><given-names initials="C">Caroline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guyot</surname><given-names initials="J">Jessica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names initials="L">Louise</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nekaa</surname><given-names initials="M">Mabrouk</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botelho-Nevers</surname><given-names initials="E">Elisabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bongue</surname><given-names initials="B">Bienvenu</given-names></name><address><email>bienvenu.bongue@univ-st-etienne.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04yznqr36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6279.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2158 1682</institution-id><institution>INSERM, SAINBIOSE, University Jean Monnet, U1059, </institution></institution-wrap>Saint-Etienne, France </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04pn6vp43</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412954.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1765 1491</institution-id><institution>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Saint-Etienne, CIC 1408, </institution></institution-wrap>Saint- Etienne, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>PRESAGE Institute, Saint-Etienne, France </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>URPS Nurses’AURA, Lyon, France </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03rth4p18</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.72960.3a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2188 0906</institution-id><institution>Lumière University Lyon 2, </institution></institution-wrap>Lyon, France </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>CPAM 42, Saint- Etienne, France </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04yznqr36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6279.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2158 1682</institution-id><institution>INSERM, SAINBIOSE, </institution><institution>University Jean Monnet, DVH Team, U1059, </institution></institution-wrap>Saint-Etienne, France </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04yznqr36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6279.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2158 1682</institution-id><institution>Chaire Santé des Ainés, Université jean Monnet, </institution></institution-wrap>10, rue de la Marandière, Saint-Priest-en-Jarez, 42270 France </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503824</issue-id><elocation-id>104</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-31 10:25:13.620"><day>31</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12912_2025_Article_4249.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="structured"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Emerging chronic diseases like Long COVID challenge traditional care models, creating therapeutic voids that nurses spontaneously fill through informal task delegation. This study examines nursing roles delegated in Long COVID care and identifies implications for nursing administration.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A cross-sectional study was conducted among 362 nurses in France’s Rhône-Alpes region (December 2023-March 2024). An online questionnaire assessed Long COVID care roles and delegation patterns.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Among participants, 39.8% (95% CI: 34.8–44.9%) had cared for Long COVID patients. Primary delegated roles included psychological support (86.8%, 95% CI: 80.0-91.8%), proximity care (72.9%), screening/detection (42.4%, 95% CI: 34.2–50.9%), and therapeutic education (70.8%). Nurses performing screening roles were significantly more likely to also perform coordination activities (OR = 3.87, 95% CI: 1.92–7.80, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and therapeutic education (OR = 5.63, 95% CI: 2.37–13.36, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Private practice nurses demonstrated significantly greater task appropriation. Despite the quasi-total absence of specific training (1.4%), 80.4% (95% CI: 73.1–86.3%) of nurses with Long COVID care experience declare themselves ready to formally assume coordination responsibilities for Long COVID patient pathways.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Nurses spontaneously appropriate medical roles when confronting emerging diseases. Nursing administration must formalize this informal delegation through structured training and policy frameworks to optimize chronic disease management. The screening role assumed by nurses represents a significant evolution in diagnostic responsibilities distribution, requiring recognition and structured support.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12912-025-04249-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Task delegation</kwd><kwd>Nursing administration</kwd><kwd>Long COVID</kwd><kwd>Care coordination</kwd><kwd>Role expansion</kwd><kwd>Chronic disease management</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>ANRS - Agence Nationale de la Recherche / Emerging Infectious Diseases.</institution></funding-source><award-id>Grant number: ANRS283</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Bongue</surname><given-names>Bienvenu</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Contemporary epidemiological evolution is characterized by the emergence of new complex chronic pathologies that challenge traditional medical care models. Long COVID, a post-infectious syndrome affecting 10–20% of SARS-CoV-2 infected patients according to the World Health Organization, constitutes a paradigmatic example of these emerging chronic diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">These new pathologies share common characteristics: fluctuating and multisystemic symptomatology, diagnostic uncertainty, absence of standardized treatments, and the necessity for prolonged follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Faced with these challenges, healthcare systems must rethink care organization, particularly through task delegation to non-physicians’ healthcare professionals.</p><p id="Par7">Task delegation, or “task shifting,” defined as the rational transfer of certain traditionally medical functions to other qualified healthcare professionals, emerges as an adaptation strategy facing the growing complexity of health needs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. This approach, initially developed to address medical shortages in certain regions according to WHO recommendations in the context of AIDS disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], finds new relevance in managing emerging chronic diseases.</p><p id="Par8">However, beyond formalized delegation through health policies, there exists a phenomenon of informal delegation that merits particular attention. Informal delegation is operationally defined in this study as nurses performing roles traditionally reserved for physicians (particularly screening/detection activities) without formal institutional protocols or specific training for these expanded responsibilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">This informal delegation is particularly illustrated in screening functions, traditionally medical but spontaneously taken on by nurses in response to failures in the early detection system. Long COVID screening, characterized by fluctuating and multisystemic symptomatology requiring continuous clinical vigilance, exemplifies this spontaneous appropriation of diagnostic responsibilities by frontline professionals. Unlike formal delegation, which relies on established protocols and structured training, informal delegation stems from practical necessity and contextual adaptation by field professionals.</p><p id="Par10">Nurses, through their clinical competencies, proximity to patients, and adaptability, appear as natural candidates to assume these new responsibilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In France, although their code of ethics and competencies already allow them to actively participate in clinical data collection, screening, health education, and care coordination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], there is no regulatory framework in the case of crisis situation.</p><p id="Par11">Despite growing documentation of task shifting in established chronic diseases, the spontaneous emergence of nursing roles in novel pathological contexts remains poorly characterized. The mechanisms by which nurses adapt their practice to fill therapeutic voids created by emerging diseases, and the factors influencing this adaptation, have not been systematically examined. This study aimed to characterize the informal delegation of tasks to nurses caring for patients with Long COVID and to examine the factors that influence this spontaneous appropriation of new roles.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design and population</title><p id="Par12">A cross-sectional study using a descriptive-analytical design was conducted between December 2023 and March 2024. The source population consisted of registered nurses (RNs) enrolled in the nurses’ order in the Rhône-Alpes region. This region was chosen for its diversity of practice (urban/rural, private/salaried) representative of task delegation challenges in French territory.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Inclusion criteria</title><p id="Par13">Registered nurses enrolled in French Nursing Order, currently practicing in Rhône-Alpes region and willing to participate voluntarily.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p id="Par14">Nursing students not yet registered, retired nurses no longer in active practice, nurses practicing exclusively outside Rhône-Alpes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par15">A convenience sampling approach was used. Invitations to participate were distributed via the URPS nurses’ mailing list (approximately 7,500 nurses) and DAC networks. An initial mailing was sent out in February 2024, followed by two reminders in March and April 2024. The final sample of 362 nurses represents a response rate of approximately 4.8%.</p><p id="Par16">Data were collected using an online self-administered questionnaire developed specifically for this study on the Lime Survey platform. The questionnaire was designed to capture informal task delegation patterns in Long COVID care, as no existing validated instrument addressed this specific phenomenon. An English translation of the complete questionnaire framework is provided as supplementary material (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The development process involved three phases:</p><p id="Par17">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par18">literature review of task delegation frameworks,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">expert consultation with 5 nursing professionals (3 clinical specialists, 1 academic, 1 administrator) reviewing content validity.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par20">pilot testing with 10 nurses assessing comprehensibility and completion time (mean: 12 min). Based on feedback, 2 questions reworded, and 1 redundant item removed.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par21">The questionnaire employed multiple response formats adapted to each construct being measured. It was constructed according to a task delegation approach and collected: the participants’ sociodemographic characteristics (age, gender, practice setting), their practice setting (determining factor in delegation), the roles exercised with Long COVID patients, notably screening/detection activities defined as early identification of persistent symptoms and diagnostic orientation of patients, their willingness to assume coordination responsibilities and their perception of training needs to assume these new tasks. Attitudes, perceptions, and willingness measures (Sections D, E, G, H, I) were assessed using four-point Likert scales ranging from “Completely disagree” to “Completely agree”. The four-point format was deliberately chosen to eliminate the neutral midpoint option, thereby encouraging respondents to take definitive positions.</p><p id="Par22">The main outcome measure in this study is informal task delegation. Most of the roles identified in this study are included in the French nursing competency framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, the detection/screening role, which can be equated with early diagnosis, is a role reserved exclusively for physicians in France. Performing this role outside of a regulatory framework may be considered as informal task delegation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par23">We performed descriptive statistics. Analyses focused on identifying task delegation patterns. Univariate logistic regression analyses were performed. Dependent variable: screening/detection role adoption (yes/no) among nurses with Long COVID care experience (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 144). Independent variables: practice setting, other role adoptions (coordination, therapeutic education, psychological support, proximity care), gender, years of experience. We did not perform multivariate analysis due to sample size limitations relative to number of potential predictors, which could lead to overfitting. All analyses were performed using Stata version 18. We selected this software for its robust handling of categorical data analysis and logistic regression analysis. Missing data were handled by pairwise deletion, with the actual number N specified for each analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Sample characteristics and delegation context</title><p id="Par24">The study included 362 nurses, predominantly women (87.2%) with an average of 20.5 ± 7.8 years of experience. The predominance of private practice nurses (90.9%) is significant as this practice mode favors autonomy and appropriation of new tasks. Among them, 39.8% (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 144) had already been confronted with the necessity of caring for Long COVID patients, a situation revealing the de facto delegation that occurs (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Participant characteristics (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 362)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Gender</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">314 (87.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (12.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age Groups</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 30 years</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (8.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30–39 years</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115 (31.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40–49 years</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120 (33.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥ 50 years</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97 (26.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>Years of nursing experience</bold>
</p><p>(mean ± SD)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.5 ± 7.8 years</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Practice Setting</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Private practice</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">329 (90.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salaried</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (9.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Long COVID Care Experience</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cared for Long COVID patients</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">144 (39.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never cared for Long COVID patients</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">218 (60.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Training Background</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Received specific Long COVID training</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No specific Long COVID training</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">142 (98.6)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Mapping of delegated tasks</title><p id="Par26">The analysis of roles exercised reveals a de facto delegation structured around multiple domains. Among the 144 nurses who cared for Long COVID patients, psychological support was the most prevalent role (86.8%, 95% CI: 80.0-91.8%), representing a substitution for often inaccessible psychiatric follow-up. Proximity care (72.9%, 95% CI: 64.9–79.8%) compensates for insufficient close medical monitoring. Therapeutic education (70.8%, 95% CI: 62.7–78.0%) replaces medical information consultations. Screening/detection (42.4%, 95% CI: 34.2–50.9%) constitutes a particularly significant delegated diagnostic function: nurses spontaneously develop skills in identifying persistent Long COVID symptoms, thus compensating for diagnostic delays and difficulties in accessing specialized consultations. Coordination activities were assumed by 55.6% (95% CI: 47.2–63.7%) of nurses providing Long COVID care (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Roles adopted by nurses in Long COVID care (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 144) ᵃ</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Role category</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Educational implications</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychological Support</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">125 (86.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Advanced therapeutic communication, crisis intervention</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proximity Care</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105 (72.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic disease monitoring, symptom assessment</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Therapeutic Education</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102 (70.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient education methodologies, health behaviour change</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prevention</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (68.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Public health principles, risk communication</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coordination</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (55.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Care pathway development, interprofessional collaboration</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Screening/Detection</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (42.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical assessment skills, diagnostic reasoning</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Consultation</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (29.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Advanced clinical judgment, scope of practice boundaries</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical Research</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (12.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Research methodology, evidence-based practice</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>ᵃ Multiple responses possible</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par28">The appropriation of the screening role by 42.4% (95% CI: 34.2–50.9%) of nurses who cared for Long COVID patients deserves analysis. This function, traditionally medical, proves particularly suited to nursing skills in clinical surveillance and symptom evaluation. In the context of Long COVID, where the complexity and variability of symptoms make medical diagnosis difficult, nurses develop field expertise based on longitudinal observation and relational proximity with patients.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Factors associated with screening role adoption</title><p id="Par29">Among the 144 nurses who cared for Long COVID patients, 61 (42.4%) adopted screening/detection roles. Logistic regression analysis revealed that nurses who assumed screening roles were significantly more likely to also perform coordination activities (OR = 3.87, 95% CI: 1.92–7.80, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and therapeutic education (OR = 5.63, 95% CI: 2.37–13.36, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Practice setting (private vs. salaried) and demographic characteristics showed no significant association with screening role adoption (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par30">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Factors associated with screening role adoption among Long COVID care providers (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 144)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Screening role<break/><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 61 (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No screening role<break/><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 83 (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds ratio<break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Practice Type</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Private practice</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (93.4)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (85.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.41 (0.73–7.94)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.152</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salaried</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.6)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (14.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Associated Roles</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coordination role</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (73.8)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (42.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.87 (1.92–7.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Therapeutic education</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (88.5)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (57.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.63 (2.37–13.36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Demographics</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53 (86.9)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (80.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60 (0.61–4.21)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.337</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Years of experience (mean ± SD)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.1 ± 10.8</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.9 ± 11.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.97–1.02) <sup>b</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.654</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>b</sup> Per year increase</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Willingness for formalized delegation</title><p id="Par31">Despite the quasi-total absence of specific training (1.4%), 80.4% (95% CI: 73.1–86.3%) of nurses with Long COVID care experience among those who responded to this question (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 138, 6 missing responses) declare themselves ready to formally assume coordination responsibilities for Long COVID patient pathways, revealing strong acceptance of task delegation among experienced nurses. Identified barriers among non-ready nurses include feeling of incompetence and lack of resources, underscoring necessary conditions for successful delegation (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par32">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Willingness and barriers to formal task delegation (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 138)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Willingness to Assume Formal Coordination Responsibilities</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ready to coordinate Long COVID patient pathways</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111/138 (80.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not ready or uncertain about coordination</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27/138 (19.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Barriers to Coordination</bold>
<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Feeling of insufficient competence</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15/27 (55.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lack of institutional resources</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8/27 (29.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time contraints</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12/27 (44.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Practice Setting and coordination Readiness</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Private practice nurses ready to coordinate</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103/123 (83.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salaried nurses ready to coordinate</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8/15(53.3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>c</sup> Among those not ready for coordination (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 27)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Informal task delegation as adaptive response to emerging chronic diseases</title><p id="Par33">This study reveals a phenomenon of spontaneous adaptation by nurses facing traditional care system failures in managing emerging chronic diseases. Long COVID, through its complexity and novelty, created a therapeutic void that nurses spontaneously invested, perfectly illustrating the concept of informal task delegation.</p><p id="Par34">This informal delegation presents distinctive characteristics documented in our study. First, contextual reactivity occurs where new role appropriation directly responds to patients’ uncovered needs. The predominance of psychological support role (86.8%) testifies to necessary substitution facing insufficient psychiatric care for Long COVID patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This reactivity fits within the “role expansion” concept described by Kleinpell et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] where professionals naturally extend their competencies to meet patient needs.</p><p id="Par35">Second, the absence of prior institutional framework distinguishes informal from formal delegation. Our results show that 39.8% of the entire sample developed and played at least one role in the care pathway of Long COVID patients, yet 98.6% of those with Long COVID care experience did not receive any specific training on this disease. This situation illustrates the “tacit delegation” concept described by Dubois et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] where delegation occurs through practical necessity rather than institutional planning.</p><p id="Par36">Third, there is dependence on individual initiatives. Analysis reveals strong inter-individual variability in role appropriation, particularly marked between private practice and employed nurses. This variability characterizes informal delegation, which largely depends on personal initiative and practice context, unlike formal delegation aiming at practice uniformity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">Finally, experiential learning processes emerge where skill acquisition occurs “in the field” through direct clinical experience, as identified in David Kolb’s Experiential Learning Theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. This explains the willingness of nurses to coordinate pathways despite absence of structured training.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Screening as a paradigm of informal diagnostic delegation and role bundling</title><p id="Par38">The screening role assumed by 42.4% of nurses who cared for Long COVID patients illustrates a major evolution in the distribution of diagnostic responsibilities. This spontaneous appropriation is explained by several convergent factors: the nature of Long COVID, with its protean and evolving manifestations, requires continuous clinical surveillance that the traditional medical system struggles to provide. Nurses, through their temporal and relational proximity with patients, become privileged observers of symptom evolution. This screening delegation fits into a logic of healthcare system efficiency. Rather than waiting for often delayed medical consultations, nurses develop early warning and diagnostic orientation skills, thus optimizing care pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. This evolution questions traditional boundaries between nursing surveillance and medical diagnosis, suggesting the emergence of an interprofessional zone where skills complement rather than substitute for each other.</p><p id="Par39">The clustering of screening with coordination and education roles suggests that informal delegation follows a pattern of comprehensive care appropriation rather than isolated skill development. This role bundling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] phenomenon indicates that in France, nurses in private practice are more likely to assume complementary responsibilities, creating integrated care models that transcend traditional professional boundaries. The strong associations found between screening adoption and both coordination (OR = 3.87) and therapeutic education (OR = 5.63) support this concept of synergistic role expansion.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Informal delegation across the Long COVID care pathway</title><p id="Par40">The distribution of roles revealed in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> reflects nurses’ spontaneous positioning throughout the entire Long COVID care pathway, creating a comprehensive care continuum managed informally by nursing professionals. This pattern suggests that nurses do not simply assume isolated tasks but rather orchestrate integrated care sequences that span from early detection to long-term management, consistent with our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par41">In the detection phase, screening activities (42.4%) and consultation roles (29.9%) position nurses as the first point of contact for patients with persistent symptoms, effectively creating alternative access pathways when traditional medical routes are saturated or delayed. The assessment and stabilization phase sees nurses providing proximity care (72.9%) and psychological support (86.8%), addressing both the clinical monitoring needs and the significant emotional burden that characterizes Long COVID patients’ experiences.</p><p id="Par42">This care pathway integration demonstrates that informal task delegation in emerging chronic diseases extends beyond simple role substitution to encompass the creation of parallel, nurse-led care systems.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Private practice status as informal delegation catalyst</title><p id="Par43">The association between private practice status and delegated task appropriation reveals the importance of professional autonomy in the informal delegation process. This observation is consistent with Maier and Aiken’s theoretical model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] identifying professional autonomy as a major determinant of successful task shifting.</p><p id="Par44">Private practice nurses, less constrained by institutional protocols and organizational hierarchies, more easily develop adaptive roles facing emerging needs. This organizational flexibility constitutes an “enabling factor” of informal delegation according to Martinez-Gonzalez et al.‘s classification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Three mechanisms explain this facilitation: first, decision-making autonomy. Private practice allows direct decision-making facing patient needs, without need for hierarchical validation. This autonomy favors personal initiative, an essential component of informal delegation as self-leading healthcare professionals take initiative and responsibility, using self-influencing strategies to improve their motivation and ability to respond to patient needs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Second, relational proximity, where care continuity in private practice creates a privileged therapeutic relationship facilitating identification of uncovered needs and encouraging professional role extension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Third, temporal flexibility, as work time organization in private practice allows adaptation to chronic patients’ specific needs, unlike institutional temporal constraints limiting practice innovation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. This situation illustrates the informal delegation paradox in health systems: the more structured and protocolized the practice framework, the less informal delegation can develop, even though it responds to real needs uncovered by formal organization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Implications for nursing administration</title><p id="Par45">From informal to formal delegation: administrative challenges: The marked willingness of nurses to assume coordination responsibilities despite absence of training reveals an informal delegation potential already operational but not institutionally recognized. This situation illustrates the informal delegation paradox: it is both necessary for system functioning and invisible to policy makers.</p><p id="Par46">Transition mechanisms from informal to formal: Literature identifies several stages in informal delegation formalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The recognition phase involves identification of existing informal practices and their added value. Our study fits within this phase by documenting roles spontaneously developed by nurses. The validation phase encompasses evaluation of effectiveness and safety of these informal practices. Positive reported results suggest de facto effectiveness of this informal delegation. The structuring phase includes development of training, protocols, and adapted regulatory frameworks.</p><p id="Par47">Administrative recommendations: Based on study findings, nursing administration should consider several key areas. Training program development should focus on creating continuing education programs specifically targeting emerging chronic diseases to structure existing informal delegation. Policy framework adaptation involves developing organizational policies recognizing expanded nursing roles while maintaining accountability frameworks. Resource allocation requires establishing dedicated support structures and resources to sustain nurses in these expanded responsibilities. Performance measurement necessitates implementing metrics to evaluate outcomes of both informal and formalized task delegation initiatives.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Study limitations</title><p id="Par48">This study presents some limitations that warrant careful consideration in interpreting findings. The response rate of 4.8% represents a limitation that introduces potential selection bias. This low rate, although consistent with online surveys, could affect the generalisation of the results.</p><p id="Par49">First, nurses who chose to respond may be more engaged with Long COVID issues or have direct experience with affected patients, potentially overestimating the prevalence of informal delegation practices in the broader nursing population. This could explain the finding that 39.8% of respondents had cared for Long COVID patients.</p><p id="Par50">Second, the predominantly private practice composition (90.9%) likely reflects both greater survey engagement among autonomous practitioners and more effective dissemination through URPS professional networks. This over-representation limits direct generalization to institutional settings where organizational constraints, hierarchical structures, and formal protocols may substantially modify informal delegation patterns. However, this finding provides valuable insights into contexts where professional autonomy enables informal delegation to emerge naturally.</p><p id="Par51">In sections containing Likert scale questions, we calculated Cronbach’s alpha coefficients but did not present them. In some cases, they were low. This is consistent with the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], as our questionnaire was designed for descriptive study purposes and not as a psychometric scale.</p><p id="Par52">Despite these limitations, several factors support the value of our findings. The large absolute sample size (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 362) enables detection of meaningful associations, as evidenced by the strong odds ratios identified (e.g., OR = 3.87 for coordination among nurses performing screening). The consistency of role clustering patterns and the theoretical coherence of findings with established task delegation frameworks suggest we have captured genuine phenomena rather than artifacts of sampling. Moreover, the exploratory nature of this first systematic documentation of informal delegation in emerging chronic diseases means these findings provide important preliminary evidence to guide more rigorous future investigations using probability sampling or mixed methods approaches.</p><p id="Par53">The absence of formal psychometric validation including internal consistency testing reflects the questionnaire’s design as a descriptive behavioral survey rather than a psychometric scale. While this limits use of the instrument for measuring change in intervention studies, it is methodologically appropriate for the present exploratory aim of documenting delegation patterns.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par54">This study demonstrates the existence of structured and functional informal task delegation that nurses spontaneously develop when facing emerging chronic diseases. Long COVID, as a paradigm of these new pathologies, reveals natural adaptive mechanisms of the care system and confirms nurses’ potential in this evolution.</p><p id="Par55">For nursing administration, the primary practical implication is clear: formal recognition and structured support of these informally developed competencies through dedicated training programs and regulatory frameworks is essential. Specific actions required include: developing nursing screening protocols for Long COVID, combined appropriate education, legitimizing demonstrated clinical expertise.</p><p id="Par56">This transition from informal to formal delegation requires immediate action to maintain care quality and professional accountability as emerging chronic diseases continue to challenge traditional care models.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12912_2025_4249_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank the Regional Union of Liberal Health Professionals (URPS nurses) and Coordination Support Devices (DAC) for their assistance in participant recruitment. We also thank all the participants of this study and Pr. Franck CHAUVIN (Director of PRESAGE Institute).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>OLK, JG, and BB drafted the project and the study design. CD and BB managed the statistics aspects. EBN, MN and BB coordinated the writing of the manuscript at all stages. OLK, MN and LR supervised data collection. All authors contributed to the design of the manuscript, read, and approved final version of the manuscript before submission.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study is part of the SPACO + project, which has received funding from ANRS - Agence Nationale de la Recherche / Emerging Infectious Diseases. (Grant number: ANRS283). The funders were not involved in the design of the study, the collection and analysis of the data, the decision to publish or the preparation of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par57">This study received approval from the ethics committee of Saint-Étienne University Hospital under reference IRBN1282023/CHUSTE and was conducted in full accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. All participants provided informed consent for participation through their completion of the online questionnaire.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par58">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar5" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par59">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19). Dashboard [Internet]. 2023 [cité 9 août 2023]. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int">https://covid19.who.int</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cárdaba-García</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durantez-Fernández</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barba-Pérez</surname><given-names>MÁ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olea</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What do we know today about Long COVID? Nursing care for a new clinical syndrome</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health 15 Juill</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>8642</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19148642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9317186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35886491</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Cárdaba-García RM, Durantez-Fernández C, Pérez LP, Barba-Pérez MÁ, Olea E. What do we know today about Long COVID? Nursing care for a new clinical syndrome. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(14):8642.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph19148642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9317186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35886491</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Topol EJ Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol [Internet]. 13 Jan 2023 [cité 25 Jan 2023];1–14. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9839201/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9839201/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9839201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno-Pérez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leon-Ramirez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arenas-Jiménez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome. Incidence and risk factors: A mediterranean cohort study</article-title><source>J Infect Mars</source><year>2021</year><volume>82</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2021.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7802523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33450302</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Moreno-Pérez O, Merino E, Leon-Ramirez JM, Andres M, Ramos JM, Arenas-Jiménez J, et al. Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome. Incidence and risk factors: a mediterranean cohort study. J Infect. 2021;82(3):378–83. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jinf.2021.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7802523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33450302</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-González</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tandjung</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Djalali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of physician-nurse task shifting in primary care on the course of disease: a systematic review</article-title><source>Hum Resour Health 7 Juill</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12960-015-0049-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4493821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26149447</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Martínez-González NA, Tandjung R, Djalali S, Rosemann T. The impact of physician-nurse task shifting in primary care on the course of disease: a systematic review. Hum Resour Health. 2015;13:55. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12960-015-0049-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4493821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26149447</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiken</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Task shifting from physicians to nurses in primary care in 39 countries: a cross-country comparative study</article-title><source>Eur J Public Health déc</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>927</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckw098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27485719</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Maier CB, Aiken LH. Task shifting from physicians to nurses in primary care in 39 countries: a cross-country comparative study. Eur J Public Health. 2016;26(6):927–34. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurpub/ckw098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27485719</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization, PEPFAR, UNAIDS. Task shifting: rational redistribution of tasks among health workforce teams: global recommendations and guidelines. 2007 [cité 13 Jun 2025];88. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/43821">https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/43821</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoskins</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strachan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Barriers and facilitators to the implementation of the advanced nurse practitioner role in primary care settings: A scoping review</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud Avr</source><year>2020</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>103443</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2019.103443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32120089</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Torrens C, Campbell P, Hoskins G, Strachan H, Wells M, Cunningham M, et al. Barriers and facilitators to the implementation of the advanced nurse practitioner role in primary care settings: a scoping review. Int J Nurs Stud. 2020;104:103443. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2019.103443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32120089</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodenheimer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rethinking the primary care Workforce - An expanded role for nurses</article-title><source>N Engl J Med 15 Sept</source><year>2016</year><volume>375</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMp1606869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27626516</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Bodenheimer T, Bauer L. Rethinking the primary care workforce - an expanded role for nurses. N Engl J Med. 2016;375(11):1015–7. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMp1606869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27626516</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Laurant M, van der Biezen M, Wijers N, Watananirun K, Kontopantelis E, van Vught AJ. Nurses as substitutes for doctors in primary care. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2018;7(7):CD001271. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD001271.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6367893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30011347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee J, Cho HS, Shin SR. Nursing strategies for the post-COVID‐19 era. Int Nurs Rev [Internet]. 2021 Jun [cité 19 juill 2023];68(2):149–52. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9292181/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9292181/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/inr.12653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9292181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33406273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Legifrance. Order of July 31, relating to the state nursing diploma [Internet]. 2009 [cité 3 août 2025]. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/jorf/id/JORFTEXT000020961044">https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/jorf/id/JORFTEXT000020961044</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smaldone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of primary care by advanced practice nurses: a systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Qual Health Care J Int Soc Qual Health Care Oct</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/intqhc/mzv054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26239474</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Swan M, Ferguson S, Chang A, Larson E, Smaldone A. Quality of primary care by advanced practice nurses: a systematic review. Int J Qual Health Care J Int Soc Qual Health Care. 2015;27(5):396–404. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/intqhc/mzv054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26239474</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinpell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudspeth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scordo</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magdic</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining NP scope of practice and associated regulations: focus on acute care</article-title><source>J Am Acad Nurse Pract Janv</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1745-7599.2011.00683.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22243676</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Kleinpell RM, Hudspeth R, Scordo KA, Magdic K. Defining NP scope of practice and associated regulations: focus on acute care. J Am Acad Nurse Pract. 2012;24(1):11–8. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1745-7599.2011.00683.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22243676</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From staff-mix to skill-mix and beyond: towards a systemic approach to health workforce management</article-title><source>Hum Resour Health 19 déc</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>87</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1478-4491-7-87</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2813845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20021682</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Dubois CA, Singh D. From staff-mix to skill-mix and beyond: towards a systemic approach to health workforce management. Hum Resour Health. 2009;7:87. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1478-4491-7-87</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2813845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20021682</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kolb’s learning styles &amp; experiential learning cycle [Internet]. 2025 [cité 13 août 2025]. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.simplypsychology.org/learning-kolb.html">https://www.simplypsychology.org/learning-kolb.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryant-Lukosius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Misener</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hospital to community transitional care by nurse practitioners: a systematic review of cost-effectiveness</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud Janv</source><year>2015</year><volume>52</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2014.07.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25443307</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Donald F, Kilpatrick K, Reid K, Carter N, Bryant-Lukosius D, Martin-Misener R, et al. Hospital to community transitional care by nurse practitioners: a systematic review of cost-effectiveness. Int J Nurs Stud Janv. 2015;52(1):436–51.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2014.07.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25443307</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen X, Deng C, Tan G, Zheng H, Yang T, Zhang X. Application efficacy of bundled nursing management in care of elderly patients with pressure ulcers. Am J Transl Res [Internet]. 15 Jun 2021 [cité 13 août 2025];13(6):6738–44. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8290705/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8290705/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8290705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34306420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kamdem OL, Dupre C, Heugno V, Baudot A, Essangui E, Blanquet M et al. SPACO+: a mixed methods protocol to assessing the effectiveness of an educative intervention in patients with Long COVID. BMC Infect Dis [Internet] 29 avr 2025 [cité 30 avr 2025];25(1):623. Disponible sur: 10.1186/s12879-025-10992-6<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-025-10992-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12039092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40301772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gaziano TA, Abrahams-Gessel S, Denman CA, Montano CM, Khanam M, Puoane T, et al. An assessment of community health workers’ ability to screen for cardiovascular disease risk with a simple, non-invasive risk assessment instrument in Bangladesh, Guatemala, Mexico, and South Africa: an observational study. Lancet Glob Health [Internet]. 1 sept 2015 [cité 2 juill 2025];3(9):e556–63. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langlo/article/PIIS2214-109X(15)00143-6/fulltext">https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langlo/article/PIIS2214-109X(15)00143-6/fulltext</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2214-109X(15)00143-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4795807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26187361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Engamba SA, Steel N, Howe A, Bachman M. Tackling multimorbidity in primary care: is relational continuity the missing ingredient? Br J Gen Pract [Internet]. févr 2019 [cité 21 Nov 2025];69(679):92–3. Disponible sur: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6355272/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6355272/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3399/bjgp19X701201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6355272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30705019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schober</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehwaldt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pulcini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Guidelines on advanced practice nursing</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>Switzerland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>International Council of Nurses</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="book">Schober M, Lehwaldt D, Rogers M, Steinke M, Turale S, Pulcini J, et al. Guidelines on advanced practice nursing. Switzerland: International Council of Nurses; 2020.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Contandriopoulos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brousselle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangster-Gormley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nurse practitioners, Canaries in the mine of primary care reform</article-title><source>Health Policy Amst Neth Jun</source><year>2016</year><volume>120</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.healthpol.2016.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27085958</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Contandriopoulos D, Brousselle A, Breton M, Sangster-Gormley E, Kilpatrick K, Dubois CA, et al. Nurse practitioners, Canaries in the mine of primary care reform. Health Policy Amst Neth. 2016;120(6):682–9. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.healthpol.2016.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27085958</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangster-Gormley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Misener</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A case study of nurse practitioner role implementation in primary care: what happens when new roles are introduced?</article-title><source>BMC Nurs 23 Janv</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6955-12-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3562226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23343534</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Sangster-Gormley E, Martin-Misener R, Burge F. A case study of nurse practitioner role implementation in primary care: what happens when new roles are introduced? BMC Nurs. 2013;12:1.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1472-6955-12-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3562226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23343534</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poghosyan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nannini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smaldone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nurse practitioner organizational climate in primary care settings: implications for professional practice</article-title><source>J Prof Nurs Off J Am Assoc Coll Nurs</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.profnurs.2013.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24267928</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Poghosyan L, Nannini A, Stone PW, Smaldone A. Nurse practitioner organizational climate in primary care settings: implications for professional practice. J Prof Nurs Off J Am Assoc Coll Nurs. 2013;29(6):338–49.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.profnurs.2013.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24267928</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lennox</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conventional wisdom on measurement: A structural equation perspective</article-title><source>Psychol Bull</source><year>1991</year><volume>110</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.110.2.305</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Bollen K, Lennox R. Conventional wisdom on measurement: a structural equation perspective. Psychol Bull. 1991;110(2):305–14. </mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Streiner</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Being inconsistent about consistency: when coefficient alpha does and doesn’t matter</article-title><source>J Pers Assess Jun</source><year>2003</year><volume>80</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15327752JPA8003_01</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12763696</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Streiner DL. Being inconsistent about consistency: when coefficient alpha does and doesn’t matter. J Pers Assess. 2003;80(3):217–22.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1207/S15327752JPA8003_01</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12763696</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>